<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
 <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
 <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
 <!ENTITY rfc3830 PUBLIC '' 
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3830.xml'>
<!ENTITY keyid SYSTEM
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4563.xml'>
 
 ]>
 <?rfc toc="yes"?>
 <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
 <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
 <?rfc symrefs="no"?>
 <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="4909" category="info">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="OMA BCAST MIKEY General Extension">
Multimedia Internet KEYing (MIKEY) General Extension Payload
for&nbsp;Open&nbsp;Mobile&nbsp;Alliance&nbsp;BCAST&nbsp;LTKM/STKM&nbsp;Transport</title>

        <author fullname="Lakshminath Dondeti" initials="L" surname="Dondeti" role="editor">
            <organization>QUALCOMM, Inc.</organization>
            <address> <postal> 
                <street>5775 Morehouse Dr</street> 
                <city>San Diego</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
                <phone>+1 858-845-1267</phone>
                <email>ldondeti@qualcomm.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="David Castleford" initials="D" surname="Castleford">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
            <address> <postal> 
                <street>4, rue du Clos Courtel </street> 
                <city>35512 Cesson Sevigne Cedex</city>
                <region/>
                <country>France </country>
            </postal>
                <phone>+ 33 (0)2 99 12 49 27</phone>
                <email>david.castleford@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Frank Hartung" initials="F" surname="Hartung">
            <organization>Ericsson Research</organization>
            <address> <postal> 
                <street>Ericsson Allee 1 </street> 
                <city>52134 Herzogenrath</city>
                <region/>
                <country>Germany</country>
            </postal>
                <phone>+49 2407 575389</phone>
                <email>frank.hartung@ericsson.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>


        <date month="June" year="2007"/>
        <area> </area>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any additional keywords (beyond those that 
appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/search.html. -->

        <keyword>MIKEY</keyword>
        <keyword>General Extension Payload</keyword>
        <keyword>IANA registration</keyword>
        <keyword>OMA BCAST</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies a new Multimedia Internet
                KEYing (MIKEY) General Extension payload
                (RFC 3830) to transport the short-term
                key message (STKM) and long-term key message (LTKM)
                payloads defined in the Open Mobile Alliance's (OMA)
                Browser and Content (BAC) Broadcast (BCAST) group's
                Service and Content protection specification.</t>
        </abstract>

    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
            <t>The Multimedia Internet Keying (MIKEY) protocol specification <xref target="RFC3830"> </xref> defines a
                General Extension payload to allow possible extensions to MIKEY without having to allocate a new payload type.
                The General Extension payload can be used in any MIKEY message and is part of the authenticated/signed
                data part. There is an 8-bit type field in that payload. The type code assignment is IANA-managed, and
                RFC 3830 requires IETF consensus for assignments from the public range of 0-240.</t>
            <t>The Open Mobile Alliance's (OMA) Browser and Content (BAC) Broadcast (BCAST) group's Service and Content
                Protection specification <xref target="SvcCnt"/> specifies the use of a short-term key message (STKM)
                and a long-term key message (LTKM) that carry attributes related to Service and Content protection. Note
                that any keys associated with the attributes are part of the MIKEY KEMAC payload. This document
                specifies the use of the General Extension payload of MIKEY to carry the LTKMs or STKMs.</t>
            <t> RFC 3830 <xref target="RFC3830"/>, the MIKEY General
                Extension payload defined in <xref target="RFC4563"/>,
                and the 3rd
                Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)'s Multimedia
                Broadcast/Multicast Service (MBMS) document <xref
                    target="PP33246"/> specify the transport of MIKEY messages via unicast or broadcast and the
                OMA specifications use either for transport of MIKEY messages.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="terms" title="Terminology">
            <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
                "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119
                    <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="OMA BCAST STKM/LTKM MIKEY General
                    Extension:">We refer to the General Extension type
                    -- 5 -- as the OMA BCAST STKM/LTKM MIKEY General Extension .</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

<?rfc needLines="20"?>
        <section title="MIKEY General Extension for OMA BCAST Usage" anchor="OMAGenExt">

<figure anchor="genExt" title="OMA BCAST MIKEY General Extension"><artwork>
<![CDATA[                           1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      ! Next   !      Type     !            Length             !
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      !       OMA BCAST S/LTKM Subtype  (variable length)      ~
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>

            <t> Section 6.1 of RFC 3830 specifies the first three fields of the General Extension Payload and defines a
                variable length Data field. This document specifies
                the use of Type 5 for OMA BCAST Service and Content Protection using the Smartcard Profile.
                The contents of the variable length data field are defined below. </t>
            <t>
            <list style="hanging" >
                <t hangText="Subtype:">
                    8 bits.  This field indicates the type of the OMA BCAST payload.  In this specification,
                    only two values are specified: LTKM (1), and STKM (2).
                </t>
                <t hangText="Subtype Specific Data:">Variable length.  The contents of this field are defined
                    in Section 6 of the OMA BCAST Service and Content
                    Protection specification <xref target="SvcCnt"/>.</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            
                <figure anchor="subType" title="STKM/LTKM Subtype
						Payload"><artwork>
<![CDATA[                      1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  !    Subtype    !   Subtype specific data (variable length)     ~
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork></figure>


        </section>

        <section title="Interoperability Considerations">
            <t>This document specifies the use of MIKEY General Extension Payload Type 5 and a couple of subtype values (1 and 2), one each for OMA BCAST Service and Content protection's
                STKM and LTKM payloads.
                Interoperability considerations span several standards bodies, with OMA BCAST 1.0 enabler compliance
                being the key aspect; as such, it is up to the OMA test planning to verify the interoperability and
                compliance of OMA BCAST 1.0 implementations. This payload type assignment does not change MIKEY beyond
                RFC 3830 <xref target="RFC3830"/> and RFC 4563 <xref target="RFC4563"/>. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t> According to RFC 3830, the general extension payload can be used in any MIKEY message and is part of the
                authenticated/signed data part. The parameters proposed to be included in the OMA BCAST MIKEY General
                Extension payload (listed in <xref target="OMAGenExt"/>) need only to be integrity protected, which is
                already allowed by the MIKEY specification. The OMA BCAST MIKEY General Extension Payload SHALL be
                integrity protected. Furthermore, keys or any parameters that require confidentiality MUST NOT be
                included in the General Extension Payload. If keys or other confidential data are to be transported via
                the General Extension Payload, such data MUST be encrypted and encapsulated independently. Finally, note that MIKEY already
                provides replay protection and that protection covers the General Extension Payload also. </t>

        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t> IANA has allocated a new General Extension Type from the "General Extensions payload name spaces" in the IANA
                registry at
                http://www.iana.org/assignments/mikey-payloads for use
                by OMA BCAST. Furthermore, IANA maintains a list of corresponding subtypes (0-255) as follows:
            </t>
            <t>
                <list>
                    <t>0 ... Reserved</t>
                    <t>1 ... LTKM</t>
                    <t>2 ... STKM</t>
                    <t>3 ... 191 (maintained by IANA and assigned by
                    IETF Review <xref target ="rfc2434bis"/>)</t>
                    <t>192 ... 255 (Private use)</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
            <t>Many thanks to Jari Arkko, Piron Laurent, and Steffen Fries for their reviews and suggestions for
                improvement.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> 
&rfc2119; 
&rfc3830; 
&keyid; 

<?rfc needLines="4"?>
<reference anchor="SvcCnt" target="http://www.openmobilealliance.org/release_program/bcast_v1_0.html">
                <front>
                    <title>Service and Content Protection for Mobile Broadcast Services</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>Open Mobile Alliance</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2007"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="OMA"
                value="TS-BCAST_SvcCntProtection-V1_0-20070529-C"/>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="PP33246">
                <front>
                    <title> 3G Security; Security of Multimedia Broadcast/Multicast Service (MBMS) </title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>3GPP</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date day="23" month="March" year="2006"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="33.246 6.6.0"/>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/33246.htm"/>
            </reference>

        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor='rfc2434bis'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Narten' fullname='Thomas  Narten'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='Harald Alvestrand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='9' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of
constants and other well-known values. Even after a protocol has been
defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned
(e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or
authentication transform for IPsec). To ensure that such quantities
have consistent values and interpretations in different
implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central
authority. For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet
Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA). In order for IANA to manage a given
name space prudently, it needs guidelines describing the conditions
under which new values can be assigned, or when modifications to
existing values can be made. If IANA is expected to play a role in the
management of a name space, the IANA must be given clear and concise
instructions describing that role. This document discusses issues that
should be considered in formulating a policy for assigning values to a
name space and provides guidelines to document authors on the specific
text that must be included in documents that place demands on
IANA.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis-06.txt' />
</reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
