<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../rfc2629xslt/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

    <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc3261 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3344 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3344.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3775 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3775.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2765 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2765.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4068 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4068.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4140 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4140.xml'>
      ]>

<rfc number="4977" category="info" >
    <front>
        <title>Problem Statement: Dual Stack Mobility</title>
        <author initials="G." surname="Tsirtsis" fullname="George Tsirtsis">
            <organization>Qualcomm</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+908-443-8174</phone>
                <email>tsirtsis@qualcomm.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="H." surname="Soliman" fullname="Hesham Soliman">
            <organization>Elevate Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <phone>+614-111-410-445</phone>
                <email>hesham@elevatemobile.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="August" year="2007"/>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

<keyword>example</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>This document discusses the issues associated with mobility management for dual stack
                mobile nodes. Currently, two mobility management protocols are defined for IPv4 and
                IPv6. Deploying both in a dual stack mobile node introduces a number of problems.
                Deployment and operational issues motivate the use of a single mobility management
                protocol. This document discusses such motivations. The document also discusses
                requirements for the Mobile IPv4 (MIPv4) and Mobile
                IPv6 (MIPv6) protocol so that they can support
                mobility management for a dual stack node. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <section title="Terminology">
            <t> This document uses the following terms as
                defined in Stateless IP/ICMP Translation (SIIT) <xref target="RFC2765"/>: IPv4-capable node, IPv4-enabled node,
                IPv6-capable node, IPv6-enabled node. </t>
            <t> The following terms are introduced in this document:</t>
            <t> - MIPv4-capable node: </t>
            <t>
                <list>
                    <t>A node that supports MIPv4 <xref target="RFC3344"/> in its implementation.
                        This allows the mobile node to configure a home address (statically or
                        dynamically) and use such address in its Mobile IPv4 signaling. A
                        MIPv4-capable node may also be IPv6-capable or IPv6-enabled and must be
                        IPv4-capable. </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> - MIPv6-capable node: </t>
            <t>
                <list>
                    <t>A node that supports MIPv6 <xref target="RFC3775"/> by configuring a home
                        address and using such address in its Mobile IPv6 signaling. A MIPv6-enabled
                        node may also be IPv4-capable or IPv4-enabled and must be IPv6-capable. </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Introduction and Motivation">
            <t> A MIPv4-capable node can use Mobile IPv4 <xref target="RFC3344"/> to maintain
                connectivity while moving between IPv4 subnets. Similarly, a MIPv6-capable node can
                use Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC3775"/> to maintain connectivity while moving
                between IPv6 subnets. </t>
            <t> One of the ways of migrating to IPv6 is to deploy nodes that are both IPv4 and IPv6
                capable. Such nodes will be able to get both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses and thus can
                communicate with the current IPv4 Internet as well as any IPv6 nodes and networks as
                they become available. </t>
            <t> A node that is both IPv4 and IPv6 capable can use Mobile IPv4 for its IPv4 stack and
                Mobile IPv6 for its IPv6 stack so that it can move between IPv4 and IPv6 subnets.
                While this is possible, it does not ensure connectivity since that also depends on
                the IP version support of the network accessed. Supporting Mobile IPv4 and Mobile
                IPv6 is also more inefficient since it requires: </t>

<vspace blankLines="100"/>

            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="-">Mobile nodes to be both MIPv4 and MIPv6 capable.</t>
                    <t hangText="-">Mobile nodes to send two sets of signaling messages on every handoff. </t>
                    <t hangText="-">Network Administrators to run and maintain two sets of mobility management
                        systems on the same network, with each of these systems requiring its own set
                        of optimizations.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> This document discusses the potential inefficiencies, IP connectivity problems, and
                operational issues that are evident when running both mobility management protocols
                simultaneously. It also proposes a work area to be taken up by the IETF on the
                subject and discusses requirements for appropriate solutions. </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Prob" title="Problem Description">
            <t> Mobile IP (v4 and v6) uses a signaling protocol (Registration requests in MIPv4
                    <xref target="RFC3344"/> and Binding updates in MIPv6 <xref target="RFC3775"/>)
                to set up tunnels between two end points. At the moment, Mobile IP signaling is
                tightly coupled to the address family (i.e., IPv4 or IPv6) used, in the connections
                it attempts to manipulate. There are no fundamental technical reasons for such
                coupling. If Mobile IP were viewed as a tunnel-setup protocol, it should be able to
                set up IP in IP tunnels, independently of the IP version used in the outer and inner
                headers. Other protocols -- for example, SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> -- are able to use
                either an IPv4- or IPv6-based signaling plane to manipulate IPv4 and IPv6 connections.</t>
            <t> A node that is both MIPv4 and MIPv6 capable, will require the following to roam
                within the Internet: </t>
            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="-">The network operator needs to ensure that the home agent supports both
                        protocols or that it has two separate Home Agents supporting the two
                        protocols, each requiring its own
                        management.</t>
<!-- [rfced]  Mixed use of "home agent" / "Home Agent" throughout 
     the document.  Please use one consistently. -->

                    <t hangText="-">Double the amount of configuration in the mobile node and the home agent
                        (e.g., security associations). </t>
                    <t hangText="-">IP-layer local network optimizations for handovers will also need to be
                        duplicated. </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> We argue that all of the above will make the deployment of Mobile IPv6, as well as
                any dual stack solution in a mobile environment, harder. We will discuss some of the
                issues with the current approach separately in the following sections. </t>
            <section title="The Impossibility of Maintaining IP Connectivity">
                <t>Even if a mobile node is both MIPv4 and MIPv6 capable, connectivity across
                    different networks would not, in fact, be guaranteed since that also depends on
                    the IPv4/IPv6 capabilities of the networks the mobile is visiting; i.e., a node
                    attempting to connect via a IPv4-only network would not be able to maintain
                    connectivity of its IPv6 applications and vice versa. This is potentially the
                    most serious problem discussed in this document. </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="Impl" title="Implementation Burdens">
                <t> As mentioned above, a node that is IPv4 and IPv6
                    capable must also be MIPv4 and MIPv6 capable to
                    roam within the Internet.  The ability to employ
                    both IP versions from one mobility protocol makes it
                    possible to implement just that one protocol,
                    assuming the protocol choice is known.  However,
                    in situations where the mobile node must be
                    capable of working in any network, it may still
                    need two protocols.</t>

            </section>
            <section anchor="oper" title="Operational Burdens">
                <t> As mentioned earlier, deploying both protocols will require managing both
                    protocols in the mobile node and the home agent. This adds significant
                    operational issues for the network operator. It would certainly require the
                    network operator to have deep knowledge in both protocols, which is something an
                    operator may not be able to justify due to the lack of substantial gains. </t>
                <t> In addition, deploying both protocols will require duplication of security
                    credentials on mobile nodes and home agents. This includes IPsec security
                    associations, keying material, and new authentication protocols for Mobile IPv6,
                    in addition to the security credentials and associations required by Mobile
                    IPv4. Depending on the security mechanisms used and with some further work, it
                    might be possible to rely on one set of set common credentials. Assuming nothing else
                    changes, however, such duplication is again significant with no gain to the
                    operator or the mobile node. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Mobility Management Inefficiencies">
                <t> Suppose that a mobile node is moving within a dual stack access network. Every
                    time the mobile node moves, it needs to send two mobile IP messages to its home
                    agent to allow its IPv4 and IPv6 connections to survive. There is no reason for
                    such duplication. If local mobility optimizations were deployed (e.g.,
                    Hierarchical Mobile IPv6 (HMIPv6) <xref target="RFC4140"/>, Fast handovers for Mobile
                    IPv4 <xref target="RFC4068"/>), the mobile node will need to update the local
                    agents running each protocol. Ironically, one local agent might be running both
                    HMIPv6 and local MIPv4 home agent. Clearly, it is not desirable to have to send
                    two messages and complete two sets of transactions for the same fundamental
                    optimization.</t>
                <t> Hence, such parallel operation of Mobile IPv4 and Mobile IPv6 will complicate
                    mobility management within the Internet and increase the amount of bandwidth
                    needed at the critical handover time for no apparent gain. </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="Trans" title="IPv4 to IPv6 Transition Mechanisms">
                <t>The IETF has standardized a number of transition mechanisms to allow networks and
                    end nodes to gain IPv6 connectivity while the Internet is migrating from IPv4 to
                    IPv6. However, while some transition mechanisms can
                    be combined with Mobile IPv4 or Mobile IPv6, none of the known mechanisms have
                    been shown to assist with the issues described in this document.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Conclusions and Recommendations">
            <t> The points above highlight the tight coupling in both Mobile IPv4 and Mobile IPv6
                between signaling and the IP addresses used by upper layers. Given that Mobile IPv4
                is currently deployed and Mobile IPv6 is expected to be deployed, there is a need
                for gradual transition from IPv4 mobility management to IPv6. Running both protocols
                simultaneously is inefficient and has the problems described above. The gradual
                transition can be done when needed or deemed appropriate by operators or
                implementers. In the meantime, it is important to ensure that the problems listed
                above can be avoided. Hence, this section lists some actions that should be taken by
                the IETF to address the problems listed above, without mandating the use of two
                mobility management protocols simultaneously. </t>

            <t>The Mobile IPv6 Working Group has reached the view
            that to allow for a gradual transition based on current
            standards and deployment, the following work areas would
            be reasonable: </t>
            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="-">It should be possible to run one mobility management protocol that can
                        manage mobility for both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses used by upper layers. Both
                        Mobile IPv4 and Mobile IPv6 should be able to
                        perform such tasks. It may
                        not be possible to support route optimization for Mobile IPv6 in all cases;
                        however, mobility management and session continuity can be supported. </t>
                    <t hangText="-">It should be possible to create IPv4 extensions to Mobile IPv6 so that an
                        IPv4 and IPv6 capable mobile node can register its IPv4 and IPv6 home
                        addresses to an IPv4- and IPv6-enabled Home Agent using MIPv6 signaling only.</t>
                    <t hangText="-">It should be possible to create IPv6 extensions to Mobile IPv4 so that an
                        IPv4 and IPv6 capable mobile node can register its IPv4 and IPv6 home
                        addresses to an IPv4- and IPv6-enabled Home Agent using Mobile IPv4 signaling
                        only. </t>
                    <t hangText="-">It should also be possible to extend MIPv4 <xref target="RFC3344"/> and
                        MIPv6 <xref target="RFC3775"/> so that a mobile node can register a single
                        care-of address (IPv4 or IPv6) to which IPv4 and/or IPv6 packets can be
                        tunneled. </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> If the IETF chooses to pursue all these paths, a
            vendor could choose to support one mobility management
            protocol while avoiding the incompatibility and inefficiency problems
            listed in this document.  Similarly, operators could decide
            to continue using one mobility management protocol
            throughout the period of IPv4 and IPv6 coexistence.
            However, a mobile node would be forced to choose one
            approach or the other, or nevertheless to install both
            and use one or the other according to circumstances.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Sec" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This document is a problem statement that does not by itself introduce any security
                issues.</t>
        </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> &rfc2765; &rfc3344;
            &rfc3775; </references>
        <references title="Informative References">&rfc3261; &rfc4068; 

<vspace blankLines="100"/> <!-- attempt to get a page break -->
&rfc4140;
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
