<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-bis.dtd"> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>

<rfc number="4968" category="info">

<front>
<title abbrev="IPv6 Link Models for IEEE 802.16"> Analysis of IPv6 Link Models for IEEE 802.16 Based Networks</title>

       <author 	initials="S" surname="Madanapalli"
		fullname="Syam Madanapalli" role="editor">

		<organization>LogicaCMG</organization> 
		<address>
		<postal>
                        <street>Global Innovation Center</street>
		        <street>125 Yemlur P.O.</street>
		        <city>Bangalore</city> 
		        <code>560037</code>
		        <country>India</country>
		</postal>
		<email>smadanapalli@gmail.com</email>
		</address>
	
	</author>



	<date month="August" year="2007"/>
	<area>Internet</area>
	<workgroup>16ng Working Group</workgroup>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->
<keyword>example</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>

This document provides different IPv6 link models that are suitable
for IEEE 802.16 based networks and provides analysis of various considerations
for each link model and the applicability of each link model under
different deployment scenarios. This document is the result of a
design team (DT) that was formed to analyze the IPv6 link models for IEEE 802.16 based networks.

</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>
IEEE 802.16 <xref target="_XREF_10" pageno="false" format="default"/> <xref 
target="_XREF_11" pageno="false" format="default"/> is a point-to-multipoint,
connection-oriented access technology for the last mile without bi-directional
native multicast support. IEEE 802.16 has defined only downlink multicast support.
This leads to two methods for running IP protocols that traditionally
assume the availability of multicast at the link layer. One method is to
use bridging, e.g., IEEE 802.1D <xref target="_XREF_14" pageno="false"
format="default"/>, to support bi-directional multicast. Another method is 
to treat the IEEE 802.16 MAC (Message Authentication Code) transport connections between an MS
(Mobile Station) and BS (Base Station) as 
point-to-point IP links so that the IP protocols (e.g., ARP (Address
Resolution Protocol), IPv6 Neighbor Discovery)
can be run without any problems. 
</t>

<t>
This is further complicated by the definition of commercial network models
like WiMAX, which defines the WiMAX transport connection that extends the IEEE 802.16 MAC
transport connection all the way to an access router by using a tunnel between
the base station and the access router <xref target="_XREF_16"/>. This leads to multiple ways of deploying
IP over IEEE 802.16 based networks.
</t>

<t>
This document looks at various considerations in selecting a link
model for IEEE 802.16 based networks and provides an analysis of the various
possible link models. And finally, this document provides a recommendation
for choosing one link model that is best suitable for the deployment.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Terminology">

<t>
The terminology in this document is based on the definitions in
<xref target="_XREF_14" pageno="false" format="default"/>, in addition
to the ones specified in this section.

</t>


<t>
   Access Router (AR): An entity that performs an IP routing function to provide
   IP connectivity for Mobile Stations. In WiMAX Networks, the AR is an Access 
   Service Network Gateway.
</t>

<t>
   Access Service Network (ASN) - The ASN is defined as a complete set
   of network functions needed to provide radio access to a WiMAX
   subscriber.  The ASN is the access network to which the MS attaches.
   The IPv6 access router is an entity within the ASN.  The term ASN is
   specific to the WiMAX network architecture.
</t>


<t>
   Dormant Mode: A state in which a mobile station restricts its ability
      to receive normal IP traffic by reducing monitoring of radio
      channels.  This allows the mobile station to save power and reduces
      signaling load on the network. In the dormant mode, the MS is only
      listening at scheduled intervals to the paging channel. The network
      (e.g., the AR) maintains state about an MS that has transitioned to
      dormant mode and can page it when needed.
</t>


</section>




<section title="IPv6 Link Models for IEEE 802.16 based Networks">
<t>
This section discusses various IPv6 link models for IEEE 802.16 based networks
and provides their operational considerations in practical deployment
scenarios.
</t>


<section title="Shared IPv6 Prefix Link Model">

<t>
In this model, all MSs attached to an AR share one or more prefixes 
for constructing their global IPv6 addresses, however this model does
not provide any multicast capability. The following figures
illustrates a high-level view of this link model wherein one or more prefixes advertised on the link
would be used by all the MSs attached to the IPv6 link.
</t>

<t>

</t>


    <figure>
        <artwork>

     +-----+
     | MS1 |-----+
     +-----+     |
                 |
                 |
     +-----+     |     +-----+          +--------+
     | MS2 |-----+-----| BS1 |----------|   AR   |-------Internet
     +-----+     |     +-----+          +--------+
        .        |           ____________
        .        |          ()__________()
     +-----+     |             L2 Tunnel
     | MSn |-----+
     +-----+


	    Figure 1. Shared IPv6 Prefix Link Model


        </artwork>
     </figure>

<t>
The above figure shows the case where the BS and AR exist as separate entities.
In this case, a tunnel exists between the BS and AR per MS basis.
</t>


<t>

   In this link model, the link between the MS and the AR at the
   IPv6 layer is viewed as a shared link, and the lower layer link
   between the MS and BS is a point-to-point link.  This point-to-point
   link between the MS and BS is extended all the way to the AR when the
   granularity of the tunnel between the BS and AR is on a per MS basis.
   This is illustrated in the following figure below.
</t>


    <figure>
        <artwork>


       MS
     +----+                                     +----+
     |    |      IPv6 (Shared link)             |    |
     | L3 |=====================================|    |
     | 	  |                                     |    |
     |----|   PTP conn. +----+	 L2 Tunnel      | AR |---Internet
     | L2 |-------------| BS |==================|    |
     |    |             |    |                  |    |
     +----+             +----+                  |    |
                                                |    |
                        +----+   L2 Tunnel      |    |
                        | BS |==================|    |
                        |    |                  |    |
                        +----+                  +----+


      Figure 2. Shared IPv6 Prefix Link Model - Layered View


        </artwork>
     </figure>
<t>
   In this link model, an AR can serve one or more BSs.  All MSs
   connected to BSs that are served by an AR are on the same IPv6 link. This
   model is different from an Ethernet Like Link model wherein the later model
   provides an Ethernet link abstraction and multicast capability to the IPv6 layer,
   whereas the Shared IPv6 Prefix Link Model defined here does not provide
   native link-layer multicast and broadcast capabilities.
</t>


<section title="Prefix Assignment">
<t>

   One or more IPv6 prefixes are assigned to the link and hence shared
   by all the nodes that are attached to the link.  The prefixes are
   advertised with the autonomous flag (A-Flag) set and the On-link flag
   (L-flag) reset for address autoconfiguration so that the nodes may
   not make an on-link assumption for the addresses in those prefixes.

</t>
</section>


<section title="Address Autoconfiguration">
<t>
 The standard IPv6 address autoconfiguration mechanisms,
 which are specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/> <xref target='RFC3315'/>,
 are used.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Duplicate Address Detection">
<t>
   The DAD procedure, as specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/>, does not adapt well to the
   IEEE 802.16 air interface as there is no native multicast support. The 
   DAD can be performed with MLD (Multicast Listener Discovery) snooping <xref target='RFC4541'/> and the AR relaying the DAD probe
   to the address owners in case the address is a duplicate, called Relay DAD.
   In this method, the MS behavior is the same as specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/>
   and the optimization is achieved with the support of AR, which
   maintains the MLD
   table for a list of multicast addresses and the nodes that joined the
   multicast address. The relay DAD works as below:


<list style="numbers">
<t>
   An MS constructs a Link Local Address as specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/>.
</t>

<t>
The MS constructs a solicited node multicast address for the
corresponding Link Local Address and sends an MLD Join request for
the solicited node multicast address.
</t>

<t>
The MS starts verifying address uniqueness by sending a DAD NS on
the initial MAC transport connection.  
</t>

<t>
The AR consults the MLD table for who joined the multicast address.
If the AR does not find any entry in the MLD table, the AR silently discards
the DAD NS. If the AR finds a match, the AR relays the DAD NS to the address
owner. 
</t>

<t>
The address owner defends the address by sending DAD NA, which is relayed to
the DAD originating MS via the AR.
</t>

<t>
If the DAD originating MS does not receive any response (DAD NA) to its DAD NS,
the MS assigns the address to its interface. If the MS receives the DAD NA, the MS
discards the tentative address and behaves as specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/>.
</t>

</list>
 
</t>

</section>


<section title="Considerations">

<section title="Reuse of Existing Specifications">
<t>
   The shared IPv6 prefix model uses the existing specification and does not
   require any protocol changes or any new protocols.  However, this
   model requires implementation changes for DAD optimization on the AR.
</t>
</section>


<section title="On-link Multicast Support">
<t>
   No native on-link multicast is possible with this method.  However,
   the multicast can be supported with using a backend process in AR
   that maintains the multicast members list and forwards the multicast
   packets to the MSs belonging to a particular multicast group in a unicast
   manner. MLD snooping <xref target='RFC4541'/> should be used for
   maintaining the multicast members list.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Consistency in IP Link Definition">
<t>
   The definition of an IPv6 link is consistent for all procedures and
   functionalities except for the support of native on-link multicast
   support.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Packet Forwarding">
<t>
   All the packets travel to the AR before being delivered to the final
   destination as the layer 2 transport connection exists between the 
   MS and AR. The AR normally handles the packets with external IPv6 addresses.
   However, the packets with link local destination addresses are
   relayed by the AR to the destination without decrementing the hop-limit.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Changes to Host Implementation">
<t>
   This link model does not require any implementation changes for the 
   host implementation.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Changes to Router Implementation">
<t>
   This link model requires MLD snooping in the AR for supporting Relay DAD.
</t>
</section>



</section>


<section title="Applicability">

<t>
   This model is good for providing shared on-link services in conjunction
   with the IP convergence sublayer with IPv6 classifiers. However, in public
   access networks like cellular networks, this model cannot be used for 
   the end users to share any of their personal devices/services with the
   public.
</t>

<t>
   This link model was also under consideration of the WiMAX Forum Network
   Working Group for use with IPv6 CS (Convergence Sublayer) access.
</t>
</section>


</section>





<section title="Point-to-Point Link Model">
<t>
   In this model, a set of MAC transport connections between an MS and 
   an AR are treated as a single link. The point-to-point link model follows
   the recommendations of <xref target='RFC3314'/>.
   In this model, each link between an MS and an AR is
   allocated a separate, unique prefix or a set of unique prefixes by the
   AR.  No other node under the AR has the same prefixes on the link
   between it and the AR. The following diagram illustrates this model.
</t>



    <figure>
        <artwork>


          
                            +----+                   +----+
        +-----+             |    |      Tunnel       |    |
        | MS1 |-------------|....|===================|    |
        +-----+             |    |                   |    |
                            |    |                   |    |
        +-----+             |    |      Tunnel       |    |
        | MS2 |-------------|....|===================|    |---Internet
        +-----+             |    |                   | AR |
                            | BS |                   |    |
        +-----+             |    |      Tunnel       |    |
        | MS3 |-------------|....|===================|    |
        +-----+             |    |                   |    |
                            +----+                   +----+

               Figure 3. Point-to-Point Link Model



        </artwork>
     </figure>



<t>

   There are multiple possible ways that the point-to-point link
   between the AR and the MS can be implemented.

 <list style="numbers">
<t>
   One way to accomplish this is to run PPP on the link  <xref target='RFC3314'/>.
   Running PPP requires that the IEEE 802.16 link use the Ethernet CS and PPP over Ethernet
   <xref target='RFC2516'/>. Since the IPv6 CS does not support PPP, whether PPP can be run
   depends on the network architecture.
</t>

<t>
   If the actual physical medium is shared, like Ethernet, but PPP is not run, the
   link can be made point to point between the MS and AR by having each MS on a separate
   VLAN <xref target="_XREF_12" pageno="false" format="default"/>.

</t>

<t>
   If neither PPP nor VLAN is used, the set of IEEE 802.16 connections can be viewed as
   a virtual point-to-point link.
</t>

</list>

</t>


<section title="Prefix Assignment">
<t>
   Prefixes are assigned to the link using the standard <xref target='RFC2461'/>
   Router Advertisement mechanism.  The AR assigns a unique prefix or a set of
   unique prefixes for each MS. In the prefix information options, both the
   A-flag and L-flag are set to 1, as they can be used for address autoconfiguration
   and the prefixes are on the link.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Address Autoconfiguration">
<t>
   MSs perform link local as well as global address autoconfiguration exactly as
   specified in <xref target='RFC2462'/>, including duplicate address detection.
   Because there is only one other node on the link, the AR, there is
   only a possibility of an address conflict with the AR, so collisions are
   statistically very unlikely, and easy to fix if they should occur.
</t>

<t>
   If DHCP is used for address configuration ('M=1' in the Router
   Advertisement), the DHCP server must provide addresses with a
   separate prefix per MS.  The prefix must of course match
   a prefix that the ASN Gateway has advertised to the MS (if any).

</t>
</section>


<section title="Considerations">

<section title="Reuse of Existing Specifications">
<t>
   This solution reuses RFC 2461, 2462, and, if PPP is used, RFC 2472 and
   RFC 2516. No changes in these protocols are required; the protocols must only
   be configured properly.
</t>

<t>
   If PPP is not used, any VLAN solution, such as IEEE 802.1Q [9] or any
   L2 tunnel, can be used.
</t>
</section>


<section title="On-link Multicast Support">
<t>
   Since the link between the MS and the AR is point to point,
   any multicast can only be sent by one or the other node.  Link local
   multicast between other nodes and the AR will not be seen.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Consistency in IP Link Definition">
<t>
   The IP link is fully consistent with a standard IP point-to-point link,
   without exception.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Packet Forwarding">
<t>
   The MS always sends all packets to the AR because it is the
   only other node on the link.  Link local unicast and multicast
   packets are also forwarded only between the two.
</t>


</section>


<section title="Changes to Host Implementation">
<t>
   Host implementations follow standard IPv6 stack procedures.  No
   changes are needed.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Changes to Router Implementation">
<t>
   If PPP is used, no changes in router implementations are needed.  If
   PPP is not used, the AR must be capable of doing the following:

<list style="numbers">
<t>
Each MS is assigned a separate VLAN when IEEE 802.1X <xref target="_XREF_13" 
pageno="false" format="default"/>  or each MS must have an L2 tunnel to the AR
to aggregate all the connections to the MS and present these set of connections
as an interface to the IPv6 layer.
</t>

<t>
The AR must be configured to include a unique prefix or a set of 
prefixes for each MS. This unique prefix or set of prefixes must be 
included in Router Advertisements every time they are sent, and if DHCP is 
used, the addresses leased to the MS must include only the uniquely 
advertised prefixes.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
Note that, depending on the router implementation, these functions may or 
may not be possible with simple configuration. No protocol changes are 
required, however.
</t>
</section>


</section>


<section title="Applicability">
<t>
   In enterprise networks, shared services including printers, fax
   machines, and other such online services are often available on
   the local link.  These services are typically discovered using some
   kind of link local service discovery protocol.  The unique prefix per
   MS model is not appropriate for these kinds of deployments,
   since it is not possible to have shared link services in the ASN.
</t>

<t>
   The p2p link model is applicable to deployments where there are no
   shared services in the ASN.  Such deployments are typical of service
   provider networks like cellular networks, which provide public access to 
   wireless networks.
</t>

</section>


</section>




<section title="Ethernet-Like Link Model">

<t>
  This model describes a scheme for configuration and provisioning of an
  IEEE 802.16 network so that it emulates a broadcast link in a manner
  similar to Ethernet. Figure 4 illustrates an example of the Ethernet model.
  This model essentially functions like an Ethernet link, which means the
  model works as described in <xref target='RFC2461'/>, <xref target='RFC2462'/>.
</t>

<t>
  One way to construct an Ethernet-like link is to implement bridging
  <xref target="_XREF_15" pageno="false" format="default"/>
  between BSs and an AR, like a switched Ethernet. In Figure 4, bridging
  performs link aggregation between BSs and an AR. Bridging also supports
  multicast packet filtering.
</t>



    <figure>
        <artwork>



           +-----+                 +---+       +----+
           | MS1 |---+             |   |   +---|AR1 |---Internet
           +-----+   |             |  S|   |   +----+
           +-----+   |   +-----+   |E w|   |
           | MS2 |---+---| BS1 |---|t i|   |
           +-----+       +-----+   |h t|---+
                                   |  c|   |   +----+
  +-----+  +-----+       +-----+   |  h|   +---|AR2 |---Internet
  |Hosts|--|MS/GW|-------| BS2 |---|   |       +----+
  +-----+  +-----+       +-----+   +---+
  A network
  may exist behind
  MS/GW

               Figure 4: Ethernet Like Link Model



        </artwork>
     </figure>


<section title="Prefix Assignment">
<t>
Prefixes are assigned as specified in <xref target='RFC2461'/>, <xref target='RFC2462'/>. 
 </t>
</section>

<section title="Address Autoconfiguration">
<t>
  It is the same as described in  <xref target='RFC2462'/>.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Duplicate Address Detection">
<t>
    It is the same as described in  <xref target='RFC2462'/>.
</t>

</section>



<section title="Considerations">
<t>

</t>

<section title="Reuse of Existing Specifications">
<t>
  All the IPv6 standards can be preserved or reused in this model.
</t>
</section>


<section title="On-link Multicast Support">
<t>
  On-link multicast can be emulated in a unicast manner by efficiently
  bridging between all BSs with IEEE 802.16 providing the links between
  the MSs and the bridge on top of the BS. MLD snooping should be used
  for efficient forwarding of multicast packets as specified in <xref
  target='RFC4541'/>. Nevertheless, in case of bridging,
  direct inter-MSs communication may not be not allowed due to restrictions
  from the service providers.

</t>

</section>


<section title="Consistency in IP Link Definition">
<t>
   This model is consistent with the IP link definition.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Packet Forwarding">
<t>
  When properly configured and assisted by simple bridging,
  IEEE 802.16 can emulate a simple broadcast network like Ethernet.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Changes to Host Implementation">
<t>
     No special impact on host implementation.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Changes to Router Implementation">
<t>
  No special impact on router implementation under a separated AR-BS
  model, if the bridging is implemented in BS.  Some networks, e.g.,  WiMAX
  networks, may require bridging to be implemented in the AR (ASN Gateway).

</t>

</section>



</section>



<section title="Applicability">
<t>
  This model works with the Ethernet CS and is chosen for fixed/nomadic WiMAX
  networks by the WiMAX Forum Network Working Group.
</t>
</section>


</section>



</section>



<section title="Renumbering">
<t>
If the downstream prefixes managed by the AR are involved in renumbering, it may be necessary to renumber each link under the AR. <xref target='RFC4192'/> discusses recommended procedures for renumbering.
</t>

<t>
If the prefixes are advertised in RAs, the AR must withdraw the
existing prefixes and advertise the new ones. Since each MS,
irrespective of the link model, is on a separate point-to-point link at
the MAC level because of the IEEE 802.16 connection oriented
architecture, the AR must send an RA withdrawing the old prefix and
advertising the new one to each link. In a point-to-point link model, the number of RAs sent is equal to the number of nodes the AR serves, whereas in the other two models, the AR sends a single RA to BS that is sent to all the MSs as separate RAs. 
</t>


<t>
If DHCP is used to assign addresses, either the DHCP address lease lifetime may be reduced prior to the renumbering event to encourage MSs to renew their addresses quickly, or a DHCP Reconfigure message may be sent to each of the MSs by the server to cause them to renew their addresses.
</t>

<t>
In conclusion, the amount of traffic on the air-interface is the same for all link models. However, the number of RAs sent by the AR to BS can be better compared to the other two models.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Effect on Dormant Mode">
<t>
If the network needs to deliver packets to an MS, which is in dormant mode, the AR pages the MS. The MS that is monitoring the paging channel receives the page and transitions out of the dormant mode to active mode. It establishes connectivity with the network by requesting and obtaining the radio resources. The network is then able to deliver the packets to the MS. In many networks, packets destined to an MS in dormant mode are buffered at the AR in the network until connectivity is established. 
</t>

<t>
Support for dormant MSs is critical in mobile networks, hence it is a
necessary feature. Paging capability and optimizations possible for
paging an MS are neither enhanced nor handicapped by the link model
itself. However, the multicast capability within a link may cause for
an MS to wake up for an unwanted packet. This can be avoided by
filtering the multicast packets and delivering the packets to only for
MSs that are listening for particular multicast packets. As the Shared
IPv6 Prefix model does not have the multicast capability and the
point-to-point link model has only one node on the link, neither has any effect on the dormant mode. The Ethernet-like link model may have the multicast capability, which requires filtering at the BS to support the dormant mode for the MSs.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Effect on Routing">
<t>
    The model used in an IEEE 802.16 network may have a significant
    impact on how routing protocols are run over such a network.
    The deployment model presented in this document discusses the
    least impacting model on routing as connectivity on the provider
    edge is intentionally limited to point-to-point connectivity
    from one BS to any one of multiple MSs. Any other deployment
    model may cause a significant impact on routing protocols,
    however, they are outside the scope of this document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Conclusions and Relevant Link Models">
<t>
Ethernet-Like Link models would be used when the deployment requires
the use of Ethernet CS, as this is the only model being proposed for
the Ethernet CS and running IPv6 over Ethernet is well understood.
</t>

<t>
For IP CS with IPv6 classifiers, a point-to-point link model appears 
to be the choice because of its simplicity for performing the DAD and
because it does not break any existing applications nor requires defining any new 
protocol. However, the IPv6 shared prefix model would be defined if 
there is any interest from the service provider community.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>

    This document provides the analysis of various IPv6 link models for
    IEEE 802.16 based networks, and as such does not
    introduce any new security threats. No matter what the link model
    is, the networks employ the same link-layer security mechanisms
    defined in [5]. However, the chosen link model affects the scope
    of link local communication, and this may have security implications
    for protocols that are designed to work within the link scope. This
    is the concern for a shared link model compared with other models wherein
    private resources e.g., personal printer, cannot be put onto a public
    WiMAX network. This may restrict the usage of a shared prefix model
    to enterprise environments.

    The Neighbor Discovery related security issues are document in
    <xref target='RFC2461'/> <xref target='RFC2462'/> and these are applicable for all the models
    described in this document. The model specific security
    considerations are documented in their respective protocol
    specifications.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
This document is a result of discussions in the v6subnet design team
for IPv6 Prefix Model Analysis. The members of this design team are (in alphabetical order): Dave Thaler, David Johnston, Junghoon Jee, Max Riegel, Myungki Shin and Syam Madanapalli. The discussion in the DT was benefited from the active participation of James Kempf, Behcet Sarikaya, Basavaraj Patil and JinHyeock Choi in the DT mailing list. The DT thanks the chairs (Gabriel Montenegro and Soohong Daniel Park) and Shepherding AD (Jari Arkko) for their active participation and motivation.
</t>
</section>



<section title="Contributors">
<t>
The members who provided the text based on the DT discussion are:
</t>

<figure>
<artwork>

Myung-Ki Shin
ETRI
EMail: myungki.shin@gmail.com

James Kempf
DoCoMo Communications Labs USA
EMail: kempf@docomolabs-usa.com

Soohong Daniel Park
Samsung Electronics
EMail: soohong.park@samsung.com

Dave Thaler
Microsoft
EMail: dthaler@microsoft.com

JinHyeock Choi
Samsung Advanced Institute of Technology
EMail: jinchoe@samsung.com

Behcet Sarikaya
Huawei USA
EMail: sarikaya@ieee.org

</artwork>
</figure>
</section>

</middle>
	
	
<back>

<references title='Normative References'>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2461" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2462" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315" ?>

</references>



<references title='Informative References'>

<reference anchor="_XREF_10"> 
<front> 
<title abbrev="IEEE802.16">IEEE 802.16-2004, IEEE standard for Local and
metropolitan area networks, Part 16:Air Interface for fixed broadband wireless access systems</title> 
<date year="2004" month="October" /> 
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="_XREF_11"> 
<front> 
<title abbrev="IEEE802.16e">IEEE 802.16e, IEEE standard for Local and
metropolitan area networks, Part 16:Air Interface for fixed and Mobile broadband wireless access systems</title> 
<date year="2005" month="October" /> 
</front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="_XREF_14">
<front><title>IP over IEEE 802.16 Problem Statement and Goals</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Jee"><organization/> </author>
<date month="October" year="2006" /></front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4541" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3314" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2516" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4192" ?> 

<reference anchor="_XREF_12"> 
<front> 
<title abbrev="IEEE 802.1Q">IEEE, Virtual Bridged Local Area Networks, IEEE 802.1Q</title> 
<date year="2003" month="May"/> 
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="_XREF_13"> 
<front> 
<title abbrev="IEEE 802.1x">IEEE, Port-based Network Access Control, IEEE 802.1X</title> 
<date year="2004" month="December"/> 
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="_XREF_15"> 
<front> 
<title abbrev="IEEE 802.1D">IEEE Std 802.1D-2004, "IEEE Standard for Local and
metropolitan area networks, Media Access Control (MAC) Bridges"</title> 
<date year="2004" month="June"/> 
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="_XREF_16" target="http://www.wimaxforum.org/technology/documents">
<front> 
<title>WiMAX End-to-End Network Systems Architecture</title> 
<date year="2006" month="August"/> 
</front>
</reference>

</references>
 		
</back>
</rfc>
