<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc number="4889" category="info">

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- FRONT: Title, Authors, Abstract ----------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->

<front>
<title abbrev='NEMO RO Space Analysis'>
  Network Mobility Route Optimization Solution Space Analysis
</title>

<!-- Insert a link to your own authors XML -->

<author fullname="Chan-Wah Ng" initials="C.N."
            surname="Ng">
      <organization abbrev="Panasonic Singapore Labs">Panasonic Singapore Laboratories Pte Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Blk 1022 Tai Seng Ave #06-3530</street>
          <city>Tai Seng Industrial Estate</city>
          <region>Singapore</region>
          <code>534415</code>
          <country>SG</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+65 65505420</phone>
        <email>chanwah.ng@sg.panasonic.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
 <author fullname="Fan Zhao" initials="F.Z."
            surname="Zhao">

 <organization abbrev="UC Davis">
                University of California Davis
        </organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Shields Avenue</street>
          <city>Davis</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95616</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 530 752 3128</phone>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
        <email>fanzhao@ucdavis.edu</email>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
      </address>
    </author>

 <author fullname="Masafumi Watari" initials="M.W."
            surname="Watari">

        <organization abbrev="KDDI R&D Labs">
                KDDI R&D Laboratories Inc.
        </organization>
        <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2-1-15 Ohara</street>
          <city>Fujimino</city>
          <region>Saitama</region>
          <code>356-8502</code>
          <country>JAPAN</country>
        </postal>
        <email>watari@kddilabs.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 <author fullname="Pascal Thubert" initials="P.T."
            surname="Thubert">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Village d'Entreprises Green Side</street>
	  <street>400, Avenue de Roumanille</street>
          <city>Batiment T3</city>
          <region>Biot - Sophia Antipolis</region>
          <code>06410</code>
          <country>FRANCE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


<date month="April" year="2007" />

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>NEMO Working Group</workgroup>

<keyword>MIPv6</keyword>
<keyword>Mobile IP</keyword>
<keyword>NEMO</keyword>
<keyword>Route Optimization</keyword>

<abstract>

<t>
  With current Network Mobility (NEMO) Basic Support, all communications to
  and from Mobile Network Nodes must go through the Mobile Router and
  Home Agent (MRHA) tunnel when the
  mobile network is away.  This results in increased length of packet route
  and increased packet delay in most cases.
  To overcome these limitations, one might have
  to turn to Route Optimization (RO) for NEMO.  This memo documents various
  types of Route Optimization in NEMO and explores the benefits and tradeoffs
  in different aspects of NEMO Route Optimization.
</t>

</abstract>

</front>


<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- MIDDLE: Main Text ------------------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->

<middle>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 1:  INTRODUCTION ------------------------------------------------>
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:intro'
	title="Introduction">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  Network Mobility Route Optimization Problem Statement
  <xref target='RFC4888'/> describes operational
  limitations and overheads incurred in a deployment of
  Network Mobility (NEMO) Basic Support <xref target="RFC3963"/>,
  which could be alleviated by a set of NEMO Route Optimization techniques
  to be defined.  
  <!-- chanwah: I would suggest removing "For this purpose of NEMO"
       and change "is accepted" to "is used" -->
  The term "Route Optimization"
  is used in a broader sense than already defined for IPv6 Host
  Mobility in <xref target="RFC3775"/> to loosely refer to any approach
  that optimizes the transmission of packets between a Mobile Network Node
  and a Correspondent Node.
</t>

<t>
  Solutions that would fit that general description were continuously
  proposed since the early days of NEMO, even before the Working Group
  was formed.
  Based on that long-standing stream of innovation, this document classifies,
  at a generic level, the solution space of the possible approaches
  that could be taken to solve the Route Optimization-related problems
  for NEMO.
<!-- /t>

<t -->
  The scope of the solutions, the benefits, and the impacts to the existing
  implementations and deployments are analyzed. This work should serve as
  a foundation for the NEMO WG to decide where to focus its Route
  Optimization effort, with a deeper understanding of the 
  relative strengths and weaknesses of each approach.
</t>

<t>
  <!--
  It is expected that readers are familiar with terminologies
  related to mobility in <xref target="RFC3775"/> and <xref target="RFC3753"/>,
  and NEMO-related terms defined in <xref target="RFC4885"/>.
  In addition, -->
  It should be beneficial for readers to keep in mind the design requirements of
  NEMO <xref target="RFC4886"/>.  A point to note is that
  since this document discusses aspects of Route Optimization, the reader may
  assume that a mobile network or a mobile host is away when they are mentioned
  throughout this document, unless it is explicitly specified that they are at
  home.
</t>

<!-- [XXXX cwng@20051003: ISSUE 17: Added terminology sub-section XXXX] -->
<section anchor='sec:intro.terms'
         title="Terminology">

<t>
  It is expected that readers are familiar with terminologies
  related to mobility in <xref target="RFC3775"/> and <xref target="RFC3753"/>,
  and NEMO-related terms defined in <xref target="RFC4885"/>.
  In addition, the following Route Optimization-specific terms are used in this
  document:
  
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText='Correspondent Router (CR)'>
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      This refers to the router that is capable of terminating a Route
      Optimization session on behalf of a Correspondent Node.
    </t>
    <t hangText='Correspondent Entity (CE)'>
      <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051003: ISSUE 13: changed CA -> CE XXXX] -->
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      This refers to the entity that a Mobile Router or Mobile Network
      Node attempts to establish a Route Optimization session with.  
      Depending on the Route Optimization approach, the Correspondent Entity
      may be a Correspondent Node or Correspondent Router.
    </t>
    <!-- t hangText='proxy Home Agent (pHA)'>
      <vspace blankLines="1"/> a Mobile IPv6 proxy Home Agent
      acts as a Home Agent for the Mobile Node and as a Mobile Node for the 
      Home Agent, the Correspondent Node, Correspondent Router, and other proxies.
      In particular, the proxy Home Agent terminates the MR-HA tunnel and the associated
      encryption, extracts the packets, and re-encapsulates them to the destination.
    </t -->
  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Intro -- Terminology -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Intro -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 2:  BENEFITS ---------------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:benefits'
	title="Benefits of NEMO Route Optimization">
<!--	title="Design Goals of NEMO Route Optimization" -->

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  NEMO Route Optimization addresses the problems discussed in
  <xref target="RFC4888"/>.
  Although a standardized NEMO Route Optimization
  solution has yet to materialize, one can expect it to show some of the
  following benefits:

  <list style="symbols">
  <t>
    Shorter Delay
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Route Optimization involves the selection and utilization of a lesser-cost
    (thus generally shorter and faster) route to be taken
    for traffic between a Mobile Network Node
    and its Correspondent Node.  Hence, Route Optimization should improve the
    latency of the data traffic between the two end nodes.
    This may
    in turn lead to better overall Quality of Service characteristics,
    such as reduced jitter and packet loss.
  </t>
  <t>
    Reduced Consumption of Overall Network Resources
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Through the selection of a shorter route, the total link utilization for
    all links used by traffic between the two end nodes should be much lower
    than that used if Route Optimization is not carried out.  This would
    result in a lighter network load with reduced congestion.
  </t>
  <t>
    Reduced Susceptibility to Link Failure
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    If a link along the bi-directional tunnel is disrupted, 
    all traffic to and from the
    mobile network will be affected until IP routing recovers from the failure.
    An optimized route would conceivably utilize a smaller number of links
    between the two end nodes.  Hence, the probability of a loss of
    connectivity due to a single point of failure at a link should be lower
    as compared to the longer non-optimized route.
  </t>
  <t>
    Greater Data Efficiency
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Depending on the actual solution for NEMO Route Optimization,
    the data packets exchanged between two end nodes may not require as many
    levels of encapsulation as that in NEMO Basic Support.  This would
    mean less packet overheads and higher data efficiency.  In particular,
    avoiding packet fragmentation that may be induced by the multiple levels
    of tunneling is critical for end-to-end efficiency from the viewpoints
    of buffering and transport protocols.
  </t>
  <vspace blankLines="100"/>
  <t>
    Reduced Processing Delay
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    In a nested mobile network, the application of Route Optimization
    may eliminate the need for multiple encapsulations required by
    NEMO Basic Support, which may result in less processing delay at the
    points of encapsulation and decapsulation.
  </t>
  <t>
    Avoiding a Bottleneck in the Home Network
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    NEMO Route Optimization allows traffic to bypass the Home Agents.
    Apart from having a more direct route, this also avoids routing traffic
    via the home network, which may be a potential bottleneck otherwise.
  </t>
  <t>
    Avoid the Security Policy Issue
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Security policy may forbid a Mobile Router from tunneling
    traffic of Visiting Mobile Nodes into the home network of the Mobile Router.
    Route Optimization
    can be used to avoid this issue by forwarding traffic from Visiting Mobile
    Nodes directly to their destinations without
    going through the home network of the Mobile Router.
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 14 XXXXX] -->
    However, it should be taken into 
    consideration that a Route Optimization mechanism may not be an
    appropriate solution since the Mobile Router may
    still be held responsible for illegal traffic sent from its
    Mobile Network Nodes even when Route Optimization is used.
    In addition, there can be a variety of
    different policies that might conflict with the deployment of
    Route Optimization for Visiting Mobile Nodes.
    Being a policy issue, solving this with a protocol
    at the policy plane might be more appropriate.
  </t>
  <t>
    Avoid the Instability and Stalemate
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    <xref target="RFC4888"/> described a potential
    stalemate situation when a Home Agent is nested within a mobile network.
    Route Optimization may circumvent such stalemate situations
    by directly forwarding traffic upstream.
    <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 14 XXXXX] -->
    However, it should be noted that
    certain Route Optimization schemes may require signaling packets to be
    first routed via the Home Agent before an optimized route can be 
    established.  In such cases, a Route Optimization solution cannot avoid
    the stalemate.
  </t>
  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- Benefits -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 3: DIFFERENT SCENARIOS OF NEMO RO   ----------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:scenarios'
	title="Different Scenarios of NEMO Route Optimization">

<t>
  There are multiple proposals for providing various forms of Route
  Optimization in the NEMO context.  In the following sub-sections,
  we describe the different scenarios that would require a Route
  Optimization mechanism and list the potential solutions that have
  been proposed in that area.
</t>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.mr'
	title="Non-Nested NEMO Route Optimization">
<!--	title="Basic NEMO Route Optimization" -->

<!-- [XXXX cwng@20051230: ISSUE 18 XXXXX] -->
<t>
  The Non-Nested NEMO Route Optimization involves a Mobile Router sending
  binding information to a Correspondent Entity.  It does not involve
  nesting of Mobile Routers or Visiting Mobile Nodes.  The Correspondent
  Entity can be a Correspondent Node or a Correspondent Router.  The interesting
  case is when the Correspondent Entity is a Correspondent Router.
  With the use of Correspondent Router, Route Optimization session is terminated
  at the Correspondent Router on behalf of the Correspondent Node.  As long as the
  Correspondent Router is located "closer" to the Correspondent Node
  than the Home Agent of the Mobile Router, the route between Mobile
  Network Node and the Correspondent Node can be said to be
  optimized.  For this purpose, Correspondent Routers may be deployed
  to provide an optimal route as 
  illustrated in <xref target="fig:CR-based-optimization"/>.

<!-- RFC Editor Comment: Figures 1 and 2 have the same figure title
(i.e., MR-CR Optimization).  Is this correct? -->
<!-- chanwah: We can change title of Figure 2 to "MR-MR Optimization".
I've made the change. -->

  <figure anchor='fig:CR-based-optimization'
        title="MR-CR Optimization">
<artwork><![CDATA[

               ************************** HAofMR
             *                            #*#
           *                            #*#   +---------------------+
         CN                           #*#     |       LEGEND        |
           o                        #*#       +---------------------+
            o   ###############   #*#         | #: Tunnel           |
             CR ooooooooooooooo MR            | *: NEMO Basic route |
                ###############  |            | o: Optimized route  |
                                MNN           +---------------------+
]]></artwork>
  </figure>
</t>
<t>
  This form of optimization can carry traffic in both directions
  or independently for the two directions of traffic:
  <list style='symbols'>
    <t>
      From MNN to CN
      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Mobile Router locates the Correspondent Router, establishes
      a tunnel with that Correspondent Router and sets up a route to
      the Correspondent Node via the Correspondent Router over the
      tunnel.  Traffic to the Correspondent Node would no longer flow
      through the Home Agent anymore.
    </t>
    <t>
      From CN to MNN
      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Correspondent Router is on the path of the traffic from the
      Correspondent Node to the Home Agent.  In addition, it has an
      established tunnel with the current Care-of Address (CoA) of the Mobile
      Router and is aware of the Mobile Network Prefix(es) managed by
      the Mobile Router.  The Correspondent Router can thus intercept
      packets going to the mobile network, and forward them to the
      Mobile Router over the established tunnel.
    </t>
  </list>

  A straightforward approach to Route Optimization in NEMO is for the
  Mobile Router to attempt Route Optimization with a Correspondent Entity.
  This can be viewed as a logical extension to NEMO Basic
  Support, where the Mobile Router would send Binding Updates
  containing one or more Mobile Network Prefix options to the
  Correspondent Entity.  The Correspondent Entity, having received the
  Binding Update, can then set up a bi-directional tunnel with the
  Mobile Router at the current Care-of Address of the Mobile Router,
  and inject a route to its routing table so that packets destined for
  addresses in the Mobile Network Prefix will be routed through the
  bi-directional tunnel.
</t>

<t>
  The definition of Correspondent Router does not limit it to be a fixed router.
  Here we consider the case where the Correspondent Router is a Mobile Router.
  Thus, Route Optimization is initiated and performed
  between a Mobile Router and its peer Mobile Router.  
  Such solutions are often posed with a
  requirement to leave the Mobile Network Nodes untouched, as with the
  NEMO Basic Support protocol, and therefore Mobile Routers handle
  the optimization management on behalf of the Mobile Network Nodes.
  Thus, providing Route Optimization for a Visiting Mobile Node is often out
  of scope for such a scenario because such interaction would require
  extensions to the Mobile IPv6 protocol.  This scenario is
  illustrated in <xref target="fig:MR-based-optimization"/>.

  <vspace blankLines='1'/>

  <figure anchor='fig:MR-based-optimization'
        title="MR-MR Optimization">
<artwork><![CDATA[
HAofCR ********************************** HAofMR
  #*#                                     #*#
    #*#                                 #*#   +---------------------+
      #*#                             #*#     |       LEGEND        |
        #*#                         #*#       +---------------------+
          #*#   ###############   #*#         | #: Tunnel           |
             CR ooooooooooooooo MR            | *: NEMO Basic route |
             |  ###############  |            | o: Optimized route  |
            MNN2                MNN1          +---------------------+
]]></artwork>
  </figure>
</t>

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<t>
  This form of optimization can carry traffic for both directions
  identically:
  <list style='symbols'>
    <t>
      MNN1 to/from MNN2

      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Mobile Router locates the Correspondent Router, establishes
      a tunnel with that Correspondent Router, and sets up a route to
      the Mobile Network Node via the Correspondent Router over the
      tunnel.  Traffic to the Mobile Networks Nodes would no longer
      flow through the Home Agents.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>


<t>
  Examples of this approach include Optimized Route Cache (ORC)
  <xref target="Paper.wakikawa-nemo-orc"
  /><xref target="I-D.wakikawa-nemo-orc"/> and Path Control Header (PCH)
  <xref target="I-D.na-nemo-path-control-header"/>.
</t>

<!--t>[OLD SECTION 3.1]</t>

<t>
  We start off with a scenario where nesting of Mobile Routers is not
  considered, and Route Optimization is initiated and performed
  between a Mobile Router and its peer Mobile Router, also known as a
  Correspondent Router.  Such solutions are often posed with a
  requirement to leave the Mobile Network Nodes untouched, as with the
  NEMO Basic Support protocol, and therefore Mobile Routers handle
  the optimization management on behalf of the Mobile Network Nodes.
  Thus, providing Route Optimization for Visiting Mobile Node is often out
  of scope for such scenario because such interaction would require
  extensions to the Mobile IPv6 protocol.  This scenario is
  illustrated in <xref target="fig:MR-based-optimization"/>.

</t>

<t>
  This form of optimization can carry traffic for both directions
  identically:
  <list style='symbols'>
    <t>
      MNN1 to/from MNN2

      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Mobile Router locates the Correspondent Router, establishes
      a tunnel with that Correspondent Router and sets up a route to
      the Mobile Network Node via the Correspondent Router over the
      tunnel.  Traffic to the Mobile Networks Nodes would no longer
      flow through the Home Agents.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>
  From the definition of Correspondent Router, it does not limit
  itself to be mobile, but can also be an entity within the fixed
  infrastructure with similar functionalities.  As long as the
  Correspondent Router is located "closer" to the Correspondent Node
  than the Home Agent of the Mobile Router, the route between Mobile
  Network Node and the Correspondent Node is somewhat
  optimized.  For this purpose, Correspondent Routers may be deployed
  to provide an optimal route as 
  illustrated in <xref target="fig:CR-based-optimization"/>.

</t>

<t>
  This form of optimization can carry traffic in both directions
  identical to the previous example in 
  <xref target="fig:MR-based-optimization"/>,
  or independently for the 2 directions of traffic:
  <list style='symbols'>
    <t>
      From MNN to CN
      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Mobile Router locates the Correspondent Router, establishes
      a tunnel with that Correspondent Router and sets up a route to
      the Correspondent Node via the Correspondent Router over the
      tunnel.  Traffic to the Correspondent Node would no longer flow
      through the Home Agent anymore.
    </t>
    <t>
      From CN to MNN
      <vspace blankLines='1' /> 

      The Correspondent Router is on the path of the traffic from the
      Correspondent Node to the Home Agent.  In addition, it has an
      established tunnel with the current Care-of Address of the Mobile
      Router and is aware of the Mobile Network Prefix(es) managed by
      the Mobile Router.  The Correspondent Router can thus intercept
      packets going to the mobile network, and forward them to the
      Mobile Router over the established tunnel.
    </t>
  </list>

  A straight-forward approach to Route Optimization in NEMO is for the
  Mobile Router to attempt Route Optimization with a Correspondent Entity.
  This can be viewed as a logical extension to NEMO Basic
  Support, where the Mobile Router would send binding updates
  containing one or more Mobile Network Prefix options to the
  Correspondent Entity.  The Correspondent Entity having received the
  binding update, can then set up a bi-directional tunnel with the
  Mobile Router at the current Care-of Address of the Mobile Router,
  and inject a route to its routing table so that packets destined for
  addresses in the Mobile Network Prefix will be routed through the
  bi-directional tunnel.
</t>

<t>
  Examples of this approach include Optimized Route Cache (ORC)
  <xref target="Paper.wakikawa-nemo-orc"
  /><xref target="I-D.wakikawa-nemo-orc"/> and Path Control Header (PCH)
  <xref target="I-D.na-nemo-path-control-header"/>.
</t-->

</section>

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.nested-mobility'
	title="Nested Mobility Optimization">

<t>
  Optimization in Nested Mobility targets scenarios where a
  nesting of mobility management protocols is created 
  (i.e., Mobile IPv6-enabled host inside
  a mobile network or multiple Mobile Routers that attach behind one
  another creating a nested mobile network).  Note that because
  Mobile IPv6 defines its own Route Optimization mechanism in its base
  protocol suite as a standard, collaboration between this and 
  NEMO protocols brings various complexities.
</t>

<t>
  There are two main aspects in providing optimization for Nested
  Mobility, and they are discussed in the following sub-sections.
</t>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.nested.decrease-ha'
	title="Decreasing the Number of Home Agents on the Path">

<t>
  The aim is to remove the sub-optimality of paths caused by multiple
  tunnels established between multiple Mobile Nodes and their Home
  Agents.  Such a solution will seek to minimize the
  number of Home Agents along the path, by bypassing some of the
  Home Agent(s) from the original path.  Unlike the scenario where no
  nesting is formed and only a single Home Agent exists along the
  path, bypassing one of the many Home Agents can still be effective.
</t>

<t>
  Solutions for Nested Mobility scenarios can usually be divided into
  two cases based on whether the nesting involves Mobile IPv6 hosts or
  only involves Mobile Routers.  Since Mobile IPv6 defines its own
  Route Optimization mechanism, providing an optimal path for such hosts
  will require interaction with the protocol and may require an
  altering of the messages exchanged during the Return Routability
  procedure with the Correspondent Node.
</t>

<t>
  An example of this approach include 
  <!-- MIRON <xref target="I-D.bernardos-nemo-miron"/> and -->
  Reverse Routing Header (RRH)
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.nested.decrease-tunnel'
	title="Decreasing the Number of Tunnels">

<t>
  The aim is to reduce the amplification effect of nested tunnels due
  to the nesting of tunnels between the Visiting Mobile Node and its
  Home Agent within the tunnel between the parent Mobile Router and
  the parent Mobile Router's Home Agent.  
  Such a solution will seek to minimize the number of
  tunnels, possibly by collapsing the amount of tunnels required
  through some form of signaling between Mobile Nodes, or between
  Mobile Nodes and their Home Agents, or by using routing headers to
  route packets through a discovered path.  These limit the
  consequences of the amplification effect of nested tunnels, and at
  best, the performance of a nested mobile network will be the same as
  though there were no nesting at all.
</t>

<t>
  Examples of this approach include the Reverse Routing
  Header (RRH) <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header"/>,
  Access Router Option (ARO) <xref target="I-D.ng-nemo-access-router-option"/>,
  and Nested Path Info (NPI) <xref target="I-D.na-nemo-nested-path-info"/>.
</t>
</section>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Scenarios.Nested -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.infra'
	title="Infrastructure-Based Optimization">

<t>
  An infrastructure-based optimization is an approach where
  optimization is carried out fully in the infrastructure.  One
  example is to make use of Mobility Anchor Points (MAPs)
  such as defined in HMIPv6
 <xref target="RFC4140"/>
  to optimize routes between themselves.  Another example is to make
  use of proxy Home Agent such as defined in the global 
  Home Agent to Home Agent (HAHA)
  protocol
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-global-haha"/>.
  A proxy Home Agent acts as a Home Agent for the 
  Mobile Node, and acts as a Mobile Node for the Home Agent, 
  Correspondent Node, Correspondent Router, and other proxies.
  In particular, the proxy Home Agent terminates the MRHA tunnel 
  and the associated encryption, extracts the packets, 
  and re-encapsulates them to the destination.
  In this case, proxy Home
  Agents are distributed in the infrastructure and each Mobile Router binds
  to the closest proxy.  The proxy, in turn, performs a primary
  binding with a real Home Agent for that Mobile Router.  Then, the
  proxy might establish secondary bindings with other Home Agents or
  proxies in the infrastructure, in order to improve the end-to-end
  path.  In this case, the proxies discover each other using some form
  of Next Hop Resolution Protocol, establish a
  tunnel and exchange the relevant Mobile Network Prefix information
  in the form of explicit prefix routes.
</t>

<t>
  Alternatively, another approach is to use prefix delegation.  Here,
  each Mobile Router in a nested mobile network is delegated a Mobile
  Network Prefix from the access router using DHCP Prefix Delegation
  <!-- xref target="I-D.troan-dhcpv6-opt-prefix-delegation"/ -->
  <xref target="RFC3633"/>.
  Each Mobile Router also autoconfigures its Care-of Address
  from this delegated prefix.  In this way, the Care-of Addresses of
  each Mobile Router are all formed from an aggregatable address space
  starting from the access router.  This may be used to eliminate the
  multiple tunnels caused by nesting of Mobile Nodes.
</t>
</section>

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:scenarios.intra'
	title="Intra-NEMO Optimization">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->
<t>
  A Route Optimization solution
  may seek to improve the communications between two Mobile Network Nodes 
  within a nested mobile network.  This
  would avoid traffic being injected out of the nested mobile network and
<!-- RFC Editor Comment: do you mean "ejected out" instead of
"injected out"?  -->
<!-- chanwah: "ejected" is correct, but sounds wierd ... 
maybe: "forwarded out" would be better -->
  route them within the nested mobile network. 
  An example is the optimized route taken between
  MNN1 and MNN2 in <xref target="fig:nested-example"/> below.
</t>

<figure anchor='fig:nested-example'
	title="An Example of a Nested Mobile Network">
<artwork><![CDATA[

               +--------+  +--------+  +--------+  +--------+
               | MR2_HA |  | MR3_HA |  | MR4_HA |  | MR5_HA |
               +------+-+  +---+----+  +---+----+  +-+------+
                       \       |           |        /
        +--------+    +------------------------------+
        | MR1_HA |----|          Internet            |-----CN
        +--------+    +--------------+---------------+
                                     |
                                +----+----+
                                |   MR1   |
                                +----+----+
                                     |
                      ---+-----------+-----------+---
                         |           |           |
                     +---+---+   +---+---+   +---+---+
                     |  MR5  |   |  MR2  |   |  MR4  |
                     +---+---+   +---+---+   +---+---+
                         |           |           |
                      ---+---    +---+---+    ---+---
                        MNN2     |  MR3  |      MNN3
                                 +---+---+
                                     |
                                 ----+----
                                    MNN1
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
<t>
  One may be able to extend a well-designed NEMO Route Optimization for
  "Nested Mobility Optimization" 
  (see <xref target="sec:scenarios.nested-mobility"/>)
  to provide for such kind of Intra-NEMO optimization, where, for example in
  <xref target="fig:nested-example"/>,  MNN1 is treated as a Correspondent
  Node by <!-- from the perspective of --> MR5/MNN2, and MNN2 is treated as a
  Correspondent Node by <!-- from the view of --> MR3/MNN1.
</t>
<t>
  Another possibility is for the "Non-Nested NEMO Route Optimization" technique
  (see <xref target="sec:scenarios.mr"/>) to
  be applied here.  Using the same example of communication 
  between MNN1 and MNN2, both MR3 and MR2 can treat MR5 as 
  Correspondent Routers for MNN2, and MR5 treats MR3 and MR2 
  as Correspondent Routers for MNN1.  
  <!-- added by cwng@20051021 -->
  An example of this approach is <xref target="I-D.baek-nemo-nested-ro"/>,
  which has the Mobile Routers announce their Mobile Network Prefixes to
  other Mobile Routers in the same nested Mobile Network.
</t>
<t>
  Yet another approach is to flatten any nested Mobile Network so that
  all nested Mobile Network Nodes appear to be virtually on the same link.
  Examples of such approaches include delegating a single prefix to the 
  nested Mobile Network, having Mobile Routers to perform Neighbor Discovery
  on behalf of their Mobile Network Nodes, and exposing a single
  prefix over the entire mobile network using a Mobile Ad-Hoc
  (MANET) protocol.
  In particular, it might prove useful to develop a new type of MANET,
  specialized for the NEMO problem, a MANET for NEMO (MANEMO).
  The MANEMO will optimize the formation of the nested NEMO and maintain
  inner connectivity, whether or not a connection to the infrastructure can be
  established.
</t>

</section>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Scenarios -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 4: ISSUES OF ROUTE OPTIMIZATION  -------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:gen-issues'
	title="Issues of NEMO Route Optimization">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  Although Route Optimization can bring benefits as described in 
  <xref target="sec:benefits"/>, the scenarios described in 
  <xref target="sec:scenarios"/> do so with some tradeoffs.
  This section explores 
  some general issues that may impact a NEMO Route Optimization mechanism.
</t>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.BU-Storm'
	title="Additional Signaling Overhead">

<t>
  The nodes involved in performing Route Optimization would be expected to
  exchange additional signaling messages in order to establish Route
  Optimization.  The required amount of signaling depends on the solution,
  but is likely to exceed the amount required in the home Binding Update
  procedure defined in NEMO Basic Support.
  The amount of signaling is likely to increase with the
  increasing number of
  Mobile Network Nodes and/or Correspondent Nodes,
  and may be amplified with nesting of mobile networks.
  It may scale to unacceptable heights, especially to the resource-scarce
  mobile node, which typically has limited power, memory, and processing
  capacity.
</t>
<t>
  This may lead to an issue that impacts
   NEMO Route Optimization, known as
  the phenomenon of "Binding Update Storm", or more generally,
  "Signaling Storm".  This occurs when a change in point of attachment
  of the mobile network is accompanied with a sudden burst of signaling
  messages, 
  resulting in temporary congestion, packet delays,
  or even packet loss.  This effect will be especially significant for
  wireless environment where bandwidth is relatively limited.
</t>
<t>
  It is possible to moderate the effect of Signaling Storm
  by incorporating mechanisms such as spreading
  the transmissions burst of signaling messages over a longer period of time,
  or aggregating the signaling messages.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 16 XXXX] -->
  Even so, the amount of signaling required might be overwhelming, since large
  mobile networks (such as those deployed on a train or plane) may potentially
  have a large number of flows with a large number of Correspondent Nodes.
  This might suggest a need to have some adaptive behavior that depends on 
  the amount of signaling required versus the effort needed to tunnel home.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- BU-Storm -->

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.complexity'
         title="Increased Protocol Complexity and Processing Load">
<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  It is expected that NEMO Route Optimization will be more complicated
  than NEMO Basic Support.  Thus, complexity
  of nodes that are required to incorporate new functionalities to
  support NEMO Route Optimization would be higher than those required to provide
  NEMO Basic Support.
</t>
<t>
  Coupled with the increased complexity, nodes that are involved
  in the establishment and maintenance of Route Optimization will have to bear
  the
  increased processing load.  If such nodes are mobile, this may prove to be a
  significant cost due to the limited power and processing resources such
  devices usually have.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Complexity -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.longer-handoff'
         title="Increased Delay during Handoff">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  Due to the diversity of locations of different nodes that Mobile Network Node
  may signal with and the complexity of NEMO Route Optimization procedure
  that may cause several rounds of signaling messages, a NEMO Route
  Optimization procedure may take a longer time to finish its handoff than
  that in NEMO Basic Support.  This may exacerbate the overall delay
  during handoffs and further cause performance degradation of the
  applications running on Mobile Network Nodes.
</t>
<t>
  Another NEMO-specific delay during handoff is that in a nested mobile
  network, a child Mobile Network Node may need to detect or be notified of the
  handoff of its parent Mobile Router so that it can begin signaling its
  own Correspondent Entities.  Apart from the compromise of mobility
  transparency and location privacy (see 
  <xref target="sec:gen-issues.mobility-trans"/> and 
  <xref target="sec:gen-issues.loc-priv"/>),
  this mechanism also increases the delay
  during handoffs.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051003: NEW TEXT IN RESPONSE TO ISSUE 5 XXXX] -->
  Some of the solutions for Mobile IPv6, such as Fast Handovers for 
<!-- RFC Editor Comment: note that we changed "handoff" to "handovers"
to match the title of RFC 4068. -->
<!-- chanwah: ok.  Thanks. -->
  Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC4068"/>, may be able to alleviate the increase in
  handoff delay.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Delay During Handoff -->

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.functionalities'
	title="Extending Nodes with New Functionalities">
<!--	title="New Functionalities" -->

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->
<t>
  In order to support NEMO Route Optimization, some nodes need to be changed
  or upgraded.  Smaller number of nodes required to be changed will allow
  for easier adoption of the NEMO Route Optimization solution in the Internet
  and create less impact on existing Internet infrastructure.
  The number and the types of nodes involved with new functionalities
  also affect how much of the route is optimized.
  <!-- vspace blankLines='1'/>
  [XXXX cwng@20051003: NEW TEXT IN RESPONSE TO ISSUE 6 XXXX] -->
  In addition, it may also be beneficial to reuse existing protocols (such as
  Mobile IPv6) as much as possible.
</t>
<t>
  Possible nodes that may be required to change include the following:
  <list style="symbols">
  <t>
    Local Fixed Nodes
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    It may prove to be difficult to introduce new functionalities at
    Local Fixed Nodes, since by definition, any IPv6 node can be a
    Local Fixed Node.  This might mean that only those Local Fixed Nodes
    that are modified can enjoy the benefits of Route Optimization.
  </t>
  <t>
    Visiting Mobile Nodes
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Visiting Mobile Nodes in general should already implement Mobile
    IPv6 functionalities, and since Mobile IPv6 is a relatively new standard,
    there is still a considerable window to allow mobile devices to implement
    new functionalities.
  </t>
  <t>
    Mobile Routers
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    It is expected that Mobile Routers will implement new functionalities in
    order to support Route Optimization.
  </t>
  <t>
    Access Routers
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Some approaches require access routers, or nodes in the access network, to
    implement some new functionalities.  It may prove to be difficult to do so,
    since access routers are, in general, standard IPv6 routers.
  </t>
  <t>
    Home Agents
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    It is relatively easier for new functionalities to be implemented
    in Home Agents.
  </t>
  <t>
    Correspondent Nodes
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    It may prove to be difficult to introduce new functionalities at
    Correspondent Nodes, since by definition, any IPv6 node can be a
    Correspondent Node.  This might mean that only those Correspondent Nodes
    that are modified can enjoy the benefits of Route Optimization.
  </t>
  <t>
    Correspondent Routers
    <vspace blankLines='1'/>
    Correspondent Routers are new entities introduced for the purpose of Route
    Optimization, and therefore new functionalities can be defined as needed.
  </t>
  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- New Functionalities -->

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.detect-new'
	title="Detection of New Functionalities">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->
<t>
  One issue that is related to the need for
  new functionalities as described in
  <xref target="sec:gen-issues.functionalities"/> is the need to detect
  the existence of such functionalities.  In these cases, a detection
  mechanism might be helpful to allow the initiator of
  Route Optimization to detect whether support for the
  new functionalities is available.
  Furthermore, it might be advantageous to have a graceful
  fall back procedure if the required functionalities are unavailable.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Detect Functionalities -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.scalability'
	title="Scalability">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->
<t>
  Given the same number of nodes, the number of Route Optimization sessions
  would usually be more than the number of NEMO Basic Support tunnels.
  If all Route Optimization sessions of a mobile network are maintained
  by a single node (such as the Mobile Router), this would mean that the
  single node has to keep track of the states of all Route Optimization
  sessions.  This may lead to scalability issues especially when that
  single node is a mobile device with limited memory and processing resources.
</t>

<t>
  A similar scalability issue may be faced by a Correspondent Entity as well
  if it maintains many route-optimized sessions on behalf of a 
  Correspondent Node(s) with a large number of Mobile Routers.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Scalability -->

<!-- [XXXX cwng@20051230: ISSUE 19 XXXX] -->
<!--section anchor='sec:gen-issues.mobility-aware'
	title="[OLD] Mobility Transparency and Location Privacy">

<t>
  One advantage of NEMO Basic Support is that the
  Correspondent Nodes and
  Mobile Network Nodes need not be aware of the actual location and mobility
  of the mobile network.  With Route Optimization, it might be necessary to
  reveal the point of attachment of the Mobile Router to other nodes,
  such as the Mobile Network Nodes or their
  Correspondent Nodes.
  This may mean a tradeoff between location privacy
  <xref target='RFC4651'/>
  (and mobility transparency) and Route Optimization.
</t>
<t>
  In Mobile IPv6, a mobile node can decide whether or
  not to perform Route Optimization with a given Correspondent Node.
  Thus, the mobile node is in control of whether to trade location privacy
  for an optimized route.  
  In NEMO Route Optimization, if
  the decision to perform Router Optimization is made by the Mobile Router,
  it will be difficult for Mobile Network Nodes to
  control the decision of having this tradeoff.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Mobility Awareness -->
<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.mobility-trans'
	title="Mobility Transparency">

<t>
  One advantage of NEMO Basic Support is that the Mobile Network Nodes 
  need not be aware of the actual location and mobility of the mobile network.  
  With some approaches for Route Optimization, it might be necessary to
  reveal the point of attachment of the Mobile Router to the 
  Mobile Network Nodes.
  This may mean a tradeoff between mobility transparency
  and Route Optimization.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Mobility Awareness -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.loc-priv'
	title="Location Privacy">

<t>
  Without Route Optimization, the Correspondent Nodes are not aware of 
  the actual location and mobility of the mobile network and its Mobile 
  Network Nodes.  To achieve Route Optimization, it might be necessary to
  reveal the point of attachment of the Mobile Router to the
  Correspondent Nodes.
  This may mean a tradeoff between location privacy
  <xref target='RFC4651'/>
  and Route Optimization.
</t>
<t>
  In Mobile IPv6, a mobile node can decide whether or
  not to perform Route Optimization with a given Correspondent Node.
  Thus, the mobile node is in control of whether to trade location privacy
  for an optimized route.  
  In NEMO Route Optimization, if
  the decision to perform Router Optimization is made by the Mobile Router,
  it will be difficult for Mobile Network Nodes to
  control the decision of having this tradeoff.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Mobility Awareness -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.security'
	title="Security Consideration">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->
<t>
  As Mobile Router and Home Agent usually belong to the same
  administration domain, it is likely that there exists a security association
  between them, which is leveraged by NEMO Basic Support to conduct
  the home Binding Update in a secure way.  However, NEMO Route
  Optimization usually involves nodes from different domains
  (for example, Mobile Router and Correspondent Entity);
  thus, the existence of such a
  security association is not a valid assumption in many
  deployment scenarios.  
  <!-- chanwah: too many "thus" ... changed to "For this reason" -->
  For this reason, the security protection of NEMO Route
  Optimization signaling message is considered "weaker" than that
  in NEMO Basic Support.
  It is expected that some additional security mechanisms are needed to achieve
  the same or similar level of security as in NEMO Basic Support.
</t>
<t>
  When considering security issues of NEMO Route Optimization,
  it might be useful to keep in mind some of the security issues considered
  when Mobile IPv6 Route Optimization was designed as documented in
  <xref target="RFC4225"/>.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Security -->

<section anchor='sec:gen-issues.legacy'
	title="Support of Legacy Nodes">

<!-- t>
  [XXXX cwng@20051003: NEW SECTION IN RESPONSE TO ISSUE 3 XXXX]  
  I am not so sure this is an issue, but added this temporarily.
</t -->
<t>
  NEMO Basic Support is designed so that all legacy Mobile Network Nodes
  (such as those that are not aware of the mobility of the network they are in, 
  and those that do not understand any mobility protocols) can still reach 
  and be reached from the Internet.  Some Route Optimization schemes, however,
  require that all Mobile Routers implement the same Route Optimization
  scheme in order for them to operate.  
  <!-- For instance -->Thus, a nested Mobile Router may not be able to 
  achieve Route Optimization if it is attached to a legacy Local Fixed Router.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -- Legacy Nodes -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: General Issues -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 5:  ANALYSIS OF SOLUTION SPACE  --------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:analysis'
	title="Analysis of Solution Space">

<t>
  As described in <xref target="sec:scenarios"/>,
  there are various different approaches to achieve Route Optimization in
  Network Mobility Support.  In this section, we attempt to analyze the vast
  solution space of NEMO Route Optimization by asking the following questions:
  <list style="numbers">
    <t>Which entities are involved?</t>
    <t>Who initiates Route Optimization? When?</t>
<!-- RFC Editor Comment: This list seems to be composed of the
subsequent section headings.  Should they match the headings entirely?
For example, should "Who initiates signaling? When?" be "Who initiates
route optimization? When?" --> 
<!-- chanwah: Yes, they should.  I've made the changes. -->
  <t>How is Route Optimization capabilities detected?</t>
    <t>How is the address of the Mobile Network Node represented?</t>
    <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051010: was "How is identity represented?" XXXX] -->
    <t>How is the Mobile Network Node's address bound to location?</t>
    <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051010: was "How is identity bound to location?" XXXX] -->
    <t>How is signaling performed?</t>
    <t>How is data transmitted?</t>
    <t>What are the security considerations?</t>
  </list>
</t>

<section anchor='sec:analysis.entities'
	 title="Which Entities Are Involved?">

<t>
  There are many combinations of entities involved in Route
  Optimization.  When considering the role each entity plays
  in Route Optimization, one has to bear in mind the considerations
  described in <xref target='sec:gen-issues.functionalities'/> and
  <xref target='sec:gen-issues.detect-new'/>.  Below is a list of
  combinations to be discussed in the following sub-sections:

  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Mobile Network Node and Correspondent Node
    </t>
    <t>
      Mobile Router and Correspondent Node
    </t>
    <t>
      Mobile Router and Correspondent Router
    </t>
    <t>
      Entities in the Infrastructure
    </t>
    <!-- t>
      Two Mobile Network Nodes
    </t -->
  </list>
</t>

<section anchor='sec:analysis.entities.MNN-CN'
	title="Mobile Network Node and Correspondent Node">

<t>
  <!-- Description -->
  A Mobile Network Node can establish Route Optimization
  with its Correspondent Node, possibly the same way as
  a Mobile Node establishes Route Optimization with its 
  Correspondent Node in Mobile IPv6.
  <!-- degree -->
  This would achieve the most optimal route,
  since the entire end-to-end path is optimized.
  <!-- Scalability -->
  However, there might be scalability issues since both the Mobile Network
  Node and the Correspondent Node may need to maintain many Route Optimization
  sessions.
  <!-- New functionalities -->
  In addition, new functionalities would be required for both the 
  Mobile Network Node and Correspondent Node.
  <!-- NEW: Issue 20 -->
  For the Mobile Network Node, it needs to be able to manage its mobility,
  and possibly be aware of the 
<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
mobility of its upstream Mobile Router(s).
  For the Correspondent Node, it needs to be able to maintain the bindings
  sent by the Mobile Network Nodes.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Entities -- MNN-CN -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.entities.MR-CN'
	title="Mobile Router and Correspondent Node">

<t>
  <!-- Description -->
  Alternatively, the Mobile Router can establish Route Optimization 
  with a Correspondent Node on behalf of the Mobile Network Node.
  <!-- degree -->
  <!-- Since the Mobile Router is merely one hop away from the Mobile 
  Network Node, -->
  Since all packets to and from the Mobile Network Node must transit the
  Mobile Router, this effectively achieves an optimal route for the
  entire end-to-end path as well.
  <!-- Scalability -->
  Compared with <xref target="sec:analysis.entities.MNN-CN"/>, 
  the scalability issue
  here may be remedied since it is possible for the Correspondent Node 
  to maintain only one session with the Mobile Router if it communicates
  with many Mobile Network Nodes associated with the same Mobile Router.
  <!-- New functionality -->
  Furthermore, with the Mobile Router handling Route Optimization,
  there is no need for Mobile Network Nodes to implement new 
  functionalities.  However, new functionality is likely to be
  required on the Correspondent Node.
  <!-- vspace blankLines='1'/>
  [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 16 XXXX] -->
  An additional point of consideration is the amount of state 
  information the Mobile Router is required to maintain.  
  Traditionally, it has been generally avoided having
  state information in the routers to increase proportionally with
  the number of pairs of communicating peers.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Entitities -- MR-CN -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.entities.MR-CR'
	title="Mobile Router and Correspondent Router">

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

<t>
  Approaches involving Mobile Routers and Correspondent Routers
  are described in <xref target="sec:scenarios.mr"/>.
  The advantage of these approaches is that no additional functionality
  is required for the Correspondent Node and Mobile Network Nodes.
  In addition, location privacy is relatively preserved, since the
  current location of the mobile network is only revealed to the
  Correspondent Router and not to the Correspondent Node 
  (please refer to <xref target="sec:analysis.security.privacy"/> for
  more discussions).  Furthermore,
  if the Mobile Router and Correspondent Router exchange prefix
  information, this approach may scale well since a single
  Route Optimization session between the Mobile Router and 
  Correspondent Router can achieve Route Optimization between 
  any Mobile Network Node in the mobile
  network, and any Correspondent Node managed by the Correspondent Router.
</t>
<t>
  The main concern with this approach is the need for a mechanism to
  allow the Mobile Router to detect the presence of the Correspondent Router
  (see <xref target="sec:analysis.RO-detect"/> for details),
  and its security impact.  Both the Mobile Router and the Correspondent 
  Router need some means to verify the validity of each other.  This
  is discussed in greater detail in <xref target="sec:analysis.security"/>.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051010: ISSUE 7:  SCALABILITY and DEPLOYMENT XXXX] -->
  A deployment consideration with respect to the use of 
  Correspondent Router is the location of the Correspondent Router 
  relative to the Correspondent Node.  On one hand, deploying the 
  Correspondent Router nearer to the Correspondent Node would result
  in a more optimal path.  On the other hand, a Correspondent Router 
  that is placed farther away from the Correspondent Node can perform
  Route Optimization on behalf of more Correspondent Nodes.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Entities -- MR-CR -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.entities.infrastructure'
	title="Entities in the Infrastructure">

<t>
  Approaches using entities in the infrastructure are described in
  <xref target="sec:scenarios.infra"/>.  The advantages of this approach
  include, firstly, not requiring new functionalities to be implemented
  on the Mobile Network Nodes and Correspondent Nodes, and secondly, having
  most of the complexity shifted to nodes in the infrastructure.  
  However, one main issue with this approach is how the Mobile Router can
  detect the presence of such entities, and why the Mobile Router should
  trust these entities.  This may be easily addressed if such entity is
  a Home Agent of the Mobile Router (such as in the global Home Agent to
  Home Agent protocol
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-global-haha"/>).
  Another concern is that the resulting path may not be
  a true optimized one, since it depends on the relative positions of the
  infrastructure entities with respect to the mobile network and the
  Correspondent Node.
</t>

<!-- cwng@20050911: comments from -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Entitities -- Infrastructure -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Entities -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.initiate'
	 title="Who Initiates Route Optimization? When?">

<!-- t>[XXXX cwng@20051003: changed "mobile" -> 'moving" in a feeble attempt 
	to resolve ISSUE 8 XXXX]</t -->
<t>
  Having determined the entities involved in the Route Optimization in
  the previous sub-section, the next question is which of these entities
  should initiate the Route Optimization session. 
  Usually, the node that is moving (i.e., Mobile Network Node or Mobile Router) 
  is in the best position to detect its mobility.  Thus, in general, 
  it is better for the mobile node to initiate the Route Optimization 
  session in order to handle the topology changes in any kind of mobility 
  pattern and achieve the optimized route promptly.  
  However, when the mobile node is within a nested mobile network, the
  detection of the mobility of upstream Mobile Routers may need to be 
  conveyed to the nested Mobile Network Node.  
  This might incur longer signaling delay as discussed in 
  <xref target="sec:gen-issues.longer-handoff"/>.
</t>
<t>
  Some solution may enable the node on the correspondent side to 
  initiate the Route Optimization session in certain situations.  For instance, when
  the Route Optimization state that is already established on the
  Correspondent Entity is about to expire but the 
  communication is still active, depending on the policy,
  the Correspondent Entity may initiate a Route Optimization
  request with the mobile node side.
</t>
<t>
  There is also the question of when Route Optimization should be initiated.  
  Because Route Optimization would <!--most--> 
  certainly incur tradeoffs of various forms,
  it might not be desirable for Route Optimization to be performed for any kind of 
  traffic.  This is, however, implementation specific and policy driven.
</t>

<t>
  A related question is how often signaling messages should be sent to maintain 
  the Route Optimization session.  Typically, signaling messages are likely
  to be sent whenever there are topological changes.  The discussion in
  <xref target="sec:gen-issues.BU-Storm"/> should be considered.
  In addition, a Lifetime value is often used to indicate
  the period of validity for the Route Optimization session.  Signaling messages
  would have to be sent before the Lifetime value expires in order to maintain
  the Route Optimization session.  The choice of Lifetime value needs to balance
  between different considerations.  On one hand, a short Lifetime value would
  increase the amount of signaling overhead.  On the other hand, a long
  Lifetime value may expose the Correspondent Entity to the risk of having an
  obsolete binding cache entry, which creates an opportunity for an
  attacker to exploit.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Who & When -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.RO-detect'
	 title="How Is Route Optimization Capability Detected?">

<t>
  The question here is how the initiator of Route Optimization 
  knows whether the Correspondent Entity supports the functionality required
  to established a Route Optimization session.  
  The usual method is for the initiator to attempt Route Optimization with the
  Correspondent Entity.  Depending on the protocol specifics, the initiator 
  may receive (i) a reply from the Correspondent Entity indicating 
  its capability, (ii) an error message from the Correspondent Entity, or (iii)
  no response from the Correspondent Entity within a certain time period.  
  This serves as an indication of whether or not the Correspondent Entity supports
  the required functionality to establish Route Optimization.
  This form of detection may incur additional delay as a penalty when 
  the Correspondent Entity does not have Route Optimization capability,
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051003: ISSUE 9 XXXX] -->
  especially when the Route Optimization mechanism is using in-band signaling.
</t>
<t>
  When the Correspondent Entity is not the Correspondent Node but a 
  Correspondent Router, an immediate question is how its presence
  can be detected.  One approach is for the initiator to send an
  Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP) message containing the
  address of the Correspondent Node to a well-known
  anycast address reserved for all Correspondent Routers
  <xref target="Paper.wakikawa-nemo-orc"
  /><xref target="I-D.wakikawa-nemo-orc"/>.  Only the Correspondent Router
  that is capable of terminating the Route Optimization session on behalf of
  the Correspondent Node will respond.  Another way is to insert a
  Router Alert Option (RAO) into a packet sent to the Correspondent Node
  <xref target="I-D.na-nemo-path-control-header"/>.  Any Correspondent Router
  en route will process the Router Alert Option and send a response to the
  Mobile Router.
</t>
<t>
  Both approaches need to consider the possibility of multiple Correspondent
  Routers responding to the initiator, and both approaches will generate
  additional traffic or processing load to other routers.  Furthermore, both
  approaches have yet to consider how the initiator can verify the
  authenticity of the Correspondent Routers that responded.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Detect -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.identity'
	 title="How is the Address of the Mobile Network Node Represented?">
<!--	 title="How Is Identity Represented?"-->

<!-- t>[XXXX cwng@20051010: ISSUE 12: "identity" -> "MNN's Address" XXXX]</t -->
<t>
  Normally, Route Optimization would mean that a binding between the address of 
  a Mobile Network Node and the location of the mobile network is registered at 
  the Correspondent Entity.
  Before exploring different ways of binding (see
  <xref target="sec:analysis.binding"/>), one must first ask how the address
  of the Mobile Network Node is represented.  Basically, there are two ways to
  represent the Mobile Network Node's address: 
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>inferred by the use of the Mobile Network Prefix, or</t>
    <t>explicitly specifying the address of the Mobile Network Node.</t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>
  Using the Mobile Network Prefix would usually mean that the initiator is the Mobile
  Router, and has the benefit of binding numerous Mobile Network Nodes with one
  signaling.  However, it also means that if location privacy is compromised, 
  the location privacy of an entire Mobile Network Prefix would be compromised.
</t>
<t>
  On the other hand, using the Mobile Network Node's address would
  mean that either
  the initiator is the Mobile Network Node itself or the Mobile Router is
  initiating Route Optimization on behalf of the Mobile Network Node.  Initiation
  by the Mobile Network Node itself means that the Mobile Network Node must have
  new functionalities implemented, while initiation by the Mobile Router means 
  that the Mobile Router must maintain some Route Optimization states for each 
  Mobile Network Node.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Identity -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.binding'
	 title="How Is the Mobile Network Node's Address Bound to Location?">
<!--	 title="How Is Identity Bound to Location?" -->

<!-- t>[XXXX cwng@20051010: ISSUE 12: "identity" -> "address" XXXX]</t -->
<t>
  In order for route to be optimized, it is generally necessary for the
  Correspondent Entity to create a binding between the address and the
  location of the Mobile Network Node.  This can be done in the following
  ways:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>binding the address to the location of the parent Mobile Router,</t>
    <t>binding the address to a sequence of upstream
	    Mobile Routers, and</t>
    <t>binding the address to the location of the root Mobile Router.</t>
  </list>
  These are described in the following sub-sections.
</t>

<section anchor='sec:analysis.binding.parent'
	 title="Binding to the Location of Parent Mobile Router">

<t>
  By binding the address of Mobile Network Node to the location of its
  parent Mobile Router, the Correspondent Entity would know how to reach
  the Mobile Network Node via the current location of the parent Mobile 
  Router.  This can be done by:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Binding Update with Mobile Network Prefix
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This can be viewed as a logical extension to NEMO Basic Support,
      where the Mobile Router would send binding updates containing one
      or more Mobile Network Prefix options to the Correspondent Entity.
      The Correspondent Entity having received the Binding Update, can then
      set up a bi-directional tunnel with the Mobile Router at the current
      Care-of Address of the Mobile Router, and inject a route to its routing
      table so that packets destined for addresses in the Mobile Network
      Prefix would be routed through the bi-directional tunnel.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Note that in this case, the address of the Mobile Network Node is
      implied by the Mobile Network Prefix 
      (see <xref target="sec:analysis.identity"/>).
    </t>
    <t>
      Sending Information of Parent Mobile Router
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This involves the Mobile Network Node sending the information of its
      Mobile Router to the Correspondent Entity, thus allowing the Correspondent
      Entity to establish a binding between the address of the Mobile Network
      Node to the location of the parent Mobile Router.  An example of
      such an approach would be <xref target="I-D.ng-nemo-access-router-option"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      Mobile Router as a Proxy
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Another approach is for the parent Mobile Router to act as a "proxy" for 
      its Mobile Network Nodes.  In this case, the Mobile Router uses the
      standard Mobile IPv6 Route Optimization procedure to bind the address 
      of a Mobile Network Node to the Mobile Router's Care-of Address.  
      <!-- vspace blankLines='1'/>
      [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 11 XXXX] -->
      For instance, when the Mobile Network Node is a Local Fixed Node without
      Mobile IPv6 Route Optimization functionality, the Mobile Router may initiate
      the Return Routability procedure with a Correspondent Node on behalf of the
      Local Fixed Node.  An example of such an approach would be 
      <xref target="Paper.miron" /><xref target="Paper.miron2" /><xref target="I-D.bernardos-nemo-miron"/>.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      On the other hand, if the Mobile Network Node is a Visiting Mobile Node,
      it might be necessary for the Visiting Mobile Node to delegate the rights
      of Route Optimization signaling to the Mobile Router 
      (see <xref target="Paper.ndss-ylitalo"/> for an example of such delegation).  
      With this delegation, either the Visiting Mobile Network Node or the 
      Mobile Router can initiate the Return Routability procedure with the 
      Correspondent Node.  For the case where the Return Routability procedure is 
      initiated by the Visiting Mobile Node, the Mobile Router will have to
      transparently
      alter the content of the Return Routability signaling messages so that packets
      sent from the Correspondent Node to the Visiting Node will be routed to the 
      Care-of Address of the Mobile Router once Route Optimization is established.
      The case where the Return Routability procedure is initiated by the
      Mobile Router is similar to the case where the Mobile Network Node is a Local
      Fixed Node.
    </t>
    <!--
    <t>
      Mobile Router as a Transparent Proxy
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      A somewhat similar approach involves the Mobile Router transparently 
      altering packets transmitted with Mobile IPv6 Route Optimization (such as
      altering messages exchanged during the return routability procedure
      between a Visiting Mobile Node and its Correspondent Node),
      so that packets sent from Correspondent Node to the Visiting Mobile
      Node will be routed to the Care-of Address of the Mobile Router once
      Route Optimization is established.
      This should be contrasted against "Mobile Router as a Proxy".  
      Here, the Mobile Router relies on the Visiting Mobile Node to 
      start the Return Routability procedure, and alters the contents 
      of the messages in Return Routability procedure to achieve 
      Route Optimization.   Whereas in "Mobile Router as a Proxy", 
      the Mobile Router initiates the Return Routability procedure
      on its own.  
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 11 XXXX]
      It might not be possible for the Mobile Router to inspect or change
      packets sent by the Visiting Mobile Node if the packets are encrypted
      in a tunnel between the Visiting Mobile Node and its Home Agent.
    </t>
    -->
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  <!-- Complexity -->
  For all of the approaches listed above, when the Mobile Network Node is 
  deeply nested within a Mobile Network, the Correspondent Entity would need
  to gather Binding Updates from all the upstream Mobile Routers in order
  to build the complete route to reach the Mobile Network Node.  
  This increases the complexity of the Correspondent Entity, as the Correspondent
  Entity may need to perform multiple binding cache look-ups before it can
  construct the complete route.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- signaling delay and overhead -->
  Other than increasing the complexity of the Correspondent Entity, these
  approaches may incur extra signaling overhead and delay for a nested 
  Mobile Network Node.  For instance, every Mobile Router on the upstream
  of the Mobile Network Node needs to send Binding Updates to the Correspondent
  Entity.  If this is done by the upstream Mobile Routers independently,
  it may incur additional signaling overhead.  Also, since each Binding Update
  takes a finite amount of time to reach and be processed by the Correspondent
  Entity, the delay from the time an optimized route is changed till the time
  the change is registered on the Correspondent Entity will increase proportionally
  with the number of Mobile Routers on the upstream of the Mobile Network Node
  (i.e., the level of nesting of the Mobile Network Node).
</t>
<t>
  <!-- New Functionality -->
  For "Binding Update with Mobile Network Prefix" and 
  "Sending Information of Parent Mobile Router", new functionality is 
<!-- RFC Editor Comment: should this match what appears in the
bulleted list on the previous page?  That is, should "Sending
Information of Upstream Mobile Router" be "Sending Information of
Parent Mobile Router"?  -->
<!-- chanwah: Yes, it should.  I've made the change -->
  required at the Correspondent Entity, whereas "Mobile Router as a Proxy"
  <!-- and "Mobile Router as a Transparent Proxy" --> keeps the functionality of
  the Correspondent Entity the same as a Mobile IPv6 Correspondent
  Node.  However, this is done at an expense of the Mobile Routers, since in 
  "Mobile Router as a Proxy"<!--and "Mobile Router as a Transparent Proxy"-->,
  the Mobile Router must maintain state information for every Route Optimization
  session its Mobile Network Nodes have.  Furthermore, <!-- for "Mobile Router
  as a Transparent Proxy"-->in some cases, the Mobile Router needs to look beyond 
  the standard IPv6 headers for ingress and egress packets,
  and alter the packet contents appropriately (this may impact
end-to-end integrity, see 5.8.2).  
</t>
<t>
  <!-- no changes to existing protocol -->
  One advantage shared by all the approaches listed here is that only mobility 
  protocol is affected.  In other words, no modification is 
<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
required on other
  existing protocols (such as Neighbor Discovery).  There is also no 
  additional requirement on existing infrastructure (such as the access
  network).
</t>
<t>
  <!-- memory requirement -->
  In addition, having upstream Mobile Routers send Binding Updates independently
  means that the Correspondent Entity can use the same binding cache entries of
  upstream Mobile Routers to construct the complete route to two Mobile Network
  Nodes that have common upstream Mobile Routers.  This may translate to lower
  memory consumption since the Correspondent Entity need not store one complete 
  route per Mobile Network Node when it is having Route Optimization sessions
  with multiple Mobile Network Nodes from the same mobile network.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Binding -- Parent -->

<!-- vspace blankLines='100'/ -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.binding.sequence'
	 title="Binding to a Sequence of Upstream Mobile Routers">

<t>
  For a nested Mobile Network Node, it might be more worthwhile to
  bind its address to the sequence of points of attachment of upstream 
  Mobile Routers.  In this way, the Correspondent Entity can build
  a complete sequence of points of attachment from a single transmission 
  of the binding information.  Examples using this approach are 
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header"/> and
  <xref target="I-D.na-nemo-nested-path-info"/>.
</t>
<t>
  Different from <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/>, this approach
  constructs the complete route to a specific Mobile Network Node at the
  mobile network side, thus offering the opportunity to reduce the signaling
  overhead.  Since the complete route is conveyed to the Correspondent Entity 
  in a single transmission, it is possible to reduce the delay from the time 
  an optimized route is changed till the time the change is registered on the
  Correspondent Entity to its minimum.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- how to get upstream locations? -->
  One question that immediately comes to mind is how the 
  Mobile Network Node gets hold of the sequence of locations of 
  its upstream Mobile Routers.  This is usually achieved by having such information
  inserted as special options in the Router Advertisement messages advertised
  by upstream Mobile Routers.  To do so, not only must a
  Mobile Router advertise its current location to its Mobile Network Nodes, 
  it must also relay information embedded in Router Advertisement messages 
  it has received from its upstream Mobile Routers.
  <!-- mobility transparency -->
  This might imply a compromise of the mobility transparency of a mobile network
  (see <xref target="sec:gen-issues.mobility-trans"/>).
  <!-- signaling storm -->
  In addition, it also means that whenever an upstream Mobile Router changes its
  point of attachment, all downstream Mobile Network Nodes must perform Route
  Optimization signaling again, possibly leading to a "Signaling Storm"
  (see <xref target="sec:gen-issues.BU-Storm"/>).
</t>
<t>
<!-- chanwah: some modification here: -->
  A different method of conveying locations of upstream Mobile Routers is 
  (such as used in
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header"/>) where upstream Mobile
  Routers insert their current point of attachment into a Reverse Routing Header
  embedded within a packet sent by the Mobile Network Node.  
  This may raise security concerns that will be discussed later in 
  <xref target="sec:analysis.security.e2e"/>.
</t>
<!--<vspace blankLines='1'/>-->
<t>
  <!-- new functionalities -->
  In order for a Correspondent Entity to bind the address of a Mobile Network Node 
  to a sequence of locations of upstream Mobile Routers, new functionalities need 
  to be implemented on the Correspondent Entity.  
  <!-- memory requirement -->
  The Correspondent Entity also needs to store the complete sequence of locations
  of upstream Mobile Routers for every Mobile Network Node.  
  This may demand more memory compared to 
  <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/> if the same Correspondent Entity
  has a lot of Route Optimization sessions with Mobile Network Nodes from
  the same nested Mobile Network.
  <!-- impact on existing protocols -->
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051017: ISSUE #10: XXXX] -->
  In addition, some amount of modifications or extension to existing protocols is 
  also required, such as a new type of IPv6 routing header or a new
  option in the Router Advertisement message.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Binding -- Sequence -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.binding.root'
	 title="Binding to the Location of Root Mobile Router">

<t>
  A third approach is to bind the address of the Mobile Network Node
  to the location of the root Mobile Router, regardless of how deeply 
  nested the Mobile Network Node is within a nested Mobile Network.
  Whenever the Correspondent Entity needs to 
  forward a packet to the Mobile Network Node, it only needs to forward the packet
  to this point of attachment.  The mobile network will figure out how to
  forward the packet to the Mobile Network Node by itself.  This kind of
  approach can be viewed as flattening the structure of a nested Mobile Network,
  so that it seems to the Correspondent Entity that every node in the
  Mobile Network is attached to the Internet at the same network segment.
</t>
<t>
  There are various approaches to achieve this:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Prefix Delegation
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Here, each Mobile Router in a nested mobile network is delegated a Mobile
      Network Prefix from the access router (such as using Dynamic
      Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) Prefix Delegation
      <!-- xref target="I-D.troan-dhcpv6-opt-prefix-delegation"/>). -->
      <xref target="RFC3633"/>).
      Each Mobile Router also autoconfigures its Care-of Address from this
      delegated prefix.  In this way, the Care-of Addresses of Mobile
      Routers are all from an aggregatable address space starting from the
      access router.  A Mobile Network Node with Mobile IPv6 functionality
      may also autoconfigure its Care-of Address from this
      delegated prefix, and use standard Mobile IPv6 mechanism's to bind
      its Home Address to this Care-of Address.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Examples of this approach include <xref target="I-D.perera-nemo-extended"/>,
      <xref target="Paper.leekj-nemo-ro-pd"/>, and <xref target="I-D.leekj-nemo-ro-pd"/>.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This approach has the advantage of keeping the implementations
      of Correspondent Nodes unchanged.  However, it 
      requires the access router (or some other entity within
      the access network) and Mobile Router to possess prefix delegation
      functionality, and also
      maintain information on what prefix is delegated to which node.  
      How to efficiently assign a subset of Mobile Network Prefix to child
      Mobile Routers could be an issue because Mobile Network Nodes may dynamically
      join and leave with an unpredictable pattern.  In addition,
      a change in the point of attachment of the root Mobile Router will also
      require every nested Mobile Router (and possibly Visiting Mobile Nodes)
      to change their Care-of Addresses and delegated prefixes.  These will
      cause a burst of Binding Updates and prefix delegation activities where
      every Mobile Router and every Visiting Mobile Node start sending Binding
      Updates to their Correspondent Entities.
    </t>
    <t>
      Neighbor Discovery Proxy
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This approach (such as <xref target="Paper.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy"
      /> and <xref target="I-D.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy"/>)
      achieves Route Optimization by
      having the Mobile Router act as a Neighbor Discovery <xref target="RFC2461"/>
      proxy for its Mobile Network Nodes.  The Mobile Router will configure a Care-of
      Address from the network prefix advertised by its access router,
      and also relay this prefix to its subnets.  When a Mobile Network Node
      configures an address from this prefix, the Mobile Router will act as
      a Neighbor Discovery proxy on its behalf.  In this way, the entire mobile
      network and its access network form a logical multilink subnet,
      thus eliminating any nesting.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This approach has the advantage of keeping the implementations
      of Correspondent Nodes unchanged.  However, it requires
      the root Mobile Router to act as a Neighbor
      Discovery proxy for all the Mobile Network Nodes that are directly
      or indirectly attached to it.  This increases the processing load
      of the root Mobile Router.  In addition,
      a change in the point of attachment of the root Mobile Router will
      require every nested Mobile Router (and possibly Visiting Mobile Nodes)
      to change their Care-of Addresses.  Not only will this cause a burst
      of Binding Updates where every Mobile Router and every Visiting Mobile Node
      start sending Binding Updates to their Correspondent Entities, 
      it will also cause a
      burst of Duplicate Address Discovery messages to be exchanged between the
      mobile network and the access network.
      <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 2 XXXX] -->
      Furthermore, Route Optimization for Local Fixed Nodes is not possible
      without new functionalities implemented on the Local Fixed Nodes.
    </t>
    <t>
      Hierarchical Registrations
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Hierarchical Registration involves Mobile Network Nodes (including
      nested Mobile Routers) registering themselves with either their
      parent Mobile Routers or the root Mobile Router itself.
      After registrations, Mobile Network Nodes would tunnel packets directly
      to the upstream Mobile Router they register with.  At the root Mobile Router,
      packets tunneled from sub-Mobile Routers or Mobile Network Nodes are
      tunneled directly to the Correspondent Entities, thus avoiding nested tunneling.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      One form of such an approach uses the principle
      of Hierarchical Mobile IPv6  <xref target="RFC4140"/>,
      where the root Mobile Router acts as a Mobility Anchor Point.  It is
      also possible for each parent Mobile Router to act as Mobility
      Anchor Points for its child Mobile Routers, thus forming a hierarchy
      of Mobility Anchor Points.  One can also view these Mobility Anchor
      Points as local Home Agents, thus forming a cascade of mobile Home Agents.
      In this way, each Mobile Router terminates its tunnel at its parent
      Mobile Router.  Hence, although there are equal numbers of tunnels as
      the level of nestings, there is no tunnel encapsulated within another.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Examples of this approach include <xref target="I-D.hkang-nemo-ro-tlmr"/>,
      <xref target="Paper.lee-hro"/>, <xref target="Paper.ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip"
      />, and <xref target="I-D.ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip"/>.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      An advantage of this approach is that the functionalities of
      the Correspondent Nodes are unchanged.
    </t>
    <t>
      Mobile Ad-Hoc Routing
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      It is possible for nodes within a mobile network to use Mobile Ad-hoc
      routing for packet-forwarding between nodes in the same
      mobile network.  An approach of doing so might involve a router
      acting as a gateway for connecting nodes in the mobile network
      to the global Internet.   All nodes in the mobile network would
      configure their Care-of Addresses from one or more prefixes advertised by
      that gateway, while their parent Mobile Routers use Mobile Ad-hoc routing 
      to forward packets to that gateway or other destinations inside the mobile
      network.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  One advantage that is common to all the approaches listed above is that
  local mobility of a Mobile Network Node within a nested mobile network 
  is hidden from the Correspondent Entity.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Binding -- Parent -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Binding -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.signaling'
	 title="How Is Signaling Performed?">

<t>
  In general, Route Optimization signaling can be done either in-plane, 
  off-plane, or both.  In-plane signaling involves
  embedding signaling information into headers of data packets.
  A good example of in-plane signaling would be Reverse Routing Header
  <xref target="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header"/>.
  Off-plane signaling uses dedicated signaling packets rather than embedding 
  signaling information into headers of data packets.  
  Proposals involving the sending of Binding Updates fall
  into this category.
</t>
<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
<t>
  The advantage of in-plane signaling is
  that any change in the mobile network topology can be rapidly propagated
  to the Correspondent Entity as long as there is a continuous stream of data
  to be transmitted.  However, this might incur a substantial
  overhead on the data packets.  Off-plane signaling, on the other hand,
  sends signaling messages independently from the data packet.  This has the
  advantage of reducing the signaling overhead in situations where there are 
  relatively fewer topological changes to the mobile network.  However, data 
  packet transmission may be disrupted while off-plane signaling takes place.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051013: NEW XXXXX] -->
  An entirely different method of signaling makes use of upper-layer protocols
  to establish the bindings between the address of a Mobile Network Node and
  the location of the mobile network.  Such binding information can then be
  passed down to the IP layer to insert the appropriate entry in the Binding
  Cache or routing table.  An example of such a mechanism is 
  <xref target="I-D.ming-nemo-sipnemo"/>, which uses the Session Initiation Protocol
  (SIP) to relay binding information.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Signaling -->

<!-- vspace blankLines='100'/ -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.data'
	 title="How Is Data Transmitted?">

<t>
  With Route Optimization established, one remaining question to be answered is
  how data packets can be routed to follow the optimized route.
  There are the following possible approaches:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Encapsulations
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      One way to route packets through the optimized path is to use IP-in-IP
      encapsulations <xref target="RFC2473"/>.  In this way, the original packet
      can be tunneled to the location bound to the address of the Mobile Network
      Node using the normal routing infrastructure.  Depending on how the location
      is bound to the address of the Mobile Network Node, 
      the number of encapsulations required might vary.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      For instance, if the Correspondent Entity knows the full sequence of
      points of attachment,
      <!-- (see <xref target="sec:solution-space.binding.full"/>)--> 
      it might be necessary for there to be multiple encapsulations in order 
      to forward the data packet through each point of attachment.  This may 
      lead to the need for multiple tunnels and extra packet header overhead.
      It is possible to alleviate this by using Robust Header Compression
      techniques <xref target="RFC3095"/><xref target="RFC3759"/><xref target="I-D.minaburo-rohc-nemo"/>
      to compress the multiple tunnel packet headers.
    </t>
    <t>
      Routing Headers
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      A second way to route packets through the optimized path is to use
      routing headers.  This is useful especially for the case where the
      Correspondent Entity knows the sequence of locations of upstream 
      Mobile Routers 
      (see <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.sequence"/>), since a
      routing header can contain multiple intermediate destinations.  Each
      intermediate destination corresponds to a point of attachment bound
      to the address of the Mobile Network Node.
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      This requires the use of a new Routing Header type, or possibly an extension
      of the Type 2 Routing Header as defined by Mobile IPv6 to contain
      multiple addresses instead of only one.
    </t>
    <t>
      Routing Entries in Parent Mobile Routers
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Yet another way is for parent Mobile Routers to 
      install routing entries in their routing table that will route
      Route Optimized packets differently, most likely based on source
      address routing.  This usually applies to approaches described in
      <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.root"/>.
      For instance, the Prefix Delegation approach 
      <xref target="I-D.perera-nemo-extended"/><!--
      --><xref target="Paper.leekj-nemo-ro-pd"/><xref target="I-D.leekj-nemo-ro-pd"/>
      would require parent Mobile Routers to route packets differently 
      if the source address belongs to the prefix delegated from the 
      access network.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Data -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.security'
	 title="What Are the Security Considerations?">

<section anchor='sec:analysis.security.binding'
	 title="Security Considerations of Address Binding">
<!--	 title="Security Considerations of Identity-Location Binding"-->
		
<t>
  <!-- security of binding -->
  The most important security consideration in Route Optimization
  is certainly the security risks a Correspondent Entity is exposed to
  by creating a binding between the address of a Mobile Network Node
  and the specified location(s) of the mobile network.  
  Generally, it is assumed that the Correspondent Entity and Mobile Network 
  Node do not share any pre-existing security association.  However,
  the Correspondent Entity
  must have some ways of verifying the authenticity of the binding 
  specified, else it will be susceptible to various attacks described in
  <xref target="RFC4225"/>, such as snooping (sending packets meant 
  for a Mobile Network Node to an attacker) or denial-of-service (DoS) 
  (flooding a victim with packets meant for a Mobile Network Node) attacks.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- simple case: normal RR -->
  When the binding is performed between the address of the Mobile Network Node
  and one Care-of Address (possibly of the Mobile Router; see
  <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/> and
  <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.root"/>), the standard Return Routability
  procedure specified in Mobile IPv6 might be sufficient to provide
  a reasonable degree of assurance to the Correspondent Entity.  This also allows
  the Correspondent Entity to re-use existing implementations.  But in other
  situations, an extension to the Return Routability procedure might be necessary.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- prefix-scoped BU -->
  For instance, consider the case where the Mobile Router sends a Binding Update 
  containing Mobile Network Prefix information to the Correspondent Entity (see
  <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/>).  Although the Return Routability
  procedure allows the Correspondent Entity to verify that the Care-of and
  Home Addresses of the Mobile Router are indeed collocated,
  it does not allow the Correspondent Entity to verify the validity of 
  the Mobile Network Prefix.  If the Correspondent Entity accepts the 
  binding without verification,  it will be exposed to attacks where the
  attacker tricks the Correspondent Entity into forwarding packets destined
  for a mobile network to the attacker (snooping) or victim (DoS);
  <xref target="I-D.ng-nemo-rrnp"/> discusses this security threat further.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- correspondent router -->
  The need to verify the validity of network prefixes is not constrained to 
  Correspondent Entities.  In approaches that involve the Correspondent Routers
  (see <xref target="sec:analysis.entities.MR-CR"/>), there have been suggestions
  for the Correspondent Router to advertise the network prefix(es) of Correspondent
  Nodes that the Correspondent Router is capable of terminating Route Optimization
  on behalf of to Mobile Network Nodes.  In such cases, the Mobile Network Nodes
  also need a mechanism to check the authenticity of such claims.  
  Even if the Correspondent Routers do not advertise the network prefix, 
  the Mobile Network Nodes also have the need to verify that the 
  Correspondent Router is indeed a valid Correspondent Router for a given
  Correspondent Node.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- upstream information -->
  <!-- chanwah: this paragraph has been modified -->
  In <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.sequence"/>, the registration signaling 
  involves sending the information about one or more upstream Mobile Routers.
  The Correspondent Entity (or Home Agent) must also have the means to verify such information.
  Again, the standard Return Routability procedure as defined in 
  <xref target="RFC3775"/> is inadequate here, as it is not designed to verify the
  reachability of an address over a series of upstream routers.
  An extension such as attaching a routing header to the Care-of Test (CoT)
  message to verify the authenticity of the locations of upstream Mobile Routers
  is likely to be needed.
  The risk, however, is not confined to Correspondent Entities.  The Mobile
  Network Nodes are also under the threat of receiving false information from
  their upstream Mobile Routers, which they might pass to Correspondent Entities
  (this also implies that Correspondent Entities cannot rely on any
  security associations they have with the Mobile Network Nodes to
  establish the validity of address bindings).
  There are some considerations that this kind of on-path threat exists
  in the current Internet anyway especially when no (or weak) end-to-end
  protection is used.
</t>
<t>
  <!-- SEND -->
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051017: REPLACE XXXX]
  All these concerns over the authenticity of addresses might suggest that perhaps
  a more radical and robust approach is necessary.  This is currently under 
  extensive study in various Working Groups of the IETF, and many related documents
  might be of interest here, such as Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND)
  <xref target="RFC3971"/>, Cryptographically Generated
  Addresses (CGAs) <xref target="RFC3972"/>, various enhancements to the 
  Route Optimization scheme of Mobile IPv6 
  <xref target="RFC4651"/>
  <xref target="I-D.zhao-mip6-rr-ext"/>, and possibly
  Host Identity Protocol (HIP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-hip-base"/> 
  with end-host mobility considerations <xref target="I-D.ietf-hip-mm"/>.
  [XXXX cwng@20051017: WITH THIS: XXXX]
  -->
  All these concerns over the authenticity of addresses might suggest that perhaps
  a more radical and robust approach is necessary.  This is currently under 
  extensive study in various Working Groups of the IETF, and many related documents
  might be of interest here.  For instance, in Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND)
  <xref target="RFC3971"/>, Cryptographically Generated
  Addresses (CGAs) <xref target="RFC3972"/> could be used to establish
  the ownership of Care-of Addresses.  
  <xref target="I-D.zhao-mip6-rr-ext"/> employs the Home Agent to check the 
  signaling messages sent by Mobile Routers to provide a way for Correspondent
  Entities to verify the authenticity of Mobile Network Prefixes specified.
  <xref target="RFC4651"/> documents various proposed 
  enhancements to the Mobile IPv6 Route Optimization mechanism that might be applied
  to NEMO Route Optimization as well, such as 
  <xref target="I-D.qiu-mip6-certificated-binding-update"/>, which allows the
  Correspondent Entity to authenticate a certain operator's Home Agent by
  verifying the associated certificate.
  The Host Identity Protocol (HIP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-hip-base"/> 
  with end-host mobility considerations <xref target="I-D.ietf-hip-mm"/>
  may be extended for NEMO Route Optimization as well.
</t>
<t>
  In addition, interested readers might want to refer to 
  <xref target="Paper.wiopt"/>, which discussed the general problem of 
  making Route Optimization in NEMO secure and explored some possible 
  solution schemes.
  There is also a proposed mechanism in <xref
  target="Paper.ndss-ylitalo"/> for Mobile Network Node to delegate
  some rights to their Mobile Routers,
  which may be used to allow the Mobile Routers to prove their authenticities
  to Correspondent Entities when establishing Route Optimization sessions on
  behalf of the Mobile Network Nodes.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Security -- Binding -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.security.e2e'
	 title="End-to-End Integrity">
	
<t>
  In some of the approaches, such as "Mobile Router as a Proxy"<!-- and "Mobile
  Router as a Transparent Proxy"--> in <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/>,
  the Mobile Router sends messages using the Mobile Network Node's address
  as the source address.  This is done mainly to achieve zero new functionalities 
  required at the Correspondent Entities and the Mobile Network Nodes.  However,
  adopting such a strategy may interfere with existing or future protocols, 
  most particularly security-related protocols.  This is especially true 
  <!-- for the
  "Mobile Router as a Transparent Proxy" approach, as it requires --> when
  the Mobile Router needs to make changes to packets sent by Mobile Network Nodes.
  In a sense, these approaches break the end-to-end integrity of packets.
  <!-- [XXXX cwng@20051011: ISSUE 15 XXXX] -->
  A related concern is that this kind of approach may also require the 
  Mobile Router to inspect the packet contents sent to/by Mobile Network Nodes.
  This may prove to be difficult or impossible if such contents are
  encrypted.
</t>
<t>
  The concern over end-to-end integrity arises for the use of a Reverse Routing
  Header (see <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.sequence"/>) too, since 
  Mobile Routers would insert new contents to the header of packets sent by 
  downstream Mobile Network Nodes.  This makes it difficult for Mobile Network
  Nodes to protect the end-to-end integrity of such information with security
  associations.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Security -- Binding -->

<!-- vspace blankLines='100'/ -->

<section anchor='sec:analysis.security.privacy'
	 title="Location Privacy">

<t>
  Another security-related concern is the issue of location privacy.
  This document currently does not consider the location privacy threats 
  caused by an on-path eavesdropper. For more information on that aspect, 
  please refer to <xref target="RFC4651"/>.
  Instead, we consider the following three aspects to location privacy:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      Revelation of Location to Correspondent Entity
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      Route optimization is achieved by creating a binding between the
      address of the Mobile Network Node and the current location of
      the Mobile Network.  It is thus inevitable that the location
      of the Mobile Network Node be revealed to the Correspondent Entity.  
      The concern may be alleviated if the Correspondent Entity is not
      the Correspondent Node, since this implies that the actual traffic
      end point (i.e., the Correspondent Node) would remain ignorant of
      the current location of the Mobile Network Node.
    </t>
    <t>
      Degree of Revelation
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      With network mobility, the degree of location exposure varies,
      especially when one considers nested mobile networks.
      For instance, for approaches that bind the address of the Mobile
      Network Node to the location of the root Mobile Router
      (see <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.root"/>), only
      the topmost point of attachment of the mobile network is revealed to
      the Correspondent Entity.  For approaches such as those described
      in <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/> and
      <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.sequence"/>, more information
      (such as Mobile Network Prefixes and current locations of 
      upstream Mobile Routers)
      is revealed.  Techniques such as exposing only locally-scoped
addresses of intermediate upstream mobile routers to Correspondent
Entities may be used to reduce the degree of revelation.
    </t>
    <t>
      Control of the Revelation
      <vspace blankLines='1'/>
      When Route Optimization is initiated by the Mobile Network Node
      itself, it is in control of whether or not to sacrifice location
      privacy for an optimized route.  However, if it is the Mobile Router
      that initiates Route Optimization (e.g., "Binding Update with 
      Mobile Network Prefix" and "Mobile Router as a Proxy" in
      <xref target="sec:analysis.binding.parent"/>), 
      then control is taken away from the Mobile Network Node.  
      An additional signaling mechanism between the Mobile Network Node
      and its Mobile Router can be used in this case to prevent the
      Mobile Router from attempting Route Optimization for a given 
      traffic stream.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Security -- privacy -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -- Security -->

</section> <!-- EndSect: Analysis -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION 6:  CONCLUSION  ------------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:conclusion'
	title="Conclusion">

<t>
  The problem space of Route Optimization in the NEMO context is multifold
  and can be split into several work areas.  It will be critical, though,
  that the solution to a given piece of the puzzle be compatible and integrated
  smoothly with others.
  With this in mind, this document attempts to present a detailed and
  in-depth analysis of the NEMO Route Optimization solution space by first
  describing the benefits a Route Optimization solution is expected to
  bring, then illustrating the different scenarios in which a Route Optimization
  solution applies, and next presenting some issues a Route Optimization 
  solution might face.  We have also asked ourselves some of the 
  basic questions about a Route Optimization solution.  By investigating
  different possible answers to these questions, we have explored different
  aspects to a Route Optimization solution.  The intent of this work
  is to enhance our common understanding of the Route Optimization
  problem and solution space.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Conclusion -->

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<!--------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION:  IANA CONSIDERATION  ------------------------------------------>
<!--------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!--<section anchor='sec:IANA'
	title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
  This is an informational document and does not require any IANA action.
</t>
</section>--> <!-- EndSect: IANA-Considerations -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>

<!--------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION:  SECURITY CONSIDERATION  -------------------------------------->
<!--------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<section anchor='sec:security'
	title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   This is an informational document that analyzes the solution space of
   NEMO Route Optimization.  Security considerations of different approaches
   are described in the relevant sections throughout this document.
   Particularly, please refer to <xref target="sec:gen-issues.security"/>
   for a brief discussion of the security concern with respect to
   Route Optimization in general, and <xref target="sec:analysis.security"/>
   for a more detailed analysis of the various Route Optimization
   approaches.
</t>
</section> <!-- EndSect: Security Considerations -->

<vspace blankLines='1'/>


<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- SECTION:  ACKNOWLEDGMENT  ----------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->

<section anchor='sec:ack'
	title="Acknowledgments">

<t>
  The authors wish to thank the co-authors of previous versions from which this
  document is derived: Marco Molteni, Paik Eun-Kyoung, Hiroyuki Ohnishi, Felix Wu,
  and Souhwan Jung.
  In addition, sincere appreciation is also extended to Jari Arkko, 
  Carlos Jesus Bernardos, Greg Daley, Thierry Ernst, T.J. Kniveton, 
  Erik Nordmark, Alexandru Petrescu, Hesham Soliman,
  Ryuji Wakikawa, and Patrick Wetterwald for their various contributions.
</t>

</section> <!-- EndSect: Acknowledgments -->

<?rfc compact="no"?>

</middle>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- BACK: References and Appendix ------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->

<back>
<?rfc needLines="30" ?>
<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3963.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3775.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3753.xml" ?>

<reference anchor='RFC4888'>
<front>
<title>Network Mobility Route Optimization Problem Statement</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Ng' fullname='Chan-Wah Ng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Thubert' fullname='Pascal Thubert'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Watari' fullname='Masafumi Watari'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='F' surname='Zhao' fullname='Fan Zhao'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>With current Network Mobility (NEMO) Basic Support, all
communications to and from Mobile Network Nodes must go through the
bi-directional tunnel established between the Mobile Router and Home
Agent when the mobile network is away. This sub-optimal routing
results in various inefficiencies associated with packet delivery,
such as increased delay and bottleneck links leading to traffic
congestion, which can ultimately disrupt all communications to and
from the Mobile Network Nodes. Additionally, with nesting of Mobile
Networks, these inefficiencies get compounded, and stalemate
conditions may occur in specific dispositions. This document
investigates such problems, and provides for the motivation behind
Route Optimization (RO) for NEMO.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4888' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-nemo-ro-problem-statement-03.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4885'>
<front>
<title>Network Mobility Support Terminology</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Ernst' fullname='Thierry Ernst'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H-Y' surname='Lach' fullname='Hong Lach'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a terminology for discussing
network mobility (NEMO) issues and solution
requirements.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4885' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-nemo-terminology-06.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4886'>
<front>
<title>Network Mobility Support Goals and Requirements</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Ernst' fullname='Thierry Ernst'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>Network mobility arises when a router connecting a
network to the Internet dynamically changes its point of attachment
to the Internet thereby causing the reachability of the said network
to be changed in relation to the fixed Internet topology. Such kind
of network is referred to as a mobile network. With appropriate
mechanisms, sessions established between nodes in the mobile network
and the global Internet can be maintained after the Mobile Router
changes its point of attachment. This document outlines the goals
expected from network mobility support and defines the requirements
that must be met by the NEMO Basic Support solution.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4886' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-nemo-requirements-06.txt' />
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2461.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2473.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3095.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3759.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3971.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3972.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4068.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4140.xml" ?>
  <!-- ?rfc include="reference.I-D.troan-dhcpv6-opt-prefix-delegation.xml" ? -->

  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4651.xml" ?>

  <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-hip-base">
	<front>
		<title>Host Identity Protocol</title>
		<author initials="R" surname="Moskowitz" fullname="Robert Moskowitz">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
		<author initials="P" surname="Nikander" fullname="Pekka Nikander">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="P" surname="Jokela" fullname="Petri Jokela">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="T" surname="Henderson" fullname="Thomas R Henderson">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="April" year="2007"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-hip-base-07.txt"/>
  </reference> 

  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-hip-base.xml" ?>-->
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-hip-mm">
	<front>
		<title>End-Host Mobility and Multihoming with the Host Identity Protocol</title>
		<author initials="T" surname="Henderson" fullname="Tom  Henderson">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<date month="March" year="2007"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-hip-mm-05.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-hip-mm.xml" ?>-->
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4225.xml" ?>

  <reference anchor="I-D.na-nemo-path-control-header">
	<front>
		<title>Route Optimization Scheme based on Path Control Header</title>
		<author initials="J" surname="Na" fullname="Jongkeun Na">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='S' surname='Cho' fullname='S. Cho'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Kim' fullname='C. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Lee' fullname='S. Lee'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kang' fullname='H. Kang'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Koo' fullname='C. Koo'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="April" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-na-nemo-path-control-header-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.na-nemo-path-control-header.xml" ?>-->
 
  <reference anchor="I-D.na-nemo-nested-path-info">
	<front>
		<title>Secure Nested Tunnels Optimization using Nested Path Information</title>
		<author initials="J" surname="Na" fullname="Jongkeun  Na">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='S' surname='Cho' fullname='S. Cho'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Kim' fullname='C. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Lee' fullname='S. Lee'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kang' fullname='H. Kang'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Koo' fullname='C. Koo'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="September" year="2003"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-na-nemo-nested-path-info-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.na-nemo-nested-path-info.xml" ?>-->
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.ng-nemo-rrnp">
	<front>
		<title>Extending Return Routability Procedure for Network Prefix (RRNP)</title>
		<author initials="C" surname="Ng" fullname="Chan Ng">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
		<author initials='J' surname='Hirano' fullname='Jun Hirano'>
			<organization />
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="October" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ng-nemo-rrnp-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ng-nemo-rrnp.xml" ?>-->
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.ng-nemo-access-router-option">
	<front>
		<title>Securing Nested Tunnels Optimization with Access Router Option</title>
		<author initials="C" surname="Ng" fullname="Chan Ng">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="T" surname="Tanaka" fullname="Takashi Tanaka">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<date month="July" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ng-nemo-access-router-option-01.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ng-nemo-access-router-option.xml" ?>-->


<reference anchor='Paper.lee-hro'>
<front>
<title>Hierarchical FRoute Optimization for Nested Mobile Network</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Lee' fullname='D. Lee'>
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Lim' fullname='K. Lim'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Kim' fullname='M. Kim'>
  <organization />
</author>

<date year='2004' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='18th' value="Int'l Conf on Advance Information Networking and Applications" />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='1' />
<seriesInfo name='pp' value='225-229' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='Paper.ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip'>
<front>
<title>Route Optimization Methods for Network Mobility with Mobile IPv6</title>

<author initials='Y' surname='Takagi' fullname='Y. Takagi'>
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Ohnishi' fullname='Hiroyiki  Ohnishi'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Sakitani' fullname='K. Sakitani'>
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Baba' fullname='K. Baba'>
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Shimojo' fullname='S. Shimojo'>
  <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' year='2004' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='IEICE' value='Trans. on Comms' />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='E87-B' />
<seriesInfo name='no' value='3' />
<seriesInfo name='pp' value='480-489' />
</reference>


  <reference anchor="I-D.ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip">
	<front>
		<title>HMIP based Route optimization method in a mobile network</title>
		<author initials="H" surname="Ohnishi" fullname="Hiroyiki  Ohnishi">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='K' surname='Sakitani' fullname='K. Sakitani'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='Y' surname='Takagi' fullname='Y. Takagi'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="October" year="2003"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip-00.txt"/>
	</reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ohnishi-nemo-ro-hmip.xml" ?>-->
  
  <!--<rfc include="reference.Paper.wakikawa-nemo-orc.xml" ?> said -->
--access denied -->
  
<reference anchor='Paper.wakikawa-nemo-orc'>
<front>
<title>ORC: Optimized Route Cache Management Protocol for Network Mobility</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Wakikawa' fullname='Ryuji Wakikawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Koshiba' fullname='S. Koshiba'>
        <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Uehara' fullname='K. Uehara'>
        <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Murai' fullname='Jun Murai'>
        <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' year='2003' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='10th' value='International Conference on Telecommunications' />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='2' />
<seriesInfo name='pp' value='1194-1200' />
</reference>


  <reference anchor="I-D.wakikawa-nemo-orc">
	<front>
		<title>Optimized Route Cache Protocol (ORC)</title>
		<author initials="R" surname="Wakikawa" fullname="Ryuji Wakikawa">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='M' surname='Watari' fullname='Masafumi Watari'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="November" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-wakikawa-nemo-orc-01.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.wakikawa-nemo-orc.xml" ?>-->

  <reference anchor="I-D.hkang-nemo-ro-tlmr">
	<front>
		<title>Route Optimization for Mobile Network by Using Bi-directional Between Home Agent and Top Level Mobile Router</title>
		<author initials="H" surname="Kang" fullname="Hyunsik Kang">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='K' surname='Kim' fullname='K. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Han' fullname='S. Han'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Lee' fullname='K. Lee'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="June" year="2003"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hkang-nemo-ro-tlmr-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.hkang-nemo-ro-tlmr.xml" ?>-->


  <!--<rfc include="reference.Paper.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy" ?> access denied-->
<reference anchor='Paper.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy'>
<front>
<title>Route Optimization based on ND-Proxy for Mobile Nodes in IPv6 Mobile Network</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Jeong' fullname='Jae-Hoon Jeong'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Lee' fullname='K. Lee'>
        <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
        <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kim' fullname='H. Kim'>
        <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2004' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='59th' value='IEEE Vehicular Technology Conference' />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='5' />
<seriesInfo name='pp' value='2461-2465' />
</reference>


  <reference anchor="I-D.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy">
	<front>
		<title>ND-Proxy based Route Optimization for Mobile Nodes in Mobile Network</title>
		<author initials="J" surname="Jeong" fullname="Jae-Hoon Jeong">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='K' surname='Lee' fullname='K. Lee'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kim' fullname='H. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="February" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy-02.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.jeong-nemo-ro-ndproxy" ?>-->

<reference anchor='Paper.leekj-nemo-ro-pd'>
<front>
<title>Route Optimization for Mobile Nodes in Mobile Network based on Prefix  Delegation</title>

<author initials='K' surname='Lee' fullname='K. Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kim' fullname='H. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2003' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='58th' value='IEEE Vehicular Technology Conference' />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='3' />
<seriesInfo name='pp' value='2035-2038' />
</reference>



  <reference anchor="I-D.leekj-nemo-ro-pd">
	<front>
		<title>Route Optimization for Mobile Nodes in Mobile Network based on Prefix Delegation</title>
		<author initials="K" surname="Lee" fullname="K. Lee">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='J' surname='Jeong' fullname='J. Jeong'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kim' fullname='H. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="February" year="2004"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-leekj-nemo-ro-pd-02.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.leekj-nemo-ro-pd" ?>-->

  <reference anchor="I-D.perera-nemo-extended">
	<front>
		<title>Extended Network Mobility Support</title>
		<author initials="E" surname="Perera" fullname="Eranga Perera">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='K' surname='Lee' fullname='K. Lee'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Kim' fullname='H. Kim'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Park' fullname='J. Park'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="July" year="2003"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-perera-nemo-extended-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.perera-nemo-extended.xml" ?>-->
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header">
	<front>
		<title>IPv6 Reverse Routing Header and its application to Mobile Networks</title>
		<author initials="P" surname="Thubert" fullname="Pascal  Thubert">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="M" surname="Molteni" fullname="Marco Molteni">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<date month="February" year="2007"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header-07.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.thubert-nemo-reverse-routing-header.xml" ?>-->

  <reference anchor="I-D.thubert-nemo-global-haha">
	<front>
		<title>Global HA to HA protocol</title>
		<author initials="P" surname="Thubert" fullname="Pascal Thubert">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='R' surname='Wakikawa' fullname='Ryuji Wakikawa'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='V' surname='Devarapalli' fullname='Vijay Devarapalli'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="September" year="2006"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-thubert-nemo-global-haha-02.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.thubert-nemo-global-haha.xml" ?> -->
  



<reference anchor='Paper.miron'>
<front>
<title>MIRON: MIPv6 Route Optimization for NEMO</title>

<author initials='C.J.' surname='Bernardos' fullname='Carlos Jesus Bernardos'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Calderon' fullname='Maria Calderon'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='August' year='2004'/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name='4th Workshop on' value='Applications and Services in Wireless Network' />
<seriesInfo name='Online:' value='http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/papers/miron_aswn2004.pdf' />
</reference>

<!-- chanwah: new reference -->
<reference anchor='Paper.miron2'>
<front>
<title>Design and Experimental Evaluation of a Route Optimisation Solution for
NEMO</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Calderon' fullname='Maria Calderon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C.J.' surname='Bernardos' fullname='Carlos Jesus Bernardos'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='I' surname='Soto' fullname='Ignacio Soto'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Oliva' fullname='Antonio de la Oliva'>
    <organization />
</author>


<date month='September' year='2006'/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name='IEEE Journal on' value='Selected Areas in Communications (J-SAC)' />
<seriesInfo name='vol' value='24' />
<seriesInfo name='no' value='9' />
</reference>


  <reference anchor="I-D.bernardos-nemo-miron">
	<front>
		<title>Mobile IPv6 Route Optimisation for Network Mobility (MIRON)</title>
		<author initials="C" surname="Bernardos" fullname="Carlos  Bernardos">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Calderon' fullname='M. Calderon'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='Soto' fullname='I. Soto'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="July" year="2005"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-bernardos-nemo-miron-00.txt"/>
  </reference>

  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.bernardos-nemo-miron.xml" ?>-->



  <reference anchor="I-D.zhao-mip6-rr-ext">
	<front>
		<title>Extensions to Return Routability Test in MIP6</title>
		<author initials="F" surname="Zhao" fullname="Fan Zhao">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="F" surname="Wu" fullname="Felix Wu">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="S" surname="Jung" fullname="Souhwan Jung">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<date month="February" year="2005"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-zhao-mip6-rr-ext-01.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.zhao-mip6-rr-ext.xml" ?>-->

  <reference anchor="I-D.ming-nemo-sipnemo">
        <front>
	        <title>SIP-based Network Mobility (SIP-NEMO) Route Optimization (RO)</title>
		<author initials="C" surname="Lee" fullname="Chao-Hsien  Lee">
		        <organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='J' surname='Zheng' fullname='J. Zheng'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='HUang' fullname='C. Huang'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="October" year="2006"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ming-nemo-sipnemo-01.txt"/>
  </reference>
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.baek-nemo-nested-ro">
	<front>
		<title>Routing Optimization in the same nested mobile network</title>
		<author initials="S" surname="Baek" fullname="Sungmin Baek">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='J' surname='Yoo' fullname='J Yoo'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='T' surname='Kwon' fullname='T Kwon'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='E' surname='Paik' fullname='E Paik'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Nam' fullname='M Nam'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="October" year="2005"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-baek-nemo-nested-ro-00.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.baek-nemo-nested-ro.xml" ?>-->
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.qiu-mip6-certificated-binding-update">
	<front>
		<title>Certificate-based Binding Update Protocol (CBU)</title>
		<author initials="F" surname="Bao" fullname="F Bao">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='R' surname='Deng' fullname='R. Deng'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='Y' surname='Qiu' fullname='Y. Qiu'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Zhou' fullname='J. Zhou'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="March" year="2005"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-qiu-mip6-certificated-binding-update-03.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.qiu-mip6-certificated-binding-update.xml" ?>-->

  <reference anchor="I-D.minaburo-rohc-nemo">
	<front>
		<title>ROHC (Robust Header Compression) in NEMO network</title>
		<author initials="A" surname="Minaburo" fullname="Ana Minaburo">
			<organization/>
		</author>
<!-- chanwah: EDIT -->
<author initials='E' surname='Paik' fullname='E. Paik'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='L' surname='Toutain' fullname='L. Toutain'>
	<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Bonnin' fullname='J. Bonnin'>
	<organization />
</author>
<!-- chanwah: END EDIT -->
		<date month="July" year="2005"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
	<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-minaburo-rohc-nemo-01.txt"/>
  </reference>
  <!--<?rfc include="reference.I-D.minaburo-rohc-nemo.xml" ?>-->
  

<reference anchor='Paper.wiopt'>
<front>
<title>Securing Route Optimization in NEMO</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Calderon' fullname='Maria Calderon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C.J.' surname='Bernardos' fullname='Carlos Jesus Bernardos'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='I' surname='Soto' fullname='Ignacio Soto'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' day='3-7' year='2005' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Third International Symposium' 
	    value='on Modeling and Optimization in Mobile, Ad Hoc, and Wireless Networks' />
<seriesInfo name='WIOPT' value='2005' />
<seriesInfo name='pages' value='248-254' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='Paper.ndss-ylitalo'>
<front>
<title>Securing Route Optimization in NEMO</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Ylitalo' fullname='Jukka Ylitalo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='2' year='2005' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Workshop of' value='12th Network and Distributed System Security Syposuim' />
<seriesInfo name='NDSS Workshop' value='2005' />
<seriesInfo name='online:'
	    value='http://www.isoc.org/isoc/conferences/ndss/05/workshop/ylitalo.pdf' />
</reference>



</references>



<!-- references title="Old References">
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.deering-ipv6-encap-addr-deletion.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.na-nemo-gen-ro-model.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.watari-nemo-nested-cn.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.zhao-nemo-ro-ps.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.droms-nemo-dhcpv6-pd.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.paakkonen-nemo-prefix-delegation.xml" ?>
  <! ?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mipshop-hmipv6" ?>
</references -->

<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!-- APPENDIX:  CHANGE-LOG --------------------------------------------------->
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------->
<!--
<section anchor="sec:changelog"
	title="Change Log">

<t>
<list style="symbols">
  <t>
    draft-ietf-nemo-ro-space-analysis-03:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
        Keepalive release
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>
    draft-ietf-nemo-ro-space-analysis-02:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
        Changed title of Sect 3.1 from "Basic NEMO Route Optimization" to
	"Non-Nested NEMO Route Optimization"
      </t>
      <t>
        Added "Terminology" Sub-section [Issue #17]
      </t>
      <t>
        Modifications to Sect 3.1 and 5.1.1 [Issues #18, #20]
      </t>
      <t>
        Break "Mobility Transparency and Location Privacy" into
        Sect 4.7 and 4.8 [Issue #19]
      </t>
      <t>
        Updated References [Issue #21]
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>
    draft-ietf-nemo-ro-space-analysis-01:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
        Changed the term "Correspondent Agent" to "Correspondent Entity" [Issue #13]
      </t>
      <t>
        Added clarifying text to some benefits listed in Sect 2 [Issue #14]
      </t>
      <t>
        Added clarifying text to Sect 4.1, 4.3 and 4.4 [Issues #5, #6, #16]
      </t>
      <t>
        Added Section 4.9 [Issue #3]
      </t>
      <t>
        Added clarifying text to various parts of Sect 5 [Issues #7, #8, #9, #11, and #16]
      </t>
      <t>
        Combined "MR as a Proxy" and "MR as a Transparent Proxy" in Sect 5.5.1 [Issue #11]
      </t>
      <t>
        Changed the term "identity of MNN" to "address of MNN" in Sect 5.5 [Issue #12]
      </t>
      <t>
        Added text on signaling using upper layer protocols in Sect 5.6
      </t>
      <t>
        Added more security consideration to Sect 5.8 [Issue #15]
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>
    draft-ietf-nemo-ro-space-analysis-00:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
        Adapted from Sections 3, 4 &amp; 5 of
        'draft-thubert-nemo-ro-taxonomy-04.txt' into:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
           Section 3 - "Different Scenarios of NEMO Route Optimization"
          </t>
          <t>
           Section 4 - "Issues of NEMO Route Optimization"
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Included various parts from 'draft-zhao-nemo-ro-ps-01.txt'
      </t>
      <t>
        Re-vamped Section 5 - "Analysis of Solution Space"
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
</list>
</t>

</section>--> <!-- EndSect: Change-Log -->

<!-- cwng@20050911: Appendix in -00 removed.  
	 Please refer to -00.xml if you need to them
-->

</back>

</rfc>
<!-- End of Doc -->

