<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY rfc3932 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3932.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2223 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2223.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2026 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3978 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3978.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc0021 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0021.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc1109 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1109.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2441 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2441.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc1810 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1810.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc1591 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1591.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2860 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2860.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4714 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4714.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4748 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4748.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2555 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2555.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2434 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2434.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<rfc number="4846" category="info">
<front>
    <title abbrev="Independent Submissions">
      Independent Submissions to the RFC Editor 
    </title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="John C Klensin"
            role="editor">
        <organization/>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>1770 Massachusetts Ave, #322</street>
                <city>Cambridge</city> <region>MA</region> <code>02140</code>
                <country>USA</country> 
            </postal>
            <phone>+1 617 491 5735 </phone>
            <email>john-ietf@jck.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Thaler" fullname="Dave Thaler"
            role="editor">
        <organization/>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
                <city>Redmond</city> <region>WA</region> <code>98052</code>
                <country>USA</country> 
            </postal>
            <phone>+1 425 703 8835 </phone>
            <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2007"/>


<!-- [rfced] Please insert any additional keywords (beyond those that 
appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/search.html. -->

    <keyword>RFC Editor</keyword>
    <keyword>Independent Submission</keyword>
    <keyword>Publications</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t> There is a long-standing tradition in the Internet community,
          predating the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) by many years, of use of the RFC Series to
          publish materials that are not rooted in the IETF standards
          process and its review and approval mechanisms.  These
          documents, known as "Independent Submissions", serve a number
          of important functions for the Internet community, both
          inside and outside of the community of active IETF
          participants. This document discusses the Independent
          Submission model and some reasons why it is important.  It then
          describes editorial and processing norms that can be used for
          Independent Submissions as the community goes forward into new
          relationships between the IETF community and its primary
          technical publisher.
      </t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
    <t> There is a long-standing tradition in the Internet community,
        predating the IETF by many years, of use of the RFC Series to
        publish materials that are not rooted in the IETF standards
        process and its review and approval mechanisms.  These
        documents, known as "Independent Submissions", serve a number
        of important functions for the Internet community, both
        inside and outside of the community of active IETF
        participants. This document discusses the Independent
        Submission model and some reasons why it is important. It
        then
        describes editorial and processing norms that can be used for
        Independent Submissions as the community goes forward into new
        relationships between the IETF community and its primary
        technical publisher.
    </t>
    <t> To understand the perspective of this document, it is
        important to remember that the RFC Editor function predates
        the creation of the IETF.  As of the time of this writing,
        the RFC Series goes back 38 years <xref target="RFC2555"/>,
        while the IETF is
        celebrating its 21st anniversary.  All of the documents that
        were published before the IETF was created, and for some
        years thereafter, would be considered Independent Submissions
        today.
        As the IETF evolved, the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) and
        then the IETF itself chose to publish IETF documents as
        RFCs while fully understanding that the RFC Editor function
        was an independent publication mechanism.  Other decisions
        were possible: e.g., the IETF could have decided to create
        its own publication series.  It was felt that there was
        considerable value in continuing to publish the IETF work in
        the same series as the one used to publish the basic
        protocols for the Internet.
    </t>

    <section title="Terminology Note">
        <t> This document describes what have historically been
            referred to as "Independent Submissions".  That term is
            distinguished from those IETF and IAB community
            documents that originate from formal groups -- the IAB, IRTF,
            and IETF Working Groups -- and from submissions submitted
to the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) for
            Standards-Track, Informational, or Experimental
            processing.  Documents produced by individuals, rather
            than IETF WGs or others IETF-affiliated groups, but
            submitted for publication via the IESG under Area Director
            sponsorship, are known as "individual submissions".
        </t>
        <t> For convenience and obvious historical reasons, the
            editor and publisher of documents that are not processed
            through the IETF is known below as the "RFC Editor".  The
            RFC Editor will typically be an organization of one or
            more senior people and associated editorial staff, and the term is
            used collectively below.  
	    That term is not intended to predict the future, either in
            terms of who does the job or what they, or the document
            series, are called.
        </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Context and Philosophical Assumptions"
            anchor="Philosophy">
        <t> This document complements
            the discussion and guidelines in <xref target="RFC4714"/>,
            which focuses on 
            Standards-Track documents.  It takes a somewhat
            stronger view than the discussions that led to that
            document, starting from the belief 
            that Independent Submissions are most valuable if they are, in
            fact, independent of the IETF process.  From the perspective
            of the IETF, Independent Submissions are especially
            important as checks on the 
            IETF processes even though such checks are not the only, or
            even a common, reason for them.  That role is compromised if  
            IETF-related entities are able to block or deprecate such
            documents to a degree beyond that needed to avoid
            difficulties with the standards process.</t>
    </section>
</section>

<section title="The Role of Independent Submissions">
    <t> When the RFC Series was fairly new, RFCs were used to
        publish general papers on networking as well as the
        types of documents we would describe as standards today.
        Those roles also developed as part of the early design and
        development of the ARPANET, long before anyone dreamt of the
        IETF and when the distinction between, e.g., Standards and
        Informational documents was less precisely drawn.  In more
        recent years, Independent Submissions have become important
        for multiple reasons, some of them relatively new.  They include:
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        <list style="symbols">
            <t> Discussion of Internet-related technologies that are
                not part of the IETF agenda.</t>
            <t> Introduction of important new ideas as a bridge
                publication venue between academia and IETF
                engineering.</t>
            <t> Informational discussions of technologies, options, or
                experience with protocols.</t>
            <t> Informational publication of vendor-specific
                protocols.</t>
            <t> Critiques and discussions of alternatives to IETF
                Standards-Track protocols.  The potential for such
                critiques provides an important check on the IETF's
                standards processes and should be seen in that
                light.</t>
            <t> Documents considered by IETF Working Groups but not standardized.
While many documents of this type are still published in the IETF
document stream (see <xref target="RFC4844"/>, Section 5.1.1)
as Informational or Experimental RFCs, the Independent Submission
path has traditionally been open to them as well. However, because
of their intimate connection to the IETF Standards Process
and WG activities and the consequent sensitivity to exact statements of
relationships and to timing, there is reason to believe that such
documents should normally be published via the IETF document stream. In
any event, these documents are published for the historical record.</t>
            <t> Satirical materials.</t>
            <t> Meeting notes and reports
                (<xref target="RFC0021">RFC 21</xref> is the earliest;
                <xref target="RFC1109">RFC 1109</xref> is probably the most
                important).</t> 
            <t> Editorials (the best example is 
                <xref target="IEN137">IEN 137</xref>, not an RFC).</t>
            <t> Eulogies (<xref target="RFC2441">RFC 2441</xref>).</t>
            <t> Technical contributions
                (e.g., <xref target="RFC1810">RFC 1810</xref>).</t>
            <t> Historically, RFC Editor and, at least prior to the handoff 
                between the Informational Sciences Institute (ISI) and
                the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
                Numbers (ICANN) and the June 2000 MOU <xref target="RFC2860"/>, 
                Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) Policy
                Statements (e.g., RFC 2223 <xref target="RFC2223"/> and 
                <xref target="RFC1591">RFC 1591</xref>).</t>
        </list>
    </t>
    <t> It should be clear from the list above that, to be
        effective, the review and approval process for Independent
        Submissions should be largely independent of the IETF.  As an
        important principle that has been applied historically, the
        RFC Editor seeks advice from the IESG about
        possible relationships and conflicts with IETF work.  
        Any submission that constitutes an
        alternative to, or is in conflict with, an IETF Standard or
        proposal for Standards-Track adoption must clearly indicate
        that relationship.  The IESG may identify such conflicts as
        part of its review.  
    </t>
    <t> The specific procedures to be followed in review are
        described in <xref target="Review"/> and <xref target="FormalReview"/>.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Document Submission">
    <t> Independent Submissions are submitted directly to the RFC
        Editor.  They must first be posted as Internet-Drafts (I-Ds), so the
        submission is typically simply a note requesting that the RFC
        Editor consider a particular Internet-Draft for publication.
        The process is described in <xref target="RFC2223"/>.  Further
        information can be found in the working draft of an update of
        that document <xref target="RFC2223BIS"/>.
    </t>
    <t> Any document that meets the requirements of this
        specification, of <xref target="RFC2223"/> and its
        successors, and of any intellectual property or other
        conditions that may be established from time to time, may be
        submitted to the RFC Editor for consideration as an
        Independent Submission.   However, the RFC Editor prefers
        that documents created through IETF processes (e.g., working
        group output) be considered by the IESG and submitted using
        this path only if a working group or the IESG declines to
        publish it.  In the latter cases, the review process 
        will be more efficient if the authors provide a history
        of consideration and reviews of the document at the time of
        submission.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="The Review Process" anchor="Review">    
<!-- Removed the following paragraph so as to make no statement about
     past practice:

    <t> While this document is consistent with the broad outline of
        Independent Submission and review as practiced over the years,
        it specifies some new arrangements in RFC Editor processing
        that will improve the balance between openness and independent
        decisions.
    </t>
-->
    <t> In general, the steps in the review process are identified in
        the subsections below.
        Any of them may be iterated and, at the discretion of the RFC
        Editor, steps after the first may be taken out of order.  In
        addition, the IESG review, as discussed
        in <xref target="FormalReview"/>, must take place before a
        final decision is made on whether to publish the
        document.
    </t> 

    <section title="Posting of Draft">
        <t> The author(s) or editor(s) of a document post it as an
            Internet-Draft.
        </t> 
    </section>

    <section title="Request for Publication">
        <t> After the normal opportunity for community review and
            feedback provided by the submission of the I-D and the
            I-D repository announcement thereof, 
            the author or editor sends a request for
            consideration for publication to the RFC Editor at
            rfc-editor@rfc-editor.org.  That request should note
            any community discussion or reviews of the document
            that have occurred before submission, as well as the
            desired document category (Informational or
            Experimental, as discussed in RFC 2026 <xref target="RFC2026"/>, 
            Section 4.2). 
        </t>
        <t> If the document requires any IANA allocations, authors
            should take care to check the assignment policy for the 
            relevant namespace, since some assignment policies
            (e.g., "IETF Consensus") cannot be used by Independent
            Submissions.  See RFC 2434 <xref target="RFC2434"/> 
            for more information.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Initial RFC Editor Review">
        <t> RFC Editor staff performs an initial check on the
            document to determine whether there are obvious issues
            or problems and to decide on the sequencing of other
            steps.
        </t>
        <t> At any time during the process, the RFC Editor may make general
            and/or specific suggestions to the author on how to improve the
            editorial quality of the document and note any specific violations
            of the rules.  The author will be expected to make the suggested
            updates, submit a new version, and inform the RFC Editor.  This
            may be repeated as often as necessary to obtain an acceptable
            editorial quality.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Review and Evaluation" anchor="Evaluation">
        <t> The RFC Editor arranges for one or more reviews of the
            document.  This may include
            Editorial Board (see <xref target="EdBoard"/>) reviews or
            reviews by others.  Unsolicited reviews from parties 
            independent of the author are welcome at any time.  
<!-- Removed this since it is contradicted by the next paragraph.
            Unsolicited reviews will be 
            shared with the author, including the identity of the 
            reviewer.
-->
        </t>
        <t> At minimum, the author of every document shall receive a written
            summary of the review(s).  Reviewer anonymity is discussed in
            <xref target="privacy"/>.  The RFC Editor may also share reviews 
            with the Editorial Board.
        </t>
        <t> An author rebuttal to some aspect of a review, followed by a  
            healthy technical dialog among the author and the reviewer(s), 
            is fully appropriate.  Consensus followed by document revision 
            is the desired outcome.
        </t>
        <t> The RFC 
            Editor is expected to consider all competent reviews
            carefully, and in the absence of some unusual circumstance, a
            preponderance of favorable reviews should lead to 
            publication.
        </t>
    </section>
         
    <section title="Additional Reviews" anchor="Additional">
        <t> If the author is dissatisfied with one or more review(s), the
            author may request that the RFC
            Editor solicit additional reviews.  In exceptional
            circumstances, the author may request that the IAB review the
            document.  Such requests to the IAB, and any reviews
            the IAB chooses to perform, will occur according to
            procedures of the IAB's choosing.   The IAB is
            not required to initiate a review or comply with a
            request for one: a request to the IAB for a review is
            not an appeal process.  
        </t>
    </section> 

    <section title="Document Rejection" anchor="Rejection">
        <t> If any stage of the review process just described leads to the
            conclusion that the document is not publishable, the RFC 
            Editor may reject the document.  Such 
            rejection would normally be based on 
            the conclusion 
            that the submission does not meet the technical or 
            editorial standards of the RFC Series or is not relevant to the 
            areas that the series covers.
        </t>
        <t> If a document is rejected by the RFC Editor,
            the author may request an
            additional review from the IAB, as described below, but
            the IAB is not obligated to perform that review, nor is the RFC
            Editor obligated to publish it, even with a favorable IAB
            review.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Final Decision and Notification">
        <t> In all cases, the ultimate decision to publish or not
            publish, and with what text, rests with the RFC
            Editor. 
        </t>
        <t> The RFC Editor will
            communicate the final decision to the author and the
            Editorial Board.  For a rejection, there will be a summary of the
            reason(s) for the action.
        </t>
        <t> Information about any IESG-requested publication delay or
            request to not publish a document will be posted to the
            RFC Editor Web site to supplement document status
            information. 
        </t>
    </section>
         
    <section title="Final Editing and Publication">
        <t> Once a document is approved for publication, it is
            handled in a fashion similar to other RFCs, with
            principles about priorities worked out with the IAB as
            appropriate.
        </t>
    </section>
</section>

<section title="Formal IESG Review" anchor="FormalReview">
    <t> At an appropriate time in the review process, normally
        after the RFC Editor has made a tentative decision to
        publish, the document is forwarded to the IESG for
        evaluation with a relatively short timeout.  If the
        nature of the document persuades the RFC Editor or the
        IESG that the interests of the community or efficiency
        in the publication process would be better served by a
        different schedule, then that schedule should be
        followed.  For example, if it appears to the RFC Editor
        that it is likely that the IESG will wish to take the
        document over and assign it to a working group, it may
        be better to ask for the IESG review prior to incurring
        the delays associated with other reviews or
        significant editorial work.
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The IESG evaluation is not a technical one.  Instead, it
        covers the issues listed in <xref target="RFC3932">RFC 3932</xref>
        or its successors,
        presumably from the perspective outlined above in
        <xref target="Philosophy"/>.  That is, the evaluation
        should focus exclusively 
        on conflicts or confusion with IETF process and
        attempts to subvert ("end run") working group
        activities.
    </t> 
    <t> At the time the document is forwarded to the IESG, the RFC
        Editor posts an indication on its Web site that
        the document is under IESG review and that comments on
        conflicts can be sent to the IESG with copies
        to the RFC Editor.    Additional mechanisms may be
        developed from time to time to inform a community that
        a document is entering formal prepublication review.
        Comments not directly related to IETF procedures or
        conflicts may be sent directly to the
        author(s) and RFC Editor. 
    </t>
    <t> In addition to the IESG review for conflict with IETF
        work, individuals in the IESG or in the broader IETF
        community are free to review a draft and, if they have
        comments of any kind --including the extreme case of
        believing that the proposal is damaging to the Internet
        as a whole-- these comments should be directed to the
        author(s) and the RFC Editor.
    </t>
    <t> If the IESG, after completing its review, identifies issues, it
        may recommend explanatory or qualifying text for the RFC
        Editor to include in the document if it is published.
    </t>
    <t> If the IESG concludes that publication of the document 
        should be delayed for a reasonable period of time 
        because its untimely publication could cause confusion or 
        other harm with proposals under consideration for 
        standardization, the
        RFC Editor will grant that request.  The current
        agreement between the RFC Editor and the IESG on
        requested 
        delays is expected to continue.  That agreement permits
        the IESG to ask for a delay of up to six months and, if
        necessary, to renew that request twice, for a total
        possible delay of 18 months. 
    </t>
    <t> If the IESG concludes that the document should not be
        published as an RFC, it will request that the RFC
        Editor not publish and provide appropriate
        justification for that request.  The RFC  Editor will
        consider the request to not publish the document.
    </t>
    <t> The RFC Editor or the author may request that the
        IAB review the IESG's request to delay or not publish
        the document and request that the IAB provide an
        additional opinion. 
        Such a request will be made public via the RFC Editor
        Web site.  As with the IESG review itself, the IAB's
        opinion, if any, will be advisory.  And, as with author
        requests for an IAB technical review (see
        <xref target="Additional"/>), the IAB is not obligated
        to perform this type of review and may decline the
        request.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="The Editorial Review Board" anchor="EdBoard">
    <t> The RFC Editor appoints and maintains the Editorial Review
        Board, which, much like the editorial boards of
        professional journals and publishers, provides the RFC
        Editor with both advice and reviews of
        particular proposed publications and general and strategic
        policy advice.  The membership list of
        the Editorial Review Board is public and can be found at
        http://www.rfc-editor.org/edboard.html.  Editorial Board
        members serve at the pleasure of the RFC Editor.   From time to
        time, the RFC Editor will solicit suggestions for new
        appointees from the IAB and other sources and will seek
        IAB comments on those to be appointed.  The RFC Editor will
        also solicit IAB comments on the
        effectiveness of the review process and the quality of
        documents being published and criteria applied.  However,
        to ensure 
        the independence of the Independent Submission process,
        the final decision to appoint (or not appoint) Editorial
        Board members rests with the RFC Editor.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Status and Availability of Reviews" anchor="privacy">
    <t> The RFC Editor will conduct the reviews discussed above with
        the intent of balancing fairness to authors, transparency of
        the review process to the general community, protection of
        reviewers from possible retaliation or undue pressure, and the
        interest of the community in having any significant dissents
        from published documents available to the community with the
        same degree of scrutiny that the original documents
        received.   To this end, reviews and information about
        reviewers will be made public under the following
        circumstances.  In special cases in which other
        considerations apply, the RFC Editor may adopt special
        provisions after reviewing the circumstances and proposed
        action with the IAB.
    </t>
    <t> Any reviewer participating in the process outlined in
        this document does so on the condition of giving consent to
        handling of the reviews as outlined in this section.  In
        special cases, individual arrangements may be worked out
        in advance with the RFC Editor.
    </t>
    <t> As described in <xref target="Evaluation"/>, 
        all reviews will be shared with the document
        authors (with possible editing to remove any extreme language).  The
        names of the reviewers will normally accompany these reviews, but
        reviewers will be granted anonymity upon request to the RFC Editor.
        The RFC Editor will in any case forward any author rebuttal messages
        to the reviewer.
    </t>
    <t> Nothing in this section or the subsections below precludes
        private communications between reviewers, the Editorial
        Board, and the RFC Editor; such communications will
        remain confidential.
    </t>

    <section title="Posted Reviews">
        <t> Once a final accept or reject decision has been made on a document,
            the RFC Editor may choose to post the full set of reviews (and
            author rebuttals, if any) associated with a document, if doing so
            would be in the best interest of the community.  The author may
            request earlier posting of reviews and rebuttals, to inspire
            additional unsolicited reviews, for example.  The names of the
            reviewers will accompany their reviews, except for a reviewer
            who requested anonymity.
        </t>
        <t> The author will be notified in advance of the intent to
            post the final reviews.  The author may then request that the document be
            withdrawn and the reviews kept private.  However, such an author
            request must be timely, generally within 14 days of the 
            notification of intent to post.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Rejected Documents">
        <t> If the RFC Editor rejects a document, the author has the following
            options for recourse.
        </t>
        <t> <list style="symbols">
                <t> Request one or more additional reviews 
                    (<xref target="Additional"/>) followed by a 
                    reconsideration.
                </t>
                <t> Request an IAB review (<xref target="Additional"/>,
                                           <xref target="Rejection"/>) 
                    followed by a reconsideration.
                </t>
                <t> Request that the reviews be published on the RFC Editor 
                    Web site.
                </t>
            </list>
        </t>        
    </section>

    <section title="Documents Approved for Publication">
        <t> In 
            considering whether to make review materials public 
            for documents accepted for publication, 
            the RFC Editor is expected to note that the 
            best way to comment on or dissent from an RFC is 
            generally another RFC; that reviews critical of a 
            document are not themselves reviewed; that the 
            review and refutation process is necessarily fragmentary; and 
            that a reviewer who feels strongly 
            about a subject about which a review has already been 
            written often would not need to do significant 
            additional work to produce an RFC-format document from 
            that review.
        </t>
    </section>
</section>

<section title="Intellectual Property Rights" anchor="IPR">
    <t> The following material was extracted from the relevant
        sections of BCP 78 <xref target="RFC3978"/>
        <xref target="RFC4748"/> in order to
        get all Independent Submission information for technical
        publications produced under the auspices of the IETF, the IETF
Administrative Support Activity (IASA) or the IETF
        Trust, or the Internet Society (ISOC) into a single place
        and to initialize the process of separating discussions of
        Independent Submissions from those about Standards-Track
        or other IETF documents.   Note that the text that follows uses
        the term "RFC Editor Contribution" to describe the same type of document
        referred to as an "Independent Submission" elsewhere in this
        document.  The RFC Editor may change these provisions from time
        to time after obtaining the advice and consent of the IETF Trust
        in the RFC Editor's capacity as the formal publisher of RFCs.
    </t>
    <t> By submission of an RFC Editor Contribution, each person actually
        submitting the RFC Editor Contribution, and each named co-
        Contributor, is deemed to agree to the following terms and
        conditions, and to grant the following rights, on his or her own
        behalf and on behalf of the organization the Contributor represents
        or is sponsored by (if any) when submitting the RFC Editor
        Contribution.
    </t>
    <t> <list style="letters">
            <t> For Internet-Drafts that are expected to be submitted as 
                RFC Editor Contributions:  To the extent that an RFC Editor 
                Contribution or any portion thereof is protected by 
                copyright and other rights of authorship,
                the Contributor, and each named co-Contributor, and the
                organization he or she represents or is sponsored by (if any)
                grant an irrevocable, non-exclusive, royalty-free,
                world-wide right and license to the IETF Trust 
                and the IETF under all
                intellectual property rights in the RFC Editor Contribution 
                for at
                least the life of the Internet-Draft, to copy, publish,
                display, and distribute the RFC Editor Contribution as an
                Internet-Draft. 
            </t>
            <t> For an RFC Editor Contribution submitted for publication as
                an RFC, and to the extent described above, the Contributor,
                each named co-Contributor, and the organizations
                represented above grant the same license to those
                organizations and to the community as a whole to copy, publish,
                display, and distribute the RFC Editor Contribution
                irrevocably and in perpetuity and, also irrevocably and in
                perpetuity, grant the rights listed below to those
                organizations and entities and to the community:

                <list style="letters">
                    <t> to prepare or allow the preparation of translations 
                        of the RFC
                        into languages other than English,
                    </t>
                    <t> unless explicitly disallowed in the notices contained
                        in an RFC Editor Contribution, to prepare
                        derivative works (other than translations) that are 
                        based on
                        or incorporate all or part of the RFC Editor 
                        Contribution, or
                        comment upon it.  The license to such derivative 
                        works shall not grant the IETF Trust, the IETF, or 
                        other party preparing a
                        derivative work any more rights than the
                        license to the original RFC Editor Contribution, and
                    </t>
                    <t> to reproduce any trademarks, service marks, or trade 
                        names that are included in the RFC Editor 
                        Contribution solely in connection with the 
                        reproduction, distribution, or publication
                        of the RFC Editor Contribution and derivative works 
                        thereof as permitted by this paragraph.  Any entity 
                        reproducing RFC Editor Contributions will, as a 
                        condition of permission of such reproduction, 
                        preserve trademark and service mark identifiers used 
                        by the Contributor of the RFC Editor Contribution, 
                        including (TM) and (R) where appropriate.
                    </t>

                    <t> The Contributor grants the IETF Trust and the IETF, 
<!-- The RFC Editor was previously mentioned in the draft, but it isn't
     mentioned in RFC 3978 section 4.2, so removed from here for consistency.
     I assume "IETF Trust" covers it, since RFCs are copyright IETF Trust.
     Removed: "and the RFC Editor" -->
                        permission to reference 
                        the name(s) and address(es) of the Contributor(s) and 
                        of the organization(s) s/he represents or is sponsored 
                        by (if any).
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </list>
    </t>
</section>
     
<section title="Security Considerations">
    <t> This document specifies an RFC Editor (and, indirectly, IETF)
        administrative and publication procedure.  It has no specific security
        implications. 
    </t>
</section>
    
<section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="Acknowledgements">
    <t> Special thanks are due to Bob Hinden and Craig Partridge, who
        made several suggestions for improved text in earlier versions
        of this document, and to Stewart Bryant, Scott Bradner, Brian Carpenter,
        Vint Cerf, Leslie Daigle, and Olaf Kolkman,
        who made a number of useful suggestions about the
        organization and content of subsequent versions.  We also
        express our appreciation to the IETF and Scott Bradner, Editor,
        for the material extracted from
        BCP 78 <xref target="RFC3978"/> and used in <xref target="IPR"/>.
    </t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">

   &rfc2026;   <!-- Base procedures doc -->
   &rfc2223;   <!-- Instrs to RFC authors -->
   &rfc3932;   <!-- IESG- RFC Editor procedures -->
   &rfc3978;   <!-- Rights in contributions -->
   &rfc4748;   <!-- IETF Trust update to 3978 -->

</references>

<references title="Informative References">
    <reference anchor="IEN137"
               target="ftp://ftp.rfc-editor.org/in-notes/ien/ien137.txt">
        <front>
            <title>On Holy Wars and a Plea for Peace</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="Cohen" fullname="Danny Cohen">
                <organization/>
                <address/>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="1980" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEN" value="137" />
   </reference>

<reference anchor="RFC4844">
  <front>
    <title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
    <author fullname="L. Daigle" initials="L." surname="Daigle" role="editor">
                <organization></organization>
            </author>
    <author fullname="Internet Architecture Board" initials="" surname="IAB">
                <organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization>
            </author>
    <date month="June" year="2007"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4844"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2223BIS">
  <front>
    <title>Instructions to Request for Comments (RFC) Authors</title>
    <author fullname="J. Reynolds" initials="J"
surname="Reynolds" role="editor">
                <organization/>
            </author>
    <author fullname="R. Braden" role="editor" initials="R"
surname="Braden" >
                <organization/>
            </author>
    <date month="August" year="2004"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>

   &rfc2555;

<!-- examples of independent submission documents -->
   &rfc0021;
   &rfc1109;
   &rfc2441;
   &rfc1810;
   &rfc1591;
   &rfc2860;

<!-- Techspec -->
   &rfc4714;
   &rfc2434;
      
</references>

<section title="IAB Members at the Time of Approval">
    <figure>
        <artwork>
Bernard Aboba
Loa Andersson
Brian Carpenter
Leslie Daigle
Elwyn Davies
Kevin Fall
Olaf Kolkman
Kurtis Lindqvist
David Meyer
David Oran
Eric Rescorla
Dave Thaler
Lixia Zhang
        </artwork>
    </figure>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
