<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc number="4845" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IAB RFC Publication Process">Process for Publication of IAB RFCs</title>
    <author fullname="Leslie L. Daigle" initials="L." surname="Daigle"
role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>ledaigle@cisco.com, leslie@thinkingcat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="" surname="Internet Architecture Board">
     <organization>
       (IAB)
     </organization>
      <address>
        <email>iab@iab.org</email>
        <uri>http://www.iab.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2007"/>


<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
 the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/search.html. -->


<abstract>
<t>
From time to time, the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) publishes
documents as Requests for Comments (RFCs).  This document defines the process by which those
documents are produced, reviewed, and published in the RFC Series.
</t>

</abstract>

</front>
<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
<t>
From time to time, the IAB has cause to publish documents as
Requests for Comments (RFCs).   These occasions include the following:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
documents that arise from consideration of an issue by the IAB and are 
authored by the IAB through a nominated editor.
</t>
<t>
documents that report on IAB activities, such as workshop reports, and are
authored by a nominated editor, generally from among the activity participants.
</t>
<t>
documents that are not the outcome of an Internet Engineering Task
Force (IETF) Working Group effort but that the IAB has determined
would be of benefit to the IETF community to publish. Such documents
need not necessarily be authored or revised by the IAB.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The majority of documents published by the IAB will be classified as 
Informational RFCs (see <xref target="RFC2026"/>).   Generally speaking, the IAB does not publish 
Standards-Track or Experimental RFCs.  If the IAB has cause to publish a 
document as a Best Current Practice (BCP), it would fall under the
approval process of the IETF standards stream of RFCs (see <xref
target="RFC4844"/>). 
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ownership" title="Review and Approval">
<t>
In many cases, the IAB publishes documents to provide a permanent
record of an IAB statement or position.  In such cases, the IAB uses its 
internal discussion processes to refine the expression and technical
content of the document, and the document is approved for publication
if, and only if, the IAB is in agreement on its substantive content.
</t>
<t>
For certain documents, it may not be appropriate for the IAB to take responsibility for technical correctness.  For example, where the 
IAB has sponsored a workshop in which not all the participants were members 
of the IAB and/or not all the members of the IAB were present, approval 
by the IAB of a report of the workshop is used only to assert that the 
report is a faithful report of the proceedings of the workshop and that the 
matter is of interest to the community. 
</t>
<t>
Documents for which the IAB takes responsibility for technical correctness 
(the most usual case)
will be indicated by noting the IAB as an author of the document, with 
individuals noted as editors or text authors.  Other documents, such
as workshop reports,  will not 
specify the IAB as an author (although this does not preclude individual 
IAB members from being authors or editors).  
</t>
<t>  
In general, the document (introductory) text should make plain 
the role of the IAB in publishing and supporting the text.
Should the IAB have significant 
issues with any individual item in the document, a note may be
included in the document explaining the issue.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="process" title="IAB RFC Publication Process">
<t>
The following is a description of the process used by the IAB to publish 
IAB documents as RFCs.
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
The document is determined to be an IAB document by the IAB, as described in <xref target="intro"/>. 
</t>
<t>
The IAB publishes an IAB draft (draft-iab-*). Comments on the draft are 
reviewed and may be integrated into successive iterations of the draft. In 
addition to considering comments received on the draft, the IAB may elect to 
refer the document to individuals or groups and explicitly solicit comments 
as appropriate.
</t>
<t>
For documents intended to be published as BCPs, the document is passed to 
the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) with a sponsoring Area
Director (AD), and follows the process outlined in <xref target="SPONSOR"/>. 
</t>
<t>
For documents intended to be Informational RFCs, the remainder of this process 
is followed.
</t>
<t>
The chair of the IAB issues an IETF-wide Call for Comment on the 
IETF Announce mailing list. The comment period is normally no shorter than 
four weeks.
</t>
<t>
Comments received are considered for integration into the document. The IAB 
shall determine whether the document is ready for publication based on 
the comments received, or whether another round of document editing and,
optionally,  a further call for input is required.
</t>
<t>
The document is passed to the RFC Editor for publication as an IAB document 
Informational RFC. 
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
This document does not discuss matters with any particular
security implications.
</t>
</section>

<!--
<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
</t>
</section>
-->
<section title="IAB Members at the Time of Approval">
<t>
Bernard Aboba
</t>
<t>
Loa Andersson
</t>
<t>
Brian Carpenter
</t>
<t>
Leslie Daigle
</t>
<t>
Elwyn Davies
</t>
<t>
Kevin Fall
</t>
<t>
Olaf Kolkman
</t>
<t>
Kurtis Lindqvist
</t>
<t>
David Meyer
</t>
<t>
David Oran
</t>
<t>
Eric Rescorla
</t>
<t>
Dave Thaler
</t>
<t>
Lixia Zhang
</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>

<references>
<reference anchor="RFC4844">
  <front>
    <title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
    <author fullname="L. Daigle" initials="L" surname="Daigle"
role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
    <date month="May" year="2007"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4844"/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="SPONSOR">
  <front>
    <title>Guidance on Area Director Sponsoring of Documents</title>
    <author fullname="J. Arkko" initials="J" surname="Arkko" role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
    <date month="May" year="2007"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ION" value=""/>
</reference>


      <reference anchor="RFC2026">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S" surname="Bradner">
    <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="1996"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2026"/>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
      </reference>        
    
<!--
      <reference anchor="rfc1601">
        <front>
          <title>Charter of the Internet Architecture Board (IAB)</title>
          <author fullname="C. Huitema" initials="C" surname="Huitema">
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1994"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1601"/>
      </reference>        
-->

</references>
</back>
</rfc>
