<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2412 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2412.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC3261 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC3711 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC3830 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3830.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC1305 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1305.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC5125 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5125.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4082 PUBLIC ''
	 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4082.xml'
	 >
<!ENTITY RFC4086 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4383 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4383.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4442 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4442.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4563 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4563.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4566 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4567 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4567.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4568 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4597 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4597.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4650 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4650.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4738 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4738.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4771 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4771.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4909 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4909.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC4949 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml' >
<!ENTITY RFC5027 PUBLIC ''  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5027.xml' >
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="5197" category="info" >
    <front>
        <title abbrev="MIKEY Modes Applicability">On the Applicability of Various Multimedia Internet KEYing (MIKEY) Modes&nbsp;and&nbsp;Extensions</title>
        <author initials="S." surname="Fries" fullname="Steffen Fries">
            <organization abbrev="Siemens">Siemens</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Otto-Hahn-Ring 6</street>
                    <city>Munich</city>
                    <region>Bavaria</region>
                    <code>81739</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>steffen.fries@siemens.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Ignjatic" fullname="Dragan Ignjatic">
            <organization abbrev="Polycom">Polycom</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1000 W. 14th Street</street>
                    <city>North Vancouver</city>
                    <region>BC</region>
                    <code>V7P 3P3</code>
                    <country>Canada</country>
                </postal>
                <email>dignjatic@polycom.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2008"/>
        <area>Security Area</area>
        <workgroup>MSEC</workgroup>

	  <!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfceditor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

        <abstract>
            <t>Multimedia Internet Keying (MIKEY) is a key management protocol that can be used
                for real-time applications. In particular, it has been defined focusing on the
                support of the Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP). MIKEY itself is standardized
                within RFC 3830 and defines four key distribution methods.
                Moreover, it is defined to allow extensions of the
                protocol. As MIKEY becomes more and more accepted, extensions to the base
                protocol arise, especially in terms of additional key distribution methods
                but also in terms of payload enhancements.</t>
            <t> This document provides an overview about the MIKEY base document in general as well
                as the existing extensions for MIKEY, which have been defined or are in the process
                of definition. It is intended as an additional source of information for developers or
                architects to provide more insight in use case scenarios and motivations as well
                as advantages and disadvantages for the different key distribution schemes.
                The use cases discussed in this document are strongly related to dedicated SIP
                call scenarios providing challenges for key management in general, among them
                media before Session Description Protocol (SDP) answer, forking, and shared key conferencing. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
            <t>Key distribution describes the process of delivering cryptographic keys to the
                required parties. MIKEY <xref target="RFC3830"/>, the Multimedia Internet Keying,
                has been defined focusing on support for the establishment of security context
                for the Secure Real-time Transport Protocol <xref target="RFC3711"/>. Note that
                RFC 3830 is not restricted to be used for SRTP only, as it features a generic approach
                and allows for extensions to the key distribution schemes. Thus, it may also be used
                for security parameter negotiation for other protocols. </t>
            <t> For MIKEY, meanwhile, seven key distribution methods are described:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Symmetric key distribution as defined in <xref target="RFC3830"/> (MIKEY-PSK)</t>
                    <t> Asymmetric key distribution as defined in <xref target="RFC3830"/> (MIKEY-RSA)</t>
                    <t> Diffie-Hellman key agreement protected by digital signatures as defined in
                        <xref target="RFC3830"/> (MIKEY-DHSIGN)</t>
                    <t> Unprotected key distribution (MIKEY-NULL)</t>
                    <t> Diffie-Hellman key agreement protected by symmetric pre-shared keys as defined
                        in <xref target="RFC4650"/> (MIKEY-DHHMAC)</t>
                    <t> Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) assisted Diffie-Hellman key agreement as defined (not available as a separate
                        document, but discussions are reflected within this document (MIKEY-DHSAML))</t>
                    <t> Asymmetric key distribution (based on asymmetric encryption) with in-band
                        certificate provision as defined in <xref target="RFC4738"/>
                        (MIKEY-RSA-R)</t>
                </list>
                Note that the latter three modes are extensions to MIKEY as there have been scenarios
                where none of the first four modes defined in <xref target="RFC3830"/> fits perfectly.
                There are further extensions to MIKEY comprising algorithm enhancements and a new payload
                definition supporting protocols other than SRTP.</t>

            <t> Algorithm extensions are defined in the following document:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC) algorithms for MIKEY as defined in <xref target="MSEC-MIKEY"/></t>
                </list>
                Payload extensions are defined in the following documents:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Bootstrapping TESLA, defining a new payload for the Timed Efficient Stream
                        Loss-tolerant Authentication (TESLA) protocol <xref target="RFC4082"/> as defined
                        in <xref target="RFC4442"/></t>
                    <t> The Key ID information type for the general extension payload as defined
                        in <xref target="RFC4563"/></t>
                    <t> Open Mobile Alliance (OMA) Broadcast (BCAST) MIKEY General Extension Payload Specification as defined in <xref target="RFC4909"/></t>
                    <t> Integrity Transform Carrying Roll-over Counter for SRTP as defined
                        in <xref target="RFC4771"/>. Note that this is rather an
                        extension to SRTP and requires MIKEY to carry a new parameter, but is
                        stated here for completeness.</t>
                </list>
                </t>
            <t>This document provides an overview about RFC 3830 and the relations to the different extensions
                to provide a framework when using MIKEY. It is intended as an additional source of information
                for developers or architects to provide more insight in use case scenarios and motivations
                as well as advantages and disadvantages for the different key distribution schemes.
                The use cases discussed in this document are inspired by specific protocol workings
                of SIP that have proved to be problematic for a general key distribution mechanisms in
                general.  These protocol workings are described in detail in Wing, et al.
                <xref target="SIP-MEDIA"/> and include the following:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Early Media (i.e., media that arrives before
		      the SDP answer)</t>
                    <t> Forking </t>
                    <t> Call Transfer/Redirect/Retarget</t>
                    <t> Shared Key Conferencing </t>
                </list>
           </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology and Definitions">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
                NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
            <t>The following definitions have been taken from <xref target="RFC3830"/>:</t>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that the following list of terms has been 
  lightly edited to make it more consistent with the rest of the
  document and itself. If you prefer to revert to the verbatim list from
  RFC 3830, please let us know. -->

            <list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="(Data) Security Protocol:"> the security protocol used to protect the actual data
                traffic.  Examples of security protocols are IPsec and SRTP.</t>
            <t hangText="Data SA"> Data Security Association information for the security protocol,
                including a TEK and a set of parameters/policies.</t>
            <t hangText="CS"> Crypto Session, uni- or bidirectional data stream(s), protected by a single
                instance of a security protocol.</t>
            <t hangText="CSB"> Crypto Session Bundle, collection of one or more Crypto Sessions, which can
                have common TGKs (see below) and security parameters.</t>
            <t hangText="CS ID"> Crypto Session ID, unique identifier for the CS within a CSB.</t>
            <t hangText="CSB ID"> Crypto Session Bundle ID, unique identifier for the CSB.</t>
            <t hangText="TGK"> TEK Generation Key, a bit-string agreed upon by two or more parties,
                associated with CSB.  From the TGK, Traffic-Encrypting Keys can then be generated
                without needing further communication.</t>
            <t hangText="TEK"> Traffic-Encrypting Key, the key used by the security protocol to protect the
                CS (this key may be used directly by the security protocol or may be used to
                derive further keys depending on the security protocol).  The TEKs are derived
                from the CSB's TGK.</t>
            <t hangText="TGK re-keying"> the process of re-negotiating/updating the TGK (and consequently
                future TEK(s)).</t>
            <t hangText="Initiator"> the initiator of the key management protocol, not necessarily the initiator
                of the communication.</t>
            <t hangText="Responder"> the responder in the key management protocol.</t>
            <t hangText="Salting key"> a random or pseudo-random (see
            <xref target="RFC4086" />)

	<!-- [rfced] RFC 3830 refers to RAND and HAC here. 

RAND was RFC 1750, so it has been updated to RFC 4086 in your
document. It has been added as an informative reference.

Do you also want to refer to HAC and add it to the references?

   [HAC]     Menezes, A., van Oorschot, P., and S. Vanstone, "Handbook
             of Applied Cryptography", CRC press, 1996.
 -->

 string used to protect against
                some off-line pre-computation attacks on the underlying security protocol.</t>
            <t hangText="HDR">       the protocol header</t>
            <t hangText="PRF(k,x)">  a keyed pseudo-random function</t>
            <t hangText="E(k,m)">    encryption of m with the key k</t>
            <t hangText="RAND">      random value</t>
            <t hangText="T">         timestamp</t>
            <t hangText="CERTx">     the certificate of x</t>
            <t hangText="SIGNx">     the signature from x using the private key of x</t>
            <t hangText="PKx">       the public key of x</t>
            <t hangText="IDx">       the identity of x</t>
            <t hangText="[]">         an optional piece of information</t>
            <t hangText="{}">         zero or more occurrences</t>
            <t hangText="||">         concatenation</t>
            <t hangText="|">          OR (selection operator)</t>
            <t hangText="^">          exponentiation</t>
            <t hangText="XOR">        exclusive or</t>
            </list>
            <t> The following definitions have been added to the ones from <xref target="RFC3830"/>:</t>
            <list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="SSRC ">       Synchronization Source Identifier</t>
            <t hangText="KEMAC ">       MIKEY Key Data Transport Payload, containing a set of encrypted
               sub-payloads and a Message Authentication Code (MAC).
 </t>
            <t hangText="V ">       MIKEY Verification Message</t>
            <t hangText="SP ">       Security Parameter</t>
            <t hangText="Forking ">       The ability of a SIP proxy to replicate an incoming request
               to multiple outgoing requests in order to efficiently find the called party for
               rendezvous.  SIP forking can be done in serial (depth-first search) or in parallel
               (breadth-first search).</t>
            <t hangText="Redirect ">       The ability of a SIP proxy to send a final response that
               redirects the caller to send a request to an alternate location.</t>
            <t hangText="Retarget ">       The ability of a SIP proxy to re-write the Request-URI
               thereby altering the destination of the request without explicitly notifying the user
               agent client.</t>
            </list>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_overview" title="MIKEY Overview">
            <t> This section will provide an overview about MIKEY. MIKEY focuses on the setup
                of cryptographic context to secure multimedia sessions in a heterogeneous environment.
                MIKEY is mainly intended to be used for peer-to-peer, simple one-to-many, and small-size
                (interactive) groups. One objective of MIKEY is to produce a data security association
                (SA) for the security protocol, including a Traffic-Encrypting Key (TEK), which is
                derived from a TEK Generation Key (TGK), and used as input for the security protocol.</t>

            <t> MIKEY supports the possibility of establishing keys and parameters for more than one
                security protocol (or for several instances of the same security protocol) at the same
                time.  The concept of Crypto Session Bundle (CSB) is used to denote a collection of one
                or more Crypto Sessions that can have common TGK and security parameters, but that
                obtain distinct TEKs from MIKEY.</t>

            <t> MIKEY as defined in RFC 3830 may proceed with one roundtrip at most, using a so-called
                Initiator message for the forward direction and a Responder message for the backward
                direction. Note that there exist MIKEY schemes that may proceed within a half roundtrip
                (e.g., based on a pre-shared key), while other schemes require a full roundtrip (e.g.,
                Diffie-Hellman-based schemes). The main objective of the Initiator's message (I_MESSAGE)
                is to transport one or more TGKs (carried in the KEMAC field) and a set of security parameters
                (SPs) to the Responder in a secure manner.  As the verification message from the Responder
                is optional for some schemes, the Initiator indicates whether or not it requires a verification
                message from the Responder.</t>

            <t>  The focus of the following subsections lies on the key distribution
   methods as well as the discussion about advantages and disadvantages
   of the different schemes.  Note that the MIKEY key distribution
   schemes rely on loosely synchronized clocks.  If clock
   synchronization is not available, the replay handling of MIKEY
   (cf. <xref target="RFC3830" />) may not work.  This is due to the fact that MIKEY does
   not use a challenge-response mechanism for replay handling; instead,
   timestamps are used together with message caching.  Thus, the required
   synchronization depends on the number of messages that can be cached
   on either side.  Therefore, MIKEY recommends adjusting the cache
   size depending on the clock skew in the deployment environment.
   Moreover, RFC 3830 recommends the ISO time synchronization protocol
   <xref target="ISO_sec_time" />.  If replay handling is not available, an attacker may 
   be able to replay an older message that he eavesdropped earlier,
   leading to different TGKs on both sides. As these are fed to the
   application utilizing MIKEY (e.g., SRTP or TESLA), both sides may rely 
   on different keys and thus may be unable to communicate with each
   other.   The format applied to the timestamps submitted in
   MIKEY have to match the NTP format described in
   <xref target="RFC1305" />.  In
   other cases, such as of a SIP endpoint, clock synchronization by
   deriving time from a trusted outbound proxy may be appropriate .</t>

            <t> The different MIKEY-related schemes are compared regarding the following criteria:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Mandatory for implementation: provides information, if RFC 3830 requires the
                        implementation of this scheme.</t>
                    <t> Scalability: describes the technical feasibility to easily deploy a solution
                        based on the considered scheme. </t>
                    <t> Dependency on PKI: states if the support of a PKI is required to support this
                        scheme. Note that PKI here relates to PKI services like key generation,
                        distribution, and revocation. </t>
                    <t> Provision of Perfect Forward Secrecy (PFS): describes the support of PFS,
                        which is, according to RFC 4949 <xref target="RFC4949"/>, the property that
                        compromising the long-term keying material does not compromise session keys
                        that were previously derived from the long-term material.</t>
                    <t> Key generation involvement: describes if both or just one of the participants
                        is actively involved in key generation. The option to involve both parties
                        in the key generation is considered here as it addresses several points:
	                <list style="symbols">
	                    <t> If both sides contribute public entropy, it is ensured that each side
	                        can guarantee that keys are fresh to avoid replay attacks. </t>
	                    <t> Involvement of both sides avoids that one side  generates (intentionally
	                        or unintentionally) weak (predictable) nonces, which in turn may result in
	                        weak keys. </t>
	                </list></t>
                    <t> Support of group keying: feasibility of the MIKEY option to be used also for
                        group keying, e.g., in conferencing scenarios. </t>
                </list></t>

            <t> If MIKEY is used for SRTP <xref target="RFC3711"/> bootstrapping, it also uses the SSRC to
                associate security policies with actual sessions. The SSRC identifies the synchronization
                source. The value is chosen randomly, with the intent that no two synchronization sources
                within the same SRTP session will have the same SSRC. Although the probability of multiple
                sources choosing the same identifier is low, all (S)RTP implementations must be prepared
                to detect and resolve collisions. Nevertheless, in multimedia communication scenarios
                supporting forking (see <xref target="mikey_forking"/>) or retargeting
                (see <xref target="mikey_calltransfer"/>) collisions may occur leading to
                so-called two-time pads; i.e., the same key is used for media streams to different
                destinations. This occurs if two branches have the same TEK (based on the MIKEY key
                establishment) and choose the same 32-bit SSRC for the SRTP streams. The SRTP key
                derivation will then produce the same session keys (as the input values are the same) and
                also derive the same initialization vector per packet, as the SSRCs are the same.
                Note that two time pads may also occur for media streams to the same
                destination. This is outlined in <xref target="RFC3711"/>.</t>

            <section anchor="mikey_symmetric" title="Pre-Shared Key (PSK) Protected Distribution"
>

               <t> This option of the key management uses a pre-shared secret key to derive key
                    material for integrity protection and encryption to protect the actual exchange
                    of key material. Note that the pre-shared secret is agreed upon before the session,
                    e.g., by out-of-band means. The response message
	<!-- [rfced] Should this be made "Responder message"?  See also paragraph 1 of section 3.2 and paragraph 2 of section 3.7. -->
 is optional and may be used for
                    mutual authentication (proof of possession of the pre-shared secret) or error signaling.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                  Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND, [IDi],[IDr],
    {SP}, KEMAC                --->
                                           R_MESSAGE =
                              [<---]       HDR, T, [IDr], V
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> The advantages of this approach lay in the fact that there is no dependency on
                    a PKI (Public Key Infrastructure), the solution consumes low bandwidth and enables
                    high performance, and is all in all a simple straightforward master key
                    provisioning. The disadvantages are that perfect forward secrecy is not provided
                    and key generation is just performed by the Initiator. Furthermore, the approach
                    is not scalable to larger configurations but is acceptable in small-sized groups.
                    Note that according to <xref target="RFC3830"/>, this option is mandatory to
                    implement. </t>
            </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_asymmetric" title="Public Key Encrypted Key Distribution">
                <t> Using the asymmetric option of the key management, the Initiator generates the
                    key material (TGKs) to be transmitted and sends it encrypted with a so-called
                    envelope key, which in turn is encrypted with the receiver's public key.
                    The envelope key, env-key, which is a random number, is used to derive the
                    auth-key and the enc-key. Moreover, the envelope key may be used as a
                    pre-shared key to establish further crypto sessions. The response message is optional
                    and may be used for mutual authentication or error signaling.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                    Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND, [IDi|CERTi],
  [IDr], {SP}, KEMAC, [CHASH],
  PKE, SIGNi                   --->
                                            R_MESSAGE =
                              [<---]         HDR, T, [IDr], V
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> An advantage of this approach is that it allows the usage of self-signed certificates,
                    which in turn  can avoid a full-blown PKI. Note that using self-signed certificates
                    may result in limited scalability and also require additional means for authentication
                    such as exchange of fingerprints of the certificates or similar techniques.
                    The disadvantages comprise the necessity of a PKI for full scalability, the performance
                    of the key generation just by the Initiator, and no provision of perfect forward
                    secrecy. Additionally, the Responder certificate needs to be available in advance at
                    the sender's side. Furthermore, the verification of certificates may not be done in
                    real time. This could be the case in scenarios where the revocation status of
                    certificates is checked through a further component. Depending on the Initiator role,
                    this scheme can also be applied in group-based communication, where a central server
                    distributes the group key protected with the public keys of the associated clients.
                    Note that according to <xref target="RFC3830"/>, this option is mandatory to implement. </t>
            </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_dh_sign" title="Diffie-Hellman Key Agreement Protected with Digital Signatures">
                <t> The Diffie-Hellman option of the key management enables a shared secret establishment
                    between the Initiator and Responder in a way where both parties contribute to the shared
                    secret. The Diffie-Hellman key agreement is authenticated (and integrity protected)
                    using digital signatures.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                 Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND, [IDi|CERTi],
     [IDr], {SP}, DHi, SIGNi   --->
                                          R_MESSAGE =
                               <---        HDR, T, [IDr|CERTr],
                                            IDi, DHr, DHi, SIGNr
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> <xref target="RFC3830"/> does mandate the support of RSA as a specific asymmetric
                   algorithm for the signature generation. Additionally, the algorithm used for signature
                   or public key encryption is defined by, and dependent on, the certificate used. Besides
                   the use of X.509v3 certificates, it is mandatory to support the Diffie-Hellman group
                   "OAKLEY5" <xref target="RFC2412"/>. It is also possible to use other Diffie-Hellman
                   groups within MIKEY.  This can be done by defining a new mapping sub-payload and the
                   associated policy payload according to <xref target="RFC3830"/>. The advantages
                   of this approach are a fair, mutual key agreement (both parties provide to the key),
                   perfect forward secrecy, and the absence of the need to fetch a certificate in
                   advance as needed for the MIKEY-RSA method depicted above. Moreover, it also provides
                   the option to use self-signed certificates to avoid a PKI deployment. Note that,
                   depending on the security policy, self-signed certificates may not be suitable for
                   every use case.</t>

               <t> Negatively to remark is that this approach scales mainly to point-to-point and
                   depends on PKI for full scalability. Multiparty conferencing is not supported using just
                   MIKEY-DHSIGN. Nevertheless, the established Diffie-Hellman-Secret may serve as
                   a pre-shared key to bootstrap group-related security parameter. Furthermore, as
                   for the MIKEY-RSA mode described above, the verification of certificates may not necessarily be done in real time. This could be the case in scenarios where the
                   revocation status of certificates is checked through a further component.
                    Note that, according to <xref target="RFC3830"/>, it is optional to implement this scheme. </t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_unprotected" title="Unprotected Key Distribution">
                <t> RFC 3830 also supports a mode to provide a key in an unprotected manner (MIKEY-NULL). This is
                    based on the symmetric key encryption option depicted in <xref target="mikey_symmetric"/>
                    but is used with the NULL encryption and the NULL authentication algorithms. It may be
                    compared with the plain approach in sdescriptions
 <xref target="RFC4568"/>. 
<!--[rfced] Is "sdescriptions" the correct term?  Although it was in
                    the filename draft-ietf-mmusic-sdescriptions that
                    became RFC 4568, it does not appear in the RFC.
                    Perhaps it should be defined or changed to
                    "security descriptions"?  See also Section 7. -->

MIKEY-NULL
                    completely relies on the security of the underlying layer, e.g., provided by TLS.
                    This option should be used with caution as it does not protect the key management.</t>
                <t> Based on the missing cryptographic protection of this method, it is obvious that
                    perfect forward secrecy is not provided. As it is based on the pre-shared secret mode,
                    only the Initiator provides to the key management.
	<!-- [rfced] Is there text missing after "provides"? -->
 The method itself is highly scalable,
                    but again, without proper protection through an underlying security layer, it is
                    not advisable for use.</t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_dhhmac" title="Diffie-Hellman Key Agreement Protected with Pre-Shared Secrets">
                <t> This is an additional option, which has been defined in
                    <xref target="RFC4650"/>. In contrast to the method described
                    in <xref target="mikey_dh_sign"/>, here the Diffie-Hellman key agreement is
                    authenticated (and integrity protected) using a pre-shared secret and keyed hash
                    function.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                  Responder

I_MESSAGE =
    HDR, T, RAND, [IDi],
    IDr, {SP}, DHi, KEMAC      --->
                                          R_MESSAGE =
                               <---           HDR, T,[IDr], IDi,
                                              DHr, DHi, KEMAC

TGK = g^(xi * yi)                        TGK = g^(xi * yi)
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> For the integrity protection of the Diffie-Hellman key agreement,
                    <xref target="RFC4650"/> mandates the use of HMAC SHA-1.
                    Regarding Diffie-Hellman groups, <xref target="RFC3830"/> is referenced.
                    Thus, it is mandatory to support the Diffie-Hellman group "OAKLEY5"
                    <xref target="RFC2412"/>. It is also possible to use other Diffie-Hellman groups
                    within MIKEY. This can be done by defining a new mapping sub-payload and the associated
                    policy payload according to RFC 3830. This option has also several advantages, as there
                    are the fair mutual key agreement, the perfect forward secrecy, and no dependency
                    on a PKI and PKI standards. Moreover, this scheme has a sound performance and
                    reduced bandwidth requirements compared to MIKEY-DH-SIGN and provides a simple
                    and straightforward master key provisioning. The establishment of shared secrets and
                    the lack of support for group keying is a disadvantage. </t>
                <t> This mode of operation provides an efficient scheme in deployments where there
                    is a central trusted server that is provisioned with shared secrets for many clients.
                    Such setups could, for example, be enterprise Private Branch Exchanges (PBXs), service provider proxies, etc.
                    In contrast to the plain pre-shared key encryption-based mode, described in
                    <xref target="mikey_symmetric"/>, this mode offers perfect forward secrecy as well
                    as active involvement in the key generation of both parties involved.</t>
            </section>

            <!-- === -->

            <section anchor="mikey_dh_saml" title="SAML-Assisted DH key Agreement">
                <t> There has been a longer discussion during IETF meetings and also on the IETF MSEC mailing list
                    about a SAML-assisted DH approach. This idea has not been submitted as a separate document.
                    Nevertheless, the discussion is reflected here as it is targeted to fulfill general
                    requirements on key management approaches. Those requirements can be summarized as:
                    <list style="numbers">
                        <t> Mutual authentication of involved parties</t>
                        <t> Both parties involved contribute to the session key generation</t>
                        <t> Provide perfect forward secrecy</t>
                        <t> Support distribution of group session keys</t>
                        <t> Provide liveliness tests when involved parties do not have a reliable clock</t>
                        <t> Support of limited parties involved</t>
                    </list>
                    To fulfill all of the requirements, it was proposed to use a classic
                    Diffie-Hellman key agreement protocol for key establishment in conjunction with a
                    User Agent's (UA's) SIP server signed element, authenticating the Diffie-Hellman key and
                    the ID using the SAML (Security Assertion Markup Language <xref target="SAML_overview"/>)
                    approach. Here the client's public Diffie-Hellman credentials are signed by the
                    server to form a SAML assertion (referred to as CRED below), which may be used for later
                    sessions with other clients. This assertion needs at least to convey the ID, public DH key,
                    expiry, and the signature from the server. It provides the involved clients with mutual
                    authentication and message integrity of the key management messages exchanged.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                             Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND1, [CREDi],
IDr, {SP}                      --->
                                      R_MESSAGE =
                               <---   HDR, T, [CREDr], IDi, DHr,
                                      RAND2, (SP)
       TGK = HMACx(RAND1|RAND2), where x = g^(xi * xr).
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> Additionally, the scheme proposes a second roundtrip to avoid the dependence on
                    synchronized clocks and provide liveliness checks. This is achieved by exchanging
                    nonces, protected with the session key. The second roundtrip can also be used for
                    distribution of group keys or to leverage a weak DH key for a stronger session
                    key. The trigger for the second roundtrip would be handled via SP, the security
                    policy communicated via MIKEY.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                             Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, SIGN(ENC(RAND3))          --->
                                      R_MESSAGE =
                               <---   SIGN(ENC(RAND4))
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> Note that if group keys are to be provided, RAND would be substituted by that group key.</t>
                <t> With the second roundtrip, this approach also provides an option for all of the
                    other key distribution methods, when liveliness checks are needed. The drawback of
                    the second roundtrip is that these messages need to be integrated into the call flow
                    of the signaling protocol. In a straight-forward call, one roundtrip may be enough to
                    set up a session. Thus, this second roundtrip would require additional messages to be
                    exchanged.</t>

                <t> Regarding the different criteria discussed in the introduction of this section, the
                    advantages of this approach are a fair, mutual key agreement (both parties
                    provide to the key), and perfect forward secrecy. Through the second roundtrip,
                    the dependency on synchronized clocks can be avoided. Moreover, this second roundtrip
                    enables the distribution of a group key and thus enhances the scalability from mainly
                    point-to-point to also multiparty conferencing. The usage of SAML-assisted DH
                    may decrease the hidden latency cost through the credential validation necessary to
                    be done for the signed DH scheme described in <xref target="mikey_dh_sign"/>. If the
                    UA received its SAML assertion from its domain's SIP server, it is trusting the
                    server implicitly, thus, it may extend that trust to relying on it to validate the
                    other party's SAML assertion.  This eliminates not only the hidden validation
                    latency but also its computational cost to the UA.</t>

                <t> Negatively to remark is that this proposal does have one significant security risk.
                    The UA's SIP server can cheat and create an extra authentication object for the
                    UA where it has the Diffie-Hellman private key.  With this, the (SIP) server issuing
                    the SAML assertion can successfully launch a Man-in-the-Middle (MITM) attack against two of its UAs. Also,
                    two SIP servers can collude so that either can successfully launch a MITM attack
                    against their UAs. A UA can block this attack if its Diffie-Hellman key is
                    authenticated by a trustworthy third party and this whole object is signed by the
                    SIP server. Moreover, this approach uses two roundtrips, increasing the necessary
                    bandwidth and also the setup time, which may be crucial for many scenarios. For
                    the credential generation, usually a separate component (server) is necessary,
                    so serverless call setup is not supported.</t>
            </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_rsar" title="Asymmetric Key Distribution with In-Band Certificate Exchange">
                <t> This is an additional option, which has been defined in
                    <xref target="RFC4738"/>. It describes the asymmetric key
                    distribution with optional in-band certificate exchange.
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                             Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, [IDi|CERTi], [IDr],
      {SP}, [RAND], SIGNi      --->
                                      R_MESSAGE =
                               <---   HDR, [GenExt(CSB-ID)], T,
                                        RAND, [IDr|CERTr], [SP],
                                        KEMAC, SIGNr
           ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> This option has some advantages compared to the asymmetric key distribution
                    stated in <xref target="mikey_asymmetric"/>. Here, the sender and receiver do
                    not need to know the certificate of the other peer in advance as it may be sent
                    in the MIKEY Initiator message (if the receiver knows the certificate in advance,
                    RFC 3830's MIKEY-RSA mode may be used instead). Thus, the receiver of this message
                    can utilize the received key material to encrypt the session parameter and send them back
                    as part of the MIKEY response message. The certificate check may be done depending
                    on the signing authority. If the certificate is signed by a publicly accepted
                    authority, the certificate validation can be done in a straightforward manner, by using the
                    commonly known certificate authority's public key. In the
                    other case, additional steps may be necessary. The disadvantage is that no
                    perfect forward secrecy is provided. </t>
                <t> This mode is meant to provide an easy option for certificate provisioning when
                    PKI is present and/or required. Specifically in SIP, session invitations can be
                    retargeted or forked.
                    MIKEY modes that require the Initiator to target a single well-known Responder
                    may be impractical here as they may require multiple roundtrips to do key
                    negotiation. By allowing the Responder to generate secret material used for key
                    derivation, this mode allows for an efficient key delivery scheme. Note that the
                    Initiator can contribute to the key material since the key is derived from
                    CSB-ID and RAND payloads in unicast use cases. This mode is also useful in multicast
                    scenarios where multiple clients are contacting a known server and are downloading
                    the key. Responder workload is significantly reduced in these scenarios compared
                    to MIKEY in public key mode. This is due to the fact that the RSA asymmetric
                    encryption requires less effort compared to the decryption using the private key
                    (the public key is usually shorter than the private key, hence less performance for
                    encryption compared to decryption). Examples of deployments where this mode can be
                    used are enterprises with PKI, service provider setups where the service provider
                    decides to provision certificates to its users, etc.</t>
            </section>

        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_extensions" title="Further MIKEY Extensions">
            <t> This section will provide an overview about further MIKEY <xref target="RFC3830"/>
                extensions for crypto algorithms and generic payload enhancements, as well as enhancements
                to support the negotiation of security parameters for security protocols other than SRTP.
                These extensions have been defined in several additional documents.</t>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_ecc" title="ECC Algorithms Support">
                <t> <xref target="MSEC-MIKEY"/> proposes extensions to the authentication,
                    encryption, and digital signature methods described for use in MIKEY, employing
                    elliptic curve cryptography (ECC).  These extensions are defined to align MIKEY
                    with other ECC implementations and standards. </t>
                <t> The motivation for supporting ECC within MIKEY stems from the following
                    advantages:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t> ECC modes are more and more added to security protocols.</t>
                        <t> ECC support requires considerably smaller keys by keeping the same
                            security level compared to other asymmetric techniques (like RSA).
                            Elliptic curve algorithms are capable of providing security consistent
                            with Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) keys of 128, 192, and 256 bits without extensive growth in
                            asymmetric key sizes.</t>
                        <t> As stated in <xref target="MSEC-MIKEY"/>, implementations
                            have shown that elliptic curve algorithms can significantly improve
                            performance and security-per-bit over other recommended algorithms. </t>
                    </list>
                    These advantages make the usage of ECC especially interesting for embedded devices,
                    which may have only limited performance and storage capabilities. </t>

                <t> <xref target="MSEC-MIKEY"/> proposes several ECC-based mechanisms to
                     enhance the MIKEY key distribution schemes:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t> Use of ECC methods extending the Diffie-Hellman key exchange:
                            MIKEY-DHSIGN with ECDSA or ECGDSA</t>
                        <t> Use of ECC methods extending the Diffie-Hellman key exchange:
                            MIKEY-DHSIGN with ECDH</t>
                        <t> Use of Elliptic Curve Integrated Encryption Scheme (MIKEY-ECIES)</t>
                        <t> Use of Elliptic Curve Menezes-Qu-Vanstone Scheme(MIKEY-ECMQV)</t>
                    </list>
                    The following subsections will provide more detailed information about the message
                    exchanges for MIKEY-ECIES and MIKEY-ECMQV.</t>

                    <!-- === -->
                    <section anchor="mikey_ecc_ecies" title="Elliptic Curve Integrated Encryption Scheme application in MIKEY">
                    <t> The following figure shows the message exchange for the MIKEY-ECIES scheme:
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                       Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND, [IDi|CERTi],
    [IDr], {SP}, KEMAC,
    [CHASH], PKE, SIGNi        --->
                                                R_MESSAGE =
                              [<---]            HDR, T, [IDr], V
                         ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    </section>

                    <!-- === -->
                    <section anchor="mikey_ecc_mqv" title="Elliptic Curve Menezes-Qu-Vanstone Scheme Application in MIKEY">
                    <t> The following figure shows the message exchange for the MIKEY-ECMQV scheme:
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                                      Responder

I_MESSAGE =
HDR, T, RAND, [IDi|CERTi],
   [IDr], {SP},
   ECCPTi, SIGNi               --->
                                               R_MESSAGE =
                              [<---]           HDR, T, [IDr], V
                         ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    </section>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_bootstrapping_tesla" title="New MIKEY Payload for Bootstrapping TESLA">
                <t>TESLA <xref target="RFC4082"/> is a protocol for providing source authentication
                    in multicast scenarios. TESLA is an efficient protocol with low communication and
                    computation overhead, which scales to large numbers of receivers, and also
                    tolerates packet loss. TESLA is based on loose time synchronization between the
                    sender and the receivers. Source authentication is realized in TESLA by using
                    Message Authentication Code (MAC) chaining. The use of TESLA within the Secure
                    Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP) has been published in
                    <xref target="RFC4383"/> targeting multicast authentication in
                    scenarios, where SRTP is applied to protect the multimedia data. This solution
                    assumes that TESLA parameters are made available by out-of-band mechanisms.</t>
                <t> <xref target="RFC4442"/> specifies payloads for MIKEY
                    to bootstrap TESLA for source authentication of secure group communications
                    using SRTP. TESLA may be bootstrapped using one of the MIKEY key management
                    approaches described above by sending the MIKEY message via unicast, multicast,
                    or broadcast. This approach provides the necessary parameter payload extensions
                    for the usage of TESLA in SRTP. Nevertheless, if the parameter set is also sufficient
                    for other TESLA use cases, it can be applied as well.</t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_newtype_keyid" title="MBMS Extensions to the Key ID Information Type">
                <t> This extension specifies a new Type (the Key ID Information Type) for the General
                    Extension Payload. This is used in, e.g., the Multimedia Broadcast/Multicast Service
                    (MBMS) specified in the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP). MBMS requires
                    the use of MIKEY to convey the keys and related security parameters needed to
                    secure the multimedia that is multicast or broadcast.</t>
                <t> One of the requirements that MBMS puts on security is the ability to
                    perform frequent updates of the keys.  The rationale behind this is
                    that it will be costly for subscribers to re-distribute the decryption
                    keys to non-subscribers.  The cost for re-distributing the keys using
                    the unicast channel should be higher than the cost of purchasing the keys
                    for this scheme to have an effect.  To achieve this, MBMS uses a three-level
                    key management, to distribute group keys to the clients, and be able to
                    re-key by pushing down a new group key.  MBMS has the need to identify
                    which types of keys are involved in the MIKEY message and their identity.</t>
                <t> <xref target="RFC4563"/> specifies a new Type for the General Extension Payload
                    in MIKEY, to identify the type and identity of involved keys. Moreover, as
                    MBMS uses MIKEY both as a registration protocol and a re-key protocol, this RFC
                    specifies the necessary additions that allow MIKEY to function both as a
                    unicast and multicast re-key protocol in the MBMS setting.</t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_gen_payload" title="OMA BCAST MIKEY General Extension Payload Specification">
                <t> The document <xref target="RFC4909"/> specifies a new general
                    extension payload type for use in the Open Mobile Alliance (OMA) Browser and Content
                    Broadcast (BCAST) group.  OMA BCAST's service and content protection specification
                    uses short-term key message and long-term key message payloads that in certain broadcast
                    distribution systems are carried in MIKEY. The document defines a general extension
                    payload to allow possible extensions to MIKEY without defining a new payload. The
                    general extension payload can be used in any MIKEY message and is part of the
                    authenticated or signed data part. Note that only a parameter description is included,
                    but no key information. </t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_rcc-transform" title="Supporting Integrity Transform Carrying the Rollover Counter">
                <t> The document <xref target="RFC4771"/> defines a new integrity
                    transform for SRTP <xref target="RFC3711"/> providing the option to also transmit
                    the Roll Over Counter (ROC) as part of dedicated SRTP packets. This extension has
                    been defined for use in the 3GPP multicast/broadcast service. While the
                    communicating parties did agree on a starting ROC, in some cases the receiver
                    may not be able to synchronize his ROC with the one used by the sender even
                    if it is signaled to him out of band. Here the new extension provides the possibility
                    for the receiver to re-synchronize to the sender's ROC. To signal the
                    use of the new integrity transform, new definitions for certain MIKEY payloads need
                    to be done. These new definitions comprise the integrity transform itself as well as a
                    new integrity transform parameters. Moreover, the document specifies additional parameter,
                    to enable the usage of different integrity transforms for SRTP and SRTCP.</t>
             </section>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_modes_overview" title="Selection and Interworking of MIKEY Modes">
            <t> While MIKEY and its extensions provide a variety of choices in terms of modes of operation,
                an implementation may choose to simplify its behavior. This can be achieved by operating
                in a single mode of operation when in the Initiator's role. Where PKI is available and/or
                required, an implementation may choose, for example, to start all sessions in RSA-R mode, and
                it would be trivial for it to act as a Responder in public key mode. If envelope keys are
                cached, it can then also choose to do re-keying in shared key mode. It is outside the scope
                of MIKEY or MIKEY extensions if the caching of envelope keys is allowed. This is a matter of
                the configuration of the involved components. This local configuration is also outside the
                scope of MIKEY. In general, modes of operation where the Initiator generates keying material
                are useful when two peers are aware of each other before the MIKEY communication takes place.
                If a peer chooses not to operate in the public key mode, it may reject the certificate of
                the Initiator. The same applies to peers that choose to operate in one of the DH modes
                exclusively.</t>

            <t> Forward MIKEY modes, where the Initiator provides the key material, like public key or
                shared key mode when used in SIP/SDP may lead to complications in some call scenarios,
                for example, forking scenarios where key derivation material gets distributed to multiple
                parties. As mentioned earlier, this may be impractical as some of the
                destinations may not have the resources to validate the message and may
                cause the Initiator to drop the session invitation. Even in the case in which
                all parties involved have all the prerequisites for interpreting the
                MIKEY message received, there is a possible problem with multiple
                Responders starting media sessions using the same key. While the SSRCs
                will be different in most of the cases, they are only 32 bits long
                and there is a high probability of a two-time pad problem. This is due to the support of
                scenarios like forking (see also <xref target="mikey_forking"/>) or retargeting (see also
                <xref target="mikey_calltransfer"/>), where a two-time pad occurs if two branches have
                the same TEK (based on the MIKEY key establishment) and choose the same 32-bit SSRC
                for the SRTP streams and transmit SRTP packets.

                As suggested earlier, forward modes are most useful when the two peers are aware of
                each other before the communication takes place (as is the case in
                key renewal scenarios when costly public key operations can be avoided
                by using the envelope key).</t>

            <t> The following list gives an idea how the different MIKEY modes may be used
                or combined, depending on available key material at the Initiator side.
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t> If the Initiator has a PSK with the Responder, it uses the PSK mode.</t>
                    <t> If the Initiator has a PSK with the Responder, but needs PFS or knows
                        that the Responder has a policy that both parties should provide entropy
                        to the key, then it uses the DH-HMAC mode.</t>
                    <t> If the Initiator has the RSA key of the Responder, it uses the RSA
                        mode to establish the TGK. Note that the TGK may be used as PSK together
                        with Option 1 for further key management operations.</t>
                    <t> If the Initiator does not expect the receiver 
<!--[rfced] Should "receiver" in this paragraph be changed to "Responder"? See also the final paragraph in this list.-->
to have his certificate, he may use
                        RSA-R. Using RSA-R, he can provide the Initiator's certificate information
                        in-band to the receiver. Moreover, the Initiator may also provide a random
                        number that can be used by the receiver for key generation. Thus, both
                        parties can be involved in the key management. But as the inclusion of
                        the random number cannot be forced by the Initiator, true PFS cannot be
                        provided. Note that in this mode, after establishing the TGK, it may be
                        used as PSK with other MIKEY modes.</t>
                    <t> The Initiator uses DH-SIGN when PFS is required by his policy and he
                        knows that the Responder has a policy that both parties should provide
                        entropy. Note that also in this mode, after establishing the TGK, it
                        may be used as PSK with other MIKEY modes.</t>
                    <t> If no PSK or certificate is available at the Initiator's side (and likewise
                        at the receiver's side) but lower-level security (like TLS or IPsec) is in place
                        the user may use the unprotected mode of MIKEY.  It has to obeyed 
<!--[rfced] Please clarify this sentence. -->
that this
                        enables intermediate nodes like proxies to actually get the exchanged
                        master key in plain. This may not be intended, especially in cases where
                        the intermediate node is not trusted.</t>
                </list> </t>

            <t> Besides the available key material, choosing between the different modes of MIKEY
                depends strongly on the use case. This section will depict dedicated scenarios to
                discuss the feasibility of the different modes in these scenarios. A comparison of
                the different modes of operation regarding the influences and requirements to the
                deploying infrastructure as well as the cryptographic strength can be found in
                <xref target="SIP-MEDIA"/>.  The following list provides the most prominent call scenarios and are matter of
                further discussion:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Early Media</t>
                    <t> Forking</t>
                    <t> Call Transfer/Redirect/Retarget</t>
                    <t> Shared Key Conferencing</t>
                </list>
             </t>


            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_early_media" title="MIKEY and Early Media">
                <t> The term early media describes two different scenarios. The first one relates to
                    the case where media data are received before the actual SDP signaling answer has
                    been received. This may arise through the different latency on the signaling and
                    media path. This case is often referred to as media before signaling answer.
                    The second scenario describes the case were media data are send from the callee
                    before sending the final SIP 200 OK message. This situation appears usually in
                    call center scenarios, when queuing a waiting loop or when providing personal
                    ring tones.</t>

                <t> In early media scenarios, SRTP data may be received before the answer over
                    the SIP signaling arrives. The two MIKEY modes, which only require one
                    message to be transported (<xref target="mikey_symmetric"/> and
                    <xref target="mikey_asymmetric"/>), work nicely in early media situations,
                    as both sender and receiver have all the necessary parameters in place before
                    actually sending/receiving encrypted data. The other modes, featuring either
                    Diffie-Hellman key agreement (<xref target="mikey_dh_sign"/>,
                    <xref target="mikey_dhhmac"/>, and <xref target="mikey_dh_saml"/>) or the
                    enhanced asymmetric variant (<xref target="mikey_rsar"/>), suffer from the
                    requirements that the Initiator has to wait for the response before being
                    able to decrypt the incoming SRTP media. In fact, even if early media
                    is not used, in other words if media is not sent before the SDP
                    answer, a similar problem may arise from the fact that SIP/SDP
                    signaling has to traverse multiple proxies on its way back and media
                    may arrive before the SDP answer. It is expected that this delay
                    would be significantly shorter than in the case of early media though. </t>

                <t> It is worth mentioning here that security descriptions
                    <xref target="RFC4568"></xref> have basically the same problem
                    as the initiating end needs the SDP answer before it can start decrypting SRTP
                    media.</t>

                <t> To cope with the early media problem, there are further approaches to describe
                    security preconditions <xref target="RFC5027"/>;
                    i.e., certain preconditions need to be met to enable voice data encryption.
                    One example, for instance, is that a scenario where a provisional response,
                    containing the required MIKEY parameter, is sent before encrypted media
                    is processed. </t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_forking" title="MIKEY and Forking">
                <t> In SIP forking scenarios, a SIP proxy server sends an INVITE request to more than one
                    location. This means also that the MIKEY payload, which is part of the SDP,
                    is sent to several (different) locations. MIKEY modes supporting signatures
                    may be used in forking scenarios (<xref target="mikey_dh_sign"/> and
                    <xref target="mikey_rsar"/>) as here the receiver can validate the signature.
                    There are limitations with the symmetric key encryption as well as the asymmetric
                    key encryption modes (<xref target="mikey_symmetric"/> and
                    <xref target="mikey_asymmetric"/>). This is due to the fact that in symmetric
                    encryption the recipient needs to possess the symmetric key before handling the
                    MIKEY data. For asymmetric MIKEY modes, if the sender is aware of the forking
                    he may not know in advance to which location the INVITE is forked and thus may
                    not use the right receiver certificate to encrypt the MIKEY envelope key.
                    Note that the sender may include several MIKEY containers into the same INVITE
                    message to cope with forking, but this requires the knowledge of all forking
                    targets in advance and also requires the possession of the target certificates.
                    It is out of the scope of MIKEY to specify behavior in such a case. DH modes or
                    the <xref target="mikey_rsar"></xref> 
<!--[rfced] Please clarify the beginning of this sentence. -->
do not have this problem.
                    In scenarios where the sender is not aware of forking, only the intended
                    receiver is able to decrypt the MIKEY container.</t>

                <t> If forking is combined with early media, the situation gets aggravated. If MIKEY
                    modes requiring a full roundtrip are used, like the signed Diffie-Hellman,
                    multiple responses may overload the end device.  An example is forking to 30
                    destinations (group pickup), while MIKEY is used with the signed Diffie-Hellman
                    mode together with security preconditions.  Here, every target would answer
                    with a provisional response, leading to 30 signature validations and Diffie-Hellman
                    calculations at the sender's site. This may lead to a prolonged media setup delay.</t>

                <t> Moreover, depending on the MIKEY mode chosen, a two-time pad may occur in dependence
                    of the negotiated key material and the SSRC.  For the non Diffie-Hellman modes other
                    than RSA-R, a two-time pad may occur when multiple receivers pick the same SSRC.</t>

             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_calltransfer" title="MIKEY and Call Transfer/Redirect/Retarget">
                <t> In a SIP environment, MIKEY exchange is tied to SDP offer/answer and
                    irrespective of the implementation model used for call transfer the
                    same properties and limitations of MIKEY modes apply as in a normal
                    call setup scenario. </t>

                <t> In certain SIP scenarios, the functionality of redirect is supported. In redirect
                    scenarios, the call initiator gets a response that the called party for instance
                    has temporarily moved and may be reached at a different destination. The caller
                    can now perform a call establishment with the new destination. Depending on the
                    originally chosen MIKEY mode, the caller may not be able to perform this mode with
                    the new destination. To be more precise, MIKEY-PSK and MIKEY-DHHMAC require a
                    pre-shared secret in advance. MIKEY-RSA requires the knowledge about the target's
                    certificate. Thus, these modes may influence the ability of the caller to initiate
                    a session. </t>

                <t> Another functionality that may be supported in SIP is retargeting. In contrast to
                    redirect, the call initiator does not get a response about the different target. The
                    SIP proxy sends the request to a different target about receiving a redirect response
                    from the originally called target. This most likely will lead to problems when using
                    MIKEY modes requiring a pre-shared key (MIKEY-PSK, MIKEY-DHHMAC) or where the caller
                    used asymmetric key encryption (MIKEY-RSA) because the key management was originally
                    targeted to a different destination. </t>
             </section>

            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_conferences" title="MIKEY and Shared Key Conferencing">
                <t> First of all, not all modes of MIKEY support shared key conferencing. Mainly
                    the Diffie-Hellman modes cannot be used straight-forward for conferencing as this
                    mechanism results in a pair wise shared secret key.
                    All other modes can be applied in conferencing scenarios by obeying the Initiator
                    and Responder roles; i.e., the half roundtrip modes need to be initiated by
                    the conferencing unit to be able to distribute the conferencing key. The remaining
                    full roundtrip mode,  MIKEY RSA-R, will be initiated by the client, while the
                    conferencing unit provides the conferencing key based on the received
                    certificate.</t>
                <t> An example conferencing architecture is defined in the IETF's XCON WG. The scope of
                    this working group relates to a mechanism for membership and authorization control, a
                    mechanism to manipulate and describe media "mixing" or "topology" for multiple media
                    types (audio, video, text), a mechanism for notification of conference-related
                    events/changes (for example, a floor change), and a basic floor control protocol.
                    A document describing possible use case scenarios is available in
                    <xref target="RFC4597"/>.</t>
             </section>
            <!-- === -->
            <section anchor="mikey_summary" title="MIKEY Mode Summary">
                <t> The following two tables summarize the discussion from the previous subsections.
                    The first table matches the scenarios discussed in this section to the different
                    MIKEY modes.

                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
MIKEY             Early    Secure      Retarget   Redirect   Shared
mode              Media    Forking                           Key Conf
---------------------------------------------------------------------
PSK  (3.1)         Yes                                        Yes*
RSA  (3.2)         Yes                                        Yes*
DH-SIGN (3.3)                Yes*         Yes       Yes
Unprotected (3.4)  Yes
DH-HMAC (3.5)
RSA-R  (3.7)                 Yes          Yes       Yes       Yes

* In centralized conferencing, the media mixer needs to send the 
  MIKEY Initiator message.

                         ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                </t>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that the sentence above was corrected from
"needs to sent" to "needs to send". Please let us know whether that is correct.
(i.e., Was "needs to be sent to" intended?) -->


                <t> The following table maps the MIKEY modes to key management-related properties.

                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[


MIKEY             Manual    Needs      PFS    Key Generation
mode              Keys      PKI	              Involvement
--------------------------------------------------------------
PSK  (3.1)         Yes      No          No     Initiator
RSA  (3.2)         No       Yes         No     Initiator
DH-SIGN (3.3)      No       Yes         Yes    Both
Unprotected (3.4)  No       No          No     Initiator
DH-HMAC (3.5)      Yes      No          Yes    Both
RSA-R  (3.7)       No       Yes         No     Both*

* Assumed the Initiator provides the (optional) RAND value
                         ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                </t>
             </section>
        </section>


        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_transport" title="Transport of MIKEY Messages">
            <t> MIKEY defines message formats to transport key information and security policies
                between communicating entities. It does not define the embedding of these messages
                into the used signaling protocol. This definition is provided in separate documents,
                depending on the used signaling protocol. Nevertheless, MIKEY can also be transported
                over plain UDP or TCP to port 2269.</t>
            <t> Several IETF-defined protocols utilize the Session Description Protocol (SDP,
                <xref target="RFC4566"/>) to transport the session parameters. Examples are the
                Session Initiation Protocol (SIP, <xref target="RFC3261"/> or the Gateway Control
                Protocol (GCP, <xref target="RFC5125"/>). The transport of MIKEY messages as part of
                SDP is described in <xref target="RFC4567"/>. Here, the complete MIKEY
                message is base64 encoded and transmitted as part of the SDP part of the signaling
                protocol message. Note that as several key distribution messages may be transported
                within one SDP container, <xref target="RFC4567"/> also comprises an
                integrity protection regarding all supplied key distribution attempts. Thus, bidding-down attacks will be recognized. Regarding RTSP, <xref target="RFC4567"/> defines
                header extensions allowing the transport of MIKEY messages. Here, the initial messages
                uses SDP, while the remaining part of the key management is performed using the header
                extensions.</t>
            <t> MIKEY is also applied in ITU-T protocols like H.323, which is used to establish
                communication sessions similar to SIP. For H.323, a security framework exists, which
                is defined in H.235. Within this framework, H.235.7 <xref target="H.235.7"/>
                describes the usage of MIKEY and SRTP in the context of H.323. In contrast to SIP,
                H.323 uses ASN.1 (Abstract Syntax Notation). Thus, there is no need to encode the
                MIKEY container as base64. Within H.323, the MIKEY container is binary encoded.
             </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_alternatives" title="MIKEY Alternatives for SRTP Security Parameter Negotiation">
            <t> Besides MIKEY, there exist several approaches to handle the security parameter
                establishment. This is due to the fact that some limitations in certain
                scenarios have been seen. Examples are early media and forking situations
                as described in <xref target="mikey_modes_overview"/>.
                The following list provides a short summary about possible alternatives:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> sdescription - <xref target="RFC4568"/>
                        describes a key management scheme, which uses SDP for transport and
                        completely relies on underlying protocol security. For transport, the
                        document defines an SDP attribute transmitting all necessary SRTP
                        parameter in clear. For security, it references TLS and S/MIME. In
                        contrast to MIKEY, the SRTP parameter in the Initiator-to-Responder direction
                        is actually sent in the message from the Initiator to the Responder rather
                        than vice versa. This may lead to problems in early media scenarios.</t>
                    <t> sdescription with early media support - <xref target="WING-MMUSIC"/>
                        enhances the above scheme with the possibility to also be usable in
                        early media scenarios, when security preconditions are not used.</t>
                    <t> Encrypted Key Transport for Secure RTP - <xref target="MCGREW-SRTP"/>
                        is an extension to SRTP that provides for the secure transport of
                        SRTP master keys, Rollover Counters, and other information, within
                        SRTCP.  This facility enables SRTP to work for decentralized conferences
                        with minimal control, and to handle situations caused by SIP forking
                        and early media. It may also be used in conjunction with MIKEY. </t>
                    <t> Diffie-Hellman support in SDP - <xref target="BAUGHER"/>
                        defines a new SDP attribute for exchanging Diffie-Hellman public keys.
                        The attribute is an SDP session-level attribute for describing DH keys,
                        and there is a new media-level parameter for describing public keying
                        material for SRTP key generation.</t>
                    <t> DTLS-SRTP describing SRTP extensions for DTLS - <xref target="AVT-DTLS"/>
                        describes a method of using DTLS key management for SRTP by using a new
                        extension that indicates that SRTP is to be used for data protection and
                        that establishes SRTP keys.</t>
                    <t> ZRTP - <xref target="ZIMMERMANN"/>
                        defines ZRTP as RTP header extensions for a Diffie-Hellman
                        exchange to agree on a session key and parameters for establishing SRTP
                        sessions.  The ZRTP protocol is completely self-contained in RTP and does
                        not require support in the signaling protocol or assume a PKI.</t>
                </list>

              There has been a long discussion regarding a preferred key management approach in the
              IETF coping with the different scenarios and requirements  continuously sorting out key
              management approaches. During IETF 68, three options were considered: MIKEY in an updated
              version (referred to as MIKEYv2), ZRTP, and DTLS-SRTP. The potential key management
              protocol for the standards track for media security was voted in favor of DTLS-SRTP.
              Thus, the reader is pointed to the appropriate resources for further information
              on DTLS-SRTP <xref target="AVT-DTLS"/>.
              Note that MIKEY has already been deployed for setting up SRTP security context and is
              also targeted for use in MBMS applications.
           </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="mikey_iana_regs" title="Summary of MIKEY-Related IANA Registrations">
            <t> For MIKEY and the extensions to MIKEY, IANA registrations have been made.
                Here only a link to the appropriate IANA registration is provided to avoid
                inconsistencies.

                The IANA registrations for MIKEY payloads can be found under
                http://www.iana.org/assignments/mikey-payloads.  These registrations comprise the MIKEY base registrations as well as
                registrations made by MIKEY extensions regarding the payload.</t>

            <t> The IANA registrations for MIKEY port numbers can be found under
                http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers (search for MIKEY).</t>

        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t> This document does not define extensions to existing protocols. It rather provides
                an overview about the set of MIKEY modes and available extensions and provides information
                about the applicability of the different modes in different scenarios to support the
                decision making for network architects regarding the appropriate MIKEY scheme or
                extension to be used in a dedicated target scenario. Choosing between the different
                schemes described in this document strongly influences the security of the target
                system as the different schemes provide different levels of security and also
                require different infrastructure support.</t>

            <t> As this document is based on the MIKEY base specification as well as the different
                specifications of the extensions, the reader is referred to the original documents
                for the specific security considerations. </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
      

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>The authors would like to thank Lakshminath Dondeti for his document
                reviews and for his guidance.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
        &RFC3830; &RFC2119;
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <reference anchor="H.235.7">
                <front>
                    <title>"ITU-T Recommendation H.235.7: Usage of the MIKEY Key Management Protocol for the Secure Real Time Transport Protocol (SRTP) within H.235"
                    </title>
                    <author>
                         <organization/>
                    </author>
                   <date year="2005"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="SAML_overview">
                <front>
                    <title>Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) 2.0 Technical Overview, Working Draft
                    </title>
<!--[rfced] Should this reference include the location http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/documents.php?wg_abbrev=security -->
                    <author initials="J." surname="Huges" fullname="J.Huges">
                         <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="E." surname="Maler" fullname="E.Maler">
                         <organization/>
                    </author>
                   <date year="2005"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="ISO_sec_time">
                <front>
                    <title>"ISO/IEC 18014 Information technology - Security techniques - Time-stamping services, Part 1-3."
                    </title>
                    <author>
                         <organization/>
                    </author>
                   <date year="2002"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

&RFC4086;
            &RFC4568; &RFC4567;
            &RFC4566; &RFC3261; &RFC3711; &RFC4082; &RFC1305; &RFC2412;
            &RFC5125; &RFC4383; &RFC4442; &RFC4563; &RFC4650;
            &RFC4771; &RFC4738; &RFC4597; &RFC4909; &RFC4949; &RFC5027;


 <!-- was &I-D.baugher-mmusic-sdp-dh;-->
<reference anchor="BAUGHER">
 <front>
  <title>Diffie-Hellman Exchanges for Multimedia Sessions</title> 
 <author initials="M" surname="Baugher" fullname="Mark Baugher">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="D" surname="McGrew" fullname="David McGrew">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="February" day="27" year="2006" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This memo defines a new Session Description Protocol (SDP) attribute for exchanging Diffie-Hellman (DH) public keys. The attribute is an SDP session-level attribute for describing DH keys, and there is a new media-level parameter for describing public keying material for SRTP key generation. The SDP attribute supports the key establishment schemes of NIST Draft Special Publication 800-56, adds domain parameters and supports external authentication of the DH endpoint without a public key infrastructure.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

 <!-- was &I-D.ietf-avt-dtls-srtp; -->

 <reference anchor="AVT-DTLS">
 <front>
  <title>Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Extension to Establish Keys for Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP)</title> 
 <author initials="D" surname="McGrew" fullname="David McGrew">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="E" surname="Rescorla" fullname="Eric Rescorla">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="February" day="25" year="2008" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This document describes a Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) extension to establish keys for secure RTP (SRTP) and secure RTP Control Protocol (SRTCP) flows. DTLS keying happens on the media path, independent of any out-of-band signalling channel present.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

<!-- was &I-D.zimmermann-avt-zrtp; -->

 <reference anchor="ZIMMERMANN">
 <front>
  <title>ZRTP: Media Path Key Agreement for Secure RTP</title> 
 <author initials="P" surname="Zimmermann" fullname="Philip Zimmermann">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="A" surname="Johnston" fullname="Alan Johnston">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="J" surname="Callas" fullname="Jon Callas">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="June" day="3" year="2008" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This document defines ZRTP, a protocol for media path Diffie-Hellman exchange to agree on a session key and parameters for establishing Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP) sessions. The ZRTP protocol is media path keying because it is multiplexed on the same port as RTP and does not require support in the signaling protocol. ZRTP does not assume a Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) or require the complexity of certificates in end devices. For the media session, ZRTP provides confidentiality, protection against man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks, and, in cases where a secret is available from the signaling protocol, authentication. ZRTP can utilize a Session Description Protocol (SDP) attribute to provide discovery and authentication through the signaling channel. To provide best effort SRTP, ZRTP utilizes normal RTP/AVP profiles.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

 <!--was &I-D.ietf-msec-mikey-ecc; -->

 <reference anchor="MSEC-MIKEY">
 <front>
  <title>ECC Algorithms for MIKEY</title> 
 <author initials="A" surname="Milne" fullname="Andrew Milne">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="June" day="20" year="2007" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This document proposes extensions to the authentication, encryption and digital signature methods described for use in MIKEY, employing elliptic-curve cryptography (ECC). These extensions are defined to align MIKEY with other ECC implementations and standards. It should be noted that this document is not self-contained; it uses the notations and definitions of [RFC3830].</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

<!-- was &I-D.wing-mmusic-sdes-early-media; -->

 <reference anchor="WING-MMUSIC">
 <front>
  <title>Security Descriptions Extension for Early Media</title> 
 <author initials="R" surname="Raymond" fullname="Rob Raymond">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="D" surname="Wing" fullname="Dan Wing">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="October" day="18" year="2005" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This document extends security descriptions to allow early media to be received and decrypted. This extension is useful when security preconditionss isn't used.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

<!--was &I-D.mcgrew-srtp-ekt; -->
 <reference anchor="MCGREW-SRTP">
 <front>
  <title>Encrypted Key Transport for Secure RTP</title> 
 <author initials="D" surname="McGrew" fullname="David McGrew">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="March" day="2" year="2007" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>SRTP Encrypted Key Transport (EKT) is an extension to SRTP that provides for the secure transport of SRTP master keys, Rollover Counters, and other information, within SRTCP. This facility enables SRTP to work for decentralized conferences with minimal control, and to handle situations caused by SIP forking and early media.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>

<!-- was &I-D.ietf-sip-media-security-requirements; -->

 <reference anchor="SIP-MEDIA">
 <front>
  <title>Requirements and Analysis of Media Security Management Protocols</title> 
 <author initials="D" surname="Wing" fullname="Dan Wing">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="S" surname="Fries" fullname="Steffen Fries">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="H" surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
 <author initials="F" surname="Audet" fullname="Francois Audet">
  <organization /> 
  </author>
  <date month="June" day="2" year="2008" /> 
 <abstract>
  <t>This document describes requirements for a protocol to negotiate a security context for SIP-signaled SRTP media. In addition to the natural security requirements, this negotiation protocol must interoperate well with SIP in certain ways. A number of proposals have been published and a summary of these proposals is in the appendix of this document.</t> 
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress" /> 
  </reference>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
