<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc0950 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0950.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc1122 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml'> 
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>    
    <!ENTITY rfc2461 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2461.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml'> 
    <!ENTITY rfc3756 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3756.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4291 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4388 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4388.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4632 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4632.xml'>    
    <!ENTITY rfc4861 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4862 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4903 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4903.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4943 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4943.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" number="5942" updates="4861">

<front>
	<title abbrev="IPv6 Subnet Model">IPv6 Subnet Model: The Relationship between Links and Subnet Prefixes</title>
    
	<author initials="H." surname="Singh"
		fullname="Hemant Singh">
	    <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

	    <address>
		<postal>
		    <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>
		    <city>Boxborough</city> <region>MA</region>
		    <code>01719</code>
		    <country>USA</country>
		</postal>

		<phone>+1 978 936 1622</phone>
		<email>shemant@cisco.com</email>
		<uri>http://www.cisco.com/</uri>
	    </address>
	</author>

        <author initials="W." surname="Beebee"
                fullname="Wes Beebee">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
    
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>
                    <city>Boxborough</city> <region>MA</region>
                    <code>01719</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
    
                <phone>+1 978 936 2030</phone>
                <email>wbeebee@cisco.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.cisco.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
	
    
    	<author initials='E' surname="Nordmark" fullname='Erik Nordmark'>
            <organization abbrev="Oracle, Inc.">
              Oracle, Inc. 
            </organization>the 
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>17 Network Circle</street>
		    <street>Menlo Park, CA 94025</street>
		    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1 650 786 2921</phone>
                <email>erik.nordmark@oracle.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="July" year="2010" />
    
        <area>Internet</area>
        <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

  <keyword>on-link</keyword>
  <keyword>off-link</keyword>
  <keyword>ND</keyword>

  <abstract>
      <t>IPv6 specifies a model of a subnet that is different
         than the IPv4 subnet model. The subtlety of the differences has resulted 
         in incorrect implementations that do not interoperate. This document spells 
         out the most important difference: that an IPv6 address isn't 
         automatically associated with an IPv6 on-link prefix. This
         document also updates (partially due to security concerns caused by 
         incorrect implementations) a part of the 
         definition of "on-link" from RFC 4861.
      </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            
            <t>IPv4 implementations typically associate a netmask with an address
               when an IPv4 address is assigned to an interface.  That netmask
               together with the IPv4 address designates an on-link prefix.  Nodes
               consider addresses covered by an on-link prefix to be directly
               attached to the same link as the sending node, i.e., they send
               traffic for such addresses directly rather than to a router.  See
               Section 3.3.1 of <xref target="RFC1122"/>.  Prior to the development of subnetting
               <xref target="RFC0950"/> and Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) <xref target="RFC4632"/>, 
               an address's netmask could be derived directly from the address simply
               by determining whether it was a Class A, B, or C address.
               Today,
               assigning an address to an interface also requires specifying a
               netmask to use.  In the absence of specifying a specific netmask
               when assigning an address, some implementations would fall back to
               deriving the netmask from the class of the address.
            </t>


	    <t>The behavior of IPv6 as specified in Neighbor Discovery (ND)
               <xref target="RFC4861"/> is quite different. The on-link determination
               is separate from the address assignment. A host can have IPv6 addresses 
               without any related on-link prefixes or can have on-link prefixes 
               that are not related to any IPv6 addresses that are assigned to the host.
               Any assigned address on an interface should initially be considered as 
               having no internal structure as shown in <xref target="RFC4291"/>.
            </t>

	    <t>In IPv6, by default, a host treats only the link-local prefix as on&nbhy;link.
            </t>

	    <t>The reception of a Prefix Information Option (PIO) with the L-bit
               set <xref target="RFC4861"/> and a non-zero valid lifetime creates (or updates)
               an entry in the Prefix List. All prefixes on a host's Prefix
               List (i.e., those prefixes that
               have not yet timed out) are considered to be on&nbhy;link by that
               host.
            </t>

	    <t>The on-link definition in the Terminology section of <xref target="RFC4861"/>, as modified by 
               this document, defines the complete list of cases in which a host considers an address to be on-link. 
               Individual address entries can be expired by the Neighbor Unreachability 
               Detection mechanism.
            </t>


            <t>IPv6 packets sent using the Conceptual Sending Algorithm as described
               in <xref target="RFC4861"/> only trigger address resolution for IPv6 
               addresses that the sender considers to be on-link.  Packets to any other address are sent to 
               a default router.  If there is no default router, then the node should 
               send an ICMPv6 Destination Unreachable indication as specified in <xref target="RFC4861"/>  -- more 
               details are provided in the "Host Behavior" and "Host Rules"
               sections of this document.  (Note 
               that <xref target="RFC4861"/> changed the behavior when the Default Router List is
               empty.  In the old version of Neighbor Discovery <xref target="RFC2461"/>, if 
               the Default Router List is empty, rather than sending the ICMPv6 Destination 
               Unreachable indication, the <xref target="RFC2461"/> node assumed that the destination 
               was on&nbhy;link.)  Note that ND is scoped to a single link.  All Neighbor Solicitation (NS)
               responses are assumed to be sent out the same interface on which the corresponding 
               query was received without using the Conceptual Sending Algorithm.
            </t>

            <t>Failure of host implementations to correctly implement the IPv6 subnet model
               can result in lack of IPv6 connectivity. See the "Observed Incorrect Implementation 
               Behavior" section for details.
            </t>

            <t>This document deprecates the last two bullets from the definition of 
               "on-link" in <xref target="RFC4861"/> to address security concerns
               arising from particular ND implementations.
            </t>

            <t>Host behavior is clarified in the "Host Behavior" and "Host
               Rules" sections.
            </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Requirements Language">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>. 
          </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Host Behavior">
           <list style="numbers">
	       <t>The original Neighbor Discovery (ND) specification <xref target="RFC4861"/>
                  was unclear in its usage of the term "on-link" in a few
                  places.
                  In IPv6, an address is on-link (with respect to a specific
                  link), if the address has been assigned to an interface
                  attached to that link.  Any node attached to the link can send
                  a datagram directly to an on-link address without forwarding
                  the datagram through a router.  However, in order for a node to
                  know that a destination is on-link, it must obtain
                  configuration information to that effect.  In IPv6, there are
                  two main ways of maintaining information about on-link
                  destinations.  First, a host maintains a Prefix List that
                  identifies ranges of addresses that are to be considered
                  on-link.  Second, Redirects can identify individual
                  destinations that are on-link; such Redirects update the
                  Destination Cache.

                  <list style="empty">
                  </list>
                  The Prefix List is populated via the following means:

                  <list style="empty">
                  </list>

               <list style="symbols">
	       <t>Receipt of a valid Router Advertisement (RA) that specifies a prefix with the L-bit
                  set. Such a prefix is considered on&nbhy;link for a period
                  specified in the Valid Lifetime and is added to the Prefix
                  List. (The link-local prefix is effectively considered a
                  permanent entry on the Prefix List.)
               </t>
               <t>Indication of an on-link prefix (which may be a /128) via
                  manual configuration, or some other yet-to-be-specified
                  configuration mechanism.
               </t>
               </list>

               <list style="empty">
                  </list>

                  A Redirect can also signal whether an address is on-link.  
                  If a host originates a packet, but the first-hop
                  router routes the received packet back out onto the same link,
                  the router also sends the host a Redirect. If the Target and
                  Destination Address of the Redirect are the same, the Target
                  Address is to be treated as on-link as specified in Section 8
                  of <xref target="RFC4861"/>. That is, the host updates its Destination Cache
                  (but not its Prefix List -- though the impact is similar).
                  </t>

                  <list style="empty">
                  </list>

                  <t>It should be noted that ND does not have a way to indicate a
                     destination is "off-link". Rather, a destination is assumed
                     to be off-link, unless there is explicit information
                     indicating that it is on-link. Such information may later
                     expire or be changed, in which case a destination may revert
                     back to being considered off-link, but that is different than
                     there being an explicit mechanism for signaling that a
                     destination is off-link.


                     Redirect messages do not contain sufficient information to
                     signal that an address is off-link.  Instead, Redirect
                     messages indicate a preferred next hop that is a more
                     appropriate choice to use than the originator of the
                     Redirect. 
                  </t>


                  <list style="empty">
                  </list>

               <t>IPv6 also defines the term "neighbor" to refer to
                  nodes attached to the same link and that can send packets
                  directly to each other. Received ND packets that pass the
                  required validation tests can only come from a neighbor
                  attached to the link on which the ND packet was
                  received. Unfortunately, <xref target="RFC4861"/> is
                  imprecise in its
                  definition of "on-link" and states that a node considers an
                  address to be on-link if:
		
                  <list style="empty">
                  </list>

                  <list style="symbols">
                  	<t>a Neighbor Advertisement (NA) message is received
                           for the (target) address, or</t>

                  	<t>any Neighbor Discovery message is received from
                      	   the address.</t>
                  </list>   
         

	          Neither of these tests are acceptable definitions for an
	          address to be considered as on-link as defined above, and this
	          document deprecates and removes both of them from the formal
	          definition of "on-link". Neither of these tests should be
                  used
	          as justification for modifying the Prefix List or
	          Destination Cache for an address. 

                 <list style="empty">
                 </list>

	          The conceptual sending algorithm of <xref target="RFC4861"/> 
                  defines a Prefix List, Destination Cache, and Default Router List. 
                  The combination of Prefix List, Destination Cache, and Default Router 
                  List form what many implementations 
                  consider to be the IP data forwarding table for a host.  Note that the 
                  Neighbor Cache is a separate data structure referenced by the
	          Destination Cache, but entries in the Neighbor Cache are not
	          necessarily in the Destination Cache.  It is quite possible
	          (and intentional) that entries be added to the Neighbor Cache
	          for addresses that would not be considered on-link as defined
	          above. For example, upon receipt of a valid NS, Section 7.2.3
	          of <xref target="RFC4861"/> states:

                 <list style="empty">
                 </list>

                 <list style="empty">
	         <t>If an entry does not already exist, the node SHOULD create
	            a new one and set its reachability state to STALE as
	            specified in Section 7.3.3.  If an entry already exists,
	            and the cached link-layer address differs from the one in
	            the received Source Link-Layer option, the cached address
	            should be replaced by the received address, and the
	            entry's reachability state MUST be set to STALE.
                  </t>
                 </list>

	         The intention of the above feature is to add an address to
	         the Neighbor Cache, even though it might not be considered on-link
	         per the Prefix List. The benefit of such a step is to
	         have the receiver populate the Neighbor Cache with an address
	         it will almost certainly be sending packets to shortly, thus
	         avoiding the need for an additional round of ND to perform
	         address resolution. But because there is no validation of the
	         address being added to the Neighbor Cache, an intruder could
	         spoof the address and cause a receiver to add an address for a
	         remote site to its Neighbor Cache. This vulnerability is a 
                 specific instance of the broad set of attacks that are possible 
                 by an on-link neighbor <xref target="RFC3756"/>.  This causes no 
                 problems in practice, so long as the entry only exists in the Neighbor
	         Cache and the address is not considered to be on-link by the
	         IP forwarding code (i.e., the address is not added to the
	         Prefix List and is not marked as on&nbhy;link in the Destination
	         Cache).

                 </t>
                 <list style="empty">
                 </list>

                 <t>After the update to the on-link definition in
                    <xref target="RFC4861"/>, 
                    certain text from Section 7.2.3 of
                    <xref target="RFC4861"/> may 
                    appear, upon a cursory examination, to be inconsistent
                    with the updated
                    definition of "on-link" because the text does not ensure
                    that the source 
                    address is already deemed on-link through other methods:

                     <list style="empty">
			<t>If the Source Address is not the unspecified
                           address and, on link 
                           layers that have addresses, the solicitation
                           includes a Source 
                           Link-Layer Address option, then the recipient
                           SHOULD create or
                           update the Neighbor Cache entry for the IP Source
                           Address of the solicitation.
                        </t>
                      </list>
                      Similarly, the following text from Section 6.2.6 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>
                           may also seem inconsistent:
                      <list style="empty">
                          <t>If there is no existing Neighbor Cache entry for the solicitation's sender, 
                           the router creates one, installs the link-layer address and sets its 
                           reachability state to STALE as specified in Section 7.3.3.
                        </t>


                      </list>
                     However, the text in the aforementioned sections of <xref target="RFC4861"/>, 
                     upon closer inspection, is actually consistent with the
                     deprecation of the 
                     last two bullets of the on-link definition because there
                     are two different ways
                     in which on-link determination can affect the state of ND: through updating the
                     Prefix List or updating the Destination Cache.  Through deprecating the last two bullets of the on-link 
                     definition, the Prefix List is explicitly not to be changed when a node receives
                     an NS, NA, or Router Solicitation (RS).  The Neighbor
                     Cache can still be updated through receipt of 
                     an NS, NA, or RS.
                   </t>

                 <list style="empty">
                 </list>

                 <t><xref target="RFC4861"/> is written from the perspective of a host with a
   		   single interface on which Neighbor Discovery is run. All ND traffic
                   (whether sent or received) traverses the single interface. On hosts
                   with multiple interfaces, care must be taken to ensure that the
                   scope of ND processing from one link stays local to that link. That
                   is, when responding to an NS, the NA would be sent out on the same
                   link on which it was received. Likewise, a host would not respond
                   to a received NS for an address only assigned to an interface on a
                   different link. Although implementations may choose to implement
                   Neighbor Discovery using a single data structure that merges the
                   Neighbor Caches of all interfaces, an implementation's behavior
                   must be consistent with the above model.
                 </t>
                 
              </list>
             </section>
             
             <section title="Host Rules">
                 <t>A correctly implemented IPv6 host MUST adhere to the following rules:
                 </t>


               <list style="numbers">
               <t>The assignment of an IPv6 address -- whether through IPv6
                  stateless address autoconfiguration <xref target="RFC4862"/>, DHCPv6
                  <xref target="RFC3315"/>, or manual configuration -- MUST
                  NOT implicitly cause a
                  prefix derived from that address to be treated as on-link and added to
                  the Prefix List.  A host considers a prefix to be on-link only through explicit
                  means, such as those specified in the on-link definition in the Terminology 
                  section of <xref target="RFC4861"/> (as modified by this document) or via manual
                  configuration.  Note that the requirement for manually
                  configured addresses is not explicitly mentioned in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
               </t>
               <list style="empty">
               </list>

               <t>In the absence of other sources of on-link information, including Redirects, 
                  if the RA advertises a prefix with the on-link (L) bit set and later the 
                  Valid Lifetime expires, the host MUST then consider addresses of the prefix to be 
                  off-link, as specified by the PIO paragraph of Section 6.3.4
                  of <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
               </t>

               <list style="empty">
               </list>
               <t>In the absence of other sources of on-link information,
                  including Redirects, if the RA advertises a prefix with the
                  on-link (L) bit set and later the Valid Lifetime expires, the
                  host MUST then update its Prefix List with respect to the
                  entry. In
                  most cases, this will result in the addresses covered by the
                  prefix defaulting back to being considered off-link, as
                  specified by the PIO paragraph of Section 6.3.4 of
                  <xref target="RFC4861"/>. However, there are cases where an address could be
                  covered by multiple entries in the Prefix List, where
                  expiration of one prefix would result in destinations then
                  being covered by a different entry.
               </t>

               <list style="empty">
               </list>

               <t>Implementations compliant with <xref target="RFC4861"/> MUST adhere to the
                  following rules. If the Default Router List is empty and there
                  is no other source of on-link information about any address or
                  prefix:

                  <list style="format %c.">
                      <t>The host MUST NOT assume that all destinations are on-link.
                      </t>
                      <t>The host MUST NOT perform address resolution for non-link-local addresses.
                      </t>
                      <t>Since the host cannot assume the destination is on-link, and off-link traffic 
                         cannot be sent to a default router (since the Default Router List is empty), 
                         address resolution cannot be performed. This case is specified in the last 
                         paragraph of Section 4 of <xref target="RFC4943"/>: when there is no route 
                         to the destination, the host should send an ICMPv6
                         Destination Unreachable 
                         indication (for example, a locally delivered error message) as specified in 
                         the Terminology section of <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
                      </t>
                  </list>
                  On-link information concerning particular addresses and prefixes can make those
                  specific addresses and prefixes on-link, but does not change the default behavior
                  mentioned above for addresses and prefixes not specified.
                  <xref target="RFC4943"/> provides justification for these rules.
               </t>
               <list style="empty">
               </list>
	       
              </list>
       </section>

       <section title="Observed Incorrect Implementation Behavior"> 
           <t>One incorrect implementation behavior illustrates the severe consequences when the IPv6 subnet model is 
              not understood by the implementers of several popular host operating systems.  In an access concentrator 
              network (<xref target="RFC4388"/>), a host receives a Router Advertisement message with no on-link prefix 
              advertised.  An address could be acquired through the DHCPv6 identity association for non-temporary addresses
              (IA_NA) option from <xref target="RFC3315"/> (which does not include a 
              prefix length), or through manual configuration (if no prefix length is specified).  The host incorrectly 
              assumes an invented prefix is on-link.  This invented prefix typically is a /64 that was written by the 
              developer of the operating system network module API to any IPv6 application as a "default" prefix length 
              when a length isn't specified.  This may cause the API to seem to work in the case of a network interface 
              initiating stateless address autoconfiguration (SLAAC); however,
              it can 
              cause connectivity problems in Non-Broadcast Multi-Access (NBMA)
              networks.  Having incorrectly assumed an invented prefix, the
              host
              performs address resolution when the host should send all non-link-local traffic to a default router.  
              Neither the router nor any other host will respond to the address resolution, preventing this host from 
              sending IPv6 traffic.
            </t>        

       </section>

       <section title="Updates to RFC 4861">
           <t>This document deprecates the following two bullets from the on-link definition in Section 2.1 of 
              <xref target="RFC4861"/>:
              <list style="symbols">
                 <t>a Neighbor Advertisement message is received for the (target) address, or
                 </t>
                 <t>any Neighbor Discovery message is received from the address.
                 </t>
              </list>
           </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Conclusion">
           <t>This document clarifies and summarizes the relationship between links 
              and subnet prefixes described in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.  Configuration of an 
              IPv6 address does not imply the existence of corresponding on-link prefixes.  
              One should also look at API considerations for prefix length as described 
              in the last paragraph of Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4903"/>. This
              document also updates the definition of "on-link" from <xref target="RFC4861"/>
              by deprecating the last two bullets.
	   </t>
       </section>

       
       <section title="Security Considerations">
	   <t>This document addresses a security concern present in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.  As a result,
              the last two bullets of the on-link definition in <xref target="RFC4861"/> have been deprecated.
	      US-CERT Vulnerability Note VU#472363 lists the implementations affected.
           </t>
       </section>
   
       <section title="Contributors">
	   <t>Thomas Narten contributed significant text and provided substantial guidance to the 
              production of this document.
	   </t>
       </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>Thanks (in alphabetical order) to Adeel Ahmed, Jari Arkko, Ralph Droms, Alun Evans, Dave Forster, 
     Prashanth Krishnamurthy, Suresh Krishnan, Josh Littlefield, Bert Manfredi, David Miles, Madhu Sudan, 
     Jinmei Tatuya, Dave Thaler, Bernie Volz, and Vlad Yasevich for their consistent input, 
     ideas, and review during the production of this document.  The security problem related to an NS message
     that provides one reason for invalidating a part of the on-link definition was found by David Miles.
     Jinmei Tatuya found the security problem to also exist with an RS message.
 
   </t>
  </section>
</middle>
<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
	&rfc4861;  
        &rfc2119;      
	</references>

        <references title="Informative References">
        &rfc0950;
	&rfc1122;
        &rfc4632;
	&rfc2461;
	&rfc3315;
        &rfc3756;
        &rfc4291;
        &rfc4388;
	&rfc4862;
        &rfc4903;
	&rfc4943;
	</references>
        
</back>

</rfc>
