<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.3550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.3611 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3611.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.5109 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5109.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.4588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4588.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.3711 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" number="5725">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Post-Repair Loss RLE Report Block Type">Post-Repair Loss
    RLE Report Block Type for RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended Reports
    (XRs)</title>

    <author fullname="Ali Begen" initials="A." surname="Begen">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>abegen@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dong Hsu" initials="D." surname="Hsu">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dohsu@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael Lague" initials="M." surname="Lague">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mlague@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2010" />

    <!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
    the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

    <!-- [rfced] Please note that after you have approved the document,
post-xml2rfc changes will be made to update the header and
boilerplate as described in RFC 5741.
-->

    <workgroup>AVT</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a new report block type within the framework of
      RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended Reports (XRs). One of the initial
      XR report block types is the Loss Run Length Encoding (RLE) Report
      Block. This report conveys information regarding the individual
      Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP) packet receipt and loss events
      experienced during the RTCP interval preceding the transmission of the
      report. The new report, which is referred to as the Post-repair Loss RLE
      report, carries information regarding the packets that remain lost after
      all loss-repair methods are applied. By comparing the RTP packet
      receipts/losses before and after the loss repair is completed, one can
      determine the effectiveness of the loss-repair methods in an aggregated
      fashion. This document also defines the signaling of the Post-repair
      Loss RLE report in the Session Description Protocol (SDP).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) is the out-of-band control protocol
      for applications that are using the Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP)
      for media delivery and communications <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>.
      RTCP allows RTP entities to monitor data delivery and provides them
      minimal control functionality via sender and receiver reports as well as
      other control packets. <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> expands the RTCP
      functionality further by introducing the RTCP Extended Reports
      (XRs).</t>

      <t>One of the initial XR report block types defined in <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref> is the Loss Run Length Encoding (RLE) Report
      Block. This report conveys information regarding the individual RTP
      packet receipt and loss events experienced during the RTCP interval
      preceding the transmission of the report. However, the Loss RLE in an
      RTCP XR report is usually collected only on the primary source stream
      before any loss-repair method is applied. Once one or more loss-repair
      methods, e.g., Forward Error Correction (FEC) <xref
      target="RFC5109"></xref> and/or retransmission <xref
      target="RFC4588"></xref>, are applied, some or all of the lost packets
      on the primary source stream may be recovered. However, the pre-repair
      Loss RLE cannot indicate which source packets were recovered and which
      are still missing. Thus, the pre-repair Loss RLE cannot specify how well
      the loss repair performed.</t>

      <t>This issue can be addressed by generating an additional report block
      (within the same or a different RTCP XR report), which reflects the
      packet receipt/loss events after all loss-repair methods are applied.
      This report block, which we refer to as the post-repair Loss RLE,
      indicates the remaining missing, i.e., unrepairable, source packets.
      When the pre-repair and post-repair Loss RLEs are compared, the RTP
      sender or another third-party entity can evaluate the effectiveness of
      the loss-repair methods in an aggregated fashion. To avoid any ambiguity
      in the evaluation, it is RECOMMENDED that the post-repair Loss RLE be
      generated for the source packets that have no further chance of being
      repaired. If the loss-repair method(s) may still recover one or more
      missing source packets, the post-repair Loss RLE SHOULD NOT be sent
      until the loss-recovery process has been completed. However, a potential
      ambiguity may result from sequence-number wrapping in the primary source
      stream. Thus, the Post-repair Loss RLE reports may not be delayed
      arbitrarily. In case of an ambiguity in the incoming reports, it is the
      sender's or the monitoring entity's responsibility to understand which
      packets the Post-repair Loss RLE report is related to.</t>

      <t>Similar to the pre-repair Loss RLE, the post-repair Loss RLE conveys
      the receipt/loss events at the packet level and considers partially
      repaired packets as unrepaired. Thus, the methods that can partially
      recover the missing data SHOULD NOT be evaluated based on the
      information provided by the Post-repair Loss RLE reports since such
      information may underestimate the effectiveness of such methods.</t>

      <t>Note that the idea of using pre-repair and post-repair Loss RLEs can
      be further extended when multiple sequential loss-repair methods are
      applied to the primary source stream. Reporting the Loss RLEs before and
      after each loss-repair method can provide specific information about the
      individual performances of these methods. However, it can be a difficult
      task to quantify the specific contribution made by each loss-repair
      method in hybrid systems, where different methods collectively work
      together to repair the lost source packets. Thus, in this specification
      we only consider reporting the Loss RLE after all loss-repair methods
      have been applied.</t>

      <t>This document registers a new report block type to cover the
      post-repair Loss RLE within the framework of RTCP XR. Applications that
      are employing one or more loss-repair methods MAY use Post-repair Loss
      RLE reports for every packet they receive or for a set of specific
      packets they have received. In other words, the coverage of the
      post-repair Loss RLEs may or may not be contiguous.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Post-Repair Loss RLE Report Block">
      <t>The Post-repair Loss RLE Report Block is similar to the existing Loss
      RLE Report Block defined in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>. The report
      format is shown in <xref target="fig_bt"></xref>. Using the same
      structure for reporting both pre-repair and post-repair Loss RLEs allows
      the implementations to compare the Loss RLEs very efficiently.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig_bt"
          title="Format for the Post-repair Loss RLE Report Block">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     BT=10     | rsvd. |   T   |         block length          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        SSRC of source                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          begin_seq            |             end_seq           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          chunk 1              |             chunk 2           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
:                              ...                              :
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          chunk n-1            |             chunk n           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>block type (BT): 8 bits <vspace blankLines="0" />A Post-repair
          Loss RLE Report Block is identified by the constant 10.</t>

          <t>rsvd.: 4 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />This field is reserved for
          future definition. In the absence of such definition, the bits in
          this field MUST be set to zero and MUST be ignored by the
          receiver.</t>

          <t>thinning (T): 4 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />The amount of
          thinning performed on the sequence-number space. Only those packets
          with sequence numbers 0 mod 2^T are reported by this block. A value
          of 0 indicates that there is no thinning and all packets are
          reported. The maximum thinning is one packet in every 32,768
          (amounting to two packets within each 16-bit sequence space).<vspace
          blankLines="1" />If thinning is desired, it is RECOMMENDED to use
          the same thinning value in the Pre-repair and Post-repair Loss RLE
          reports. This will allow easier report processing and correlation.
          However, based on the specific needs of the application or the
          monitoring entity, different values of thinning MAY be used for
          Pre-repair and Post-repair Loss RLE reports.</t>

          <t>block length: 16 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />The length of this
          report block, including the header, in 32-bit words minus one.</t>

          <t>SSRC of source: 32 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />The SSRC of the
          RTP data packet source being reported upon by this report block.</t>

          <t>begin_seq: 16 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />The first sequence
          number that this block reports on.</t>

          <t>end_seq: 16 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />The last sequence number
          that this block reports on plus one.</t>

          <t>chunk i: 16 bits<vspace blankLines="0" />There are three chunk
          types: run length, bit vector, and terminating null. These are
          defined in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>. If the chunk
          is all zeroes, then it is a terminating null chunk. Otherwise, the
          left-most bit of the chunk determines its type: 0 for run length and
          1 for bit vector.</t>
        </list>Note that the sequence numbers that are included in the report
      refer to the primary source stream.</t>

      <t>When using Post-repair Loss RLE reports, the amount of bandwidth
      consumed by the detailed reports should be considered carefully. The
      bandwidth usage rules, as they are described in <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>, apply to Post-repair Loss RLE reports as
      well.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Session Description Protocol Signaling">
      <t>A new parameter is defined for the Post-repair Loss RLE Report Block
      to be used with Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref
      target="RFC4566"></xref> using the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
      <xref target="RFC5234"></xref>. It has the following syntax within the
      "rtcp-xr" attribute <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[pkt-loss-rle-post = "post-repair-loss-rle" ["=" max-size]

         max-size = 1*DIGIT ; maximum block size in octets

]]></artwork>

          <!-- [rfced] Is the use of "=/" correct above?  Using Bill Fenner's ABNF
parser (http://tools.ietf.org/tools/bap/abnf.cgi), we get the following error
messager: 

Errors are noted by line number and column, e.g. line:column: Something bad.

stdin(3:0): error: Rule xr-format does not yet exist; treating /= as =

parsing failed: 1 errors encountered
-->
        </figure></t>

      <t>Refer to Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> for a detailed
      description and the full syntax of the "rtcp-xr" attribute. The
      "pkt-loss-rle-post" parameter is compatible with the definition of
      "format-ext" in the "rtcp-xr" attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_security_considerations"
             title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> apply
      in this document as well. Additional security considerations are briefly
      mentioned below.</t>

      <t>An attacker who monitors the regular Pre-repair Loss RLE reports sent
      by a group of receivers in the same multicast distribution network may
      infer the network characteristics (Multicast Inference of Network
      Characteristics). However, monitoring the Post-repair Loss RLE reports
      will not reveal any further information about the network. Without the
      regular Pre-repair Loss RLE reports, the Post-repair ones will not be
      any use to attackers. Even when used with the regular Pre-repair Loss
      RLE reports, the Post-repair Loss RLE reports only reveal the
      effectiveness of the repair process. However, this does not enable any
      new attacks, nor does it provide information to an attacker that could
      not be similarly obtained by watching the RTP packets fly by himself,
      performing the repair algorithms and computing the desired output.</t>

      <t>An attacker may interfere with the repair process for an RTP stream.
      In that case, if the attacker is able to see the post-repair Loss RLEs,
      the attacker may infer whether or not the attack is effective. If not,
      the attacker may continue attacking or alter the attack. In practice,
      however, this does not pose a security risk.</t>

      <t>An attacker may put incorrect information in the regular Pre-repair
      and Post-repair Loss RLE reports such that it impacts the proactive
      decisions made by the sender in the repair process or the reactive
      decisions when responding to the feedback messages coming from the
      receiver. A sender application should be aware of such risks and should
      take the necessary precautions to minimize the chances for (or, better,
      eliminate) such attacks.</t>

      <t>Similar to other RTCP XR reports, the Post-repair Loss RLE reports
      MAY be protected by using the Secure RTP (SRTP) and Secure RTP Control
      Protocol (SRTCP) <xref target="RFC3711"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>New block types for RTCP XR are subject to IANA registration. For
      general guidelines on IANA considerations for RTCP XR, refer to <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document assigns the block type value 10 in the RTCP XR Block
      Type Registry to "Post-repair Loss RLE Report Block". This document also
      registers the SDP <xref target="RFC4566"></xref> parameter
      "post-repair-loss-rle" for the "rtcp-xr" attribute in the RTCP XR SDP
      Parameters Registry.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <preamble>The contact information for the registrations
          is:</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
Ali Begen
abegen@cisco.com

170 West Tasman Drive
San Jose, CA 95134 USA]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank the members of the VQE Team at Cisco
      and Colin Perkins for their inputs and suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &__reference.RFC.2119;

      &__reference.RFC.3550;

      &__reference.RFC.3611;

      &__reference.RFC.4566;

      &__reference.RFC.5234;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &__reference.RFC.5109;

      &__reference.RFC.4588;

      &__reference.RFC.3711;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
