<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc4181 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4181.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>

<rfc number="5249" category="bcp" seriesNo="139">
  <front>
 
    <title abbrev="MIB Module Document Templates">Templates for Internet-Drafts
    Containing MIB Modules</title>

      <author fullname="David Harrington" initials="D" role="editor"
            surname="Harrington">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Drive, Suite 100</street>

          <city>Plano, TX 75075</city>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 603 436 8634</phone>

        <email>dharrington@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <date month="July" year="2008" />

    <area>Operations &amp; Management Area</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Network Management</keyword>

    <keyword>Management Information Base</keyword>

    <keyword>MIB</keyword>

    <keyword>SMIv2</keyword>
    
    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>   This memo references three annotated templates for IETF documents
   that contain the definition of MIB modules.  It is intended to
   reduce the work of the editors of such documents, making these
   documents more uniform and easier to read and review, thus furthering the
   quality of such documents and expediting their publication.
</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>This memo references three annotated templates for IETF documents
   that contain the definition of MIB modules.  It is intended to
   reduce the work of the editors of such documents, making these
   more uniform and easier to read and review, thus furthering the
   quality of such documents and expediting their publication.
</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Overview">

<t>
The MIB Doctors directorate has produced three templates specifically aimed at Internet-Drafts containing MIB modules. 
The templates are available at the IETF Tools web site, listed as
"Templates for MIB Documents".


<list style="symbols"> 
<t>The first is an XML template for editors that use XML2RFC. Some advice echoing guidelines 
from RFC 4181 is embedded in comments. </t>
<t>A second template is a text template for MIB documents with advice embedded in the document. </t>
<t>A third template is a plain text template with no advice included. </t></list>
</t>

      <t>The templates were developed 
      to make IETF documents that contain MIB modules more consistent. This makes it easier for a MIB Doctor 
      and other IETF participants 
      to review the document. There are a number of MUSTs in the templates, especially in the advice; these usually 
      refer to IESG requirements for Internet-Drafts, and MIB Doctors are likely to check for these requirements.</t>
      

      <t>The templates contain boilerplates that are required for IETF MIB module documents. It has been common practice for 
      editors to use existing MIB module documents as templates. This approach has problems because boilerplates and other 
      required elements change over time. The templates referenced by this document will be made available on the IETF Tools web site, 
      and occasionally updated to reflect the latest requirements.  The most up-to-date revisions of the templates are 
      available at http://www.tools.ietf.org.</t>
      
      <t>The templates contain sections that describe the purpose and organization of the MIB module, and the relationship
      between this MIB module and other MIB modules. This makes it easier for MIB Doctors to understand the MIB module, 
      which speeds the review process. </t>
      
      <t>Editors should read RFC 4181 "Guidelines for Authors and Reviewers 
      of MIB Documents" <xref target="RFC4181"></xref>, which describes best current practices for MIB module document editing. 
      </t>
      
      <t>The document templates do not include a template for the MIB module itself. Tools to validate MIB modules typically require that the 
      MIB module be separated from the surrounding document. The MIB Doctors feel that the simplest approach is to develop the 
      MIB module outside the document that contains the surrounding text, and then include the MIB module into the surrounding
      document written using the templates.</t>
      
    </section>

     <section title="Security Considerations">
 <t>This memo recommends templates for editing; it has no direct impact on network security. 
 The templates include boilerplates and associated advice for
writing the Security Considerations section of an Internet-Draft
that documents a MIB module.
</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">

     <t>These templates are based on contributions from the MIB Doctors,
      especially Juergen Schoenwaelder, Dave Perkins, C.M. Heard, and Randy
      Presuhn.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
 
      &rfc4181;

    </references>

    <!--
$LId: draft-harrington-text-mib-doc-template.xml,v $

	place for source control log here
  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
