<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>
 
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="5310" category='std'>
<front>
<title abbrev="IS-IS Generic Crypto Authentication">
IS-IS Generic Cryptographic Authentication</title>

<author initials="M." surname="Bhatia" fullname="Manav Bhatia">
  <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <city>Bangalore</city> <region></region> <code></code>
      <country>India</country>
    </postal>
    <email>manav@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="V." surname="Manral" fullname="Vishwas Manral">
  <organization>IP Infusion</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
<city>Almora</city> <region>Uttarakhand</region> <code></code>
<country>India</country>
    </postal>
    <email>vishwas@ipinfusion.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="T." surname="Li" fullname="Tony Li">
  <organization>Redback Networks Inc.</organization>
  <address>
    <postal> 
      <street> 300 Holger Way</street>
      <city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region> <code>95134 </code>
      <country>USA </country>
    </postal>
    <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="R." surname="Atkinson" fullname="Randall J. Atkinson">
  <organization>Extreme Networks</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>3585  Monroe Street</street>
      <city>Santa Clara</city> <region>CA</region> <code>95051</code>
      <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <email>rja@extremenetworks.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="R." surname="White" fullname="Russ White">
  <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <city></city> <region>RTP North Carolina</region> <code></code>
      <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <email>riw@cisco.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="M." surname="Fanto" fullname="Matthew J. Fanto">
  <organization>Aegis Data Security</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <city>Dearborn</city> <region>MI</region> <code></code>
      <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <email>mfanto@aegisdatasecurity.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date month="January" year="2009" />

<area>Routing</area>
<workgroup>IS-IS</workgroup>

<keyword>IS-IS</keyword>
<keyword>Security</keyword>
<keyword>HMAC-SHA</keyword>
<keyword>Cryptographic Authentication</keyword>
<abstract><t>

  This document proposes an extension to Intermediate System to 
   Intermediate System (IS-IS) to allow the use of any cryptographic 
   authentication algorithm in addition to the already-documented 
   authentication schemes, described in the base specification and RFC 
   5304. IS-IS is specified in International Standards Organization  
   (ISO) 10589, with extensions to support Internet Protocol version 4 
   (IPv4) described in RFC 1195. 
    </t>
<t>    
   Although this document has been written specifically for using the 
   Hashed Message Authentication Code (HMAC) construct along with the 
   Secure Hash Algorithm (SHA) family of cryptographic hash functions, 
   the method described in this document is generic and can be used to 
   extend IS-IS to support any cryptographic hash function in the 
   future. 

</t>
</abstract>
</front>
<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<t>
  The Intermediate System to Intermediate System (IS-IS) specification  
  (<xref target="ISO"></xref>, <xref target="RFC1195"></xref>) allows for authentication of its Protocol Data Units 
  (PDUs) via the authentication TLV 10 that is carried as a part of the 
   PDU. The base specification has provision for only cleartext 
   passwords and RFC 5304 <xref target="RFC5304"></xref> augments this to provide the 
   capability to use Hashed Message Authentication Code - Message Digest 
   5 (HMAC-MD5) authentication for its PDUs. 
</t>
<t>    
   The first octet of the value field of TLV 10 specifies the type of 
   authentication to be carried out. Type 0 is reserved, Type 1 
   indicates a cleartext password, Type 54 indicates HMAC MD5, and Type 
   255 is used for routing domain private authentication methods. The 
   remainder of the value field contains the actual authentication data, 
   determined by the value of the authentication type. 
</t>
<t>    
   This document proposes a new authentication type to be carried in TLV 
   10, called the generic cryptographic authentication (CRYPTO_AUTH). 
   This can be used to specify any authentication algorithm for 
   authenticating and verifying IS-IS PDUs.  
</t>
<t>        
   This document also explains how HMAC-SHA authentication can be used 
   in IS-IS. 
</t>
<t>    
   By definition, HMAC (<xref target="RFC2104"></xref>, <xref target="FIPS-198"></xref>) requires a cryptographic hash function. 
   We propose to use any one of SHA-1, SHA-224, SHA-256, SHA-384, or
   SHA-512 <xref target="FIPS-180-3"></xref> to authenticate the IS-IS PDUs. 
</t>    
<t>
   We propose to do away with the per-interface keys and instead have 
   Key IDs that map to unique IS-IS Security Associations (SAs).  
</t>
<t>    
   While at the time of this writing there are no openly published 
   attacks on the HMAC-MD5 mechanism, some
   reports (<xref target="Dobb96a"></xref>, <xref target="Dobb96b"></xref>)
   create concern about the ultimate strength of the MD5 cryptographic 
   hash function. 
</t>    
<t>
   The mechanism described in this document does not provide 
   confidentiality, since PDUs are sent in the clear.  However, the 
   objective of a routing protocol is to advertise the routing topology, 
   and confidentiality is not normally required for routing protocols. 
</t>

<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
           <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", 
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this  
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
       </section>
</section>
<section title="IS-IS Security Association">

<t>
   An IS-IS Security Association contains a set of parameters shared 
   between any two legitimate IS-IS speakers.  
</t>
<t>    
   Parameters associated with an IS-IS SA: 
</t>

<list style="symbols">
   <t> Key Identifier (Key ID): This is a two-octet unsigned integer used 
   to uniquely identify an IS-IS SA, as manually configured by the 
   network operator.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>

   The receiver determines the active SA by looking at the Key ID field 
   in the incoming PDU.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>

   The sender, based on the active configuration, selects the Security 
   Association to use and puts the correct Key ID value associated with 
   the Security Association in the IS-IS PDU. If multiple valid and 
   active IS-IS Security Associations exist for a given outbound 
   interface at the time an IS-IS PDU is sent, the sender may use any of 
   those Security Associations to protect the packet. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>

   Using Key IDs makes changing keys while maintaining protocol 
   operation convenient. Each Key ID specifies two independent parts:
   the authentication protocol and the authentication key, explained 
   below. Normally, an implementation would allow the network operator 
   to configure a set of keys in a key chain, with each key in the chain 
   having a fixed lifetime. The actual operation of these mechanisms is 
   outside the scope of this document. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>

   Note that each Key ID can indicate a key with a different 
   authentication protocol. This allows multiple authentication 
   mechanisms to be used at various times without disrupting an IS-IS 
   peering, including the introduction of new authentication
   mechanisms. </t>

   <t> Authentication Algorithm: This signifies the authentication 
   algorithm to be used with the IS-IS SA. This information is never 
   sent in cleartext over the wire. Because this information is not sent 
   on the wire, the implementer chooses an implementation-specific 
   representation for this information. At present, the following values 
   are possible: HMAC-SHA-1, HMAC-SHA-224, HMAC-SHA-256, HMAC-SHA-384, 
   and HMAC-SHA-512. 
   </t>

   <t> Authentication Key: This value denotes the cryptographic 
   authentication key associated with the IS-IS SA. The length of this 
   key is variable and depends upon the authentication algorithm 
   specified by the IS-IS SA.  
</t>
</list>
</section>

<section title="Authentication Procedures">
<section title="Authentication TLV ">

<t>

   A new authentication code, 3, indicates that the CRYPTO_AUTH mechanism 
   described in this document is in use and is inserted in the first octet 
   of the existing IS-IS Authentication TLV (10). 
</t>
<figure anchor="Figure 1">
           <artwork>
                   0                   1  
                   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                   |    Type 10    |       
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                   |    Length     |    
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                   |  Auth Type 3  |    
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                   |     Key ID                    |
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-|
                   |                               |
                   +                               +
                   | Authentication Data (Variable)|
                   +                               +
                   |                               |
                   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 

                   
            </artwork>
       </figure>

</section>
<section title="Authentication Process">

<t>
   When calculating the CRYPTO_AUTH result for Sequence Number PDUs, 
   Level 1 Sequence Number PDUs SHALL use the Area Authentication string, 
   as in Level 1 Link State PDUs. Level 2 Sequence Number PDUs shall use 
   the domain authentication string, as in Level 2 Link State PDUs. 
   </t>
<t>  
   IS-IS HELLO PDUs SHALL use the Link Level Authentication string, 
   which MAY be different from that of Link State PDUs. The CRYPTO_AUTH   
   result for the IS-IS HELLO PDUs SHALL be calculated after the PDU is 
   padded to the MTU size, if padding is not disabled.  Implementations 
   that support the optional checksum for the Sequence Number PDUs and 
   IS-IS HELLO PDUs MUST NOT include the Checksum TLV. 
</t>
</section>
<section title="Cryptographic Aspects">
<t>
   In the algorithm description below, the following nomenclature, which 
   is consistent with <xref target="FIPS-198"></xref> is used: 
   </t>

<figure><artwork>

   H    is the specific hashing algorithm (e.g., SHA-256).
   K    is the password for the PDU type as per the International 
        Standard ISO/IEC 10589 [ISO].
   Ko   is the cryptographic key used with the hash algorithm.

   B    is the block size of H, measured in octets rather than bits.     
        Note that B is the internal block size, not the hash size. 
             For SHA-1 and SHA-256:   B == 64
             For SHA-384 and SHA-512: B == 128

   L    is the length of the hash, measured in octets rather than bits.

   XOR  is the exclusive-or operation.

   Opad is the hexadecimal value 0x5c repeated B times.
   Ipad is the hexadecimal value 0x36 repeated B times.
   Apad is the hexadecimal value 0x878FE1F3 repeated (L/4) times.
</artwork></figure>

<list style="format (%d)">
   <t>Preparation of the Key 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      In this application, Ko is always L octets long. 

<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      If the Authentication Key (K) is L octets long, then Ko is equal 
      to K. &nbsp;If the Authentication Key (K) is more than L octets long, 
      then Ko is set to H(K).  If the Authentication Key (K) is less 
      than L octets long, then Ko is set to the Authentication Key (K) 
      with zeros appended to the end of the Authentication Key (K) such 
      that Ko is L octets long. </t>

   <t>First Hash 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      First, the IS-IS packet's Authentication Data field is filled with  
      the value Apad, and the Authentication Type field is set to 0x3. 

<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Then, a first hash, also known as the inner hash, is computed 
      as follows: </t>

<figure><artwork>
              First-Hash = H(Ko XOR Ipad || (IS-IS PDU)) 
</artwork></figure>

   <t>Second Hash 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Then a second hash, also known as the outer hash, is computed 
      as follows: </t>

<figure><artwork>
              Second-Hash = H(Ko XOR Opad || First-Hash) 
</artwork></figure>

   <t>Result 

<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The resulting second hash becomes the authentication data that is 
      sent in the Authentication Data field of the IS-IS PDU. The length  
      of the Authentication Data field is always identical to the  
      message digest size of the specific hash function H that is being  
      used. 

<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      This also means that the use of hash functions with larger output  
      sizes will also increase the size of the IS-IS PDU as transmitted  
      on the wire.</t>
</list>
</section>

<section title='Procedures at the Sending Side '>
<t> 
   An appropriate IS-IS SA is selected for use with an outgoing IS-IS   
   PDU. This is done based on the active key at that instant. If IS-IS   
   is unable to find an active key, then the PDU is discarded.  
   </t>
<t>      
   If IS-IS is able to find the active key, then the key provides the 
   authentication algorithm (HMAC-SHA-1, HMAC-SHA-224, HMAC-SHA-256, 
   HMAC-SHA-384, or HMAC-SHA-512) that needs to be applied on the PDU. 
   </t>
<t>  
   An implementation MUST fill the authentication type and the length 
   before the authentication data is computed. The authentication data 
   is computed as explained in the previous section. The length of the 
   TLV is set as per the authentication algorithm that is being used.  
   </t>
<t>  
   The length is set to 23 for HMAC-SHA-1, 31 for HMAC-SHA-224, 35 for 
   HMAC-SHA-256, 51 for HMAC-SHA-384, and 67 for HMAC-SHA-512. Note that 
   two octets have been added to account for the Key ID and one octet 
   for the authentication type.  
   </t>
<t>  
   The Key ID is filled. 
   </t>
<t>  
   The Checksum and Remaining Lifetime fields are set to zero for the 
   Link State Packets (LSPs) before authentication is calculated. 
   </t>
<t>  
   The result of the authentication algorithm is placed in the 
   authentication data, following the Key ID. 
   </t>
<t>  
   The authentication data for the IS-IS IIH PDUs MUST be computed after 
   the IS-IS Hello (IIH) has been padded to the MTU size, if padding is not explicitly 
   disabled.  
 </t>
</section>
<section title='Procedure at the Receiving Side'>
<t>
  The appropriate IS-IS SA is identified by looking at the Key ID from 
   the Authentication TLV 10 from the incoming IS-IS PDU. 
 </t>
<t>    
   Authentication-algorithm-dependent processing needs to be performed, 
   using the algorithm specified by the appropriate IS-IS SA for the 
   received packet. 
 </t>
<t>    
   Before an implementation performs any processing, it needs to save the 
   values of the Authentication Value, the Checksum, and the 
   Remaining Lifetime fields. 
 </t>
<t>    
   It should then set the Authentication Value field with Apad and 
   the Checksum and Remaining Lifetime fields with zero before the authentication 
   data is computed. The calculated data is compared with the received 
   authentication data in the PDU, and the PDU is discarded if the two do 
   not match. In such a case, an error event SHOULD be logged. 
 </t>
<t>    
   An implementation MAY have a transition mode where it includes 
   CRYPTO_AUTH information in the PDUs but does not verify this 
   information. This is provided as a transition aid for networks in the 
   process of migrating to the new CRYPTO_AUTH-based authentication 
   schemes.     
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title='Security Considerations'>
<t> 
   This document proposes extensions to IS-IS that make it more 
   secure than what it is today. It does not provide confidentiality as 
   a routing protocol contains information that does not need to be kept 
   secret. It does, however, provide means to authenticate the sender of 
   the PDUs, which is of interest to us. 
 </t>
<t>    
   It should be noted that authentication method described in this 
   document is not being used to authenticate the specific originator of 
   a PDU, but is rather being used to confirm that the PDU has indeed 
   been issued by an intermediate system that had access to either the area or 
   domain password, depending upon the kind of PDU it is. 
 </t>
<t>    
   The mechanism described here is not perfect and does not need to be 
   perfect. Instead, this mechanism represents a significant increase in 
   the work function of an adversary attacking the IS-IS 
   protocol, while not causing undue implementation, deployment, or 
   operational complexity. 
 </t>
<t>    
   The mechanism detailed in this document does not protect IS-IS 
   against replay attacks. An adversary could in theory replay old IIHs 
   and bring down the adjacency <xref target="CRYPTO"></xref> or
   replay old Complete Sequence Number PDUs (CSNPs) and Partial Sequence
   Number PDUs (PSNPs) 
   that would cause a flood of LSPs in the network. Using some sort of 
   crypto sequence numbers in IS-IS IIHs and CSNP/PSNPs is an option to 
   solve this problem. Discussing this is beyond the scope of this 
   document. 
 </t>
<t>    
   This document states that the remaining lifetime of the LSP MUST be 
   set to zero before computing the authentication, thus this field is 
   not authenticated. This field is excluded so that the LSPs may be 
   aged by the ISes in between, without requiring re-computation of the 
   authentication data. This can be exploited by an attacker. 
 </t>
<t>    
   There is a transition mode suggested where routers can ignore the 
   CRYPTO_AUTH information carried in the PDUs. The operator must ensure 
   that this mode is only used when migrating to the new
   CRYPTO_AUTH-based authentication scheme, as this leaves the router vulnerable to 
   an attack. 
 </t>
<t>    
   To ensure greater security, the keys used should be changed 
   periodically, and implementations MUST be able to store and use more 
   than one key at the same time. Operators should ensure that the 
   authentication key is never sent over the network in cleartext via 
   any protocol. Care should also be taken to ensure that the selected 
   key is unpredictable, avoiding any keys known to be weak for the 
   algorithm in use. <xref target="RFC4086"></xref> contains helpful information on both key 
   generation techniques and cryptographic randomness. 
 </t>
<t>    
   It should be noted that the cryptographic strength of the HMAC 
   depends upon the cryptographic strength of the underlying hash 
   function and on the size and quality of the key. 
 </t>
<t>    
   If a stronger authentication were believed to be required, then the 
   use of a full digital signature <xref target="RFC2154"></xref> would be an approach that 
   should be seriously considered.  It was rejected for this purpose at 
   this time because the computational burden of full digital signatures 
   is believed to be much higher than is reasonable given the current 
   threat environment in operational commercial networks.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t> 
  The authors would like to thank Hugo Krawczyk, Arjen K. Lenstra (Bell 
   Labs), and Eric Grosse (Bell Labs) for educating us on some of the 
   finer points related to Crypto Mathematics. 
 </t>
<t>    
   We would also like to thank Bill Burr, Tim Polk, John Kelsey, and 
   Morris Dworkin of (US) NIST for review of portions of this document 
   that are directly derived from the closely related work on RIPv2 
   Cryptographic Authentication <xref target="RFC4822"></xref>. 
 </t>
<t>    
   We would also like to mention Alfred Hoenes for his careful and 
   detailed review during the last call.</t>

   <t>Lastly, we would like to acknowledge Brian and Stephen Eisenberg
     for their continued support.</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t> IANA has registered the value for the CRYPTO_AUTH method in the
"IS-IS Authentication Type Codes for TLV 10" subregistry established
by <xref target="RFC5304"></xref>.  The value 3 denotes the
CRYPTO_AUTH mechanism for authenticating IS-IS PDUs.
</t>

<figure>
           <artwork>
   +--------------------------------------------+-------+-------------+ 
   | Authentication Type Code                   | Value | Reference   | 
   +--------------------------------------------+-------+-------------+ 
   | Cryptographic Authentication (CRYPTO_AUTH) |   3   |  [RFC5310]  | 
   +--------------------------------------------+-------+-------------+ 
</artwork>
</figure>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title='Normative References'>
  <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2001" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
      </reference>
<reference anchor="ISO">
        <front>
          <title>Intermediate system to Intermediate system routeing information exchange protocol for use in conjunction with the Protocol for providing the Connectionless-mode Network Service (ISO 8473)</title>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:1992" />
      </reference>
 <reference anchor="RFC1195">
        <front>
          <title>Use of OSI IS-IS for routing in TCP/IP and 
              dual environments</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Callon">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="1990" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1195" />
      </reference>
 <reference anchor="RFC5304">
        <front>
          <title>Intermediate System to Intermediate System (IS-IS) Cryptographic Authentication</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Li">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Atkinson">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5304" />
      </reference>
 <reference anchor="RFC2104">
        <front>
          <title>HMAC: Keyed-Hashing for Message  Authentication</title>
          <author initials="H." surname="Krawczk">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="1997" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2104" />
      </reference>
<reference anchor="FIPS-180-3">
        <front>
          <title>Secure Hash Standard (SHS)</title>
          <author initials="" surname="US National Institute of Standards & Technology">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
       <date month="October" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FIPS PUB" value="180-3" />
      </reference>

<reference anchor="FIPS-198">
        <front>
          <title> The  Keyed-Hash Message Authentication Code (HMAC)</title>
         <author initials="" surname="US National Institute of Standards & Technology">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
       <date month="March" year="2002" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FIPS PUB" value="198" />
      </reference>

</references>

<references title='Informative References'>

<reference anchor='Dobb96a'>
<front>
<title>Cryptanalysis of MD5 Compress</title>
<author initials="H" surname="Dobbertin">
 <organization>Unknown</organization>
</author>
<date month='May' day='2' year='1996' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Technical" value="Report" />
</reference>

<reference anchor='Dobb96b'>
<front>
<title>The Status of MD5 After a Recent Attack </title>
<author initials="H" surname="Dobbertin">
<organization>Unknown</organization>
</author>
<date month='Summer'  year='1996' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Cryptobytes, Volume" value="2" />
<seriesInfo name="No" value="2" />
</reference>

 <reference anchor="CRYPTO">
        <front>
          <title>Issues with existing Cryptographic Protection Methods for Routing Protocols</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Vishwas">
            <organization>IP Infusion</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="White">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bhatia">
            <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

 <reference anchor="RFC4086">
        <front>
          <title>Randomness Requirements for Security</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
 <author initials="J." surname="Schiller">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
 <author initials="S." surname="Crocker">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4086" />
      </reference>

 <reference anchor="RFC2154">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF with Digital Signatures</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Murphy">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
 <author initials="M." surname="Badger">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
 <author initials="B." surname="Wellington">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="1997" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2154" />
      </reference>

 <reference anchor="RFC4822">
        <front>
          <title>RIPv2 Cryptographic Authentication</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Atkinson">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>
 <author initials="M." surname="Fanto">
            <organization>Unknown</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2007" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4822" />
      </reference>


</references>
</back>
</rfc>


