<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc number="5183" category="std">
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>

<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
	
<front>

<title abbrev="Sieve Environment Extension">
Sieve Email Filtering: 
Environment Extension
</title>

<author initials="N." surname="Freed" fullname="Ned Freed">
<organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3401 Centrelake Drive, Suite 410</street>
<city>Ontario</city> <region>CA</region>  <code>92761-1205</code>
<country>USA</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 909 457 4293</phone>
<email>ned.freed@mrochek.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="May" year="2008" />
<area>Applications</area>

<keyword>RFC</keyword>
<keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
<keyword>SMTP</keyword>
<keyword>ESMTP</keyword>
<keyword>Sieve</keyword>

<abstract><t>
This document describes the "environment" extension to the Sieve
email filtering language.  The "environment" extension gives a Sieve
script access to information about the Sieve interpreter itself, where
it is running, and about any transport connection currently involved
in transferring the message. 
</t></abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

<t>
Sieve <xref target='RFC5228' /> is a language for filtering email
messages at or around the time of final delivery.  It is designed to be
implementable on either a mail client or mail server. It is suitable for
running on a mail server where users may not be allowed to execute arbitrary
programs, such as on black box Internet Message Access Protocol <xref target="RFC3501" />
servers, as it has no user-controlled loops or the ability to run external
programs.
</t>

<t>
Although Sieve is intended to be independent of access protocol, mail
architecture, and operating system, in some cases it is useful to allow
scripts to access information about their execution context.
The "environment" extension provides a new environment test that can
be used to implement scripts that behave differently when moved from
one system to another, when messages arrive from different remote sources
or when otherwise operated in different contexts.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions Used in This Document">

<t>

The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
</t>
<vspace blankLines="100" />
<t>
The terms used to describe the various components of the Sieve
language are taken from Section 1.1 of <xref target='RFC5228' />.
</t>

<t>
This document refers to the ABNF productions IPv4-address-literal,
IPv6-address-literal, and General-address-literal
defined in Section 4.1.3 of <xref target='RFC2821'/>.
</t>

<t>
The location item makes use of standard terms for email service
components. Additional information and background on these terms can be found in
<xref target='EMAIL-ARCH'/>.
</t>

</section>

<section title='Capability Identifiers'>

<t>
The capability string associated with the extension defined in this
document is "environment".
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="environment" title="Environment Test">

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Usage:   environment [COMPARATOR] [MATCH-TYPE]
                     <name: string>
                     <key-list: string-list>
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
The environment test retrieves the item of environment information
specified by the name string and matches it to the values
specified in the key-list argument.  The test succeeds if a match occurs. The type of
match defaults to ":is" and the default comparator is "i;ascii-casemap".
</t>

<t>
The current message is not a direct source of information for the environment
test; the item of information specified by the name string is extracted from the
script's operating environment and the key-list argument comes from the script.
</t>

<t>
The environment test MUST fail unconditionally if the specified information 
item does not exist. A script MUST NOT fail with an error if the item does not
exist. This allows scripts to be written that handle nonexistent items
gracefully. In particular, the test:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  if environment :contains "item" "" { ... }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
only succeeds if "item" is known to the implementation, and always succeeds
if it is.
</t>

<t>
The "relational" extension <xref target='RFC5231' /> adds a match
type called ":count".  The count of an environment test is 0 if the environment
information returned is the empty string, or 1 otherwise. 
</t>
<vspace blankLines="100" />
<t>
Environment items can be standardized or vendor-defined. An IANA registry
is defined for both types of items. Extensions designed for interoperable use
SHOULD be defined in standards track or experimental RFCs.
</t>

<section anchor="standarditems" title="Initial Standard Environment Items">

<t>
The initial set of standardized environment items is as follows:
</t>

<figure><artwork>
 "domain"  =&gt; The primary DNS domain associated with the Sieve
              execution context, usually but not always a proper
              suffix of the host name.

 "host"    =&gt; The fully-qualified domain name of the host where
              the Sieve script is executing.

 "location"
           =&gt; Sieve evaluation can be performed at various
              different points as messages are processed.  This item
              provides additional information about the type of
              service that is evaluating the script. Possible values
              are "MTA", meaning the Sieve is being evaluated by a
              Message Transfer Agent, "MDA", meaning evaluation is
              being performed by a Mail Delivery Agent, "MUA",
              meaning evaluation is being performed by a Mail User
              Agent, and "MS", meaning evaluation is being performed
              by a Message Store.  Additional information and
              background on these terms can be found in
              [EMAIL-ARCH].

 "name"    =&gt; The product name associated with the Sieve interpreter.

 "phase"   =&gt; The point relative to final delivery where the
              Sieve script is being evaluated. Possible values are
              "pre", "during", and "post", referring respectively to
              processing before, during, and after final delivery
              has taken place.

 "remote-host"
           =&gt; Host name of remote SMTP/LMTP/Submission client
              expressed as a Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN), 
              if applicable and available. The empty string will be
              returned if for some reason this information cannot be
              obtained for the current client. 




 "remote-ip"
           =&gt; IP address of remote SMTP/LMTP/Submission client, if
              applicable and available. IPv4, IPv6, and other types
              of addresses are respectively represented in the
              formats defined by the IPv4-address-literal,
              IPv6-address-literal, and General-address-literal
              productions defined in Section 4.1.3 of [RFC2821].

 "version" =&gt; The product version associated with the Sieve
              interpreter. The meaning of the product version string
              is product-specific and should always be considered
              in the context of the product name given by the
              "name" item.
</artwork></figure>
<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
<t>
Implementations SHOULD support as many of the items on this initial list as
possible. Additional standardized items can only be defined in standards-track
or experimental RFCs.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="vendoritems" title="Vendor-defined Environment Items">

<t>
Environment item names beginning with "vnd." represent vendor-defined
extensions.  Such extensions are not defined by Internet standards or
RFCs, but are still registered with IANA in order to prevent
conflicts.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="IANA-env" title="IANA Registration of Environment Items">

<t>
A registry of environment items is
provided by IANA. Item names may be registered on a first-come, first-served
basis.
</t>

<t>
Groups of items defined in a standards track or experimental RFC
MAY choose to use a common name prefix
of the form "name.", where "name" is a string that identifies the group of
related items.
</t>

<t>
Items not defined in a standards track or experimental RFC MUST
have a name that begins with the "vnd." prefix, and this prefix is
followed by the name of the vendor or product, such as "vnd.acme.rocket-sled-status".
</t>
<vspace blankLines="100" />
<section title="Template for Environment Registrations">

<t>
The following template is to be used for registering new Sieve
environment item names with IANA.
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   To: iana@iana.org
   Subject: Registration of new Sieve environment item

   Item name: [the string for use in the 'environment' test]
   Description:     [a brief description of the semantics of the
                     value the item returns]

   RFC number:      [for extensions published as RFCs]
   Contact address: [email and/or physical address to contact for
                     additional information]
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
Multiple items and descriptions MAY be specified in a single registration
request. Both standardized and vendor-defined items use this form.
</t>

</section>

</section>

</section>


<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>
The environment extension may be used to obtain information about the system
the Sieve implementation is running on. This information in turn may reveal
details about service provider or enterprise infrastructure.
</t>

<t>
An implementation can use any technique to determine the
remote-host environment item defined in this specification, and
the trustworthiness of the result will vary.  One common method
will be to perform a PTR DNS lookup on the client IP address.
This information may come from an untrusted source.  For
example, the test:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  if environment :matches "remote-host" "*.example.com" { ... }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
is not a good way to test whether the message came from "outside" because anyone
who can create a PTR record can create one that refers to whatever domain they choose.
</t>

<t>
All of the security considerations given in the base Sieve
specification also apply to this extension. 
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<figure>
<preamble>
The following template specifies the IANA registration of the Sieve
extension specified in this document:
</preamble>
<artwork>
   To: iana@iana.org
   Subject: Registration of new Sieve extension

   Capability name: environment
   Description:     The "environment" extension provides a new
                    environment test that can be used to implement
                    scripts that behave differently when moved
                    from one system to another or otherwise
                    operated in different contexts.
   RFC number:      RFC 5183
   Contact address: Sieve discussion list &lt;ietf-mta-filters@imc.org&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>
This specification also defines a new IANA registry for Sieve environment item names.
The specifics of this registry are given in <xref target="IANA-env" />. The initial
contents of the registry are given in the following section.
</t>

<section title="Initial Environment Item Registrations">

<figure>
<preamble>
The following template specifies the initial IANA registrations for the
environment items defined in this document:
</preamble>
<artwork>
   To: iana@iana.org
   Subject: Registration of new Sieve environment items

   Capability name: domain
   Description:     The primary DNS domain associated with the Sieve
                    execution context, usually but not always a
                    proper suffix of the host name.

   Capability name: host
   Description:     The fully-qualified domain name of the host
                    where the Sieve script is executing.

   Capability name: location
   Description:     Type of service executing the Sieve script.

   Capability name: name
   Description:     The product name associated with the Sieve
                    interpreter.

   Capability name: phase
   Description:     Point relative to final delivery at which the
                    Sieve script is being evaluated.

   Capability name: remote-host
   Description:     Host name of remote SMTP client, if applicable
                    and available. 

   Capability name: remote-ip
   Description:     IP address of remote SMTP client, if applicable
                    and available.

   Capability name: version
   Description:     The product version associated with the Sieve
                    interpreter.

   RFC number:      RFC &rfc.number;
   Contact address: Sieve discussion list &lt;ietf-mta-filters@imc.org&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>

</section>


</section>

</middle>

<back>
<?rfc needLines="10" ?>
<references title="Normative references">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2821" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5228" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5231" ?>

</references>

<references title="Informative references">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3501" ?>

<reference anchor='EMAIL-ARCH'>
<!--
           target='http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-crocker-email-arch'>
-->
<front>
<title>Internet Mail Architecture</title>
<author initials='D' surname='Crocker' fullname='Dave'>
    <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
</author>
<date month='February' year='2008' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

</references>
<vspace blankLines="100" />

<section title='Acknowledgements'>

<t>
Brian Carpenter, Dave Crocker, Cyrus Daboo, Philip Guenther,  Kjetil Torgrim Homme,
John Klensin, Mark Mallett, Alexey Melnikov, and Dilyan Palauzo provided helpful
suggestions and corrections.
</t>

</section>

</back>
</rfc>
