<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % rfc2629 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY % rfc3654 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3654.xml">
<!ENTITY % rfc3746 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3746.xml">

<!ENTITY RFC1126 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1992 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1992.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2071 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2071.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2072 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2072.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4364 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3031 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3221 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3221.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3345 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3345.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3471 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3471.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3963 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that after you have approved the content of
the document, post-xml2rfc changes will be made to update the header
and boilerplate as described in RFC 5741.  Also, the copyright notice
will be updated as in TLP 4.0.
-->

<rfc number="5772" category="historic">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IRTF Routing Requirements">A Set of Possible Requirements
    for a Future Routing Architecture</title>

    <author fullname="Avri Doria" initials="A.D." surname="Doria">
      <organization>LTU</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Lulea</city>

          <code>971 87</code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46 73 277 1788</phone>

        <email>avri@ltu.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Elwyn B. Davies" initials="E.B." surname="Davies">
      <organization>Folly Consulting</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Soham, Cambs</street>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 7889 488 335</phone>

        <email>elwynd@dial.pipex.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Frank Kastenholz" initials="F.K." surname="Kastenholz">
      <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Moulton St.</street>

          <city>Cambridge</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>02183</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

       <phone>+1 617 873 8047</phone>

        <email>frank@bbn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2010" />

    <area>IRTF</area>

    <keyword>IRTF</keyword>

    <keyword>Routing Research Group</keyword>

    <keyword>RRG</keyword>

    <keyword>Routing Requirements</keyword>

    <keyword>IDR</keyword>

    <keyword>FDR</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The requirements for routing architectures described in this document
      were produced by two sub-groups under the IRTF Routing Research Group (RRG) in
      2001, with some editorial updates up to 2006. The two sub-groups worked
      independently, and the resulting requirements represent two separate
      views of the problem and of what is required to fix the problem. This
      document may usefully serve as part of the recommended reading for
      anyone who works on routing architecture designs for the Internet in the
      future.</t>

      <t>The document is published with the support of the IRTF RRG as a
      record of the work completed at that time, but with the understanding
      that it does not necessarily represent either the latest technical
      understanding or the technical consensus of the research group at the
      date of publication.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Background">
      <t>In 2001, the IRTF Routing Research Group (IRTF RRG) chairs, Abha
      Ahuja and Sean Doran, decided to establish a sub-group to look at
      requirements for inter-domain routing (IDR). A group of well-known
      routing experts was assembled to develop requirements for a new routing
      architecture. Their mandate was to approach the problem starting from a
      blank slate. This group was free to take any approach, including a
      revolutionary approach, in developing requirements for solving the
      problems they saw in inter-domain routing.</t>

      <t>Simultaneously, an independent effort was started in Sweden with a
      similar goal. A team, calling itself Babylon, with participation from
      vendors, service providers, and academia assembled to understand the
      history of inter-domain routing, to research the problems seen by the
      service providers, and to develop a proposal of requirements for a
      follow-on to the current routing architecture. This group's remit
      required an evolutionary approach starting from current routing
      architecture and practice. In other words, the group limited itself to
      developing an evolutionary strategy. The Babylon group was later folded
      into the IRTF RRG as Sub-Group B to distinguish it from the original RRG
      Sub-Group A.</t>

      <t>One of the questions that arose while the groups were working in
      isolation was whether there would be many similarities between their
      sets of requirements. That is, would the requirements that grew from a
      blank sheet of paper resemble those that started with the evolutionary
      approach? As can be seen from reading the two sets of requirements,
      there were many areas of fundamental agreement but some areas of
      disagreement.</t>

      <t>There were suggestions within the RRG that the two teams should work
      together to create a single set of requirements. Since these
      requirements are only guidelines to future work, however, some felt that
      doing so would risk losing content without gaining any particular
      advantage. It is not as if any group, for example, the IRTF RRG or the
      IETF Routing Area, was expected to use these requirements as written and
      to create an architecture that met these requirements. Rather, the
      requirements were in practice strong recommendations for a way to
      proceed in creating a new routing architecture. In the end, the decision
      was made to include the results of both efforts, side by side, in one
      document.</t>

      <t>This document contains the two requirement sets produced by the
      teams. The text has received only editorial modifications; the
      requirements themselves have been left unaltered. Whenever the editors
      felt that conditions had changed in the few years since the text was
      written, an editors' note has been added to the text.</t>

      <t>In reading this document, it is important to keep in mind that all of
      these requirements are suggestions, which are laid out to assist those
      interested in developing new routing architectures. It is also important
      to remember that, while the people working on these suggestions have
      done their best to make intelligent suggestions, there are no
      guarantees. So a reader of this document should not treat what it says
      as absolute, nor treat every suggestion as necessary. No architecture is
      expected to fulfill every "requirement".  Hopefully, though, future
      architectures will consider what is offered in this document.</t>

      <t>The IRTF RRG supported publication of this document as a historical
      record of the work completed on the understanding that it does not
      necessarily represent either the latest technical understanding or the
      technical consensus of the research group at the time of publication.
      The document has had substantial review by members of the two teams,
      other members of the IRTF RRG, and additional experts over the years.</t>

      <t>Finally, this document does not make any claims that it is possible
      to have a practical solution that meets all the listed requirements.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Results from Group A">
      <t>This section presents the results of the work done by Sub-Group A of
      the IRTF RRG during 2001-2002. The work originally appeared under the
      title: "Requirements For a Next Generation Routing and Addressing
      Architecture" and was edited by Frank Kastenholz.</t>

      <section anchor="a-reqs"
               title="Group A - Requirements for a Next Generation Routing and Addressing Architecture">
        <t>The requirements presented in this section are not presented in any
        particular order.</t>

        <section title="Architecture">
          <t>The new routing and addressing protocols, data structures, and
          algorithms need to be developed from a clear, well thought-out, and
          documented architecture.</t>

          <t>The new routing and addressing system must have an architectural
          specification that describes all of the routing and addressing
          elements, their interactions, what functions the system performs,
          and how it goes about performing them. The architectural
          specification does not go into issues such as protocol and data
          structure design.</t>

          <t>The architecture should be agnostic with regard to specific
          algorithms and protocols.</t>

          <t>Doing architecture before doing detailed protocol design is good
          engineering practice. This allows the architecture to be reviewed
          and commented upon, with changes made as necessary, when it is still
          easy to do so. Also, by producing an architecture, the eventual
          users of the protocols (the operations community) will have a better
          understanding of how the designers of the protocols meant them to be
          used.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Separable Components">
          <t>The architecture must place different functions into separate
          components.</t>

          <t>Separating functions, capabilities, and so forth into individual
          components and making each component "stand alone" is generally
          considered by system architects to be "A Good Thing". It allows
          individual elements of the system to be designed and tuned to do
          their jobs "very well". It also allows for piecemeal replacement and
          upgrading of elements as new technologies and algorithms become
          available.</t>

          <t>The architecture must have the ability to replace or upgrade
          existing components and to add new ones, without disrupting the
          remaining parts of the system. Operators must be able to roll out
          these changes and additions incrementally (i.e., no "flag days").
          These abilities are needed to allow the architecture to evolve as
          the Internet changes.</t>

          <t>The architecture specification shall define each of these
          components, their jobs, and their interactions.</t>

          <t>Some thoughts to consider along these lines are: <list
              hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="o ">Making topology and addressing separate
              subsystems. This may allow highly optimized topology management
              and discovery without constraining the addressing structure or
              physical topology in unacceptable ways.</t>

              <t hangText="o ">Separate "fault detection and healing" from
              basic topology. From Mike O'Dell: <list>
                  <t>Historically the same machinery is used for both. While
                  attractive for many reasons, the availability of exogenous
                  topology information (i.e., the intended topology) should,
                  it seems, make some tasks easier than the general case of
                  starting with zero knowledge. It certainly helps with
                  recovery in the case of constraint satisfaction. In fact,
                  the intended topology is a powerful way to state certain
                  kinds of policy. <xref target="ODell01"></xref></t>
                </list></t>

              <t hangText="o ">Making policy definition and application a
              separate subsystem, layered over the others.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The architecture should also separate topology, routing, and
          addressing from the application that uses those components. This
          implies that applications such as policy definition, forwarding, and
          circuit and tunnel management are separate subsystems layered on top
          of the basic topology, routing, and addressing systems.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Scalable">
          <t>Scaling is the primary problem facing the routing and addressing
          architecture today. This problem must be solved and it must be
          solved for the long term.</t>

          <t>The architecture must support a large and complex network.
          Ideally, it will serve our needs for the next 20 years.
          Unfortunately: <list hangIndent="3" style="numbers">
              <t>we do not know how big the Internet will grow over that time,
              and</t>

              <t>the architecture developed from these requirements may change
              the fundamental structure of the Internet and therefore its
              growth patterns. This change makes it difficult to predict
              future growth patterns of the Internet.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>As a result, we can't quantify the requirement in any meaningful
          way. Using today's architectural elements as a mechanism for
          describing things, we believe that the network could grow to: <list
              hangIndent="3" style="numbers">
              <t>tens of thousands of ASs <list style="empty">
                  <t>Editors' Note: As of 2005, this level had already been
                  reached.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>tens to hundreds of millions of prefixes, during the lifetime
              of this architecture.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>These sizes are given as a "flavor" for how we expect the
          Internet to grow. We fully believe that any new architecture may
          eliminate some current architectural elements and introduce new
          ones.</t>

          <t>A new routing and addressing architecture designed for a specific
          network size would be inappropriate. First, the cost of routing
          calculations is based only in part on the number of ASs or prefixes
          in the network. The number and locations of the links in the network
          are also significant factors. Second, past predictions of Internet
          growth and topology patterns have proven to be wildly inaccurate, so
          developing an architecture to a specific size goal would at best be
          shortsighted. <list>
              <t>Editors' Note: At the time of these meetings, the BGP
              statistics kept at sites such as www.routeviews.org either did
              not exist or had been running for only a few months. After 5
              years of recording public Internet data trends in AS growth,
              routing table growth can be observed (past) with some short-term
              prediction. As each year of data collection continues, the
              ability to observe and predict trends improves. This
              architecture work pointed out the need for such statistics to
              improve future routing designs.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Therefore, we will not make the scaling requirement based on a
          specific network size. Instead, the new routing and addressing
          architecture should have the ability to constrain the increase in
          load (CPU, memory space and bandwidth, and network bandwidth) on ANY
          SINGLE ROUTER to be less than these specific functions:</t> <list
              hangIndent="3" style="numbers">
              <t>The computational power and memory sizes required to execute
              the routing protocol software and to contain the tables must
              grow more slowly than hardware capabilities described by Moore's
              Law, doubling every 18 months. Other observations indicate that
              memory sizes double every 2 years or so.</t>

              <t>Network bandwidth and latency are some key constraints on how
              fast routing protocol updates can be disseminated (and therefore
              how fast the routing system can adapt to changes). Raw network
              bandwidth seems to quadruple every 3 years or so. However, it
              seems that there are some serious physics problems in going
              faster than 40 Gbit/s (OC768); we should not expect raw network
              link speed to grow much beyond OC768. On the other hand, for
              economic reasons, large swathes of the core of the Internet will
              still operate at lower speeds, possibly as slow as DS3. <list
                  hangIndent="3" style="empty">
                  <t>Editors' Note: Technology is running ahead
                  of imagination and higher speeds are already common.</t>
                </list> Furthermore, in some sections of the Internet, even
              lower speed links are found. Corporate access links are often
              T1, or slower. Low-speed radio links exist. Intra-domain links
              may be T1 or fractional-T1 (or slower). <vspace blankLines="1" />Therefore, the architecture must not make
              assumptions about the bandwidth available.</t>

              <t>The speeds of high-speed RAMs (Static RAMs (SRAMs), used for caches and the
              like) are growing, though slowly. Because of their use in caches
              and other very specific applications, these RAMs tend to be
              small, a few megabits, and the size of these RAMs is not
              increasing very rapidly.<vspace blankLines="1" /> On the other
              hand, the speed of "large" memories (Dynamic RAMs (DRAMs)) is increasing even
              slower than that for the high-speed RAMs. This is because the
              development of these RAMs is driven by the PC market, where size
              is very important, and low speed can be made up for by better
              caches. <vspace blankLines="1" />
              Memory access rates should not
              be expected to increase significantly. 
                <list style="empty">
                  <t>Editors' Note: Various techniques have significantly
                  increased memory bandwidth. 800 MHz is now possible, compared
                  with less than 100 MHz in the year 2000. This does not, however,
                  contradict the next paragraph, but rather just extends the
                  timescales somewhat.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list>

          <t>The growth in resources available to any one router will
          eventually slow down. It may even stop. Even so, the network will
          continue to grow. The routing and addressing architecture must
          continue to scale in even this extreme condition. We cannot continue
          to add more computing power to routers forever. Other strategies
          must be available. Some possible strategies are hierarchy,
          abstraction, and aggregation of topology information.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Lots of Interconnectivity">
          <t>The new routing and addressing architecture must be able to cope
          with a high degree of interconnectivity in the Internet. That is,
          there are large numbers of alternate paths and routes among the
          various elements. Mechanisms are required to prevent this
          interconnectivity (and continued growth in interconnectivity) from
          causing tables, compute time, and routing protocol traffic to grow
          without bound. The "cost" to the routing system of an increase in
          complexity must be limited in scope; sections of the network that do
          not see, or do not care about, the complexity ought not pay the cost
          of that complexity.</t>

          <t>Over the past several years, the Internet has seen an increase in
          interconnectivity. Individual end sites (companies, customers,
          etc.), ISPs, exchange points, and so on, all are connecting to more
          "other things". Companies multi-home to multiple ISPs, ISPs peer
          with more ISPs, and so on. These connections are made for many
          reasons, such as getting more bandwidth, increased reliability and
          availability, policy, and so on. However, this increased
          interconnectivity has a price. It leads to more scaling problems as
          it increases the number of AS paths in the networks.</t>

          <t>Any new architecture must assume that the Internet will become a
          denser mesh. It must not assume, nor can it dictate, certain
          patterns or limits on how various elements of the network
          interconnect.</t>

          <t>Another facet of this requirement is that there may be multiple
          valid, loop-free paths available to a destination. See <xref
          target="A-multi-path"></xref> for a further discussion.</t>

          <t>We wryly note that one of the original design goals of IP was to
          support a large, heavily interconnected network, which would be
          highly survivable (such as in the face of a nuclear war).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Random Structure">
          <t>The routing and addressing architecture must not place any
          constraints on or make assumptions about the topology or
          connectedness of the elements comprising the Internet. The routing
          and addressing architecture must not presume any particular network
          structure. The network does not have a "nice" structure. In the past,
          we used to believe that there was this nice
          "backbone/tier-1/tier-2/end-site" sort of hierarchy. This is not so.
          Therefore, any new architecture must not presume any such
          structure.</t>

          <t>Some have proposed that a geographic addressing scheme be used,
          requiring exchange points to be situated within each geographic
          "region". There are many reasons why we believe this to be a bad
          approach, but those arguments are irrelevant. The main issue is that
          the routing architecture should not presume a specific network
          structure.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-Homing">
          <t>The architecture must provide multi-homing for all elements of
          the Internet. That is, multi-homing of hosts, subnetworks, end-sites, "low-level" ISPs, and backbones (i.e., lots of redundant
          interconnections) must be supported. Among the reasons to multi-home
          are reliability, load sharing, and performance tuning.</t>

          <t>The term "multi-homing" may be interpreted in its broadest sense
          -- one "place" has multiple connections or links to another
          "place".</t>

          <t>The architecture must not limit the number of alternate paths to
          a multi-homed site.</t>

          <t>When multi-homing is used, it must be possible to use one, some
          (more than one but less than all), or all of the available paths to
          the multi-homed site. The multi-homed site must have the ability to
          declare which path(s) are used and under what conditions (for
          example, one path may be declared "primary" and the other "backup"
          and to be used only when the primary fails).</t>

          <t>A current problem in the Internet is that multi-homing leads to
          undue increases in the size of the BGP routing tables. The new
          architecture must support multi-homing without undue routing table
          growth.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-multi-path" title="Multi-Path">
          <t>As a corollary to multi-homing, the architecture must allow for
          multiple paths from a source to a destination to be active at the
          same time. These paths need not have the same attributes. Policies
          are to be used to disseminate the attributes and to classify traffic
          for the different paths.</t>

          <t>There must be a rich "language" for specifying the rules for
          classifying the traffic and assigning classes of traffic to
          different paths (or prohibiting it from certain paths). The rules
          should allow traffic to be classified based upon, at least, the
          following: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="o ">IPv6 FlowIDs,</t>

              <t hangText="o">Diffserv Code Point (DSCP) values,</t>

              <t hangText="o ">source and/or destination prefixes, or</t>

              <t hangText="o ">random selections at some probability.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>A mechanism is needed that allows operators to plan and manage
          the traffic load on the various paths. To start, this mechanism can
          be semi-automatic or even manual. Eventually, it ought to become
          fully automatic.</t>

          <t>When multi-path forwarding is used, options must be available to
          preserve packet ordering where appropriate (such as for individual
          TCP connections).</t>

          <t>Please refer to <xref target="A-dyn-load"></xref> for a
          discussion of dynamic load-balancing and management over multiple
          paths.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convergence">
          <t>The speed of convergence (also called the "stabilization time")
          is the time it takes for a router's routing processes to reach a
          new, stable, "solution" (i.e., forwarding information base) after a
          change someplace in the network. In effect, what happens is that the
          output of the routing calculations stabilizes -- the Nth iteration
          of the software produces the same results as the N-1th
          iteration.</t>

          <t>The speed of convergence is generally considered to be a function
          of the number of subnetworks in the network and the amount of
          connections between those networks. As either number grows, the time
          it takes to converge increases.</t>

          <t>In addition, a change can "ripple" back and forth through the
          system. One change can go through the system, causing some other
          router to change its advertised connectivity, causing a new change
          to ripple through. These oscillations can take a while to work their
          way out of the network. It is also possible that these ripples never
          die out. In this situation, the routing and addressing system is
          unstable; it never converges.</t>

          <t>Finally, it is more than likely that the routers comprising the
          Internet never converge simply because the Internet is so large and
          complex. Assume it takes S seconds for the routers to stabilize on a
          solution for any one change to the network. Also, assume that changes
          occur, on average, every C seconds. Because of the size and
          complexity of the Internet, C is now less than S. &nbsp;Therefore, if a
          change, C1, occurs at time T, the routing system would stabilize at
          time T+S, but a new change, C2, will occur at time T+C, which is
          before T+S. &nbsp;The system will start processing the new change before
          it's done with the old.</t>

          <t>This is not to say that all routers are constantly processing
          changes. The effects of changes are like ripples in a pond. They
          spread outward from where they occur. Some routers will be
          processing just C1, others C2, others both C1 and C2, and others
          neither.</t>

          <t>We have two separate scopes over which we can set requirements
          with respect to convergence: </t><list hangIndent="4" style="numbers">
              <t>Single Change: In this requirement, a single change
              of any type (link addition or deletion, router failure or
              restart, etc.) is introduced into a stabilized system. No
              additional changes are introduced. The system must re-stabilize
              within some measure of bounded time. This requirement is a
              fairly abstract one as it would be impossible to test in a real
              network. Definition of the time constraints remains an open
              research issue.</t>

              <t>System-Wide: Defining a single target for maximum
              convergence time for the real Internet is absurd. As we
              mentioned earlier, the Internet is large enough and diverse
              enough so that it is quite likely that new changes are
              introduced somewhere before the system fully digests old
              ones.</t>
            </list>

          <t>So, the first requirement here is that there must be mechanisms
          to limit the scope of any one change's visibility and effects. The
          number of routers that have to perform calculations in response to a
          change is kept small, as is the settling time.</t>

          <t>The second requirement is based on the following assumptions:
          <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">the scope of a change's visibility and impact
              can be limited. That is, routers within that scope know of the
              change and recalculate their tables based on the change. Routers
              outside of the scope don't see it at all.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Within any scope, S, network changes are
              constantly occurring and the average inter-change interval is Tc
              seconds.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">There are Rs routers within scope S.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">A subset of the destinations known to the
              routers in S, Ds, are impacted by a given change.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">We can state that for Z% of the changes, within
              Y% of Tc seconds after a change, C, X% of the Rs routers have
              their routes to Ds settled to a useful answer (useful meaning
              that packets can get to Ds, though perhaps not by the optimal
              path -- this allows some "hunting" for the optimal solution).
              <vspace blankLines="1" /> X, Y, and Z are yet to be defined.
              Their definition remains a research issue.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This requirement implies that the scopes can be kept relatively
          small in order to minimize Rs and maximize Tc.</t>

          <t>The growth rate of the convergence time must not be related to
          the growth rate of the Internet as a whole. This implies that the
          convergence time either: <list style="numbers">
              <t>not be a function of basic network elements (such as prefixes
              and links/paths), and/or</t>

              <t>that the Internet be continuously divisible into chunks that
              limit the scope and effect of a change, thereby limiting the
              number of routers, prefixes, links, and so on, involved in the
              new calculations.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-security-1" title="Routing System Security">
          <t>The security of the Internet's routing system is paramount. If
          the routing system is compromised or attacked, the entire Internet
          can fail. This is unacceptable. Any new architecture must be
          secure.</t>

          <t>Architectures by themselves are not secure. It is the
          implementation of an architecture, its protocols, algorithms, and
          data structures that are secure. These requirements apply primarily
          to the implementation. The architecture must provide the elements
          that the implementation needs to meet these security requirements.
          Also, the architecture must not prevent these security requirements
          from being met.</t>

          <t>Security means different things to different people. In order for
          this requirement to be useful, we must define what we mean by
          security. We do this by identifying the attackers and threats we
          wish to protect against. They are: <list hangIndent="4"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Masquerading"><vspace /> The system, including its
              protocols, must be secure against intruders adopting the
              identity of other known, trusted elements of the routing system
              and then using that position of trust for carrying out other
              attacks. Protocols must use cryptographically strong
              authentication.</t>

              <t hangText="Denial-of-Service (DoS) Attacks"><vspace /> The
              architecture and protocols should be secure against DoS attacks
              directed at the routers. <vspace blankLines="1" /> The new
              architecture and protocols should provide as much information as
              it can to allow administrators to track down sources of DoS and
              Distributed DOS (DDoS) attacks.</t>

              <t hangText="No Bad Data"><vspace /> Any new architecture and
              protocols must provide protection against the introduction of
              bad, erroneous, or misleading data by attackers. Of particular
              importance, an attacker must not be able to redirect traffic
              flows, with the intent of: <vspace blankLines="0" /> <list
                  hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="o ">directing legitimate traffic away from a
                  target, causing a denial-of-service attack by preventing
                  legitimate data from reaching its destination,</t>

                  <t hangText="o ">directing additional traffic (going to
                  other destinations that are "innocent bystanders") to a
                  target, causing the target to be overloaded, or</t>

                  <t hangText="o ">directing traffic addressed to the target
                  to a place where the attacker can copy, snoop, alter, or
                  otherwise affect the traffic.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t hangText="Topology Hiding"><vspace /> Any new architecture
              and protocols must provide mechanisms to allow network owners to
              hide the details of their internal topologies, while maintaining
              the desired levels of service connectivity and reachability.</t>

              <t hangText="Privacy"><vspace /> By "privacy" we mean privacy of
              the routing protocol exchanges between routers. <vspace blankLines="1" />When the routers are on point-to-point links,
              with routers at each end, there may not be any need to encrypt
              the routing protocol traffic as the possibility of a third party
              intercepting the traffic is limited, though not impossible. We do
              believe, however, that it is important to have the ability to
              protect routing protocol traffic in two cases: <list
                  hangIndent="3" style="numbers">
                  <t>When the routers are on a shared network, it is possible
                  that there are hosts on the network that have been
                  compromised. These hosts could surreptitiously monitor the
                  protocol traffic.</t>

                  <t>When two routers are exchanging information "at a
                  distance" (over intervening routers and, possibly, across
                  administrative domain boundaries). In this case, the
                  security of the intervening routers, links, and so on,
                  cannot be assured. Thus, the ability to encrypt this traffic
                  is important.</t>
                </list> <vspace /> Therefore, we believe that the option to
              encrypt routing protocol traffic is required.</t>

              <t hangText="Data Consistency"><vspace /> A router should be
              able to detect and recover from any data that is received from
              other routers that is inconsistent. That is, it must not be
              possible for data from multiple routers, none of which is
              malicious, to "break" another router.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Where security mechanisms are provided, they must use methods
          that are considered to be cryptographically secure (e.g., using
          cryptographically strong encryption and signatures -- no cleartext
          passwords!).</t>

          <t>Use of security features should not be optional (except as
          required above). This may be "social engineering" on our part, but
          we believe it to be necessary. If a security feature is optional,
          the implementation of the feature must default to the "secure"
          setting.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-security-2" title="End Host Security">
          <t>The architecture must not prevent individual host-to-host
          communications sessions from being secured (i.e., it cannot
          interfere with things like IPsec).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Rich Policy">
          <t>Before setting out policy requirements, we need to define the
          term. Like "security", "policy" means different things to different people.
          For our purposes, "policy" is the set of administrative influences
          that alter the path determination and next-hop selection procedures
          of the routing software.</t>

          <t>The main motivators for influencing path and next-hop selection
          seem to be transit rules, business decisions, and load
          management.</t>

          <t>The new architecture must support rich policy mechanisms.
          Furthermore, the policy definition and dissemination mechanisms
          should be separated from the network topology and connectivity
          dissemination mechanisms. Policy provides input to and controls the
          generation of the forwarding table and the abstraction, filtering,
          aggregation, and dissemination of topology information.</t>

          <t>Note that if the architecture is properly divided into subsystems,
          then at a later time, new policy subsystems that include new
          features and capabilities could be developed and installed as
          needed.</t>

          <t>We divide the general area of policy into two sub-categories:
          routing information and traffic control. Routing Information
          Policies control what routing information is disseminated or
          accepted, how it is disseminated, and how routers determine paths
          and next-hops from the received information. Traffic Control
          Policies determine how traffic is classified and assigned to
          routes.</t>

          <section anchor="A-security-3" title="Routing Information Policies">
            <t>There must be mechanisms to allow network administrators,
            operators, and designers to control receipt and dissemination of
            routing information. These controls include, but are not limited
            to: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
                <t hangText="- ">Selecting to which other routers routing
                information will be transmitted.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Specifying the "granularity" and type of
                transmitted information. The length of IPv4 prefixes is an
                example of granularity.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selection and filtering of topology and
                service information that is transmitted. This gives different
                "views" of internal structure and topology to different
                peers.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selecting the level of security and
                authenticity for transmitted information.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Being able to cause the level of detail that
                is visible for some portion of the network to reduce the
                farther you get from that part of the network.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selecting from whom routing information will
                be accepted. This control should be "provisional" in the sense
                of "accept routes from "foo" only if there are no others
                available".</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Accepting or rejecting routing information
                based on the path the information traveled (using the current
                system as an example, this would be filtering routes based on
                an AS appearing anywhere in the AS path). This control should
                be "use only if there are no other paths available".</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selecting the desired level of granularity
                for received routing information (this would include, but is
                not limited to, things similar in nature to the prefix-length
                filters widely used in the current routing and addressing
                system).</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selecting the level of security and
                authenticity of received information in order for that
                information to be accepted.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Determining the treatment of received routing
                information based on attributes supplied with the
                information.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Applying attributes to routing information
                that is to be transmitted and then determining treatment of
                information (e.g., sending it "here" but not "there") based on
                those tags.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Selection and filtering of topology and
                service information that is received.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Traffic Control Policies">
            <t>The architecture should provide mechanisms that allow network
            operators to manage and control the flow of traffic. The traffic
            controls should include, but are not limited to:</t>
 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">

            <t hangText="- ">The ability to detect and eliminate congestion points in the
            network (by redirecting traffic around those points).</t>

            <t hangText="- ">The ability to develop multiple paths through the network
            with different attributes and then assign traffic to those paths
            based on some discriminators within the packets (discriminators
            include, but are not limited to, IP addresses or prefixes, IPv6
            flow ID, DSCP values, and MPLS labels).</t>

            <t hangText="- ">The ability to find and use multiple, equivalent paths
            through the network (i.e., they would have the "same" attributes)
            and allocate traffic across the paths.</t>

            <t hangText="- ">The ability to accept or refuse traffic based on some traffic
            classification (providing, in effect, transit policies).</t> 

            <t hangText="">Traffic classification must at least include the source and
            destination IP addresses (prefixes) and the DSCP value. Other
            fields may be supported, such as: </t>
<list style="symbols">
                <t>Protocol and port-based functions,</t>

                <t>DSCP/QoS (Quality of Service) tuple (such as ports),</t>

                <t>Per-host operations (i.e., /32 s for IPv4 and
                /128 s for IPv6), and</t>

                <t>Traffic matrices (e.g., traffic from prefix X
                and to prefix Y).</t>
              </list>
</list>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Incremental Deployment">
          <t>The reality of the Internet is that there can be no Internet-wide
          cutover from one architecture and protocol to another. This means
          that any new architecture and protocol must be incrementally
          deployable; ISPs must be able to set up small sections of the new
          architecture, check it out, and then slowly grow the sections.
          Eventually, these sections will "touch" and "squeeze out" the old
          architecture.</t>

          <t>The protocols that implement the architecture must be able to
          interoperate at "production levels" with currently existing routing
          protocols. Furthermore, the protocol specifications must define how
          the interoperability is done.</t>

          <t>We also believe that sections of the Internet will never convert
          over to the new architecture. Thus, it is important that the new
          architecture and its protocols be able to interoperate with "old
          architecture" regions of the network indefinitely.</t>

          <t>The architecture's addressing system must not force existing
          address allocations to be redone: no renumbering!</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Mobility">
          <t>There are two kinds of mobility: host mobility and network
          mobility. Host mobility is when an individual host moves from where
          it was to where it is. Network mobility is when an entire network
          (or subnetwork) moves.</t>

          <t>The architecture must support network-level mobility. Please
          refer to <xref target="A-host-mobility"></xref> for a discussion of
          host mobility.</t><list>
              <t>Editors' Note: Since the time of this work, the Network Mobility (NEMO)
              extensions to Mobile-IP <xref target="RFC3963"></xref> to
              accommodate mobile networks have been developed.</t>
            </list>
        </section>

        <section title="Address Portability">
          <t>One of the big "hot items" in the current Internet political
          climate is portability of IP addresses (both v4 and v6). The short
          explanation is that people do not like to renumber when changing
          connection point or provider and do not trust automated renumbering
          tools.</t>

          <t>The architecture must provide complete address portability.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-Protocol">
          <t>The Internet is expected to be "multi-protocol" for at least the
          next several years. IPv4 and IPv6 will co-exist in many different
          ways during a transition period. The architecture must be able to
          handle both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses. Furthermore, protocols that
          supplant IPv4 and IPv6 may be developed and deployed during the
          lifetime of the architecture. The architecture must be flexible and
          extensible enough to handle new protocols as they arise.</t>

          <t>Furthermore, the architecture must not assume any given
          relationships between a topological element's IPv4 address and its
          IPv6 address. The architecture must not assume that all topological
          elements have IPv4 addresses/prefixes, nor can it assume that they
          have IPv6 addresses/prefixes.</t>

          <t>The architecture should allow different paths to the same
          destination to be used for different protocols, even if all paths
          can carry all protocols.</t>

          <t>In addition to the addressing technology, the architecture need
          not be restricted to only packet-based multiplexing/demultiplexing
          technology (such as IP); support for other multiplexing/
          demultiplexing technologies may be added.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-security-4" title="Abstraction">
          <t>The architecture must provide mechanisms for network designers
          and operators to: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="o ">Group elements together for administrative
              control purposes,</t>

              <t hangText="o ">Hide the internal structure and topology of
              those groupings for administrative and security reasons,</t>

              <t hangText="o ">Limit the amount of topology information that
              is exported from the groupings in order to control the load
              placed on external routers,</t>

              <t hangText="o ">Define rules for traffic transiting or
              terminating in the grouping.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The architecture must allow the current Autonomous System
          structure to be mapped into any new abstraction schemes.</t>

          <t>Mapping mechanisms, algorithms, and techniques must be
          specified.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Simplicity">
          <t>The architecture must be simple enough so that someone who is
          extremely knowledgeable in routing and who is skilled at creating
          straightforward and simple explanations can explain all the
          important concepts in less than an hour.</t>

          <t>This criterion has been chosen since developing an objective
          measure of complexity for an architecture can be very difficult and
          is out of scope for this document.</t>

          <t>The requirement is that the routing architecture be kept as
          simple as possible. This requires careful evaluation of possible
          features and functions with a merciless weeding out of those that
          "might be nice" but are not necessary.</t>

          <t>By keeping the architecture simple, the protocols and software
          used to implement the architecture are simpler. This simplicity in
          turn leads to:</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>Faster implementation of the protocols. If there are fewer
              bells and whistles, then there are fewer things that need to be
              implemented.</t>

              <t>More reliable implementations. With fewer components, there
              is less code, reducing bug counts, and fewer interactions
              between components that could lead to unforeseen and incorrect
              behavior.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-security-5" title="Robustness">
          <t>The architecture, and the protocols implementing it, should be
          robust. Robustness comes in many different flavors. Some
          considerations with regard to robustness include (but are not
          limited to): <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="o ">Continued correct operation in the face of:
              <list style="symbols">
                  <t>Defective (even malicious) trusted routers.</t>

                  <t>Network failures. Whenever possible, valid alternate
                  paths are to be found and used.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t hangText="o">Failures must be localized. That is, the
              architecture must limit the "spread" of any adverse effects of a
              misconfiguration or failure. Badness must not spread.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Of course, the general robustness principle of being liberal in
          what's accepted and conservative in what's sent must also be
          applied. <vspace blankLines="0" /> <list style="hanging">
              <t>Original Editor's Note: Some of the
              contributors to this section have argued that robustness is an
              aspect of security. I have exercised editor's discretion by
              making it a separate section. The reason for this is that to too
              many people "security" means "protection from break-ins" and
              "authenticating and encrypting data". This requirement goes
              beyond those views.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Media Independence">
          <t>While it is an article of faith that IP operates over a wide
          variety of media (such as Ethernet, X.25, ATM, and so on), IP
          routing must take an agnostic view toward any "routing" or
          "topology" services that are offered by the medium over which IP is
          operating. That is, the new architecture must not be designed to
          integrate with any media-specific topology management or routing
          scheme.</t>

          <t>The routing architecture must assume, and must work over, the
          simplest possible media.</t>

          <t>The routing and addressing architecture can certainly make use of
          lower-layer information and services, when and where available, and
          to the extent that IP routing wishes.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Stand-Alone">
          <t>The routing architecture and protocols must not rely on other
          components of the Internet (such as DNS) for their correct
          operation. Routing is the fundamental process by which data "finds
          its way around the Internet" and most, if not all, of those other
          components rely on routing to properly forward their data. Thus,
          routing cannot rely on any Internet systems, services, or
          capabilities that in turn rely on routing. If it did, a dependency
          loop would result.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Safety of Configuration">
          <t>The architecture, protocols, and standard implementation defaults
          must be such that a router installed "out of the box" with no
          configuration, etc., by the operators will not cause "bad things" to
          happen to the rest of the routing system (e.g., no dial-up customers
          advertising routes to 18/8!).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Renumbering">
          <t>The routing system must allow topological entities to be
          renumbered.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-Prefix">
          <t>The architecture must allow topological entities to have multiple
          prefixes (or the equivalent under the new architecture).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Cooperative Anarchy">
         <t>As RFC 1726<xref target="RFC1726"></xref> states:</t>           

             <list style="empty"> 
              <t>A major contributor to the Internet's success is the
              fact that there is no single, centralized, point of control or
              promulgator of policy for the entire network. This allows
              individual constituents of the network to tailor their own
              networks, environments, and policies to suit their own needs.
              The individual constituents must cooperate only to the degree
              necessary to ensure that they interoperate.</t>
            </list>

          <t>This decentralization, called "cooperative anarchy", is still a
          key feature of the Internet today. The new routing architecture must
          retain this feature. There can be no centralized point of control or
          promulgator of policy for the entire Internet.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Network-Layer Protocols and Forwarding Model">
          <t>For the purposes of backward compatibility, any new routing and
          addressing architecture and protocols must work with IPv4 and IPv6
          using the traditional "hop-by-hop" forwarding and packet-based
          multiplex/demultiplex models. However, the architecture need not be
          restricted to these models. Additional forwarding and
          multiplex/demultiplex models may be added.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Routing Algorithm">
          <t>The architecture should not require a particular routing
          algorithm family. That is to say, the architecture should be
          agnostic about link-state, distance-vector, or path-vector routing
          algorithms.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Positive Benefit">
          <t>Finally, the architecture must show benefits in terms of
          increased stability, decreased operational costs, and increased
          functionality and lifetime, over the current schemes. This benefit
          must remain even after the inevitable costs of developing and
          debugging the new protocols, enduring the inevitable instabilities
          as things get shaken out, and so on.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Administrative Entities and the IGP/EGP Split">
          <t>We explicitly recognize that the Internet consists of resources
          under control of multiple administrative entities. Each entity must
          be able to manage its own portion of the Internet as it sees fit.
          Moreover, the constraints that can be imposed on routing and
          addressing on the portion of the Internet under the control of one
          administration may not be feasibly extended to cover multiple
          administrations. Therefore, we recognize a natural and inevitable
          split between routing and addressing that is under a single
          administrative control and routing and addressing that involves
          multiple administrative entities. Moreover, while there may be
          multiple administrative authorities, the administrative authority
          boundaries may be complex and overlapping, rather than being a
          strict hierarchy.</t>

          <t>Furthermore, there may be multiple levels of administration, each
          with its own level of policy and control. For example, a large
          network might have "continental-level" administrations covering its
          European and Asian operations, respectively. There would also be
          that network's "inter-continental" administration covering the
          Europe-to-Asia links. Finally, there would be the "Internet" level
          in the administrative structure (analogous to the "exterior" concept
          in the current routing architecture).</t>

          <t>Thus, we believe that the administrative structure of the
          Internet must be extensible to many levels (more than the two
          provided by the current IGP/EGP split). The interior/exterior
          property is not absolute. The interior/exterior property of any
          point in the network is relative; a point on the network is interior
          with respect to some points on the network and exterior with respect
          to others.</t>

          <t>Administrative entities may not trust each other; some may be
          almost actively hostile toward each other. The architecture must
          accommodate these models. Furthermore, the architecture must not
          require any particular level of trust among administrative
          entities.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <!-- Section 3 -->

      <section title="Non-Requirements">
        <t>The following are not required or are non-goals. This should not be
        taken to mean that these issues must not be addressed by a new
        architecture. Rather, addressing these issues or not is purely an
        optional matter for the architects.</t>

        <section title="Forwarding Table Optimization">
          <t>We believe that it is not necessary for the architecture to
          minimize the size of the forwarding tables (FIBs). Current memory
          sizes, speeds, and prices, along with processor and Application-specific Integrated Circuit (ASIC)
          capabilities allow forwarding tables to be very large, O(E6), and
          allow fast (100 M lookups/second) tables to be built with little
          difficulty.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Traffic Engineering">
          <t>"Traffic engineering" is one of those terms that has become
          terribly overloaded. If one asks N people what traffic engineering
          is, one would get something like N! disjoint answers. Therefore, we
          elect not to require "traffic engineering", per se. Instead, we have
          endeavored to determine what the ultimate intent is when operators
          "traffic engineer" their networks and then make those capabilities
          an inherent part of the system.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multicast">
          <t>The new architecture is not designed explicitly to be an
          inter-domain multicast routing architecture. However, given the
          notable lack of a viable, robust, and widely deployed inter-domain
          multicast routing architecture, the architecture should not hinder
          the development and deployment of inter-domain multicast routing
          without an adverse effect on meeting the other requirements.</t>

          <t>We do note however that one respected network sage <xref
          target="Clark91"></xref> has said (roughly): <list>
              <t>When you see a bunch of engineers standing around
              congratulating themselves for solving some particularly ugly
              problem in networking, go up to them, whisper "multicast", jump
              back, and watch the fun begin...</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Quality of Service (QoS)">
          <t>The architecture concerns itself primarily with disseminating
          network topology information so that routers may select paths to
          destinations and build appropriate forwarding tables. Quality of
          Service (QoS) is not a part of this function and we make no
          requirements with respect to QoS.</t>

          <t>However, QoS is an area of great and evolving interest. It is
          reasonable to expect that in the not too distant future,
          sophisticated QoS facilities will be deployed in the Internet. Any
          new architecture and protocols should be developed with an eye
          toward these future evolutions. Extensibility mechanisms, allowing
          future QoS routing and signaling protocols to "piggy-back" on top of
          the basic routing system are desired.</t>

          <t>We do require the ability to assign attributes to entities and
          then do path generation and selection based on those attributes.
          Some may call this QoS.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="IP Prefix Aggregation">
          <t>There is no specific requirement that CIDR-style (Classless Inter-Domain Routing) IP prefix
          aggregation be done by the new architecture. Address allocation
          policies, societal pressure, and the random growth and structure of
          the Internet have all conspired to make prefix aggregation
          extraordinarily difficult, if not impossible. This means that large
          numbers of prefixes will be sloshing about in the routing system and
          that forwarding tables will grow quite big. This is a cost that we
          believe must be borne.</t>

          <t>Nothing in this non-requirement should be interpreted as saying
          that prefix aggregation is explicitly prohibited. CIDR-style IP
          prefix aggregation might be used as a mechanism to meet other
          requirements, such as scaling.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Perfect Safety">
          <t>Making the system impossible to misconfigure is, we believe, not
          required. The checking, constraints, and controls necessary to
          achieve this could, we believe, prevent operators from performing
          necessary tasks in the face of unforeseen circumstances.</t>

          <t>However, safety is always a "good thing", and any results from
          research in this area should certainly be taken into consideration
          and, where practical, incorporated into the new routing
          architecture.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-dyn-load" title="Dynamic Load Balancing">
          <t>History has shown that using the routing system to perform
          highly dynamic load balancing among multiple more-or-less-equal
          paths usually ends up causing all kinds of instability, etc., in the
          network. Thus, we do not require such a capability.</t>

          <t>However, this is an area that is ripe for additional research,
          and some believe that the capability will be necessary in the
          future. Thus, the architecture and protocols should be "malleable"
          enough to allow development and deployment of dynamic load-balancing
          capabilities, should we ever figure out how to do it.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Renumbering of Hosts and Routers">
          <t>We believe that the routing system is not required to "do
          renumbering" of hosts and routers. That's an IP issue.</t>

          <t>Of course, the routing and addressing architecture must be able
          to deal with renumbering when it happens.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="A-host-mobility" title="Host Mobility">
          <t>In the Internet architecture, host mobility is handled on a
          per-host basis by a dedicated, Mobile-IP protocol <xref
          target="RFC3344"></xref>. Traffic destined for a mobile-host is
          explicitly forwarded by dedicated relay agents. Mobile-IP <xref
          target="RFC3344"></xref> adequately solves the host-mobility problem
          and we do not see a need for any additional requirements in this
          area. Of course, the new architecture must not impede or conflict
          with Mobile-IP.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Backward Compatibility">
          <t>For the purposes of development of the architecture, we assume
          that there is a "clean slate". Unless specified in <xref
          target="a-reqs"></xref>, there are no explicit requirements that
          elements, concepts, or mechanisms of the current routing
          architecture be carried forward into the new one.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <!-- Non Requirements -->
    </section>

    <!-- Group A -->

    <section title="Requirements from Group B">
      <t>The following is the result of the work done by Sub-Group B of the
      IRTF RRG in 2001-2002. It was originally released under the title:
      "Future Domain Routing Requirements" and was edited by Avri Doria and
      Elwyn Davies.</t>

      <!-- 1. Introduction -->

      <section title="Group B - Future Domain Routing Requirements">
        <t>It is generally accepted that there are major shortcomings in the
        inter-domain routing of the Internet today and that these may result
        in meltdown within an unspecified period of time. Remedying these
        shortcomings will require extensive research to tie down the exact
        failure modes that lead to these shortcomings and identify the best
        techniques to remedy the situation.<list>
            <t>Reviewer's Note: Even in 2001, there was a wide difference of
            opinion across the community regarding the shortcomings of
            inter-domain routing. In the years between writing and publication,
            further analysis, changes in operational practice, alterations to
            the demands made on inter-domain routing, modifications made to
            BGP, and a recognition of the difficulty of finding a replacement
            may have altered the views of some members of the community.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Changes in the nature and quality of the services that users want
        from the Internet are difficult to provide within the current
        framework, as they impose requirements never foreseen by the original
        architects of the Internet routing system.</t>

        <t>The kind of radical changes that have to be accommodated are
        epitomized by the advent of IPv6 and the application of IP mechanisms
        to private commercial networks that offer specific service guarantees
        beyond the best-effort services of the public Internet. Major changes
        to the inter-domain routing system are inevitable to provide an
        efficient underpinning for the radically changed and increasingly
        commercially-based networks that rely on the IP protocol suite.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 2. Underlying principles -->

      <section title="Underlying Principles">
        <t>Although inter-domain routing is seen as the major source of
        problems, the interactions with intra-domain routing, and the
        constraints that confining changes to the inter-domain arena would
        impose, mean that we should consider the whole area of routing as an
        integrated system. This is done for two reasons: <list hangIndent="3"
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="- ">Requirements should not presuppose the solution.
            A continued commitment to the current definitions and split
            between inter- domain and intra-domain routing would constitute
            such a presupposition. Therefore, this part of the document uses
            the name Future Domain Routing (FDR).</t>

            <t hangText="- ">It is necessary to understand the degree to which
            inter-domain and intra-domain routing are related within today's
            routing architecture.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>We are aware that using the term "domain routing" is already
        fraught with danger because of possible misinterpretation due to prior
        usage. The meaning of "domain routing" will be developed implicitly
        throughout the document, but a little advance explicit definition of
        the word "domain" is required, as well as some explanation on the
        scope of "routing".</t>

        <t>This document uses "domain" in a very broad sense, to mean any
        collection of systems or domains that come under a common authority
        that determines the attributes defining, and the policies controlling,
        that collection. The use of "domain" in this manner is very similar to
        the concept of region that was put forth by John Wroclawski in his
        Metanet model <xref target="Wroclawski95"></xref>. The idea includes
        the notion that certain attributes will characterize the behavior of
        the systems within a domain and that there will be borders between
        domains. The idea of domain presented here does not presuppose that
        two domains will have the same behavior. Nor does it presuppose
        anything about the hierarchical nature of domains. Finally, it does
        not place restrictions on the nature of the attributes that might be
        used to determine membership in a domain. Since today's routing
        domains are an example of the concept of domains in this document,
        there has been no attempt to create a new term.</t>

        <t>Current practice in routing-system design stresses the need to
        separate the concerns of the control plane and the forwarding plane in
        a router. This document will follow this practice, but we still use
        the term "routing" as a global portmanteau to cover all aspects of the
        system. Specifically, however, "routing" will be used to mean the
        process of discovering, interpreting, and distributing information
        about the logical and topological structure of the network.</t>

        <section title="Inter-Domain and Intra-Domain">
          <t>Throughout this section, the terms "intra-domain" and "inter-domain"
          will be used. These should be understood as relative terms. In all
          cases of domains, there will be a set of network systems that are
          within that domain; routing between these systems will be termed
          "intra-domain". In some cases there will be routing between domains,
          which will be termed "inter-domain". It is possible that the routing
          exchange between two network systems can be viewed as intra-domain
          from one perspective and as inter-domain from another
          perspective.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Influences on a Changing Network">
          <t>The development of the Internet is likely to be driven by a
          number of changes that will affect the organization and the usage of
          the network, including: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">Ongoing evolution of the commercial
              relationships between (connectivity) service providers, leading
              to changes in the way in which peering between providers is
              organized and the way in which transit traffic is routed.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Requirements for traffic engineering within and
              between domains including coping with multiple paths between
              domains.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Addition of a second IP addressing technique,
              in the form of IPv6.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">The use of VPNs and private address space with
              IPv4 and IPv6.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Evolution of the end-to-end principle to deal
              with the expanded role of the Internet, as discussed in <xref
              target="Blumenthal01"></xref>: this paper discusses the
              possibility that the range of new requirements, especially the
              social and techno-political ones that are being placed on the
              future, may compromise the Internet's original design
              principles. This might cause the Internet to lose some of its
              key features, in particular, its ability to support new and
              unanticipated applications. This discussion is linked to the
              rise of new stakeholders in the Internet, especially ISPs; new
              government interests; the changing motivations of the ever
              growing user base; and the tension between the demand for
              trustworthy overall operation and the inability to trust the
              behavior of individual users.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Incorporation of alternative forwarding
              techniques such as the explicit routing (pipes) supplied by the
              MPLS <xref target="RFC3031"></xref> and GMPLS <xref
              target="RFC3471"></xref> environments.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Integration of additional constraints into
              route determination from interactions with other layers (e.g.,
              Shared Risk Link Groups <xref
              target="InferenceSRLG"></xref>). This includes the
              concern that redundant routes should not fate-share, e.g.,
              because they physically run in the same trench.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Support for alternative and multiple routing
              techniques that are better suited to delivering types of content
              organized in ways other than into IP-addressed packets.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Philosophically, the Internet has the mission of transferring
          information from one place to another. Conceptually, this
          information is rarely organized into conveniently sized,
          IP-addressed packets, and the FDR needs to consider how the
          information (content) to be carried is identified, named, and
          addressed. Routing techniques can then be adapted to handle the
          expected types of content.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="High-Level Goals">
          <t>This section attempts to answer two questions: <list
              hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">What are we trying to achieve in a new
              architecture?</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Why should the Internet community care?</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>There is a third question that needs to be answered as well, but
          that has seldom been explicitly discussed: <list hangIndent="3"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">How will we know when we have succeeded?</t>
            </list></t>

          <section title="Providing a Routing System Matched to Domain Organization">
            <t>Many of today's routing problems are caused by a routing system
            that is not well matched to the organization and policies that it
            is trying to support. Our goal is to develop a routing
            architecture where even a domain organization that is not
            envisioned today can be served by a routing architecture that
            matches its requirements. We will know when this goal is achieved
            when the desired policies, rules, and organization can be mapped
            into the routing system in a natural, consistent, and easily
            understood way.


  
</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Supporting a Range of Different Communication Services">
            <t>Today's routing protocols only support a single data forwarding
            service that is typically used to deliver a best-effort service in
            the public Internet. On the other hand, Diffserv for example, can
            construct a number of different bit transport services within the
            network. Using some of the per-domain behaviors (PDB)s that have
            been discussed in the IETF, it is possible to construct services
            such as Virtual Wire <xref
            target="DiffservVW"></xref> and Assured Rate <xref
            target="DiffservAR"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Providers today offer rudimentary promises about traffic
            handling in the network, for example, delay and long-term packet
            loss guarantees. As time goes on, this becomes even more relevant.
            Communicating the service characteristics of paths in routing
            protocols will be necessary in the near future, and it will be
            necessary to be able to route packets according to their service
            requirements.</t>

            <t>Thus, a goal of this architecture is to allow adequate
            information about path service characteristics to be passed
            between domains and consequently, to allow the delivery of bit
            transport services other than the best-effort datagram
            connectivity service that is the current common denominator.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Scalable Well Beyond Current Predictable Needs">
            <t>Any proposed FDR system should scale beyond the size and
            performance we can foresee for the next ten years. The previous
            IDR proposal as implemented by BGP, has, with some massaging, held
            up for over ten years. In that time the Internet has grown far
            beyond the predictions that were implied by the original
            requirements.</t>

            <t>Unfortunately, we will only know if we have succeeded in this
            goal if the FDR system survives beyond its design lifetime without
            serious massaging. Failure will be much easier to spot!</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Alternative Forwarding Mechanisms">
            <t>With the advent of circuit-based technologies (e.g., MPLS <xref
            target="RFC3031"></xref> and GMPLS <xref target="RFC3471"></xref>)
            managed by IP routers there are forwarding mechanisms other than
            the datagram service that need to be supported by the routing
            architecture.</t>

            <t>An explicit goal of this architecture is to add support for
            forwarding mechanisms other then the current hop-by-hop datagram
            forwarding service driven by globally unique IP addresses.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Separation of Topology Map from Connectivity Service">
            <t>It is envisioned that an organization can support multiple
            services within a single network. These services can, for example,
            be of different quality, of different connectivity type, or of
            different protocols (e.g., IPv4 and IPv6). For all these services,
            there may be common domain topology, even though the policies
            controlling the routing of information might differ from service
            to service. Thus, a goal with this architecture is to support
            separation between creation of a domain (or organization) topology
            map and service creation.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Separation between Routing and Forwarding">
            <t>The architecture of a router is composed of two main separable
            parts: control and forwarding. These components, while
            inter-dependent, perform functions that are largely independent of
            each other. Control (routing, signaling, and management) is
            typically done in software while forwarding typically is done with
            specialized ASICs or network processors.</t>

            <t>The nature of an IP-based network today is that control and
            data protocols share the same network and forwarding regime. This
            may not always be the case in future networks, and we should be
            careful to avoid building in this sharing as an assumption in the
            FDR.</t>

            <t>A goal of this architecture is to support full separation of
            control and forwarding, and to consider what additional concerns
            might be properly considered separately (e.g., adjacency
            management).</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Different Routing Paradigms in Different Areas of the Same Network">
            <t>A number of routing paradigms have been used or researched, in
            addition to the conventional shortest-path-by-hop-count paradigm
            that is the current mainstay of the Internet. In particular,
            differences in underlying transport networks may mean that other
            kinds of routing are more relevant, and the perceived need for
            traffic engineering will certainly alter the routing chosen in
            various domains.</t>

            <t>Explicitly, one of these routing paradigms should be the
            current routing paradigm, so that the new paradigms will
            inter-operate in a backward-compatible way with today's system.
            This will facilitate a migration strategy that avoids flag
            days.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="B-security-1"
                   title="Protection against Denial-of-Service and Other Security Attacks">
            <t>Currently, existence of a route to a destination effectively
            implies that anybody who can get a packet onto the network is
            entitled to use that route. While there are limitations to this
            generalization, this is a clear invitation to denial-of-service
            attacks. A goal of the FDR system should be to allow traffic to be
            specifically linked to whole or partial routes so that a
            destination or link resources can be protected from unauthorized
            use.<list>
                <t>Editors' Note: When sections like this one and the previous
                ones on quality differentiation were written, the idea of
                separating traffic for security or quality was considered an
                unqualified advantage. Today, however, in the midst of active
                discussions on Network Neutrality, it is clear that such
                issues have a crucial policy component that also needs to be
                understood. These, and other similar issues, are open to
                further research.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Provable Convergence with Verifiable Policy Interaction">
            <t>It has been shown both analytically, by Griffin, et al. (see <xref
            target="Griffin99"></xref>), and practically (see <xref
            target="RFC3345"></xref>) that BGP will not converge stably or is
            only meta-stable (i.e., will not re-converge in the face of a
            single failure) when certain types of policy constraint are
            applied to categories of network topology. The addition of policy
            to the basic distance-vector algorithm invalidates the proofs of
            convergence that could be applied to a policy-free
            implementation.</t>

            <t>It has also been argued that global convergence may no longer
            be a necessary goal and that local convergence may be all that is
            required.</t>

            <t>A goal of the FDR should be to achieve provable convergence of
            the protocols used that may involve constraining the topologies
            and domains subject to convergence. This will also require vetting
            the policies imposed to ensure that they are compatible across
            domain boundaries and result in a consistent policy set.<list>
                <t>Editors' Note: This requirement is very optimistic in that
                it implies that it is possible to get operators to cooperate
                even it is seen by them to be against their business
                practices. Though perhaps Utopian, this is a good goal.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Robustness Despite Errors and Failures">
            <t>From time to time in the history of the Internet, there have
            been occurrences where misconfigured routers have destroyed
            global connectivity.</t>

            <t>A goal of the FDR is to be more robust to configuration errors
            and failures. This should probably involve ensuring that the
            effects of misconfiguration and failure can be confined to some
            suitable locality of the failure or misconfiguration.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Simplicity in Management">
            <t>The policy work (<xref target="rap-charter02"></xref>, <xref
            target="snmpconf-charter02"></xref>, and <xref
            target="policy-charter02"></xref>) that has been done at IETF
            provides an architecture that standardizes and simplifies
            management of QoS. This kind of simplicity is needed in a Future
            Domain Routing architecture and its protocols.</t>

            <t>A goal of this architecture is to make configuration and
            management of inter-domain routing as simple as possible.<list>
                <t>Editors' Note: Snmpconf and rap are the hopes of the past.
                Today, configuration and policy hope is focused on netconf
                <xref target="netconf-charter"></xref>.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="LegacyRFC1126"title="The Legacy of RFC 1126">
            <t>RFC 1126 outlined a set of requirements that were used to guide
            the development of BGP. While the network has changed in the years
            since 1989, many of the same requirements remain. A future domain
            routing solution has to support, as its base requirement, the
            level of function that is available today. A detailed discussion
            of RFC 1126 and its requirements can be found in <xref
            target="RFC5773"></xref>. Those requirements,
            while specifically spelled out in that document, are subsumed by
            the requirements in this document.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="High-Level User Requirements">
        <t>This section considers the requirements imposed by the target
        audience of the FDR both in terms of organizations that might own
        networks that would use FDR, and the human users who will have to
        interact with the FDR.</t>

        <section title="Organizational Users">
          <t>The organizations that own networks connected to the Internet
          have become much more diverse since RFC 1126 <xref
          target="RFC1126"></xref> was published. In particular, major parts
          of the network are now owned by commercial service provider
          organizations in the business of making profits from carrying data
          traffic.</t>

          <section anchor="B-security-2" title="Commercial Service Providers">
            <t>The routing system must take into account the commercial
            service provider's need for secrecy and security, as well as
            allowing them to organize their business as flexibly as
            possible.</t>

            <t>Service providers will often wish to conceal the details of the
            network from other connected networks. So far as is possible, the
            routing system should not require the service providers to expose
            more details of the topology and capability of their networks than
            is strictly necessary.</t>

            <t>Many service providers will offer contracts to their customers
            in the form of Service Level Agreements (SLAs). The routing system
            must allow the providers to support these SLAs through traffic
            engineering and load balancing as well as multi-homing, providing
            the degree of resilience and robustness that is needed.</t>

            <t>Service providers can be categorized as: <list hangIndent="3"
                style="hanging">
                <t hangText="- ">Global Service Providers (GSPs) whose
                networks have a global reach. GSPs may, and usually will, wish
                to constrain traffic between their customers to run entirely
                on their networks. GSPs will interchange traffic at multiple
                peering points with other GSPs, and they will need extensive
                policy-based controls to control the interchange of traffic.
                Peering may be through the use of dedicated private lines
                between the partners or, increasingly, through Internet
                Exchange Points.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">National, or regional, Service Providers
                (NSPs) that are similar to GSPs but typically cover one
                country. NSPs may operate as a federation that provides
                similar reach to a GSP and may wish to be able to steer
                traffic preferentially to other federation members to achieve
                global reach.</t>

                <t hangText="- ">Local Internet Service Providers (ISPs)
                operate regionally. They will typically purchase transit
                capacity from NSPs or GSPs to provide global connectivity, but
                they may also peer with neighboring, and sometimes distant,
                ISPs.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The routing system should be sufficiently flexible to
            accommodate the continually changing business relationships of the
            providers and the various levels of trustworthiness that they
            apply to customers and partners.</t>

            <t>Service providers will need to be involved in accounting for
            Internet usage and monitoring the traffic. They may be involved in
            government action to tax the usage of the Internet, enforce social
            mores and intellectual property rules, or apply surveillance to
            the traffic to detect or prevent crime.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Enterprises">
            <t>The leaves of the network domain graph are in many cases
            networks supporting a single enterprise. Such networks cover an
            enormous range of complexity. Some multi-national companies own
            networks that rival the complexity and reach of a GSP, whereas
            many fall into the Small Office-Home Office (SOHO) category. The
            routing system should allow simple and robust configuration and
            operation for the SOHO category, while effectively supporting the
            larger enterprise.</t>

            <t>Enterprises are particularly likely to lack the capability to
            configure and manage a complex routing system, and every effort
            should be made to provide simple configuration and operation for
            such networks.</t>

            <t>Enterprises will also need to be able to change their service
            provider with ease. While this is predominantly a naming and
            addressing issue, the routing system must be able to support
            seamless changeover; for example, if the changeover requires a
            change of address prefix, the routing system must be able to cope
            with a period when both sets of addresses are in use.</t>

            <t>Enterprises will wish to be able to multi-home to one or more
            providers as one possible means of enhancing the resilience of
            their network.</t>

            <t>Enterprises will also frequently need to control the trust that
            they place both in workers and external connections through
            firewalls and similar mid-boxes placed at their external
            connections.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Domestic Networks">
            <t>Increasingly domestic, i.e., non-business home, networks are
            likely to be 'always on' and will resemble SOHO enterprises
            networks with no special requirements on the routing system.</t>

            <t>The routing system must also continue to support dial-up
            users.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Internet Exchange Points">
            <t>Peering of service providers, academic networks, and larger
            enterprises is happening increasingly at specific Internet
            Exchange Points where many networks are linked together in a
            relatively small physical area. The resources of the exchange may
            be owned by a trusted third party or owned jointly by the
            connecting networks. The routing systems should support such
            exchange points without requiring the exchange point to either
            operate as a superior entity with every connected network
            logically inferior to it or by requiring the exchange point to be
            a member of one (or all) connected networks. The connecting
            networks have to delegate a certain amount of trust to the
            exchange point operator.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Content Providers">
            <t>Content providers are at one level a special class of
            enterprise, but the desire to deliver content efficiently means
            that a content provider may provide multiple replicated origin
            servers or caches across a network. These may also be provided by
            a separate content delivery service. The routing system should
            facilitate delivering content from the most efficient
            location.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Individual Users">
          <t>This section covers the most important human users of the FDR and
          their expected interactions with the system.</t>

          <section title="All End Users">
            <t>The routing system must continue to deliver the current global
            connectivity service (i.e., any unique address to any other unique
            address, subject to policy constraints) that has always been the
            basic aim of the Internet.</t>

            <t>End user applications should be able to request, or have
            requested on their behalf by agents and policy mechanisms,
            end-to-end communication services with QoS characteristics
            different from the best-effort service that is the foundation of
            today's Internet. It should be possible to request both a single
            service channel and a bundle of service channels delivered as a
            single entity.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Network Planners">
            <t>The routing system should allow network planners to plan and
            implement a network that can be proved to be stable and will meet
            their traffic engineering requirements.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Network Operators">
            <t>The routing system should, so far as is possible, be simple to
            configure, operate and troubleshoot, behave in a predictable and
            stable fashion, and deliver appropriate statistics and events to
            allow the network to be managed and upgraded in an efficient and
            timely fashion.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Mobile End Users">
            <t>The routing system must support mobile end users. It is clear
            that mobility is becoming a predominant mode for network
            access.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Mandated Constraints">
        <t>While many of the requirements to which the protocol must respond
        are technical, some aren't. These mandated constraints are those that
        are determined by conditions of the world around us. Understanding
        these requirements requires an analysis of the world in which these
        systems will be deployed. The constraints include those that are
        determined by: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="- ">environmental factors,</t>

            <t hangText="- ">geography,</t>

            <t hangText="- ">political boundaries and considerations, and</t>

            <t hangText="- ">technological factors such as the prevalence of
            different levels of technology in the developed world compared to
            those in the developing or undeveloped world.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section anchor="B-security-3" title="The Federated Environment">
          <t>The graph of the Internet network, with routers and other control
          boxes as the nodes and communication links as the edges, is today
          partitioned administratively into a large number of disjoint
          domains.</t>

          <t>A common administration may have responsibility for one or more
          domains that may or may not be adjacent in the graph.</t>

          <t>Commercial and policy constraints affecting the routing system
          will typically be exercised at the boundaries of these domains where
          traffic is exchanged between the domains.</t>

          <t>The perceived need for commercial confidentiality will seek to
          minimize the control information transferred across these
          boundaries, leading to requirements for aggregated information,
          abstracted maps of connectivity exported from domains, and mistrust
          of supplied information.</t>

          <t>The perceived desire for anonymity may require the use of zero-
          knowledge security protocols to allow users to access resources
          without exposing their identity.</t>

          <t>The requirements should provide the ability for groups of peering
          domains to be treated as a complex domain. These complex domains
          could have a common administrative policy.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Working with Different Sorts of Networks">
          <t>The diverse Layer 2 networks, over which the Layer 3 routing
          system is implemented, have typically been operated totally
          independently from the Layer 3 network and often with their own
          routing mechanisms. Consideration needs to be given to the desirable
          degree and nature of interchange of information between the layers.
          In particular, the need for guaranteed robustness through diverse
          routing layers implies knowledge of the underlying networks.</t>

          <t>Mobile access networks may also impose extra requirements on
          Layer 3 routing.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Delivering Resilient Service">
          <t>The routing system operates at Layer 3 in the network. To achieve
          robustness and resilience at this layer requires that, where
          multiple diverse routes are employed as part of delivering the
          resilience, the routing system at Layer 3 needs to be assured that
          the Layer 2 and lower routes are really diverse. The "diamond
          problem" is the simplest form of this problem -- a Layer 3 provider
          attempting to provide diversity buys Layer 2 services from two
          separate providers who in turn buy Layer 1 services from the same
          provider:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                          Layer 3 service
                           /           \
                          /             \
                      Layer 2         Layer 2
                    Provider A      Provider B
                          \             /
                           \           /
                          Layer 1 Provider
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Now, when the backhoe cuts the trench, the Layer 3 provider has no
          resilience unless he had taken special steps to verify that the
          trench wasn't common. The routing system should facilitate avoidance
          of this kind of trap.</t>

          <t>Some work is going on to understand the sort of problems that
          stem from this requirement, such as the work on Shared Risk Link
          Groups <xref target="InferenceSRLG"></xref>.
          Unfortunately, the full generality of the problem requires diversity
          be maintained over time between an arbitrarily large set of mutually
          distrustful providers. For some cases, it may be sufficient for
          diversity to be checked at provisioning or route instantiation time,
          but this remains a hard problem requiring research work.</t>
        </section>

        <section title=" When Will the New Solution Be Required?">
          <t>There is a full range of opinion on this subject. An informal
          survey indicates that the range varies from 2 to 6 years. And
          while there are those, possibly outliers, who think there is no need
          for a new routing architecture as well as those who think a new
          architecture was needed years ago, the median seems to lie at around
          4 years. As in all projections of the future, this is not provable
          at this time. <list>
              <t>Editors' Note: The paragraph above was written in 2002, yet
              could be written without change in 2006. As with many technical
              predictions and schedules, the horizon has remained fixed
              through this interval.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <!---->

      <section title="Assumptions">
        <t>In projecting the requirements for the Future Domain Routing, a
        number of assumptions have been made. The requirements set out should
        be consistent with these assumptions, but there are doubtless a number
        of other assumptions that are not explicitly articulated here: <list
            hangIndent="3" style="numbers">
            <t>The number of hosts today is somewhere in the area of 100
            million. With dial-in, NATs, and the universal deployment of IPv6,
            this is likely to become up to 500 million users (see <xref
            target="CIDR"></xref>). In a number of years, with wireless
            accesses and different appliances attaching to the Internet, we
            are likely to see a couple of billion (10^9) "users" on the
            Internet. The number of globally addressable hosts is very much
            dependent on how common NATs will be in the future.</t>

            <t>NATs, firewalls, and other middle-boxes exist, and we cannot
            assume that they will cease being a presence in the networks.</t>

            <t>The number of operators in the Internet will probably not grow
            very much, as there is a likelihood that operators will tend to
            merge. However, as Internet-connectivity expands to new countries,
            new operators will emerge and then merge again.</t>

            <t>At the beginning of 2002, there are around 12000 registered
            ASs. With current use of ASs (e.g., multi-homing) the number
            of ASs could be expected to grow to 25000 in about 10 years<xref
            target="Broido02"></xref>. This is down from a previously reported
            growth rate of 51% per year <xref target="RFC3221"></xref>. Future
            growth rates are difficult to predict. <list style="empty">
                <t>Editors' Note: In the routing report table of August 2006,
                the total number of ASs present in the Internet Routing Table
                was 23000. In 4 years, this is substantial progress on the
                prediction of 25000 ASs. Also, there are significantly more
                ASs registered than are visibly active, i.e., in excess of
                42000 in mid-2006. It is possible, however, that many are
                being used internally.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>In contrast to the number of operators, the number of domains
            is likely to grow significantly. Today, each operator has
            different domains within an AS, but this also shows in SLAs and
            policies internal to the operator. Making this globally visible
            would create a number of domains; 10-100 times the number of ASs,
            i.e., between 100,000 and 1,000,000.</t>

            <t>With more and more capacity at the edge of the network, the IP
            network will expand. Today, there are operators with several
            thousands of routers, but this is likely to be increased. Some
            domains will probably contain tens of thousands of routers.</t>

            <t>The speed of connections in the (fixed) access will technically
            be (almost) unconstrained. However, the cost for the links will
            not be negligible so that the apparent speed will be effectively
            bounded. Within a number of years, some will have multi-gigabit
            speed in the access.</t>

            <t>At the same time, the bandwidth of wireless access still has a
            strict upper-bound. Within the foreseeable future each user will
            have only a tiny amount of resources available compared to fixed
            accesses (10 kbps to 2 Mbps for a Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS) with only a few achieving the
            higher figure as the bandwidth is shared between the active users
            in a cell and only small cells can actually reach this speed, but
            11 Mbps or more for wireless LAN connections). There may also be
            requirements for effective use of bandwidth as low as 2.4 Kbps or
            lower, in some applications.</t>

            <t>Assumptions 7 and 8 taken together suggest a minimum span of
            bandwidth between 2.4 kbps to 10 Gbps.</t>

            <t>The speed in the backbone has grown rapidly, and there is no
            evidence that the growth will stop in the coming years.
            Terabit-speed is likely to be the minimum backbone speed in a
            couple of years. The range of bandwidths that need to be
            represented will require consideration on how to represent the
            values in the protocols.</t>

            <t>There have been discussions as to whether Moore's Law will
            continue to hold for processor speed. If Moore's Law does not
            hold, then communication circuits might play a more important role
            in the future. Also, optical routing is based on circuit
            technology, which is the main reason for taking "circuits" into
            account when designing an FDR.</t>

            <t>However, the datagram model still remains the fundamental model
            for the Internet.</t>

            <t>The number of peering points in the network is likely to grow,
            as multi-homing becomes important. Also, traffic will become more
            locally distributed, which will drive the demand for local
            peering.<list hangIndent="" style="empty">
                <t>Editors' Note: On the other hand, peer-to-peer networking
                may shift the balance in demand for local peering.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The FDR will achieve the same degree of ubiquity as the current
            Internet and IP routing.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Functional Requirements">
        <t>This section includes a detailed discussion of new requirements for
        a Future Domain Routing architecture. The nth requirement carries the
        label "R(n)". As discussed in <xref target="LegacyRFC1126" />, a new architecture must
        build upon the requirements of the past routing framework and must not
        reduce the functionality of the network. A discussion and analysis of
        the RFC 1126 requirements can be found in <xref
        target="RFC5773"></xref>.</t>

        <section title="Topology">
          <section title="Routers Should Be Able to Learn and to Exploit the Domain Topology">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!-- R(1) -->Routers must be able to acquire and hold
                sufficient information on the underlying topology of the
                domain to allow the establishment of routes on that
                topology.</t>

                <t><!-- R(2) -->Routers must have the ability to control the
                establishment of routes on the underlying topology.</t>

                <t><!-- R(3) -->Routers must be able, where appropriate, to
                control Sub-IP mechanisms to support the establishment of
                routes.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The OSI Inter-Domain Routing Protocol (IDRP)<xref
            target="ISO10747"></xref> allowed a collection of topologically
            related domains to be replaced by an aggregate domain object, in a
            similar way to the Nimrod <xref target="Chiappa02"></xref> domain
            hierarchies. This allowed a route to be more compactly represented
            by a single collection instead of a sequence of individual
            domains. <list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!-- R(4) -->Routers must, where appropriate, be able to
                construct abstractions of the topology that represent an
                aggregation of the topological features of some area of the
                topology.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="The Same Topology Information Should Support Different Path Selection Ideas">
            <t>The same topology information needs to provide the more
            flexible spectrum of path selection methods that we might expect
            to find in a future Internet, including distributed techniques
            such as hop-by-hop, shortest path, local optimization
            constraint-based, class of service, source address routing, and
            destination address routing, as well as the centralized, global
            optimization constraint-based "traffic engineering" type. Allowing
            different path selection techniques will produce a much more
            predictable and comprehensible result than the "clever tricks"
            that are currently needed to achieve the same results. Traffic
            engineering functions need to be combined. <list counter="req"
                hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!-- R(5) -->Routers must be capable of supporting a small
                number of different path selection algorithms.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Separation of the Routing Information Topology from the Data      Transport Topology">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!-- R(6)  -->The controlling network may be logically
                separate from the controlled network.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The two functional "planes" may physically reside in the same
            nodes and share the same links, but this is not the only
            possibility, and other options may sometimes be necessary. An
            example is a pure circuit switch (that cannot see individual IP
            packets) combined with an external controller. Another example may
            be multiple links between two routers, where all the links are
            used for data forwarding but only one is used for carrying the
            routing session.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.2 Distribution -->

        <section title="Distribution">
          <!-- 6.2.1 Distribution mechanisms -->

          <section title="Distribution Mechanisms">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!-- R(7) -->Relevant changes in the state of the network,
                including modifications to the topology and changes in the
                values of dynamic capabilities, must be distributed to every
                entity in the network that needs them, in a reliable and
                trusted way, at the earliest appropriate time after the
                changes have occurred.</t>

                <t><!-- R(8) -->Information must not be distributed outside
                areas where it is needed, or believed to be needed, for the
                operation of the routing system.</t>

                <t><!-- R(9) r-minload -->Information must be distributed in
                such a way that it minimizes the load on the network,
                consistent with the required response time of the network to
                changes.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.2.2 Path advertisement -->

          <section anchor="B-security-4" title="Path Advertisement">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(10) -->The router must be able to acquire and
                store additional static and dynamic information that relates
                to the capabilities of the topology and its component nodes
                and links and that can subsequently be used by path selection
                methods.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The inter-domain routing system must be able to advertise more
            kinds of information than just connectivity and domain paths.
            <list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(11) -->The routing system must support service
                specifications, e.g., the Service Level Specifications (SLSs)
                developed by the Differentiated Services working group <xref
                target="RFC3260"></xref>.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Careful attention should be paid to ensuring that the
            distribution of additional information with path advertisements
            remains scalable as domains and the Internet get larger, more
            numerous, and more diversified.</t>

            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(12) r-distscale-->The distribution mechanism used
                for distributing network state information must be scalable
                with respect to the expected size of domains and the volume
                and rate of change of dynamic state that can be expected.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The combination of <!--
   <xref target = "r-minload"/> and
   <xref target = "r-distscale"/>
--> R(9) and R(12) may result in a compromise between the responsiveness of
            the network to change and the overhead of distributing change
            notifications. Attempts to respond to very rapid changes may
            damage the stability of the routing system.</t>

            <t>Possible examples of additional capability information that
            might be carried include: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
                <t hangText="- ">QoS information<vspace blankLines="1" /> To
                allow an ISP to sell predictable end-to-end QoS service to any
                destination, the routing system should have information about
                the end-to-end QoS. This means that:</t>
              </list> <list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(13) -->The routing system must be able to support
                different paths for different services.</t>

                <t><!--    R(14) -->The routing system must be able to forward
                traffic on the path appropriate for the service selected for
                the traffic, either according to an explicit marking in each
                packet (e.g., MPLS labels, Diffserv Per-Hop Behaviors (PHBs) or DSCP values) or
                implicitly (e.g., the physical or logical port on which the
                traffic arrives).</t>

                <t><!--    R(15) -->The routing system should also be able to
                carry information about the expected (or actually, promised)
                characteristics of the entire path and the price for the
                service.</t>
              </list> <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
                <t hangText="">(If such information is exchanged at all
                between network operators today, it is through bilateral
                management interfaces, and not through the routing protocols.)</t>
                <t hangText="" > This would allow for the operator to
                optimize the choice of path based on a price/performance
                trade-off.</t> <t hangText="" > In addition to providing
                dynamic QoS information, the system should be able to use
                static class-of-service information.</t>

                <t hangText="-">Security information <vspace
                blankLines="1" />Security characteristics of other domains
                referred to by advertisements can allow the routing entity to
                make routing decisions based on political concerns. The
                information itself is assumed to be secure so that it can be
                trusted.</t>

                <t hangText="-">Usage and cost information<vspace
                blankLines="1" /> Usage and cost information can be used for
                billing and traffic engineering. In order to support
                cost-based routing policies for customers (i.e., peer ISPs),
                information such as "traffic on this link or path costs XXX
                per Gigabyte" needs to be advertised, so that the customer can
                choose a more or a less expensive route.</t>

                <t hangText="-">Monitored performance<vspace
                blankLines="1" /> Performance information such as delay and
                drop frequency can be carried. (This may only be suitable
                inside a domain because of trust considerations.) This should
                support at least the kind of delay-bound contractual terms
                that are currently being offered by service providers. Note
                that these values refer to the outcome of carrying bits on the
                path, whereas the QoS information refers to the proposed
                behavior that results in this outcome.</t>

                <t hangText="-">Multicast information<vspace
                blankLines="1" /></t>
              </list> <list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(16) -->The routing system must provide
                information needed to create multicast distribution trees.
                This information must be provided for one-to-many distribution
                trees and should be provided for many-to-many distribution
                trees.</t>
              </list> <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
                <t hangText="">The actual construction of distribution
                trees is not necessarily done by the routing system.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Stability of Routing Information">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(17) -->The new network architecture must be
                stable without needing global convergence, i.e., convergence
                is a local property.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The degree to which this is possible and the definition of
            "local" remain research topics. Restricting the requirement for
            convergence to localities will have an effect on all of the other
            requirements in this section. <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
                style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(18) -->The distribution and the rate of
                distribution of changes must not affect the stability of the
                routing information. For example, commencing redistribution of
                a change before the previous one has settled must not cause
                instability.</t>
              </list></t>

            <section title="Avoiding Routing Oscillations">
              <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                  <t><!--    R(19) -->The routing system must minimize
                  oscillations in route advertisements.</t>
                </list></t>
            </section>

            <section title="Providing Loop-Free Routing and Forwarding">
              <t>In line with the separation of routing and forwarding
              concerns: <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
                  style="format R(%d)">
                  <t><!--    R(20) -->The distribution of routing information
                  must be, so far as is possible, loop-free.</t>

                  <t><!--    R(21) -->The forwarding information created from
                  this routing information must seek to minimize persistent
                  loops in the data-forwarding paths.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>It is accepted that transient loops may occur during
              convergence of the protocol and that there are trade-offs
              between loop avoidance and global scalability.</t>
            </section>

            <!-- 6.2.3.3 Detection, notification, and repair of failures -->

            <section title="Detection, Notification, and Repair of Failures">
              <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                  <t><!--    R(22) -->The routing system must provide means
                  for detecting failures of node equipment or communication
                  links.</t>

                  <t><!--    R(23) -->The routing system should be able to
                  coordinate failure indications from Layer 3 mechanisms, from
                  nodal mechanisms built into the routing system, and from
                  lower-layer mechanisms that propagate up to Layer 3 in order
                  to determine the root cause of the failure. This will allow
                  the routing system to react correctly to the failure by
                  activating appropriate mitigation and repair mechanisms if
                  required, while ensuring that it does not react if lower-layer repair mechanisms are able to repair or mitigate the
                  fault.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Most Layer 3 routing protocols have utilized keepalives or
              "hello" protocols as a means of detecting failures at Layer 3.
              The keepalive mechanisms are often complemented by analog
              mechanisms (e.g., laser-light detection) and hardware mechanisms
              (e.g., hardware/software watchdogs) that are built into routing
              nodes and communication links. Great care must be taken to make the
              best possible use of the various failure repair methods
              available while ensuring that only one repair mechanism at a
              time is allowed to repair any given fault. Interactions between,
              for example, fast reroute mechanisms at Layer 3 and Synchronous Optical Network/Synchronous Digital Hierarchy (SONET/SDH)
              repair at Layer 1 are highly undesirable and are likely to cause
              problems in the network.</t>

              <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                  <t><!--    R(24) -->Where a network topology and routing
                  system contains multiple fault repair mechanisms, the
                  responses of these systems to a detected failure should be
                  coordinated so that the fault is repaired by the most
                  appropriate means, and no extra repairs are initiated.</t>

                  <t><!--    R(25) -->Where specialized packet exchange
                  mechanisms (e.g., Layer 3 keepalive or "hello" protocol
                  mechanisms) are used to detect failures, the routing system
                  must allow the configuration of the rate of transmission of
                  these keepalives. This must include the capability to turn
                  them off altogether for links that are deliberately broken
                  when no real user or control traffic is present (e.g., ISDN
                  links).</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>This will allow the operator to compromise between the speed
              of failure detection and the proportion of link bandwidth
              dedicated to failure detection.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.3 Addressing -->

        <section title="Addressing">
          <!-- 6.3.1 Support mix of IPv4, IPv6 and other types of addresses -->

          <section title="Support Mix of IPv4, IPv6, and Other Types of Addresses">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(26) -->The routing system must support a mix of
                different kinds of addresses.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>This mix will include at least IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, and
            preferably various types of non-IP addresses, too. For instance,
            networks like SDH/SONET and Wavelength Division Multiplexing (WDM) may prefer to use non-IP
            addresses. It may also be necessary to support multiple sets of
            "private" (e.g., RFC 1918) addresses when dealing with multiple
            customer VPNs.</t>

            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(27) -->The routing system should support the use
                of a single topology representation to generate routing and
                forwarding tables for multiple address families on the same
                network.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>This capability would minimize the protocol overhead when
            exchanging routes.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Support for Domain Renumbering/Readdressing">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(28) -->If a domain is subject to address
                reassignment that would cause forwarding interruption, then
                the routing system should support readdressing (e.g., when a
                new prefix is given to an old network, and the change is known
                in advance) by maintaining routing during the changeover
                period <xref target="RFC2071"></xref> <xref
                target="RFC2072"></xref>.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.3.3 Multicast and anycast -->

          <section title="Multicast and Anycast">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(29) -->The routing system must support multicast
                addressing, both within a domain and across multiple
                domains.</t>

                <t><!--    R(30) -->The routing system should support anycast
                addressing within a domain. The routing system may support
                anycast addressing across domains.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>An open question is whether it is possible or useful to support
            anycast addressing between cooperating domains.</t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.3.4 Address scoping -->

          <section title="Address Scoping">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(31) -->The routing system must support scoping of
                unicast addresses, and it should support scoping of multicast
                and anycast address types.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The unicast address scoping that is being designed for IPv6
            does not seem to cause any special problems for routing. IPv6
            inter-domain routing handles only IPv6 global addresses, while
            intra-domain routing also needs to be aware of the scope of
            private addresses. <list>
                <t>Editors' Note: the original reference was to site-local
                addresses, but these have been deprecated by the IETF.
                Link-local addresses are never routed at all.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>More study may be needed to identify the requirements and
            solutions for scoping in a more general sense and for scoping of
            multicast and anycast addresses.</t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.3.5 Mobility support -->

          <section title="Mobility Support">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(32) -->The routing system must support system
                mobility. The term "system" includes anything from an end
                system to an entire domain.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>We observe that the existing solutions based on renumbering
            and/or tunneling are designed to work with the current routing, so
            they do not add any new requirements to future routing. But the
            requirement is general, and future solutions may not be restricted
            to the ones we have today.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.4 Statistics support -->

        <section title="Statistics Support">
          <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(33) -->Both the routing and forwarding parts of the
              routing system must maintain statistical information about the
              performance of their functions.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.5 Management requirements -->

        <section title="Management Requirements">
          <t>While the tools of management are outside the scope of routing,
          the mechanisms to support the routing architecture and protocols are
          within scope. <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
              style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(34) -->Mechanisms to support Operational,
              Administrative, and Management control of the routing
              architecture and protocols must be designed into the original
              fabric of the architecture.</t>
            </list></t>

          <!-- 6.5.1 Simple policy management -->

          <section title="Simple Policy Management">
            <t>The basic aims of this specification are: <list hangIndent="3"
                style="hanging">
                <t hangText="- ">to require less manual configuration than
                today, and</t>

                <t hangText="- ">to satisfy the requirements for both easy
                handling and maximum control. That is: <list hangIndent="3"
                    style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="- ">All the information should be
                    available,</t>

                    <t hangText="- ">but should not be visible except for when
                    necessary.</t>

                    <t hangText="- ">Policies themselves should be advertised
                    and not only the result of policy, and</t>

                    <t hangText="- ">policy-conflict resolution must be
                    provided.</t>
                  </list></t>
              </list></t>

            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(35) -->The routing system must provide management
                of the system by means of policies. For example, policies that
                can be expressed in terms of the business and services
                implemented on the network and reflect the operation of the
                network in terms of the services affected. <list
                    hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="    ">Editors' Note: This requirement is
                    optimistic in that it implies that it is possible to get
                    operators to cooperate even if it is seen by them to be
                    against their business practices.</t>
                  </list></t>

                <t><!--    R(36) -->The distribution of policies must be
                amenable to scoping to protect proprietary policies that are
                not relevant beyond the local set of domains.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.5.2 Startup and Maintenance of Routers -->

          <section title="Startup and Maintenance of Routers">
            <t>A major problem in today's networks is the need to perform
            initial configuration on routers from a local interface before a
            remote management system can take over. It is not clear that this
            imposes any requirements on the routing architecture beyond what
            is needed for a ZeroConf host.</t>

            <t>Similarly, maintenance and upgrade of routers can cause major
            disruptions to the network routing because the routing system and
            management of routers is not organized to minimize such
            disruption. Some improvements have been made, such as graceful
            restart mechanisms in protocols, but more needs to be done. <list
                counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(37) -->The routing system and routers should
                provide mechanisms that minimize the disruption to the network
                caused by maintenance and upgrades of software and hardware.
                This requirement recognizes that some of the capabilities
                needed are outside the scope of the routing architecture
                (e.g., minimum impact software upgrade).</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.6 Provability -->

        <section title="Provability">
          <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(38) -->The routing system and its component
              protocols must be demonstrated to be locally convergent under
              the permitted range of parameter settings and policy options
              that the operator(s) can select.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>There are various methods for demonstration and proof that
          include, but are not limited to: mathematical proof, heuristic, and
          pattern recognition. No requirement is made on the method used for
          demonstrating local convergence properties.</t>

          <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(39) -->Routing protocols employed by the routing
              system and the overall routing system should be resistant to bad
              routing policy decisions made by operators.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Tools are needed to check compatibility of routing policies.
          While these tools are not part of the routing architecture, the
          mechanisms to support such tools are.</t>

          <t>Routing policies are compatible if their interaction does not
          cause instability. A domain or group of domains in a system is
          defined as being convergent, either locally or globally, if and only
          if, after an exchange of routing information, routing tables reach a
          stable state that does not change until the routing policies or the
          topology changes again.</t>

          <t>To achieve the above-mentioned goals: <list counter="req"
              hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(40) -->The routing system must provide a mechanism
              to publish and communicate policies so that operational
              coordination and fault isolation are possible.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Tools are required that verify the stability characteristics of
          the routing system in specified parts of the Internet. The tools
          should be efficient (fast) and have a broad scope of operation
          (check large portions of Internet). While these tools are not part
          of the architecture, developing them is in the interest of the
          architecture and should be defined as a Routing Research Group
          activity while research on the architecture is in progress.</t>

          <t>Tools analyzing routing policies can be applied statically or
          (preferably) dynamically. A dynamic solution requires tools that can
          be used for run time checking for oscillations that arise from
          policy conflicts. Research is needed to find an efficient solution
          to the dynamic checking of oscillations.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.7 Traffic engineering -->

        <section title="Traffic Engineering">
          <t>The ability to do traffic engineering and to get the feedback
          from the network to enable traffic engineering should be included in
          the future domain architecture. Though traffic engineering has many
          definitions, it is, at base, another alternative or extension for
          the path selection mechanisms of the routing system. No fundamental
          changes to the requirements are needed, but the iterative processes
          involved in traffic engineering may require some additional
          capabilities and state in the network.</t>

          <t>Traffic engineering typically involves a combination of off-line
          network planning and administrative control functions in which the
          expected and measured traffic flows are examined, resulting in
          changes to static configurations and policies in the routing system.
          During operations, these configurations control the actual flow of
          traffic and affect the dynamic path selection mechanisms; the
          results are measured and fed back into further rounds of network
          planning.</t>

          <!-- 6.7.1 Support for and provision of traffic engineering tools -->

          <section title="Support for, and Provision of, Traffic Engineering Tools">
            <t>At present, there is an almost total lack of effective traffic
            engineering tools, whether in real time for network control or
            off-line for network planning. The routing system should encourage
            the provision of such tools. <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
                style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(41) -->The routing system must generate
                statistical and accounting information in such a way that
                traffic engineering and network planning tools can be used in
                both real-time and off-line planning and management.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <!-- 6.7.2 Support of multiple parallel paths -->

          <section title="Support of Multiple Parallel Paths">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(42) -->The routing system must support the
                controlled distribution over multiple links or paths of
                traffic toward the same destination. This applies to domains
                with two or more connections to the same neighbor domain, and
                to domains with connections to more than one neighbor domain.
                The paths need not have the same metric.</t>

                <t><!--    R(43) -->The routing system must support forwarding
                over multiple parallel paths when available. This support
                should extend to cases where the offered traffic is known to
                exceed the available capacity of a single link, and to the
                cases where load is to be shared over paths for cost or
                resiliency reasons.</t>

                <t><!--    R(44) -->Where traffic is forwarded over multiple
                parallel paths, the routing system must, so far as is
                possible, avoid the reordering of packets in individual
                micro-flows.</t>

                <t><!--    R(45) -->The routing system must have mechanisms to
                allow the traffic to be reallocated back onto a single path
                when multiple paths are not needed.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Peering Support">
            <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(46) -->The routing system must support peer-level
                connectivity as well as hierarchical connections between
                domains.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The network is becoming increasingly complex, with private
            peering arrangements set up between providers at every level of
            the hierarchy of service providers and even by certain large
            enterprises, in the form of dedicated extranets. <list
                counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
                <t><!--    R(47) -->The routing system must facilitate traffic
                engineering of peer routes so that traffic can be readily
                constrained to travel as the network operators desire,
                allowing optimal use of the available connectivity.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <!-- 6.8 Support for middleboxes -->

        <section title="Support for Middleboxes">
          <t>One of our assumptions is that NATs and other middle-boxes such
          as firewalls, web proxies, and address family translators (e.g., IPv4
          to IPv6) are here to stay. <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
              style="format R(%d)">
              <t><!--    R(48) -->The routing system should work in
              conjunction with middle-boxes, e.g., NAT, to aid in
              bi-directional connectivity without compromising the additional
              opacity and privacy that the middle-boxes offer.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This problem is closely analogous to the abstraction problem,
          which is already under discussion for the interchange of routing
          information between domains.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <!-- 7. Performance requirements -->

      <section title="Performance Requirements">
        <t>Over the past several years, the performance of the routing system
        has frequently been discussed. The requirements that derive from those
        discussions are listed below. The specific values for these
        performance requirements are left for further discussion. <list
            counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(49) -->The routing system must support domains of at
            least N systems. A system is taken to mean either an individual
            router or a domain.</t>

            <t><!--    R(50) -->Local convergence should occur within T units
            of time.</t>

            <t><!--    R(52) -->The routing system must be measurably
            reliable. The measure of reliability remains a research
            question.</t>

            <t><!--    R(53) -->The routing system must be locally stable to a
            measured degree. The degree of measurability remains a research
            issue.</t>

            <t><!--    R(54) -->The routing system must be globally stable to
            a measured degree. The degree of measurability remains a research
            issue.</t>

            <t><!--    R(55) -->The routing system should scale to an
            indefinitely large number of domains.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>There has been very little data or statistical evidence for many of
        the performance claims made in the past. In recent years, several
        efforts have been initiated to gather data and do the analyses
        required to make scientific assessments of performance issues and
        requirements. In order to complete this section of the requirements
        analysis, the data and analyses from these studies needs to be
        gathered and collated into this document. This work has been started
        but has yet to be completed. <list>
            <t>Editors' Note: This work was never completed due to corporate reorganizations.</t>
        </list> </t>
      </section>

      <!-- 8. Backwards compatibility (cutover) and maintainability -->

      <section title="Backward Compatibility (Cutover) and Maintainability">
        <t>This area poses a dilemma. On one hand, it is an absolute
        requirement that: <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
            style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(56) -->The introduction of the routing system must
            not require any flag days.</t>

            <t><!--    R(57) -->The network currently in place must continue
            to run at least as well as it does now while the new network is
            being installed around it.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>However, at the same time, it is also an requirement that: <list
            counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t anchor="R57"><!--    R(58) -->The new architecture must not be
            limited by the restrictions that plague today's network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It has to be admitted that R(57) is not a well-defined requirement,
        because we have not fully articulated what the restrictions might be.
        Some of these restrictions can be derived by reading the discussions
        for the positive requirements above. It would be a useful exercise to
        explicitly list all the restrictions and irritations with which we wish to
        do away. Further, it would be useful to determine if these
        restrictions can currently be removed at a reasonable cost or whether we
        are actually condemned to live with them.</t>

        <t>Those restrictions cannot be allowed to become permanent baggage on
        the new architecture. If they do, the effort to create a new system
        will come to naught. It may, however, be necessary to live with some
        of them temporarily for practical reasons while providing an
        architecture that will eventually allow them to be removed. <!-- mark -->
        The last three requirements have significance not only for the
        transition strategy but also for the architecture itself. They imply
        that it must be possible for an internet such as today's
        BGP-controlled network, or one of its ASs, to exist as a domain
        within the new FDR.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- 9. Security requirements -->

      <section anchor="B-security-5" title="Security Requirements">
        <t>As previously discussed, one of the major changes that has
        overtaken the Internet since its inception is the erosion of trust
        between end users making use of the net, between those users and the
        suppliers of services, and between the multiplicity of providers.
        Hence, security, in all its aspects, will be much more important in the
        FDR.</t>

        <t>It must be possible to secure the routing communication. <list
            counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(59) -->The communicating entities must be able to
            identify who sent and who received the information
            (authentication).</t>

            <t><!--    R(60) -->The communicating entities must be able to
            verify that the information has not been changed on the way
            (integrity).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Security is more important in inter-domain routing where the
        operator has no control over the other domains, than in intra-domain
        routing where all the links and the nodes are under the administration
        of the operator and can be expected to share a trust relationship.
        This property of intra-domain trust, however, should not be taken for
        granted: <list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(61) -->Routing communications must be secured by
            default, but an operator must have the option to relax this
            requirement within a domain where analysis indicates that other
            means (such as physical security) provide an acceptable
            alternative.</t>

            <t><!--    R(62) -->The routing communication mechanism must be
            robust against denial-of-service attacks.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><list counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t>It should be possible to verify that the originator of the
            information was authorized to generate the information.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Further considerations that may impose further requirements
        include: <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="- ">whether no one else but the intended recipient is
            able to access (privacy) or understand (confidentiality) the
            information,</t>

            <t hangText="- ">whether it is possible to verify that all the
            information has been received and that the two parties agree on
            what was sent (validation and non-repudiation),</t>

            <t hangText="- ">whether there is a need to separate security of
            routing from security of forwarding, and</t>

            <t hangText="- ">whether traffic flow security is needed (i.e.,
            whether there is value in concealing who can connect to whom, and
            what volumes of data are exchanged).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Securing the BGP session, as done today, only secures the exchange
        of messages from the peering domain, not the content of the
        information. In other words, we can confirm that the information we
        got is what our neighbor really sent us, but we do not know whether or not this information (that originated in some remote domain) is true.</t>

        <t>A decision has to be made on whether to rely on chains of trust (we
        trust our peers who trust their peers who..), or whether we also need
        authentication and integrity of the information end-to-end. This
        information includes both routes and addresses. There has been
        interest in having digital signatures on originated routes as well as
        countersignatures by address authorities to confirm that the
        originator has authority to advertise the prefix. Even understanding
        who can confirm the authority is non-trivial, as it might be the
        provider who delegated the prefix (with a whole chain of authority
        back to ICANN) or it may be an address registry. Where a prefix
        delegated by a provider is being advertised through another provider
        as in multi-homing, both may have to be involved to confirm that the
        prefix may be advertised through the provider who doesn't have any
        interest in the prefix! <list counter="req" hangIndent="6"
            style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(63) -->The routing system must cooperate with the
            security policies of middle-boxes whenever possible.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This is likely to involve further requirements for abstraction of
        information. For example, a firewall that is seeking to minimize
        interchange of information that could lead to a security breach. The
        effect of such changes on the end-to-end principle should be carefully
        considered as discussed in <xref target="Blumenthal01"></xref>. <list
            counter="req" hangIndent="6" style="format R(%d)">
            <t><!--    R(64) -->The routing system must be capable of
            complying with local legal requirements for interception of
            communication.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <!-- 10.Debatable issues -->

      <section title="Debatable Issues">
        <t>This section covers issues that need to be considered and resolved
        in deciding on a Future Domain Routing architecture. While they can't
        be described as requirements, they do affect the types of solution
        that are acceptable. The discussions included below are very open-
        ended.</t>

        <!-- 10.1Network modeling -->

        <section title="Network Modeling">
          <t>The mathematical model that underlies today's routing system uses
          a graph representation of the network. Hosts, routers, and other
          processing boxes are represented by nodes and communications links
          by arcs. This is a topological model in that routing does not need
          to directly model the physical length of the links or the position
          of the nodes; the model can be transformed to provide a convenient
          picture of the network by adjusting the lengths of the arcs and the
          layout of the nodes. The connectivity is preserved and routing is
          unaffected by this transformation.</t>

          <t>The routing algorithms in traditional routing protocols utilize a
          small number of results from graph theory. It is only recently that
          additional results have been employed to support constraint-based
          routing for traffic engineering.</t>

          <t>The naturalness of this network model and the "fit" of the graph
          theoretical methods may have tended to blind us to alternative
          representations and inhibited us from seeking alternative strands of
          theoretical thinking that might provide improved results.</t>

          <t>We should not allow this habitual behavior to stop us from looking for
          alternative representations and algorithms; topological revolutions
          are possible and allowed, at least in theory.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.2 System modeling -->

        <section title="System Modeling">
          <t>The assumption that object modeling of a system is an essential
          first step to creating a new system is still novel in this context.
          Frequently, the object modeling effort becomes an end in itself and
          does not lead to system creation. But there is a balance, and a lot
          that can be discovered in an ongoing effort to model a system such
          as the Future Domain Routing system. It is recommended that this
          process be included in the requirements. It should not, however, be
          a gating event to all other work.</t>

          <t>Some of the most important realizations will occur during the
          process of determining the following: <list hangIndent=" 3"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">Object classification</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Relationships and containment</t>

              <t hangText="- ">Roles and Rules</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.3 One, Two or Many Protocols -->

        <section title="One, Two, or Many Protocols">
          <t>There has been a lot of discussion of whether the FDR protocol
          solution should consist of one (probably new) protocol, two (intra-
          and inter-domain) protocols, or many protocols. While it might be
          best to have one protocol that handles all situations, this seems
          improbable. On the other hand, maintaining the "strict" division
          evident in the network today between the IGP and EGP may be too
          restrictive an approach. Given this, and the fact that there are
          already many routing protocols in use, the only possible answer
          seems to be that the architecture should support many protocols. It
          remains an open issue, one for the solution, to determine if a new
          protocol needs to be designed in order to support the highest goals
          of this architecture. The expectation is that a new protocol will be
          needed.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.4C lass of protocol to use -->

        <section title="Class of Protocol">
          <t>If a new protocol is required to support the FDR architecture,
          the question remains open as to what kind of protocol this ought to
          be. It is our expectation that a map distribution protocol will be
          required to augment the current path-vector protocol and shortest
          path first protocols.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.5 Map abstraction -->

        <section title="Map Abstraction">
          <t>Assuming that a map distribution protocol, as defined in <xref
          target="RFC1992"></xref> is required, what are the requirements on
          this protocol? If every detail is advertised throughout the
          Internet, there will be a lot of information. Scalable solutions
          require abstraction. <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="- ">If we summarize too much, some information will
              be lost on the way.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">If we summarize too little, then more
              information than required is available, contributing to scaling
              limitations.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">One can allow more summarization, if there also
              is a mechanism to query for more details within policy
              limits.</t>

              <t hangText="- ">The basic requirement is not that the
              information shall be advertised, but rather that the information
              shall be available to those who need it. We should not
              presuppose a solution where advertising is the only possible
              mechanism.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.6 Clear identification for all entities -->

        <section title="Clear Identification for All Entities">
          <t>As in all other fields, the words used to refer to concepts and
          to describe operations about routing are important. Rather than
          describe concepts using terms that are inaccurate or rarely used in
          the real world of networking, it is necessary to make an effort to
          use the correct words. Many networking terms are used casually, and
          the result is a partial or incorrect understanding of the underlying
          concept. Entities such as nodes, interfaces, subnetworks, tunnels,
          and the grouping concepts such as ASs, domains, areas, and regions,
          need to be clearly identified and defined to avoid confusion.</t>

          <t>There is also a need to separate identifiers (what or who) from
          locators (where) from routes (how to reach). <list>
              <t>Editors' Note: Work was undertaken in the shim6 working group
              of the IETF on this sort of separation. This work needs to be
              taken into account in any new routing architecture.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.7 Robustness and redundancy: -->

        <section title="Robustness and Redundancy">
          <t>The routing association between two domains should survive even
          if some individual connection between two routers goes down.</t>

          <t>The "session" should operate between logical "routing entities"
          on each domain side, and not necessarily be bound to individual
          routers or addresses. Such a logical entity can be physically
          distributed over multiple network elements. Or, it can reside in a
          single router, which would default to the current situation.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.8 Hierarchy -->

        <section title="Hierarchy">
          <t>A more flexible hierarchy with more levels and recursive
          groupings in both upward and downward directions allows more
          structured routing. The consequence is that no single level will get
          too big for routers to handle.</t>

          <t>On the other hand, it appears that the real-world Internet is
          becoming less hierarchical, so that it will be increasingly
          difficult to use hierarchy to control scaling.</t>

          <t>Note that groupings can look different depending on which aspect
          we use to define them. A Diffserv area, an MPLS domain, a trusted
          domain, a QoS area, a multicast domain, etc., do not always
          coincide; nor are they strict hierarchical subsets of each
          other. The basic distinction at each level is "this grouping versus
          everything outside".</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.9 Will new control mechanisms be needed? -->

        <section title="Control Theory">
          <t>Is it possible to apply a control theory framework to analyze the
          stability of the control system of the whole network domain, with
          regard to, e.g., convergence speed and the frequency response, and
          then use the results from that analysis to set the timers and other
          protocol parameters?</t>

          <t>Control theory could also play a part in QoS routing, by
          modifying current link-state protocols with link costs dependent on
          load and feedback. Control theory is often used to increase the
          stability of dynamic systems.</t>

          <t>It might be possible to construct a new, totally dynamic routing
          protocol solely on a control theoretic basis, as opposed to the
          current protocols that are based in graph theory and static in
          nature.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.10 Byzantium -->

        <section title="Byzantium">
          <t>Is solving the Byzantine Generals problem a requirement? This is
          the problem of reaching a consensus among distributed units if some
          of them give misleading answers. The current intra-domain routing
          system is, at one level, totally intolerant of misleading
          information. However, the effect of different sorts of misleading or
          incorrect information has vastly varying results, from total
          collapse to purely local disconnection of a single domain. This sort
          of behavior is not very desirable.</t>

          <t>There are, possibly, other network robustness issues that must be
          researched and resolved.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.11 VPN support -->

        <section title="VPN Support">
          <t>Today, BGP is also used for VPNs, for example, as described in
          RFC 4364 <xref target="RFC4364"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Internet routing and VPN routing have different purposes and most
          often exchange different information between different devices. Most
          Internet routers do not need to know VPN-specific information. The
          concepts should be clearly separated.</t>

          <t>But when it comes to the mechanisms, VPN routing can share the
          same protocol as ordinary Internet routing; it can use a separate
          instance of the same protocol or it can use a different protocol.
          All variants are possible and have their own merits. These
          requirements are silent on this issue.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.12  End to end reliability -->

        <section title="End-to-End Reliability">
          <t>The existing Internet architecture neither requires nor provides
          end-to-end reliability of control information dissemination. There
          is, however, already a requirement for end-to-end reliability of
          control information distribution, i.e., the ends of the VPN
          established need to have an acknowledgment of the success in setting
          up the VPN. While it is not necessarily the function of a routing
          architecture to provide end-to-end reliability for this kind of
          purpose, we must be clear that end-to-end reliability becomes a
          requirement if the network has to support such reliable control
          signaling. There may be other requirements that derive from
          requiring the FDR to support reliable control signaling.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- 10.13  End to end transparency -->

        <section title="End-to-End Transparency">
          <t>The introduction of private addressing schemes, Network Address
          Translators, and firewalls has significantly reduced the end-to-end
          transparency of the network. In many cases, the network is also no
          longer symmetric, so that communication between two addresses is
          possible if the communication session originates from one end but
          not from the other. This impedes the deployment of new peer-to-peer
          services and some "push" services where the server in a client-
          server arrangement originates the communication session. Whether a
          new routing system either can or should seek to restore this
          transparency is an open issue.</t>

          <t>A related issue is the extent to which end-user applications
          should seek to control the routing of communications to the rest of
          the network.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Group B -->

    <!--     6  Security Considerations -a -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>We address security issues in the individual requirements. We do
      require that the architecture and protocols developed against this set
      of requirements be "secure". Discussion of specific security issues can
      be found in the following sections: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Group A: Routing System Security - <xref
          target="A-security-1"></xref></t>

          <t>Group A: End Host Security - <xref
          target="A-security-2"></xref></t>

          <t>Group A: Routing Information Policies - <xref
          target="A-security-3"></xref></t>

          <t>Group A: Abstraction - <xref target="A-security-4"></xref></t>

          <t>Group A: Robustness - <xref target="A-security-5"></xref></t>

          <t>Group B: Protection against Denial-of-Service and Other Security
          Attacks - <xref target="B-security-1"></xref></t>

          <t>Group B: Commercial Service Providers - <xref
          target="B-security-2"></xref></t>

          <t>Group B: The Federated Environment - <xref
          target="B-security-3"></xref></t>

          <t>Group B: Path Advertisement - <xref
          target="B-security-4"></xref></t>

          <t>Group B: Security Requirements - <xref
          target="B-security-5"></xref></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!--     7  IANA Considerations - a -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document is a set of requirements from which a new routing and
      addressing architecture may be developed. From that architecture, a new
      protocol, or set of protocols, may be developed.</t>

      <t>While this note poses no new tasks for IANA, the architecture and
      protocols developed from this document probably will have issues to be
      dealt with by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!--     9  Acknowledgments - a-->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>This document is the combined effort of two groups in the IRTF.
      Group A, which was formed by the IRTF Routing Research chairs, and Group B,
      which was self-formed and later was folded into the IRTF Routing
      Research Group. Each group has it own set of acknowledgments. <vspace
      blankLines="1" /> <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Group A Acknowledgments"><vspace blankLines="1" />
          This originated in the IRTF Routing Research Group's sub-group on
          Inter-domain routing requirements. The members of the group
          were:</t>
        </list></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
        Abha Ahuja                      Danny McPherson 
        J. Noel Chiappa                 David Meyer 
        Sean Doran                      Mike O'Dell 
        JJ Garcia-Luna-Aceves           Andrew Partan 
        Susan Hares                     Radia Perlman 
        Geoff Huston                    Yakov Rehkter 
        Frank Kastenholz                John Scudder 
        Dave Katz                       Curtis Villamizar 
        Tony Li                         Dave Ward 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>We also appreciate the comments and review received from Ran
          Atkinson, Howard Berkowitz, Randy Bush, Avri Doria, Jeffery Haas,
          Dmitri Krioukov, Russ White, and Alex Zinin. Special thanks to Yakov
          Rehkter for contributing text and to Noel Chiappa. <vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Group B Acknowledgments"><vspace blankLines="1" /> The
          document is derived from work originally produced by Babylon. Babylon
          was a loose association of individuals from academia, service
          providers, and vendors whose goal was to discuss issues in Internet
          routing with the intention of finding solutions for those problems.
          <vspace blankLines="1" /> The individual members who contributed
          materially to this document are: Anders Bergsten, Howard Berkowitz,
          Malin Carlzon, Lenka Carr Motyckova, Elwyn Davies, Avri Doria,
          Pierre Fransson, Yong Jiang, Dmitri Krioukov, Tove Madsen, Olle
          Pers, and Olov Schelen. <vspace blankLines="1" /> Thanks also go to
          the members of Babylon and others who did substantial reviews of
          this material. Specifically, we would like to acknowledge the helpful
          comments and suggestions of the following individuals: Loa
          Andersson, Tomas Ahlstrom, Erik Aman, Thomas Eriksson, Niklas Borg,
          Nigel Bragg, Thomas Chmara, Krister Edlund, Owe Grafford, Torbjorn
          Lundberg, Jeremy Mineweaser, Jasminko Mulahusic, Florian-Daniel
          Otel, Bernhard Stockman, Tom Worster, and Roberto Zamparo. <vspace
          blankLines="1" /> In addition, the authors are indebted to the folks
          who wrote all the references we have consulted in putting this paper
          together. This includes not only the references explicitly listed
          below, but also those who contributed to the mailing lists we have
          been participating in for years. <vspace blankLines="1" />The editors thank Lixia Zhang, as IRSG document shepherd, 
for her help and her perseverance, 
without which this document would never have been published.
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Finally,
         it is the editors who are responsible for any lack of clarity, any
         errors, glaring omissions or misunderstandings.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--
<references title='Normative References'>
<note title = 'Note:'>
<t>
As this is an Informational document, there aren't any Normative References.
</t>
</note>
</references>
-->

<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1126;

      &RFC1992;

      &RFC2071;

      &RFC2072;

      &RFC4364;

      &RFC3031;

      &RFC3221;

      &RFC3345;

      &RFC3471;

      &RFC3963;

      <reference anchor="RFC5773">
        <front>
          <title>Analysis of Inter-Domain Routing Requirements and History</title>

          <author fullname="E. Davies" initials="E." surname="Davies">
             <organization> </organization> 
           </author>
          <author fullname="A. Doria" initials="A." surname="Doria">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="5773" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chiappa02"
                 target="http://ana-3.lcs.mit.edu/~jnc/nimrod/overview.txt">
        <front>
          <title>A New IP Routing and Addressing Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="N.  Chiappa" initials="N." surname="Chiappa">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="1991" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Wroclawski95">
        <front>
          <title>The Metanet White Paper - Workshop on Research Directions for
          the Next Generation Internet</title>

          <author fullname="J.  Wroclowski" initials="J." surname="Wroclowski">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1995" />
        </front>

        <!-- seriesInfo name="" value="" / -->
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Griffin99">
        <front>
          <title>An Analysis of BGP Convergence Properties</title>

          <author fullname="T. G.  Griffin" initials="T. G." surname="Griffin">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G.  Wilfong" initials="G." surname="Wilfong">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>
      
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM" value="1999" />
      </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-diffserv-pdb-vw -->
      <reference anchor="DiffservVW">
        <front>
          <title>The 'Virtual Wire' Per-Domain Behavior</title>

          <author fullname="V.  Jacobson" initials="V." surname="Jacobson">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K Nichols" initials="K." surname="Nichols">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K.  Poduri" initials="K." surname="Poduri">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2000" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in"
                    value="Progress" />
      </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-diffserv-pdb-ar -->
      <reference anchor="DiffservAR">
        <front>
          <title>An Assured Rate Per-Domain Behaviour for Differentiated
          Services</title>

          <author fullname="N.  Seddigh" initials="N." surname="Seddigh">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B.  Nandy" initials="B." surname="Nandy">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J.  Heinanen" initials="J." surname="Heinanen">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2001" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in"
                    value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="rap-charter02"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/OLD/rap-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Resource Allocation Protocol working group</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="snmpconf-charter02"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/OLD/snmpconf-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Configuration management with SNMP working group</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="policy-charter02"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/OLD/policy-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Policy working group</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="netconf-charter"
                 target="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/netconf-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Network Configuration working group</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Internet Engineering Task Force</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2005" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CIDR" target="http://www.cidr-report.org/">
        <front>
          <title>CIDR Report</title>

          <author fullname="G. Huston">
            <organization>Telcordia Technologies</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

      </reference>


<!-- draft-many-inference-srlg -->
      <reference anchor="InferenceSRLG">
        <front>
          <title>Inference of Shared Risk Link Groups</title>

          <author fullname="Dimitri Papadimitriou" initials="D."
                  surname="Papadimitriou">
            <organization>Alcatel</organization>
          </author>
         
   <author fullname="F. Poppe" initials="F." surname="Poppe" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="J. Jones" initials="J." surname="J. Jones" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="S. Venkatachalam" initials="S." surname="S. Venkatachalam" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="S. Dharanikota" initials="S." surname="S. Dharanikota" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="R. Jain" initials="R." surname="Jain" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="R. Hartani" initials="R." surname="Hartani" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>
   <author fullname="D. Griffith" initials="D." surname="Griffith" >
            <organization> </organization>
           </author>

          <date month="November" year="2001" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Blumenthal01"
                 target="http://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/1519">
        <front>
          <title>Rethinking the design of the Internet: The end to end
          arguments vs. the brave new world</title>

          <author fullname="Marjory S Blumenthal" initials="M. S."
                  surname="Blumenthal">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="David D.  Clark" initials="D. D." surname="Clark">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2001" />
        </front>

      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISO10747">
        <front>
          <title>Protocol for Exchange of Inter-Domain Routeing Information
          among Intermediate Systems to Support Forwarding of ISO 8473
          PDUs</title>

          <author fullname=" ISO/IEC" initials="" surname="ISO/IEC">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1993" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="International Standard 10747"
                    value="ISO/IEC JTC 1, Switzerland" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3260">
        <front>
          <title>New Terminology and Clarifications for Diffserv</title>

          <author fullname="Dan Grossman" initials="D." surname="Grossman">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3260" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Broido02">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Expansion, Refinement and Churn</title>

          <author fullname="A.  Broido" initials="A." surname="Broido">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E.  Nemeth" initials="E." surname="Nemeth">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K Claffy" initials="K." surname="Claffy">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="CAIDA elves" initials="C." surname="Elves">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC1726">
        <front>
          <title>Technical Criteria for Choosing IP The Next Generation
          (IPng)</title>

          <author fullname="C. Partridge" initials="C." surname="Partridge">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Frank Kastenholz" initials="F."
                  surname="Kastenholz">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Dec" year="1994" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1726" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3344">
        <front>
          <title>IP Mobility Support.</title>

          <author fullname="Charles Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
            <organization>aaa</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3344" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ODell01">
        <front>
          <title>Private Communication</title>

          <author fullname="Mike O'Dell" initials="M." surname="O'Dell">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2001" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Clark91">
        <front>
          <title>Quote reportedly from IETF Plenary discussion</title>

          <author fullname="Dave Clark" initials="D." surname="Clark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1991" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  </back>
</rfc>
