<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle='yes'?>

<rfc number="5744"
  category="info" ipr="trust200902" updates="4846">

<?rfc toc='yes'?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Rights for Independent Submissions">Procedures for
    Rights Handling in the RFC Independent Submission Stream
	</title>

    <author fullname="Robert Braden" initials="R." surname="Braden">
      <organization abbrev="ISI">USC Information Sciences Institute</organization>
	<address>
	   <postal>
		<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
	      <city>Marina del Rey</city>
	  	<region>CA</region>
		<code>90292</code>
		<country>US</country>
	   </postal>
		<email>braden@isi.edu</email>
	</address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Joel M. Halpern" initials="J.M." surname="Halpern">
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P. O. Box 6049</street>
          <city>Leesburg</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20178</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jhalpern@redback.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2009" />

    <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the procedures by which authors of
RFC Independent Submission documents grant the community "incoming" rights
	for copying and using the text. It also specifies the
	"outgoing" rights the community grants to readers and users of
	those documents, and it requests that the IETF Trust manage
	the outgoing rights to effect this result.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>As the IETF has grown, the process and the community have gotten
more careful about defining the rights relating to copying documents that are 
granted by authors to the community, and the corresponding
	rights that are granted by the community to readers and users
	of these documents.</t>

      <t>This document defines the copyright procedures for RFC
      Independent Submission documents. It parallels the procedures for
      IETF-produced documents defined
      in <xref target="RFC5377"></xref>
      and <xref target="RFC5378"></xref>.

</t><t>
In summary, submissions in the Independent Submission stream use the same
submission procedures and mechanisms that are defined in
RFC 5378, and hence require the same "incoming rights" as IETF-stream documents.
This document provides advice to the Trustees of the IETF Trust on
"outgoing" rights to be granted to readers and users of Independent
Submission documents, and it explicitly requests the IETF Trust to
manage the rights in accordance with this advice.</t>

      <t>This document also specifies the policies 
regarding the disclosure of Patents and Trademarks that may be
relevant to a submission intended for the Independent Submission stream.
</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Background">
    <t>The concept of RFC streams in general, and the Independent
    Submission stream in particular, are
 described in <xref target="RFC4844">Section 5 of</xref> and
in <xref target="RFC4846">RFC 4846</xref>.  In general terms,
the Independent Submission stream continues the long-established tradition in the
    Internet community of allowing and encouraging the RFC Editor to
    publish documents that are relevant to the community but are not
    products of, and do not conflict with, the IETF process.  These
    may be comments on IETF documents or they may be other work
    relevant to the Internet that, historically, the RFC Editor has
    chosen to publish.

</t><t>
With the publication of <xref target="RFC5620"></xref>, the
IETF began a process shift in which the responsibility for Independent
Submission stream publication will move to an individual designated by the IAB as
the Independent Submission Editor (ISE). 
</t>
<t>
Section 8 of RFC 4846 presented the copyright rules for the
Independent Submission stream. The present document
is intended to be fully consistent with that section and to update it by clarifying the
formal procedures that the IETF Trust will use to effect those rules.
</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Goals">
<t>The goal of the RFC Independent Submission stream is to publish information that is
intended to advance the state of the art and the interoperability of solutions for use in
conjunction with the Internet.  As specified in Section 8 of RFC 4846, the community
has determined that this objective will best be met with a liberal copyright
policy on Independent Submission documents.  Therefore, the
  Independent Submission policy is to allow any
individual reading such documents to use the content thereof 
in any manner.  The only restriction is that proper credit ("attribution") must be given.
Lawyers describe this liberal policy by saying that this stream 
normally permits "unlimited derivative works".  (It should be noted that this liberal policy was
always followed by the original RFC Editor, Jon Postel; in a sense,
  the present document is a formalization of a 30-year-old policy on RFC copyrights.)
</t>
<t>However, for a small subset of documents published as Independent Submissions,
it is not reasonable to permit unlimited derivative
works.  Examples are proprietary protocols and output from other standards bodies.
In such cases, authors are permitted to request that the published
  Independent Submission documents permit no
derivative works.
</t>
<t>
   Note also that this unlimited derivative works policy applies to all
   parts of an Independent Submission document, including any code.
   Therefore, no separate licensing procedure is
   required for extracting and adapting code that is contained in
   an Independent Submission document submitted under the (preferred) unlimited
   derivative works terms.  On the other hand, code may not be extracted and
   adapted from Independent Submission documents submitted under the
   no derivative works terms. 
</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Rules for Submission and Use of Material">
<t>Independent Submission authors will submit their material as Internet-Drafts.  These drafts will be submitted
to, and stored in, the IETF Internet-Drafts repository in the same fashion as IETF Internet-Drafts.
</t>
<t>During Internet-Draft submission, authors who intend to submit their document
for publication in the Independent Submission stream will grant rights
  as described in
<xref target="RFC5378"></xref>.  To request that the contribution be
published as an RFC that permits no derivative works, an author may
use the form specified for use with RFC 5378.
</t>
<t>The IETF Trust will indicate that, in cooperation with the
  Independent Submission Editor, the Trust
grants to readers and users of material from Independent Submission
  documents the right to make unlimited derivative works, unless the document specifies that no derivative works are permitted.  This will permit anyone to copy,
  extract, modify, or otherwise use material from Independent Submission
  documents as long as suitable attribution is given.
</t>
<t>Contributors of Internet-Drafts intended for the Independent
  Submission stream will include suitable boilerplate defined by the
  IETF Trust.  This boilerplate shall indicate compliance with RFC
  5378 and shall explicitly indicate either that no derivative works
  can be based on the contribution or, as is preferred, that unlimited
  derivative works may be crafted from the contribution.
</t>
<t>It should be understood that the final publication decision for the
  Independent Submission stream rests with the Independent Submission Editor
  (ISE).  Compliance with these terms is not a guarantee of
  publication. In particular, the ISE may question the appropriateness
  of a "no derivative works" restriction requested by an author. The
  appropriateness of such usage must be negotiated among the authors and the ISE.
</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Procedures Requested of the IETF Trust">
<t>The Independent Submission Editor requests that the IETF Trust and
  its Trustees assist in meeting the goals and procedures set forth in
  this document.
</t>
<t>The Trustees are requested to publicly confirm their willingness
  and ability to accept responsibility for the Intellectual Property
  Rights for the Independent Submission stream.  They are also
  requested to indicate their willingness and intent to work according
  to the procedures and goals defined by the ISE.
</t>
<t>Specifically, the Trustees are asked to develop the necessary
  boilerplate to enable the suitable marking of documents so that the
  IETF Trust receives the rights as specified in RFC 5378.  These
  procedures need to also allow documents to grant either no rights to
  make derivative works or, preferentially, the right to make
  unlimited derivative works from the documents.  It is left to the
  Trust to specify exactly how this shall be clearly indicated in each document.
</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Patent and Trademark Rules for the Independent Submission Stream">
<t>As specified above, contributors of documents for the Independent Submission stream
are expected to use the IETF Internet-Draft process, complying therein
  with the rules specified in the latest version of BCP 9, whose
  version at the time of writing was <xref target="RFC2026"></xref>.
This includes the disclosure of Patent and Trademark issues that are known, or can be
reasonably expected to be known, by the contributor.
</t>
<t>Disclosure of license terms for patents is also requested, as
  specified in the most recent version of BCP 79. The version of BCP
  79 at the time of this writing was <xref target="RFC3979"></xref>,
  updated by <xref target="RFC4879"></xref>.
The Independent Submission stream has chosen to use the IETF's
IPR disclosure mechanism, www.ietf.org/ipr/, for this purpose.

The Independent Submission Editor would prefer the most liberal terms
  possible be made available for specifications published as
  Independent Submission documents.
Terms that do not require fees or licensing are preferable.  
Non-discriminatory terms are strongly preferred over those that discriminate among users.
However, although disclosure is required, there are no specific requirements on the
licensing terms for intellectual property related to Independent Submission publication.
</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>The integrity and quality of the Independent Submission stream are the
responsibility of the Independent Submission Editor.  This document does 
not change those responsibilities.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2026" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4844" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4846" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5378" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3979" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4879" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5620" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5377" ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
