<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- may be omitted for very short documents -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<!-- these two save paper: start new sections from the same page etc. -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?> <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<!-- other categories: bcp, exp, historic, std -->
<rfc number="5294" category="info" >

<front>
<title abbrev="Host Threats to PIM">Host Threats to Protocol Independent Multicast (PIM)</title>

<author fullname="Pekka Savola" initials="P." surname="Savola">
	<organization abbrev="CSC/FUNET">CSC - Scientific Computing Ltd.</organization>
	<address>
	<postal>
		<street/>
		<city>Espoo</city>
		<country>Finland</country>
	</postal>
	<email> psavola@funet.fi </email>
	</address>
</author>
 <author fullname="James Lingard" initials="J.C.H." surname="Lingard">
        <organization abbrev="Arastra">Arastra, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
        <postal>
                <street>P.O. Box 10905</street>
                <city>Palo Alto</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>94303</code>
                <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email> jchl@arastra.com </email>
        </address>
</author>
<date month="August" year="2008"/>

<!-- not used for anything ? -->

<!--[rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->
<area>Routing</area>

<!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF fine for individual submissions -->
<workgroup>PIM WG</workgroup>

<abstract>
	<t>This memo complements the list of multicast infrastructure security threat analysis
documents by describing Protocol Independent Multicast (PIM) threats specific to router interfaces
connecting hosts.</t>
</abstract>
</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
	<t>There has been some analysis of the security threats to the
multicast routing infrastructures <xref
target="RFC4609"/>, some work on implementing confidentiality,
integrity, and authorization in the multicast payload <xref
target="RFC3740"/>, and also some analysis of security threats in Internet Group Management Protocol/Multicast Listener Discovery (IGMP/MLD)
<xref target="DALEY-MAGMA"/>, but no comprehensive analysis of
security threats to PIM at the host-connecting (typically "Local Area
Network") links.</t>
	<t>We define these PIM host threats to include:</t>
	<list style="symbols">
		<t>Nodes using PIM to attack or deny service to hosts on the same link,</t>
		<t>Nodes using PIM to attack or deny service to valid multicast routers on the link, or</t>
		<t>Nodes using PIM (Register messages) to bypass the controls of multicast routers on the link.</t>
	</list>
	<t>The attacking node is typically a host or a host acting as an
illegitimate router.</t>
	<t>A node originating multicast data can disturb existing
receivers of the group on the same link, but this issue is not PIM-specific
so it is out of scope.  Subverting legitimate routers is out of scope.
Security implications on multicast routing infrastructure are described in <xref target="RFC4609"/>.</t>
	<t>This document analyzes the PIM host-interface vulnerabilities,
formulates a few specific threats, proposes some potential ways
to mitigate these problems, and analyzes how well those methods accomplish
fixing the issues.</t>
	<t>It is assumed that the reader is familiar with the basic concepts
of PIM.</t>
	<t>Analysis of PIM-DM <xref target="RFC3973"/> is out of scope of this document.</t>
</section>

<section title="Host-Interface PIM Vulnerabilities">
	<t>This section briefly describes the main attacks against
host-interface PIM signaling, before we get to the actual threats and mitigation methods
in the next sections.</t>
	<t>The attacking node may be either a malicious host or an
illegitimate router.</t>
	<section title="Nodes May Send Illegitimate PIM Register Messages">
		<t>PIM Register messages are sent unicast, and contain encapsulated
multicast data packets.  Malicious hosts or routers could also send Register messages themselves, for example,
to get around rate-limits or to interfere with foreign Rendezvous Points (RPs),
as described in <xref target="RFC4609"/>.</t>
		<t>The Register message can be targeted to any IP address, whether
in or out of the local PIM domain. The source address may be
spoofed, unless spoofing has been prevented <xref target="RFC3704"/>, to
create arbitrary state at the RPs.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Nodes May Become Illegitimate PIM Neighbors">
		<t>When PIM has been enabled on a router's host interface,
any node can also become a PIM neighbor using PIM Hello messages. Having become
a PIM neighbor in this way, the node is able to send other PIM messages
to the router and may use those messages to attack the router.</t>
<!--		<t>The PIM-SM specification recommends that further PIM messages should
not be accepted except from valid PIM neighbors; if implementations are
compliant to this recommendation, becoming a PIM neighbor using Hello messages is
the first step to be able to send other PIM messages.</t> -->
	</section>
	<section title="Routers May Accept PIM Messages from Non-Neighbors">
		<t>The PIM-SM (Sparse Mode) specification recommends that PIM messages
other than Hellos should
not be accepted, except from valid PIM neighbors.  The
Bidirectional-PIM (BIDIR-PIM) specification specifies that packets
from non-neighbors "SHOULD NOT" be accepted; see Section 5.2 of <xref
target="RFC5015"/>.  However, the specification
does not mandate this, so some implementations may be susceptible to
attack from PIM messages sent by non-neighbors.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="An Illegitimate Node May Be Elected as the PIM DR or DF">
		<section title="PIM-SM Designated Router Election">
		<t>In PIM-SM, the Designated Router (DR) on a Local Area Network (LAN) is responsible for
Register-encapsulating data from new sources on the LAN, and for generating PIM Join/Prune messages
on behalf of group members on the LAN.</t>
		<t>A node that can become a PIM neighbor can also cause itself to be
   elected DR, whether or not the DR Priority option is being used in
   PIM Hello messages on the LAN.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="BIDIR-PIM Designated Forwarder Election">
	        <t>In BIDIR-PIM <xref target="RFC5015"/>, a Designated Forwarder (DF) is elected per
      link.  The DF is responsible for forwarding data downstream onto
         the link, and also for forwarding data from its link upstream.</t>
   <t>A node that can become a BIDIR-PIM neighbor (this is just like
   becoming a PIM neighbor, except that the PIM Hello messages must
   include the Bidirectional Capable PIM-Hello option) can cause
   itself to be elected DF by sending DF Offer messages with a better
   metric than its neighbors.</t>
   <t>There are also some other BIDIR-PIM attacks related to DF election,
   including spoofing DF Offer and DF Winner messages (e.g., using
      a legitimate router's IP address), making all but the impersonated
         router believe that router is the DF.  Also, an attacker might
            prevent the DF election from converging by sending an infinite
               sequence of DF Offer messages.</t>
    <t>For further discussion of BIDIR-PIM threats, we refer to the
   Security Considerations section in <xref target="RFC5015"/>.</t>
		</section>
   	</section>
	<section title="A Node May Become an Illegitimate PIM Asserted Forwarder">
		<t>With a PIM Assert message, a router can be elected to be in
charge of forwarding all traffic for a particular (S,G) or (*,G) onto the LAN.
This overrides DR behavior.</t>
		<t>The specification says that Assert messages should only be
accepted from known PIM neighbors, and "SHOULD" be discarded otherwise.
So, either the node must be able to spoof an IP address of a current
neighbor, form a PIM adjacency first, or count on these checks being
disabled.</t>
		<t>The Assert Timer, by default, is 3 minutes; the
state must be refreshed or it will be removed automatically.</t>
		<t>As noted before, it is also possible to spoof an Assert
(e.g., using a legitimate router's IP address) to cause a temporary disruption on the LAN.</t>
<!--
However, it is not 100% clear what happens when the router which was spoofed
receives "its own assert" and CouldAssert(S,G,I) is False?  [XXX: a PIM
expert should say something?  Is this an issue in the state machine?] -->
	</section>
	<section title="BIDIR-PIM Does Not Use RPF Check">
		<t> PIM protocols do not perform Reverse Path Forwarding (RPF) check on the shared
	tree (e.g., in
	PIM-SM from the RP to local receivers).  On the other hand, RPF
	check is performed, e.g., on stub host interfaces. Because all
	forwarding in BIDIR-PIM is based on the shared tree principle,
	it
	does not use RPF check to verify that the forwarded packets are
	being received from a "topologically correct" direction.  This
has two immediately obvious implications:</t>
		<list style="numbers">
			<t>A node may maintain a forwarding loop until the
Time to Live (TTL) runs out by passing
packets from interface A to B.  This is not believed to cause significant
new risk as with a similar ease such a node could generate original packets
that would loop back to its other interface.</t>
			<t>A node may spoof source IP addresses in
multicast packets it sends.  Other PIM protocols drop such packets when
performing the RPF check.  BIDIR-PIM accepts such packets, allowing easier
Denial-of-Service (DoS) attacks on the multicast delivery tree and making the attacker less
traceable.</t>
		</list>		
	</section>
</section>

<section title="On-Link Threats">
	<t>The previous section described some PIM vulnerabilities; this section
gives an overview of the more concrete threats exploiting those
vulnerabilities.</t>
	<section title="Denial-of-Service Attack on the Link">
		<t>The easiest attack is to deny the multicast service on
the link.  This could mean either not forwarding all (or parts of) multicast
traffic from upstream onto the link, or not registering or forwarding upstream the multicast
transmissions originated on the link.</t>
		<t>These attacks can be done in multiple ways: the most typical
one would be becoming the DR through becoming a neighbor with Hello messages
and winning the DR election. After that, one could, for example:</t>
		<list style="symbols">
			<t>Not send any PIM
Join/Prune messages based on the IGMP reports, or</t>
			<t>Not forward or register any
sourced packets.</t>
		</list>
		<t>Sending PIM Prune messages may also be an effective
		attack vector even if the attacking node is not elected DR,
		since
		PIM Prune messages are accepted from downstream
interfaces even if the router is not a DR.</t>
		<t>An alternative mechanism is to send a PIM
Assert message, spoofed to come from a valid PIM neighbor or non-spoofed if
a PIM adjacency has already been formed.  For the particular (S,G) or (*,G)
from the Assert message, this creates the same result as
getting elected as a DR.
With BIDIR-PIM, similar attacks can be done by becoming the DF or
by preventing the DF election from converging.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Denial-of-Service Attack on the Outside">
	<t>It is also possible to perform Denial-of-Service attacks on
nodes beyond the link, especially in environments where a
multicast router and/or a DR is considered to be a trusted node.</t>
	<t>In particular, if DRs perform some form of rate-limiting, for
example, on new Join/Prune messages, becoming a DR and sending those messages
yourself allows one to subvert these restrictions; therefore, rate-limiting
functions need to be deployed at multiple layers, as described in <xref
target="RFC4609"/>.</t>
	<t>In addition,
any host can send PIM Register messages on their own, to
whichever RP it wants; further, if unicast RPF (Reverse Path Forwarding) mechanisms <xref
target="RFC3704"/> have not been applied, the packet may be spoofed.
This can be done to get around rate-limits, and/or to attack remote RPs,
and/or to interfere with the integrity of an ASM group.  This attack is also
described in <xref target="RFC4609"/>.</t>
	<t>Also, BIDIR-PIM does not prevent nodes from using topologically
incorrect addresses (source address spoofing) making such an attack more difficult to trace.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Confidentiality, Integrity, or Authorization Violations">
		<t>Contrary to unicast, any node is able to legitimately
receive all multicast transmission on the link by just adjusting the
appropriate link-layer multicast filters.  Confidentiality (if needed) must be obtained
by cryptography.</t>
		<t>If a node can become a DR, it is able to violate the integrity of
   any data streams sent by sources on the LAN, by modifying (possibly in
   subtle, unnoticeable ways) the packets sent by the sources before
   Register-encapsulating them.</t>
   		<t>If a node can form a PIM neighbor adjacency or spoof the IP address of
   a current neighbor, then if it has external connectivity by some other
   means other than the LAN, the node is able to violate the integrity of
   any data streams sent by external sources onto the LAN.  It would do
   this by sending an appropriate Assert message onto the LAN to prevent
   the genuine PIM routers forwarding the valid data, obtaining the
   multicast traffic via its other connection, and modifying those data
   packets before forwarding them onto the LAN.</t>
   		<t>In either of the above two cases, the node could operate as normal for
   some traffic, while violating integrity for some other traffic.</t>
		<t>A more elaborate attack is on authorization.  There are
some very questionable models <xref target="HAYASHI"/> where the current multicast
architecture is used to provide paid multicast service, and where the
authorization/authentication is added to the group management protocols such
as IGMP.  Needless to say, if a host would be able to act as a router, it
might be possible to perform all kinds of attacks: subscribe to multicast
service without using IGMP (i.e., without having to pay for it), deny
the service for the others on the same link, etc.  In short, to be able to
ensure authorization, a better architecture should be used instead (e.g.,
<xref target="RFC3740"/>).</t>
	</section>
</section>

<section title="Mitigation Methods">
	<t>This section lists some ways to mitigate the vulnerabilities and
threats listed in previous sections.</t>
	<section title="Passive Mode for PIM">
		<t>The current PIM specification seems to mandate running
the PIM Hello protocol on all PIM-enabled interfaces.  Most implementations
require PIM to be enabled on an interface in order to send PIM Register messages for
data sent by sources on that interface or to do any other PIM processing.</t>
		<t>As described in <xref
target="RFC4609"/>,
running full PIM, with Hello messages and all, is unnecessary
for those stub networks for which only one router is providing multicast
service.  Therefore, such
  implementations should provide an option to specify that the
  interface is "passive" with regard to PIM: no PIM packets are sent
  or processed (if received), but hosts can still send and receive
  multicast on that interface.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Use of IPsec among PIM Routers">
		<t>Instead of passive mode, or when multiple PIM routers
exist on a single link, one could also use IPsec to secure the PIM
messaging, to prevent anyone from subverting it.  The actual procedures have
been described in <xref target="RFC4601"/> and <xref
target="LINKLOCAL"/>.</t>
		<t>However, it is worth noting that setting up IPsec Security Associations (SAs)
manually can be a very tedious process, and the routers might not even
support IPsec; further automatic key negotiation may not be feasible in
these scenarios either.  A Group Domain of Interpretation (GDOI) <xref
target="RFC3547"/> server
might be able to mitigate this negotiation.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="IP Filtering PIM Messages">
		<t>To eliminate both the unicast and multicast PIM messages,
in similar scenarios to those for which PIM passive mode is applicable, it might be possible to
block IP protocol 103 (all PIM messages) in an input access list.
This is more effective than PIM passive mode, as this also blocks
Register messages.</t>
		<t>This is also acceptable when there is more than one
PIM router on the
   link if IPsec is used (because the access-list processing sees the
      valid PIM messages as IPsec AH/ESP packets).  In this case,
         unicast Register messages must also be protected with IPsec or
            the routing topology must be such that the link is never used to
               originate, or transit unicast Register messages.</t>
		<t>When multiple routers exist on a link, IPsec is not
required if it is possible to prevent hosts from sending PIM messages at
the Ethernet switch (or equivalent) host ports.  This could be accomplished in
at least two ways:</t>
		<list style="numbers">
			<t>Use IP access lists on the stub routers to allow PIM messages from
the valid neighbor IP addresses only, and implement IP spoofing prevention
at the Ethernet-switch-port level using proprietary mechanisms, or</t>
			<t>Filter out all PIM messages at configured host
ports on Ethernet switches instead of doing it on the routers.</t>
		</list>
		<t>The main benefit of this approach is that
multiple stub routers can still communicate through the LAN without IPsec
but hosts are not able to disturb the PIM protocol.  The drawback is that
Ethernet switches need to implement much finer-grained IP layer filtering,
and the operational requirements of carefully maintaining these filters
could be significant.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Summary of Vulnerabilities and Mitigation Methods">
	<t>This section summarizes the vulnerabilities, and how well the
mitigation methods are able to cope with them.</t>
        <?rfc needLines="14" ?>
        <figure anchor="vulnsum">
          <preamble>Summary of vulnerabilities and mitigations:</preamble>
          <artwork>
  +-----+---------------------+-----------------+-----------------+
  | Sec | Vulnerability       | One stub router | >1 stub routers |
  |     |                     | PASV|IPsec|Filt | PASV|IPsec|Filt |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.1 | Hosts Registering   |  N  | N+  |  Y  |  N  | N+  | Ysw |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.2 | Invalid Neighbor    |  Y  |  Y  |  Y  |  *  |  Y  | Ysw |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.3 | Adjacency Not Reqd  |  Y  |  Y  |  Y  |  *  |  Y  | Ysw |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.4 | Invalid DR /DF      |  Y  |  Y  |  Y  |  *  |  Y  | Ysw |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.5 | Invalid Forwarder   |  Y  |  Y  |  Y  |  *  |  Y  | Ysw |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
  | 2.6 | No RPF Check (BIDIR)|  x  |  x  |  x  |  x  |  x  |  x  |
  +-----+---------------------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
          </artwork>
        </figure>
	<t>"*" means Yes if IPsec is used in addition; No otherwise.</t>
	<t>"Ysw" means Yes if IPsec is used in addition or IP filtering is
done on Ethernet switches on all host ports; No otherwise.</t>
	<t>"N+" means that the use of IPsec between the on-link routers does
not protect from this; IPsec would have to be used at RPs.</t>
	<t>"x" means that, with BIDIR-PIM, IP access lists or RPF mechanisms
need to be applied in stub interfaces to prevent originating packets with topologically incorrect source addresses.
This needs to be done in addition to any other
chosen approach.</t>
	<t>To summarize, IP protocol filtering for all PIM messages appears
to be the most complete solution when coupled with the use of IPsec between
the real stub routers when there are more than one of them.  However, IPsec
is not required if PIM message filtering or a certain kind of IP spoofing
prevention is applied on all the host ports on Ethernet switches. If hosts
performing registering is not considered a serious problem, IP protocol
filtering and passive-mode PIM seem to be equivalent approaches. 
Additionally, if BIDIR-PIM is used, ingress filtering will need to be applied
in stub interfaces to multicast packets, as well as unicast, to prevent hosts using wrong source
addresses.</t>
	</section>
</section>
<section title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>Greg Daley and Gopi Durup wrote an excellent analysis of MLD
security issues <xref target="DALEY-MAGMA"/>, which gave inspiration in exploring the on-link PIM threats
problem space.</t>
	<t>Ayan Roy-Chowdhury, Beau Williamson, Bharat Joshi, Dino
Farinacci, John Zwiebel, Stig Venaas, Yiqun Cai, and Eric Gray provided good feedback for this
memo.</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
	<t>This memo analyzes the threats to the PIM multicast routing protocol
on host interfaces and proposes some possible mitigation techniques.</t>
</section>
</middle>
<back>

<!-- references split to informative and normative -->
<references title="Normative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4601" ?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4609" ?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5015" ?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3973" ?>
<!--	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.daley-magma-smld-prob" ?> -->

<reference anchor='DALEY-MAGMA'>
<front>
<title>Securing Neighbour Discovery Proxy Problem Statement</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Daley' fullname='Greg Daley'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Combes' fullname='Jean-Michel Combes'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='25' year='2008' />

<abstract><t>Neighbour Discovery Proxy is used to provide an address presence on a link from nodes which are no themselves present.  It allows a node to receive packets directed at its address by allowing another device to neighbour advertise on its behalf.  Neighbour Discovery Proxy is used in Mobile IPv6 and related protocols to provide reachability from nodes on the home network when a Mobile Node is not at home, by allowing the Home Agent to act as proxy.  It is also used as a mechanism to allow a global prefix to span multiple links, where proxies act as relays for neighbour discovery messages.  Neighbour Discovery Proxy currently cannot be secured using SEND. Today, SEND assumes that a node advertising an address is the address owner and in possession of appropriate public and private keys for that node.  This document describes how existing practice for proxy Neighbour Discovery relates to Secured Neighbour Discovery.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-daley-send-spnd-prob-02.txt' />
</reference>


<!--	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal" ?> -->

<reference anchor='LINKLOCAL'>
<front>
<title>Authentication and Confidentiality in PIM-SM Link-local Messages</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Atwood' fullname='John  Atwood'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Islam' fullname='Salekul Islam'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Siami' fullname='Maziar Siami'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='25' year='2008' />

<abstract><t>RFC 4601 mandates the use of IPsec to ensure authentication of the link-local messages in the Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) routing protocol.  This document specifies mechanisms to authenticate the PIM-SM link local messages using the IP security (IPsec) Authentication Header (AH) or Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP).  It specifies optional mechanisms to provide confidentiality using the ESP.  Manual keying is specified as the mandatory and default group key management solution.  To deal with issues of scalability and security that exist with manual keying, an optional automated group key management mechanism is specified.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-pim-sm-linklocal-03.txt' />
</reference>

<!--	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.hayashi-igap" ?> -->

<reference anchor='HAYASHI'>
<front>
<title>Internet Group membership Authentication Protocol (IGAP)</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Hayashi' fullname='Tsunemasa  Hayashi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='August' day='18' year='2003' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hayashi-igap-03.txt' />
</reference>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3740" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3704" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3547" ?>
</references>
</back>
</rfc>
