<?xml version='1.0' encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
<!ENTITY eap-keying PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-eap-keying.xml'>
<!ENTITY pana-mobopts PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pana-mobopts.xml'>
<!ENTITY pana-cxtp PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pana-cxtp.xml'>
<!ENTITY pana-pana PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pana-pana.xml'>
<!ENTITY pana-framework PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pana-framework.xml'>
<!ENTITY hokey-key-mgm PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-hokey-key-mgm.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2828 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2828.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2865 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3748 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4067 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4067.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4306 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4306.xml'> 
<!ENTITY rfc4962 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4962.xml'> 
<!ENTITY rfc5191 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5191.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5193 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5193.xml'>
] >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc inline="no"?>

<rfc ipr='trust200811' category='std' number="5807">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PaC-EP Master Key">
      Definition of Master Key between PANA Client and Enforcement
      Point
    </title>

  <author initials="Y." surname="Ohba"
    fullname="Yoshihiro Ohba">
    <organization abbrev="Toshiba">
      Toshiba Corporate Research and Development Center
    </organization>
    <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>1 Komukai-Toshiba-cho</street>
	  <city>Saiwai-ku, Kawasaki</city>
	  <region>Kanagawa</region>
	  <code>212-8582</code>
	  <country>Japan</country>
	</postal>
	<phone>+81 44 549 2230</phone>
	<email>yoshihiro.ohba@toshiba.co.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="A." surname="Yegin"
    fullname="Alper Yegin">
    <organization abbrev="Samsung">
      Samsung
    </organization>
    <address>
	<postal>
	  <city>Istanbul</city>
	  <country>Turkey</country>
	</postal>
	<email>alper.yegin@yegin.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2010"/>
    <workgroup>PANA Working Group </workgroup>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that after you have approved the document,
post-xml2rfc changes will be made to update the header and
boilerplate as described in RFC 5741.
-->

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a master key used between a client of
        the Protocol for carrying Authentication for Network Access
        (PANA) and an enforcement point, for bootstrapping lower-layer
        ciphering.  The master key is derived from the Master Session
        Key of the Extensible Authentication Protocol as a result of
        successful PANA authentication.  The master key guarantees
        cryptographic independence among enforcement points
        bootstrapped from PANA authentication across different address
        families.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t>
        The Protocol for carrying Authentication for Network Access (PANA)
        <xref target='RFC5191'/> is designed to facilitate network
        access authentication and authorization of clients in access
        networks.  It carries Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) <xref target='RFC3748'/> between a
        PANA Client (PaC) and a PANA Authentication Agent (PAA) where
        the PAA functions as an authentication gateway to the
        Authentication Server (AS).  The PANA framework <xref
        target='RFC5193'/> defines an another entity referred to as an
        Enforcement Point (EP), which resides in the access network and
        allows access (data traffic) of authorized PaCs while
        preventing access of others depending on the PANA
        authentication and authorization result (<xref
        target='figure-pana-functional-model'/>).  The EP and PAA may
        be implemented on the same device or separate devices.
      </t>
      <figure anchor='figure-pana-functional-model' 
	title='PANA Functional Model'
	align='center'>
	<artwork>
                                           RADIUS,
                                           Diameter,
     +-----+       PANA        +-----+     LDAP, API, etc. +-----+
     | PaC |&lt;-----------------&gt;| PAA |&lt;-------------------&gt;| AS  |
     +-----+                   +-----+                     +-----+
        ^                         ^
        |                         |
        |         +-----+         |
IKE,    +--------&gt;| EP  |&lt;--------+ ANCP, API, etc.
4-way handshake,  +-----+          
etc.                 .
                     .
                     .
                     v
                Data traffic
	</artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        The EP uses non-cryptographic or cryptographic filters to
        selectively allow and discard data packets.  These filters may
        be applied at the link-layer or the IP-layer <xref
        target='PANA-IPSEC'/>.  When cryptographic access
        control is used, a secure association protocol <xref
        target='RFC3748'/> needs to run between the PaC and EP.  After
        completion of the secure association protocol, link- or
        network-layer per-packet security (for example, IPsec ESP) is enabled
        for integrity protection, data origin authentication, replay
        protection, and optionally confidentiality protection.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the PaC-EP Master Key (PEMK) that is used by
        a secure association protocol as the pre-shared secret between
        the PaC and EP to enable cryptographic filters in the access
        network.  The PEMK is defined to guarantee cryptographic
        independence among EPs bootstrapped from PANA authentication
        across different address families.  This document also
        describes a guideline for distributing PEMKs from the PAA to
        EP.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does not specify a mechanism for a PaC to know
        whether the lower layer requires a secure association protocol
        or the pre-shared secret for the secure association protocol
        needs to be bootstrapped from PANA authentication.  Such a
        mechanism may be defined by each lower-layer protocol.
      </t>
      <section title="Specification of Requirements">
        <t>
          In this document, several words are used to signify the
          requirements of the specification.  These words are often
          capitalized.  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
          "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted
          as described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor='section-terminology' title='Terminology'>
      <t>
         This document reuses the following terms defined in <xref
         target='RFC5191'/>: PaC (PANA Client), PAA (PANA
         Authentication Agent), EP (Enforcement Point), MSK (Master
         Session Key), PANA Session, and Session Identifier.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor='section-pac-ep-master-key'
      title='PaC-EP Master Key'>

      <t> A PEMK (PaC-EP Master Key) is derived from an available MSK.
      The PEMK is 64 octets in length and is calculated as follows:
      </t>

      <artwork>
PEMK = prf+(MSK, "IETF PEMK" | SID | KID | EPID)
       where | denotes concatenation.
      </artwork>

      <list style='symbols'>
        <t>The prf+ function is defined in IKEv2 <xref
        target='RFC4306'/>.  The pseudo-random function used for the
        prf+ function is specified in the PRF-Algorithm AVP carried in
        a PANA-Auth-Request message with 'S' (Start) bit set.</t>

        <t>"IETF PEMK" is the ASCII code representation of the
        non-NULL terminated string (excluding the double quotes around
        it).</t>

        <t>SID is a four-octet Session Identifier <xref
        target='RFC5191'/>.</t>

        <t> KID is the content of the Key-ID AVP <xref
        target='RFC5191'/> associated with the MSK.</t>

        <t> EPID is the identifier of the EP. The first two octets
        represents the AddressType, which contains an Address Family
        defined in <xref target='IANAADFAM'/>.  The remaining octets
        encode the address value.  The length of the address value is
        determined by the AddressType.  The AddressType is used to
        discriminate the content and format of the remaining octets
        for the address value.  The use of the combination of address
        family and address value guarantees the cryptographic
        independence of PEMKs among multiple EPs that are bootstrapped
        from PANA authentication across multiple address families.
        How a PaC discovers an EPID is out of the scope of this
        document.
        </t>
      </list>
      <section title='Key Name of PEMK'>
        <t>The key name of the PEMK is defined as follows.</t> 

        <t>PEMKname = SHA1(EPID | SID | KID), where SHA1 denotes the
        SHA-1 algorithm specified in <xref target='SHS'/>.  Inclusion
        of the EPID, SID, and KID provides uniqueness of PEMK names
        among multiple PaC-EP pairs under a given PAA.</t>

      </section>
      <section title='Scope of PEMK'>
        <t>One PEMK is used between one PaC and one EP.  A PEMK MUST
        NOT be shared among multiple PaCs or EPs.</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Context of PEMK'>
        <t>A PEMK is used as the pre-shared key of the secure
        association protocol in the scope of the PEMK.  A PEMK MUST
        NOT be used for any other usage.</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Lifetime of PEMK'>
        <t>The lifetime of a PEMK MUST be less than or equal to the
        lifetime of the MSK from which it is derived.  At the end of
        the lifetime, the PEMK and its associated states MUST be
        deleted.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
        The following considerations are specifically made to follow
        the Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) key management guidance <xref target='RFC4962'/>.
        Other AAA key management requirements such as key lifetime,
        key scope, key context, and key name are described in <xref
        target='section-pac-ep-master-key'/>.
      </t>
      <section title='Channel Binding'>
        <t>
          Since the device identifier of the EP is involved in the key
          derivation function, Channel Binding on a PEMK is made
          between the PaC and PAA at the time when the PEMK is
          generated.  If a malicious EP advertises a different device
          identifier than that registered with the PAA, the
          malicious attempt will not succeed since the secure
          association protocol will fail due to the difference in the
          PEMK values calculated by the PaC and the EP.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title='Guideline for Distributing PEMK from PAA to EP'>
        <t>
          When an EP is implemented on the same device as the PAA, no
          protocol needs to be used for distributing a PEMK from the
          PAA to the EP.  
        </t>
        <t>
          In the case where the EP is implemented on a separate device
          from the PAA, a protocol is needed to distribute a PEMK from
          the PAA to the EP.  Such a key distribution protocol may
          depend on the architecture and deployment using PANA.  A key
          distribution protocol for a PEMK MUST ensure that the PEMK
          is encrypted as well as integrity and replay protected, with
          a security association between the PAA and EP, where the
          security association MUST be cryptographically bound to the
          identities of the PAA and EP known to the PaC.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Acknowledgments'>
      <t>
        We would like to thank Jari Arkko, Basavaraj Patil, Pasi
        Eronen, Russ Mundy, Alexey Melnikov, and all members of the
        PANA working group for their valuable comments to this
        document.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      &rfc3748; &rfc4306; &rfc5191; 
      <reference anchor='SHS'>
	<front>
	  <title>Secure Hash Standard</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>
	      National Institute of Standards and Technology,
	      U.S. Department of Commerce
	    </organization>
	  </author>
          <date month='August' year='2002'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='NIST FIPS' value='PUB 180-2'/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='IANAADFAM'>
	<front>
	  <title>Address Family Numbers</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>
	      IANA
	    </organization>
	  </author>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name=''
	value='http://www.iana.org' />
      </reference>
     </references>
    <references title='Informative References'>
      &rfc2119; &rfc4962; &rfc5193;
   <reference anchor="PANA-IPSEC">

     <front>
       <title>PANA Enabling IPsec based Access Control</title>

       <author initials="M." surname="Parthasarathy" fullname="M. Parthasarathy">
         <organization>Nokia</organization>
       </author>

       <date month ="July" year="2005" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
   </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
