<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC1195 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1704 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1704.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2104 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2154 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2154.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3359 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3359.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3563 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3563.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3567 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3567.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4593 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4593.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="5304" category="std" obsoletes='3567' updates='1195'> 
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Cryptographic Authentication">
      IS-IS Cryptographic Authentication
    </title> 

    <author fullname="Tony Li" initials="T." surname="Li">
      <organization>Redback Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>300 Holger Way</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 750 5160</phone>

        <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="R. Atkinson" initials="R." surname="Atkinson">
      <organization>Extreme Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3585 Monroe St.</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95051</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 579 2800</phone>
        <email>rja@extremenetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="September" year="2008" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>IS-IS for IP Internets</workgroup>

    <keyword>IS-IS authentication MD5 HMAC-MD5 security routing</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>

	This document describes the authentication of Intermediate System
	to Intermediate System (IS-IS) Protocol Data Units (PDUs) using the
	Hashed Message Authentication Codes - Message Digest 5 (HMAC-MD5)
	algorithm as found in RFC 2104.  IS-IS is specified in
	International Standards Organization (ISO) 10589, with extensions
	to support Internet Protocol version 4 (IPv4) described in RFC
	1195.  The base specification includes an authentication mechanism
	that allows for multiple authentication algorithms.  The base
	specification only specifies the algorithm for cleartext passwords.
	This document replaces RFC 3567.

      </t>
      <t>

	This document proposes an extension to that specification that allows
	the use of the HMAC-MD5 authentication algorithm to be used in
	conjunction with the existing authentication mechanisms.

      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>

	The IS-IS protocol, as specified in <xref target="ISO-10589"/>,
	provides for the authentication of Link State Protocol Data Units (LSPs) through
	the inclusion of authentication information as part of the LSP.
	This authentication information is encoded as a Type-Length-Value
	(TLV) tuple.  The use of IS-IS for IPv4 networks is described in
	<xref target='RFC1195'/>.

      </t>
      <t>

	The type of the TLV is specified as 10.  The length of the TLV is
	variable.  The value of the TLV depends on the authentication
	algorithm and related secrets being used.  The first octet of the
	value is used to specify the authentication type.  Type 0 is
	reserved, type 1 indicates a cleartext password, and type 255 is used
	for routing domain private authentication methods.  The remainder of
	the TLV value is known as the Authentication Value.

      </t>
      <t>

	This document extends the above situation by allocating a new
	authentication type for HMAC-MD5 and specifying the algorithms for
	the computation of the Authentication Value.  This document also
	describes modifications to the base protocol to ensure that the
	authentication mechanisms described in this document are effective.

      </t>
      <t>

	This document is a publication of the IS-IS Working Group within
	the IETF.  This document replaces <xref target='RFC3567'/>, which
	is an Informational RFC.  This document is on the Standards Track.
	This document has revised <xref target='Security'/>, with the
	significant addition of a discussion of recent attacks on MD5 in
	<xref target='Collisions'/>.  This document has also added a
	substantive "IANA Considerations" section to create a missing codepoint registry.

      </t>
      <t>

	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.

      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Authentication Procedures">
      <t>

	The authentication type used for HMAC-MD5 is 54 (0x36).  The length
	of the Authentication Value for HMAC-MD5 is 16, and the length field
	in the TLV is 17.

      </t>
      <t>

	The HMAC-MD5 algorithm requires a key K and text T as
	input <xref target='RFC2104'/>.  The key K is the password for the
	PDU type, as specified in ISO 10589.  The text T is the IS-IS PDU
	to be authenticated with the Authentication Value field (inside of
	the Authentication Information TLV) set to zero.  Note that the
	Authentication Type is set to 54 and the length of the TLV is set
	to 17 before authentication is computed.  When LSPs are
	authenticated, the Checksum and Remaining Lifetime fields are set
	to zero (0) before authentication is computed.  The result of the
	algorithm is placed in the Authentication Value field.

      </t>
      <t>

	When calculating the HMAC-MD5 result for Sequence Number PDUs, Level
	1 Sequence Number PDUs SHALL use the Area Authentication string as in
	Level 1 Link State PDUs.  Level 2 Sequence Number PDUs SHALL use the
	domain authentication string as in Level 2 Link State PDUs.  IS-IS
	Hello PDUs SHALL use the Link Level Authentication String, which MAY
	be different from that of Link State PDUs.  The HMAC-MD5 result for
	the IS-IS Hello PDUs SHALL be calculated after the packet is padded
	to the MTU size, if padding is not disabled.  Implementations that
	support the optional checksum for the Sequence Number PDUs and IS-IS
	Hello PDUs MUST NOT include the Checksum TLV.

      </t>
      <t>

	To authenticate an incoming PDU, a system should save the values of
	the Authentication Value field, the Checksum field, and the Remaining
	Lifetime field, set these fields to zero, compute authentication, and
	then restore the values of these fields.

      </t>
      <t>

	An implementation that implements HMAC-MD5 authentication and
	receives HMAC-MD5 Authentication Information MUST discard the PDU if
	the Authentication Value is incorrect.

      </t>
      <t>

	An implementation MAY have a transition mode where it includes HMAC-
	MD5 Authentication Information in PDUs but does not verify the HMAC-
	MD5 Authentication Information.  This is a transition aid for
	networks in the process of deploying authentication.

      </t>
      <t>

	An implementation MAY check a set of passwords when verifying the
	Authentication Value.  This provides a mechanism for incrementally
	changing passwords in a network.

      </t>
      <t>

	An implementation that does not implement HMAC-MD5 authentication MAY
	accept a PDU that contains the HMAC-MD5 Authentication Type.  ISes
	(routers) that implement HMAC-MD5 authentication and initiate LSP
	purges MUST remove the body of the LSP and add the authentication
	TLV.  ISes implementing HMAC-MD5 authentication MUST NOT accept
	unauthenticated purges.  ISes MUST NOT accept purges that contain
	TLVs other than the authentication TLV.  These restrictions are
	necessary to prevent a hostile system from receiving an LSP, setting
	the Remaining Lifetime field to zero, and flooding it, thereby
	initiating a purge without knowing the authentication password.

      </t>

      <section title='Implementation Considerations'>
	<t>

	  There is an implementation issue that occurs just after password rollover on an
	  IS-IS router and that might benefit from additional commentary.
	  Immediately after password rollover on the router, the router or IS-IS process may restart.  If this happens, this causes the LSP
	  Sequence Number to restart from the value 1 using the new password.
	  However, neighbors will reject those new LSPs because the Sequence
	  Number is smaller.  The router cannot increase its own LSP Sequence
	  Number because it fails to authenticate its own old LSP that
	  neighbors keep sending to it.  So the router cannot update its LSP
	  Sequence Number to its neighbors until all the neighbors time out all
	  of the original LSPs.  One possible solution to this problem is for
	  the IS-IS process to detect if any inbound LSP with an authentication
	  failure has the local System ID and also has a higher Sequence Number
	  than the IS-IS process has.  In this event, the IS-IS process SHOULD
	  increase its own LSP Sequence Number accordingly and re-flood the
	  LSPs.  However, as this scenario could also be triggered by an active
	  attack by an adversary, it is recommended that a counter be kept
	  on this case to mitigate the risk from such an attack.

	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>

	This document enhances the security of the IS-IS routing protocol.
	Because a routing protocol contains information that need not be
	kept secret, privacy is not a requirement.  However, authentication
	of the messages within the protocol is of interest in order to reduce the
	risk of an adversary compromising the routing system by
	deliberately injecting false information into that system.

      </t>
      <section title='Security Limitations'>
	<t>

	  The technology in this document provides an authentication
	  mechanism for IS-IS.  The mechanism described here is not perfect
	  and does not need to be perfect.  Instead, this mechanism
	  represents a significant increase in the work function of an
	  adversary attacking the IS-IS protocol, while not causing undue
	  implementation, deployment, or operational complexity.  It
	  provides improved security against passive attacks, as defined in
	  <xref target='RFC1704'/>, when compared to cleartext password
	  authentication.

	</t>
	<t>

	  This mechanism does not prevent replay attacks;
	  however, in most cases, such attacks would trigger existing
	  mechanisms in the IS-IS protocol that would effectively reject
	  old information.  Denial-of-service attacks are not generally
	  preventable in a useful networking protocol <xref target='DoS'/>.

	</t>
	<t>

	  The mechanisms in this document do not provide protection against
	  compromised, malfunctioning, or misconfigured routers.  Such
	  routers can, either accidentally or deliberately, cause
	  malfunctions that affect the whole routing domain.  The reader is
	  encouraged to consult <xref target='RFC4593'/> for a more
	  comprehensive description of threats to routing protocols.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor='Collisions' title='Assurance'>
	<t>

	  Users need to understand that the quality of the security
	  provided by this mechanism depends completely on the strength of
	  the implemented authentication algorithms, the strength of the
	  key being used, and the correct implementation of the security
	  mechanism in all communicating IS-IS implementations.  This
	  mechanism also depends on the IS-IS Authentication Key being kept
	  confidential by all parties.  If any of these are incorrect or
	  insufficiently secure, then no real security will be provided to
	  the users of this mechanism.

	</t>
	<t>

	  Since Dobbertin's attacks on MD5 <xref target='Dobb96a'/>
	  <xref target='Dobb96b'/> <xref target='Dobb98'/> were first
	  published a dozen years ago, there have been growing concerns
	  about the effectiveness of the compression function within MD5.
	  More recent work by Wang and Yu <xref target='WY05'/> accentuates
	  these concerns.  However, despite these research results, there
	  are no published attacks at present on either Keyed-MD5 or
	  HMAC-MD5.  A recent paper by Bellare <xref target='Bell06a'/>
	  <xref target='Bell06b'/> provides new proofs for the security of
	  HMAC that require fewer assumptions than previous published
	  proofs for HMAC.  Those proofs indicate that the published issues
	  with MD5 (and separately with SHA-1) do not create an attack on
	  HMAC-MD5 (or HMAC SHA-1).  Most recently, Fouque and others
	  <xref target='FLN07'/> have published new attacks on NMAC-MD4,
	  HMAC-MD4, and NMAC-MD5.  However, their attacks are non-trivial
	  computationally, and they have not found an equivalent attack on
	  HMAC-MD5.  So, despite the published issues with the MD5
	  algorithm, there is currently no published attack that applies to
	  HMAC-MD5 as used in this IS-IS specification.  As with any
	  cryptographic technique, there is the possibility of the
	  discovery of future attacks against this mechanism.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Key Configuration'>
	<t>

	  It should be noted that the key configuration mechanism of 
	  routers may restrict the possible keys that may be used
	  between peers. It is strongly recommended that an 
	  implementation be able to support, at minimum, a key composed
	  of a string of printable ASCII of 80 bytes or less, as this
	  is current practice.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Other Considerations'>
	<t>

	  Changes to the authentication mechanism described here
	  (primarily: to add a Key-ID field such as that of OSPFv2 and RIPv2)
	  were considered at some length, but ultimately were rejected.
	  The mechanism here was already widely implemented in 1999.  As of
	  this writing, this mechanism is fairly widely deployed within the
	  users interested in cryptographic authentication of IS-IS.  The
	  improvement provided by the proposed revised mechanism was not
	  large enough to justify the change, given the installed base and
	  lack of operator interest in deploying a revised mechanism.

	</t>
	<t>

	  If and when a key management protocol appears that is both widely
	  implemented and easily deployed to secure routing protocols such
	  as IS-IS, a different authentication mechanism that is designed
	  for use with that key management schema could be added if
	  desired.

	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Future Directions'>
	<t>

	  If a stronger authentication were believed to be required, then
	  the use of a full digital signature <xref target='RFC2154'/>
	  would be an approach that should be seriously considered.  It was
	  rejected for this purpose at this time because the computational
	  burden of full digital signatures is believed to be much higher
	  than is reasonable, given the current threat environment in
	  operational commercial networks.

	</t>
	<t>

	  If and when additional authentication mechanisms are defined
	  (for
	  example, to provide a cryptographically stronger hash function), it
	  will also be necessary to define mechanisms that allow graceful
	  transition from the existing mechanisms (as defined in this
	  document) to any future mechanism.

	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
	IANA has created a new codepoint registry to  
	administer the Authentication Type codepoints for TLV 10. This  
	registry is part of the existing IS-IS codepoints registry as   
	established by <xref target='RFC3563'/> and
	<xref target='RFC3359'/>.  This registry is
	managed using the Designated Expert policy as described in 
	<xref target='RFC5226'/> and is called "IS-IS Authentication
	Type Codes for TLV 10".
      </t>

      <t>
	The values in the "IS-IS Authentication Type Codes for TLV 10"
	registry should be recorded in decimal and should only be
	approved after a designated expert, appointed by the IESG area
	director, has been consulted.  The intention is that any
	allocation will be accompanied by a published RFC.  However,
	the designated expert can approve allocations once it seems
	clear that an RFC will be published, allowing for the
	allocation of values prior to the document being approved for
	publication as an RFC. New items should be documented in a
	publicly and freely available specification. We should also
	allow external specifications to allocate and use the IS-IS
	Authentication Type Codes maintained by this registry.
      </t>

      <t>
        Initial values for the "IS-IS Authentication Type Codes for
	TLV 10" registry are  
	given below; future assignments are to be made through Expert Review. 
	Assignments consist of an authentication type name and its associated 
	value.  
      </t>
      
      <texttable>
	<ttcol align="left">Authentication Type Code</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

	<c>Reserved</c>
        <c>0</c>
        <c><xref target="ISO-10589"/></c>

	<c>Cleartext Password</c>
        <c>1</c>
        <c><xref target="ISO-10589"/></c>

	<c>ISO 10589 Reserved</c>
        <c>2</c>
        <c><xref target="ISO-10589"/></c>

	<c>HMAC-MD5 Authentication</c>
        <c>54</c>
	<c>RFC &rfc.number;</c>

	<c>Routeing Domain private authentication method</c>
	<c>255</c>
        <c><xref target="ISO-10589"/></c>
      </texttable>
    </section>


    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>

	The authors would like to thank (in alphabetical order) Stephen
	Farrell, Dave Katz, Steven Luong, Tony Przygienda, Nai-Ming Shen,
	and Henk Smit for their comments and suggestions on this document.

      </t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2104;
      &RFC2119;

      <reference anchor="ISO-10589">
	<front>
	  <title>Intermediate System to Intermediate System
	    intra-domain routeing information exchange protocol for
	    use in conjunction with the protocol for providing the
	    connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)</title>
	  <author><organization>ISO</organization></author>
	  <date year="2002"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="International Standard"
		    value="10589:2002, Second Edition"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1195;
      &RFC1704;
      &RFC2154;
      &RFC3359;
      &RFC3563;
      &RFC3567;
      &RFC4593;
      &RFC5226;

      <reference anchor='Bell06a'>
	<front>
	  <title>New Proofs for NMAC and HMAC: Security without
	    Collision-Resistance</title>
	  <author initials='M.' surname='Bellare'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date month='August' year='2006'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='Preliminary Version, in Proceedings of Crypto
			  2006, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Vol.'
		    value='4117' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Bell06b'
		 target='http://www-cse.ucsd.edu/users/mihir/papers/hmac-new.html'>
	<front>
	  <title>New Proofs for NMAC and HMAC: Security without
	    Collision-Resistance</title>
	  <author initials='M.' surname='Bellare'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date month='August' year='2006'/>
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='FLN07'>
	<front>
	  <title>Full Key-Recovery Attacks on HMAC/NMAC-MD5 and
	    NMAC-MD5</title>
	  <author initials='P.' surname='Fouque'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <author initials='G.' surname='Leurent'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <author initials='P.' surname='Nguyen'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date month='August' year='2007'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='Proceedings of Crypto' value='2007'/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor='Dobb96a'>
	<front>
	  <title>Cryptanalysis of MD5 Compress</title>
	  <author initials='H.' surname='Dobbertin'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date day='2' month='May' year='1996'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='EuroCrypt Rump Session' value='1996'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Dobb96b'>
	<front>
	  <title>The Status of MD5 After a Recent Attack</title>
	  <author initials='H.' surname='Dobbertin'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date year='1996'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='CryptoBytes, Vol. 2,' value='No. 2'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Dobb98'>
	<front>
	  <title>Cryptanalysis of MD4</title>
	  <author initials='H.' surname='Dobbertin'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date year='1998'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='Journal of Cryptology, Vol. 11,' value='No. 4'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='DoS'>
	<front>
	  <title>Security Mechanisms in High-level Networks</title>
	  <author initials='V.' surname='Voydock'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <author initials='S.' surname='Kent'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date month='June' year='1983'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="ACM Computing Surveys" value='Vol. 15, No. 2'/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='WY05'>
	<front>
	  <title>How to Break MD5 and Other Hash Functions</title>
	  <author initials='X.' surname='Wang'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <author initials='H.' surname='Yu'>
	    <organization></organization></author>
	  <date year='2005'/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='Proceedings of EuroCrypt 2005, Lecture Notes in
			  Computer Science, Vol.' value='3494'/>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
