<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"
[
]>
    
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc number="5713" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ANCP Threats">Security Threats and Security Requirements for the Access&nbsp;Node&nbsp;Control&nbsp;Protocol&nbsp;(ANCP)</title>
    <author fullname="Hassnaa Moustafa" initials="H." surname="Moustafa">
      <organization abbrev="France Telecom">France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>38-40 rue du General Leclerc</street>
          <city>Issy Les Moulineaux</city>
          <region/>
          <code>92794 Cedex 9</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hassnaa.moustafa@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization abbrev="Nokia Siemens Networks">Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>          
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
	</postal>
        <phone>  +358 (50) 4871445 </phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stefaan De Cnodder" initials="S." surname="De Cnodder">
      <organization abbrev="Alcatel-Lucent">Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Copernicuslaan 50</street>
          <city>B-2018 Antwerp</city>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
	<phone>+32 3 240 85 15</phone>
        <email>stefaan.de_cnodder@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2009"/>
    <area>Internet Area</area>
    <workgroup>ANCP Working Group</workgroup>


    <abstract>
      <t>The Access Node Control Protocol (ANCP) aims to communicate
        Quality of Service (QoS)-related, service-related, and
        subscriber-related configurations and operations between a
        Network Access Server (NAS) and an Access Node (e.g., a
        Digital Subscriber Line Access Multiplexer (DSLAM)). The main
        goal of this protocol is to allow the NAS to configure,
        manage, and control access equipment, including the ability
        for the Access Nodes to report information to the NAS.</t>

      <t>This present document investigates security threats that all
      ANCP nodes could encounter. This document develops a threat
      model for ANCP security, with the aim of deciding which security
      functions are required. Based on this, security requirements
      regarding the Access Node Control Protocol are defined.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Access Node Control Protocol (ANCP) aims to communicate QoS-related, service-related, and
        subscriber-related configurations and operations between a
        Network Access Server (NAS) and an Access Node (e.g., a
        Digital Subscriber Line Access Multiplexer (DSLAM)).</t>
      <t>
        <xref target="ANCP-FRAME"/> illustrates the framework, usage scenarios, and
        general requirements for ANCP. This document focuses on
        describing security threats and deriving security requirements
        for the Access Node Control Protocol, considering the ANCP use
        cases defined in 	<xref target="ANCP-FRAME"/> as well as
        the guidelines for IETF protocols' security requirements given
        in <xref target="RFC3365"/>. <xref target="attacks"/> and 
        <xref target="attacksmeans"/>, respectively, describe the
        potential attacks and the different attack forms that are
        liable to take place within ANCP, while
        <xref target="ANCPAttacks"/> applies the described potential
        attacks to ANCP and its different use cases. Security policy
        negotiation, including authentication and 
        authorization to define the per-subscriber policy at the
        policy/AAA (Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting)
        server, is out of the scope of this work. As a high-level
        summary, the following aspects need to be
        considered:<list style="hanging"> 
	<t></t>
          <t hangText="Message Protection:"> 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> Signaling message content can be protected against
            eavesdropping, modification, injection, and replay while in transit. This applies to both 
            ANCP headers and payloads.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Prevention against Impersonation:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> It is important that protection
            be available against a device impersonating an ANCP node
            (i.e., an unauthorized device generating an ANCP message
            and pretending it was generated by a valid ANCP
            node).
          </t>
          <t hangText="Prevention of Denial-of-Service Attacks:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> ANCP nodes and the network have finite resources (state
            storage, processing power, bandwidth). 
   It is important to protect against exhaustion attacks on
   these resources and to prevent ANCP nodes from being used to launch
   attacks on other network elements.</t>

        </list>
     </t>
     
    </section>


    <section title="Specification Requirements">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>, with the qualification that, unless otherwise stated, they apply
        to the design of the Access Node Control Protocol (ANCP), not its implementation or
        application.</t>

      <t>The relevant components are described in <xref target="introduction"/>.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="introduction" title="System Overview and Threat Model">
      <t>As described in <xref target="ANCP-FRAME"/> and schematically shown in <xref
          target="overview"/>, the Access Node Control system consists of the following
          components:<list style="hanging">
	<t></t>
          <t hangText="Network Access Server (NAS):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> A NAS provides access to a service (e.g., network access) and
            operates as a client of the AAA protocol. The AAA client is responsible for passing
            authentication information to designated AAA servers and then acting on the response
            that is returned. 
          </t>
          <t hangText="Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) server:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> A AAA server is responsible for authenticating users, 
            authorizing access to services, and returning
            authorization information (including configuration
            parameters) back to the AAA client to deliver service to
            the user. As a consequence, service usage accounting might
            be enabled and information about the user's resource usage
            will be sent to the AAA server. 
          </t>
          <t hangText="Access Node (AN):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The AN is a network device, usually located at a service
            provider central office or street cabinet, that terminates access-loop connections from
            subscribers. In case the access loop is a Digital Subscriber Line (DSL), this is often
            referred to as a DSL Access Multiplexer (DSLAM).
          </t>
          <t hangText="Customer Premises Equipment (CPE):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> A CPE is a device located inside
            a subscriber's premise that is connected at the LAN side
            of the Home Gateway (HGW).
          </t>
          <t hangText="Home Gateway (HGW):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The HGW connects the different Customer Premises Equipments
            (CPEs) to the Access Node and the access network. In case of DSL, the HGW is a DSL
            Network Termination (NT) that could either operate as a layer 2 bridge or as a layer 3
            router. In the latter case, such a device is also referred to as a Routing Gateway
          (RG).
         </t>
 	<t hangText="Aggregation Network:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The aggregation network provides traffic aggregation from multiple ANs towards the 
             NAS. ATM or Ethernet transport technologies can be used.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
  For the threat analysis, this document focuses on the ANCP
  communication between the Access Node and the NAS.
However, communications with the other components (such as HGW, CPE,
         and the AAA server) play a role in the 
         understanding of the system architecture and of what triggers ANCP communications. Note that the NAS 
         and the AN might belong to two different administrative realms. The threat model and the security requirements in 
         this document consider this latter case.</t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="overview" title="System Overview">
          <artwork><![CDATA[          
                                                          +--------+
                                                          | AAA    |
                                                          | Server |
                                                          +--------+
                                                               |
                                                               |
   +---+   +---+   +------+    +-----------+    +-----+   +--------+
   |CPE|---|HGW|---|      |    |Aggregation|    |     |   |        |
   +---+   +---+   |Access|    | Network   |    |     |   |Internet|
                   | Node |----|           |----| NAS |---|   /    |
   +---+   +---+   | (AN) |    |           |    |     |   |Regional|
   |CPE|---|HGW|---|      |    |           |    |     |   |Network |
   +---+   +---+   +------+    +-----------+    +-----+   +--------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>In the absence of an attack, the NAS receives configuration information from the AAA server
        related to a CPE attempting to access the network. A number of parameters, including Quality
        of Service information, need to be conveyed to the Access Node in order to become effective.
        The Access Node Control Protocol is executed between the NAS and the AN to initiate control
        requests. The AN returns responses to these control requests and provides information
        reports. </t>
      <t> For this to happen, the following individual steps must occur:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The AN discovers the NAS. </t>
          <t>The AN needs to start the protocol communication with the NAS to announce its presence.</t>
          <t>The AN and the NAS perform a capability exchange.</t>
          <t>The NAS sends requests to the AN.</t>
          <t>The AN processes these requests, authorizes the actions, and responds with the
            appropriate answer. In order to fulfill the commands, it might be necessary for the AN to
            communicate with the HGW or other nodes, for example, as part of a keep-alive mechanism.</t>
          <t>The AN provides status reports to the NAS.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Attackers can be:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>off-path, i.e., they cannot see the messages exchanged between the AN and the NAS;</t>
          <t>on-path, i.e., they can see the messages exchanged between the AN and the NAS.</t>
        </list>
      </t>


      <t>Both off-path and on-path attackers can be:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>passive, i.e., they do not participate in the network
          operation but rather listen to all transfers
            to obtain the maximum possible information;</t>
          <t>active, i.e., they participate in the network operation
          and can inject falsified packets.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>We assume the following threat model: <list style="symbols">
          <t>An off-path adversary located at the CPE or the HGW.</t>
          <t>An off-path adversary located on the Internet or a regional network that connects one
            or more NASes and associated access networks to Network Service Providers (NSPs) and
            Application Service Providers (ASPs). </t>
          <t>An on-path adversary located at network elements between the AN and the NAS.</t>
          <t>An on-path adversary taking control over the NAS.</t>
          <t>An on-path adversary taking control over the AN.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Objectives of Attackers">
      <t>Attackers may direct their efforts either against an individual entity or against a large
        portion of the access network. Attacks fall into three classes:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Attacks to disrupt the communication for individual customers.</t>
          <t>Attacks to disrupt the communication of a large fraction of customers in an access
            network. These also include attacks to the network itself or a portion of it, such as attacks to disrupt the network services or attacks to destruct the network functioning.</t>
          <t>Attacks to gain profit for the attacker through modifying
             the QoS settings. Also, through replaying old packets (of
             another privileged client, for instance), an attacker can
             attempt to configure a better QoS profile on its own DSL
             line, increasing its own benefit.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="attacks" title="Potential Attacks">
 	<t>This section discusses the different types of attacks against ANCP, while <xref target="attacksmeans"/>           describes the possible means of their occurrence.</t> 

      <t>ANCP is mainly susceptible to the following types of attacks:</t>

      <section title="Denial of Service (DoS)">
        <t>A number of denial-of-service (DoS) attacks can cause ANCP nodes to malfunction. When state is established or 
           certain functions are performed without requiring prior authorization, there is a chance to mount denial-of-service attacks. An adversary can utilize this fact to transmit a large number of signaling messages to 
           allocate state at nodes and to cause consumption of resources. Also, an adversary, through DoS, can prevent 
           certain subscribers from accessing certain services. Moreover, DoS can take place at the AN or the NAS themselves,
           where it is possible for the NAS (or the AN) to intentionally ignore the requests received from the AN 
           (or the NAS) through not replying to them. This causes the sender of the request to retransmit the request, 
           which might allocate additional state at the sender side to process the reply. Allocating more state may result
           in memory depletion. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Integrity Violation">
        <t>Adversaries gaining illegitimate access on the transferred
           messages can act on these messages, causing integrity
           violation. Integrity violation can cause unexpected network
           behavior, leading to a disturbance in the network services
           as well as in the network functioning.</t>

	 </section>
      <section title="Downgrading">            
        <t> Protocols may be useful in a variety of scenarios with different security and functional requirements. 
            Different parts of a network (e.g., within a building, across a public carrier's network, or over a private 
            microwave link) may need different levels of
            protection. It is often difficult to meet these (sometimes 
            conflicting) requirements with a single mechanism or fixed
            set of parameters; thus, often a selection of 
            mechanisms and parameters is offered. A protocol is required to agree on certain (security) mechanisms and 
            parameters. An insecure parameter exchange or security
            negotiation protocol can give an adversary the opportunity to 
            mount a downgrading attack to force selection of mechanisms weaker than those mutually desired. 
            Thus, without binding the negotiation process to the legitimate parties and protecting it, ANCP might only be 
            as secure as the weakest mechanism provided (e.g., weak authentication) and the benefits of defining 
            configuration parameters and a negotiation protocol are lost.</t>
      </section>
     <section anchor="analysis" title="Traffic Analysis">            
        <t> An adversary can be placed at the NAS, the AN, or any other network element capturing all traversing 
            packets. Adversaries can thus have unauthorized information access. As well, they can gather information
            relevant to the network and then use this information in gaining later unauthorized access. This attack can 
            also help adversaries in other malicious purposes -- for example, capturing messages sent from the AN to the 
            NAS announcing that a DSL line is up and containing some information related to the connected client. 
	    This could be any form of information about the client and
            could also be an indicator of whether or not the DSL 
            subscriber is at home at a particular moment.</t>
      </section>

 <section anchor="Management" title="Management Attacks">            
     <t> Since the ANCP sessions are configured in the AN and not in
     the NAS <xref target="ANCP-FRAME"/>, most configurations of ANCP
     are done in the AN. Consequently, the management attacks to ANCP
     mainly concern the AN configuration phase. In this context, the
     AN MIB module could create disclosure- and
     misconfiguration-related attacks. <xref target="ANCP-MIB"/>
     defines the vulnerabilities on the management objects within the AN MIB
     module. These attacks mainly concern the unauthorized changes of
     the management objects, leading to a number of attacks such as session
     deletion, a session using an undesired/unsupported protocol, disabling
     certain ANCP capabilities or enabling undesired capabilities,
     ANCP packets being sent out to the wrong interface (and thus being
     received by an unintended receiver), harming the synchronization
     between the AN and the NAS, and impacting traffic in the
     network other than ANCP.</t>
      </section>

 </section>

 <section anchor="attacksmeans" title="Attack Forms">

    <t>The attacks mentioned above in <xref target="attacks"/> can be carried out through the following means:</t>
	<t>
	<list style="hanging">      
        <t hangText="Message Replay:">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/> This threat scenario covers the case in which an adversary eavesdrops, collects 
            signaling messages, and replays them at a later time (or at a different place or in a different way; e.g., 
            cut-and-paste attacks). Through replaying signaling messages, an adversary might mount denial-of-service and theft-of-service attacks.
        </t>
     
        <t hangText="Faked Message Injection:">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/> An adversary may be able to inject
           false error or response messages, causing unexpected
           protocol behavior and succeeding with a DoS attack. This
           could be achieved at the signaling-protocol level, at 
           the level of specific signaling parameters (e.g., QoS
           information), or at the transport layer. An adversary 
           might, for example, inject a signaling message to request
           allocation of QoS resources. As a consequence, other 
           users' traffic might be impacted. The discovery protocol,
           especially, exhibits vulnerabilities with regard to 
           this threat scenario.
        </t>

        <t hangText="Messages Modification:"> 
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>This involves integrity violation,
           where an adversary can modify signaling messages in 
           order to cause unexpected network behavior. Possible
           related actions an adversary might consider for its attack
           are the reordering and delaying of messages, causing a
           protocol's process failure.
         </t>
      
        <t hangText="Man-in-the-Middle:">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>An adversary might claim to be a
           NAS or an AN, acting as a man-in-the-middle to later 
            cause communication and services disruption. The
           consequence can range from DoS to fraud. An adversary
           acting as a man-in-the-middle could modify the intercepted
           messages, causing integrity violation, or could drop or 
           truncate the intercepted messages, causing DoS and a
           protocol's process failure. In addition, a
           man-in-the-middle adversary can signal
           information to an illegitimate entity in place of the right
           destination. In this case, the protocol could appear to
           continue working correctly. This may result in an AN
           contacting a wrong NAS. For the AN, this could mean that
           the protocol failed for unknown reasons. A
           man-in-the-middle adversary can also cause downgrading
           attacks through initiating faked configuration parameters
           and through forcing selection of weak security parameters
           or mechanisms.
         </t>
    
        <t hangText="Eavesdropping:"> 
         <vspace blankLines="1"/>This is related to adversaries that
         are able to eavesdrop on transferred messages. The 
         collection of the transferred packets by an adversary may
         allow traffic analysis or be used later to mount replay
         attacks. The eavesdropper might learn QoS parameters,
         communication patterns, policy rules for firewall traversal,
         policy information, application identifiers, user identities,
         NAT bindings, authorization objects, network
         configuration, performance information, and more.
       </t>

     </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
     <section anchor="ANCPAttacks" title="Attacks against ANCP">
      <t>ANCP is susceptible to security threats, causing disruption/unauthorized access to network
        services, manipulation of the transferred data, and interference with network functions.
        Based on the threat model given in <xref target="introduction"/> and the potential attacks
        presented in <xref target="attacks"/>, this section describes the possible attacks against ANCP, considering the 
        four use cases defined in <xref target="ANCP-FRAME"/>.</t>
      <t>Although ANCP is not involved in the communication between the NAS and the AAA/policy server, the 
         secure communication between the NAS and the AAA/policy server is important for ANCP security. Consequently, 
         this document considers the attacks that are related to the ANCP operation associated with the communication 
         between the NAS and the AAA/Policy server. In other words, the threat model and security requirements in this 
         document take into consideration the data transfer between the NAS and the AAA server, when this data is used 
         within the ANCP operation.</t>

      <t>Besides the attacks against the four ANCP use cases described
      in the following subsections, ANCP is 
          susceptible to a number of attacks that can take place
      during the protocol-establishment phase. These attacks are
      mainly on-path attacks, taking the form of DoS or
          man-in-the-middle attacks, which could be as
          follows:<list style="symbols">

	<t>Attacks during the session initiation from the AN to the
	NAS: <vspace blankLines="0" /> DoS attacks could take place affecting the 
           session-establishment process. Also, man-in-the-middle
	attacks could take place, causing message truncation 
           or message modification and leading to session-establishment failure.</t>

	<t>Attacks during the peering establishment:
          <vspace blankLines="0" /> DoS attacks could take place
          during state synchronization between the AN and the
          NAS. Also, man-in-the-middle attacks could take place through
          message modification during identity 
          discovery, which may lead to loss of contact between the AN
          and the NAS.</t>

	<t>Attacks during capabilities negotiation:
	<vspace blankLines="0" /> Message replay
	could take place, leading to DoS. Also, 
          man-in-the-middle attacks could take place, leading to message
	modification, message truncation, or 
          downgrading through advertising lesser capabilities.</t>  
	</list>  
	</t>

      <section title="Dynamic Access-Loop Attributes">
        <t>This use case concerns the communication of access-loop
        attributes for dynamic, access-line topology discovery. Since the access-loop rate may
        change over time, advertisement is
          beneficial to the NAS to gain knowledge about the topology
        of the access network for QoS
          scheduling. Besides data rates and access-loop links
        identification, other information may also be transferred
          from the AN to the NAS (examples in case of a DSL access loop
        are DSL type, maximum achievable data rate, and 
          maximum data rate configured for the access loop). This use
        case is thus vulnerable to a number of on-path and 
          off-path attacks that can be either active or passive.</t>

        <t>On-path attacks can take place between the AN and the NAS,
        on the AN or on the NAS, during the access-loop attributes
           transfer. These attacks may be:<list style="symbols">  

	<t> Active, acting on the transferred attributes and injecting
	falsified packets. The main attacks here
	are:<list style="symbols">

        <t> Man-in-the-middle attacks can cause access-loop attributes
        transfer between the AN and a forged NAS or 
            a forged AN and the NAS, which can directly cause faked
       attributes and message modification or truncation.</t>

        <t> Signaling replay, by an attacker between the AN and the
        NAS, on the AN or on the NAS itself, causing DoS.</t>

        <t> An adversary acting as man-in-the-middle can cause
        downgrading through changing the actual data rate of the access loop,
            which impacts the downstream shaping from the NAS.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
         
          <t>Passive, only learning these attributes. The main attacks here are caused by:<list style="symbols">
              <t> Eavesdropping through learning access-loop
              attributes and information about the clients'
                  connection state, and thus impacting their privacy
              protection.</t>

              <t> Traffic analysis allowing unauthorized information
              access, which could allow later unauthorized access
                  to the NAS.</t>
	 </list>	
        </t>

	</list>	
        </t>

        <t></t>

	<t>Off-path attacks can take place on the Internet, affecting
           the access-loop attribute sharing between the NAS 
           and the AAA/policy server. These attacks may
           be:<list style="symbols">        

	<t> Active attacks, which are mainly
	concerning:<list style="symbols">

        <t>DoS through flooding the communication links to the AAA/policy
        server, causing service disruption.</t>

        <t>Man-in-the-middle, causing access-loop configuration
        retrieval by an illegitimate NAS.</t>

	</list>
        </t>           
        <t>Passive attacks, gaining information on the access-loop
        attributes. The main attacks in this case
        are: <list style="symbols">

	<t>Eavesdropping through learning access-loop attributes and
	learning information about the clients' connection 
          states, and thus impacting their privacy protection.</t>

	<t>Traffic analysis allowing unauthorized information access,
	which could allow later unauthorized access to the NAS.</t>
	</list>		
        </t>
	
	</list>	
        </t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="configuration" title="Access-Loop Configuration">
        <t>This use case concerns the dynamic, local-loop line
        configuration through allowing the NAS
          to change the access-loop parameters (e.g., rate) in a
        dynamic fashion. This allows for
          centralized, subscriber-related service data. This dynamic
        configuration can be achieved, for
          instance, through profiles that are pre-configured on
        ANs. This use case is vulnerable to
          a number of on-path and off-path attacks.</t>


	<t>On-path attacks can take place where the attacker is
	between the AN and the NAS, is on the AN, or is on the 
         NAS. These can be as follows:<list style="symbols">

	<t>Active attacks, taking the following
	forms:<list style="symbols">

	<t>DoS attacks of the AN can take place by an attacker,
	through replaying the Configure Request messages.</t>

	<t> An attacker on the AN can prevent the AN from reacting on
	the NAS request for the access-loop configuration, 
          leading to the NAS continually sending the Configure Request
	message and, hence, allocating additional states.</t>

	<t>Damaging clients' profiles at ANs can take place by adversaries
	that gained control on the network through discovery
	of users' information from a previous traffic analysis.</t>

	<t>An adversary can replay old packets, modify messages, or
	inject faked messages.  Such adversary can also be a 
          man-in-the-middle.  These attack forms can be related to a
	privileged client profile (having more services) in order
           to configure this profile on the adversary's own DSL line,
	which is less privileged.  In order that the 
          attacker does not expose its identity, he may also use these
	attack forms related to the privileged client 
          profile to configure a number of illegitimate DSL lines. The
	adversary can also force configuration 
          parameters other than the selected ones, leading to, for
	instance, downgrading the service for a privileged client.</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>Passive attacks, where the attacker listens to the ANCP
	messages. This can take place as
	follows:<list style="symbols">

          <t>Learning configuration attributes is possible during the
          update of the access-loop configuration. An adversary
          might profit to see the configuration that someone else gets
          (e.g., one ISP might be interested
          to know what the customers of another ISP get and therefore
          might break into the AN to see this).</t>

	 </list>
	</t>
	
	</list>	
	</t>

     <t></t>

	<t>Off-path attacks can take place as follows:<list style="symbols">
          <t>An off-path passive adversary on the Internet can exert
          eavesdropping during the access-loop configuration 
           retrieval by the NAS from the AAA/policy server.</t>

	  <t>An off-path active adversary on the Internet can threaten
	  the centralized subscribers-related service data in 
           the AAA/policy server through, for instance, making
	  subscribers' records inaccessible.</t>

	</list>
	</t>
	        
      </section>

      <section title="Remote Connectivity Test">
        <t>In this use case, the NAS can carry out a Remote Connectivity
        Test using ANCP to initiate an
          access-loop test between the AN and the HGW. Thus, multiple
        access-loop technologies can
          be supported. This use case is vulnerable to a number of active attacks. Most of the
          attacks in this use case concern the network operation.</t>

          <t>On-path active attacks can take place in the following
          forms:<list style="symbols"> 

          <t> Man-in-the-middle attack during the NAS's triggering to
              the AN to carry out the test, where an adversary can 
              inject falsified signals or can truncate the
              triggering.</t>

          <t> Message modification can take place during the
          Subscriber Response message transfer from the AN to the NAS 
              announcing the test results, causing failure of the test
          operation.</t>

	<t>An adversary on the AN can prevent the AN from sending the
           Subscriber Response message to the NAS announcing the
           test results, and hence the NAS will continue triggering
           the AN to carry out the test, which results in more 
           state being allocated at the NAS. This may result in
           unavailability of the NAS to the ANs.</t>

	</list>
        </t>
   
	<t></t>

        <t>Off-path active attacks can take place as
        follows:<list style="symbols"> 

        <t>An adversary can cause DoS during the access-loop test, in
        case of an ATM-based access loop, when the AN generates
        loopback cells. This can take place through signal
        replaying.</t>

        <t>Message truncating can take place by an adversary during
        the access-loop test, which can lead to service 
           disruption due to assumption of test failures.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
       
      </section>

      <section title="Multicast">
        <t>In this use case, ANCP could be used in exchanging
        information between the AN and the NAS,
          allowing the AN to perform replication inline with the policy and configuration of the
          subscriber. Also, this allows the NAS to follow subscribers' multicast (source, group)
          membership and control replication performed by the AN. Four
        multicast use cases are expected to take place, 
          making use of ANCP; these are typically multicast
        conditional access, multicast admission control, 
          multicast accounting, and spontaneous admission response. This section gives a high-level description of the possible attacks that can take place in these cases.  Attacks that can occur are mostly active attacks.</t>

 	<t> On-path active attacks can be as follows:<list style="symbols">

	  <t> DoS attacks, causing inability for certain subscribers to
	  access particular multicast streams or only
               access the multicast stream at a reduced bandwidth,
	  impacting the quality of the possible video 
               stream. This can take place through message replay by
	  an attacker between the AN and the NAS, on the AN 
               or on the NAS. Such DoS attacks can also be done by
	  tempering, for instance, with white/black list 
               configuration or by placing attacks to the
	  bandwidth-admission-control mechanism.</t>

       <t> An adversary on the NAS can prevent the NAS from reacting
       on the AN requests for white/black/grey lists or for 
           admission control for the access line.  The AN in this case
       would not receive a reply and would continue sending
       its requests, resulting in more states being allocated at the
       AN. A similar case happens for admission control 
           when the NAS can also send requests to the AN. When the NAS
       does not receive a response, it could also 
           retransmit requests, resulting in more state being allocated
       at the NAS side to process responses. 
           This may result in the unavailability of the NAS to the ANs.</t>

         <t>Man-in-the-middle, causing the exchange of messages
         between the AN and a forged NAS or a forged AN and the
         NAS. This can lead to the following:<list style="symbols"> 

             <t> Message modification, which can cause service
             downgrading for legitimate subscribers -- for 
                instance, an illegitimate change of a subscriber's
             policy.</t>

             <t>Message truncation between the AN and the NAS, which
             can result in the non-continuity of services.</t>

	    <t>Message replay between the AN and the NAS, on the AN
	    or on the NAS, leading to a DoS or services fraud.</t>

	    <t>Message modification to temper with accounting
	    information, for example, in order to avoid service 
               charges or, conversely, in order to artificially
	    increase service charges on other users. </t>
        </list>
	</t>
    
         </list>
        </t>

	<t> An off-path active attack is as follows:<list style="symbols">
	<t> DoS could take place through message replay of join/leave requests by the HGW or CPE, frequently triggering 
            the ANCP activity between the AN and the NAS. DoS
            could also result from generating heaps of IGMP
            join/leaves by the HGW or CPE, leading to very high rate of ANCP query/response.</t>
	</list>
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Security Requirements">
      <t>This section presents a number of requirements motivated by the different types of attacks defined 
         in the previous section. These requirements are as follows:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The protocol solution MUST offer authentication of the AN to the NAS.</t>
          <t>The protocol solution MUST offer authentication of the NAS to the AN.</t>	 
          <t>The protocol solution MUST allow authorization to take place at the NAS and the AN.</t>
          <t>The protocol solution MUST offer replay protection.</t>
          <t>The protocol solution MUST provide data-origin authentication.</t>
          <t>The protocol solution MUST be robust against denial-of-service (DoS) attacks. In this context, the protocol 
             solution MUST consider a specific mechanism for the DoS
             that the user might create by sending many IGMP 
             messages.</t>
          <t>The protocol solution SHOULD offer confidentiality protection.</t>
	  <t>The protocol solution SHOULD ensure that operations in
             default configuration guarantees a low number
             of AN/NAS protocol interactions.</t>
         <t>The protocol solution SHOULD ensure the access control of
         the management objects and possibly encrypt the 
            values of these objects when sending them over the networks.</t>
          </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document focuses on security threats, deriving a threat
      model for ANCP and presenting
        the security requirements to be considered for the design of ANCP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t> Many thanks go to Francois Le Faucher for reviewing this
      document and for all his useful comments. The authors 
        would also like to thank Philippe Niger, Curtis Sherbo, and
      Michael Busser for reviewing this document. Other thanks 
        go to Bharat Joshi, Mark Townsley, Wojciech Dec, and Kim
      Hylgaard who have had valuable comments during the 
        development of this work.</t>
    </section>
   
    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
  </middle>
  <back><references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3365" ?>


    </references>
    <references title="Informative References"> 


<reference anchor="ANCP-MIB">
	<front>
	<title>
Access Node Control Protocol (ANCP) MIB module for Access Nodes
</title>
	<author initials="S" surname="De Cnodder" fullname="Stefaan De Cnodder">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="M" surname="Morgenstern" fullname="Moti Morgenstern">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="July" year="2009"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ANCP-FRAME">
	<front>
	<title>
Framework and Requirements for an Access Node Control Mechanism in Broadband  Multi-Service Networks
</title>
	<author initials="S" surname="Ooghe" fullname="Sven Ooghe">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="N" surname="Voigt" fullname="Norbert Voigt">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="M" surname="Platnic" fullname="Michel Platnic">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="T" surname="Haag" fullname="Thomas Haag">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="S" surname="Wadhwa" fullname="Sanjay Wadhwa">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="October" day="5" year="2009"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>
    
 </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
