<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc
    category="std"
    number="5665"
    updates="1833" >


<front>
    <title abbrev="RPC Netids">IANA Considerations for Remote
    Procedure Call (RPC) Network&nbsp;Identifiers&nbsp;and&nbsp;Universal&nbsp;Address&nbsp;Formats</title>

    <author fullname="Mike Eisler" 
            initials="M." 
            surname="Eisler">
        <organization abbrev="NetApp">NetApp</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>5765 Chase Point Circle</street>
                <city>Colorado Springs</city>
                <region>CO</region>
                <code>80919</code>
                <country>US</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+1-719-599-9026</phone>
            <email>mike@eisler.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010" month="January"/>

    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>NFSv4</workgroup>



    <abstract>
      <t>
      This document lists IANA Considerations for Remote Procedure
      Call (RPC) Network Identifiers (netids) and RPC Universal
      Network Addresses (uaddrs). This document updates, but does not
      replace, RFC 1833.

      </t>
    </abstract>


</front>
<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and Motivation" >
<t>
The concepts of an RPC (defined in <xref target="RFC5531">RFC
 5531</xref>) Network Identifier (netid)
and an RPC Universal Address (uaddr) were
introduced in <xref target="RFC1833">RFC 1833</xref> for distinguishing
network addresses of multiple protocols and representing those
addresses in a canonical form.
RFC 1833 states that a netid "is defined by a
system administrator based on local conventions, and cannot
be depended on to have the same value on every system".
(The netid is contained in the field r_netid of the data type rpcb_entry,
and the uaddr is contained in the field r_addr of the same data type, where
rpcb_entry is defined in RFC 1833.) 
Since the publication of RFC 1833, it has been found
that protocols like <xref target="RFC3530">Network File System version
 4 (NFSv4.0)</xref> and
<xref target="RFC5666">RPC/RDMA (Remote Direct Memory Access)</xref> depend on
consistent values of netids and representations of uaddrs.
Current practices tend to ensure this consistency. Thus,
this document identifies the considerations for IANA to
establish registries of netids and uaddr formats for RPC and specifies
the initial content of the two registries.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Requirements Language">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
&quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="sctp_considerations" title="Considerations for the
					     Netid of the Stream
					     Control Transmission Protocol">
<t>
 The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) (described in <xref
 target="RFC4960">RFC 4960</xref>) is a
 connection-oriented protocol that supports both
 byte-streamed and record-oriented data transfer.
 When the "sctp" and "sctp6" netids are used, the Open Network
 Computing (ONC)
 RPC Record Marking standard (see Section 11 of RFC 5531 <xref
 target="RFC5531"></xref>) is not used; instead, SCTP's
 native record-oriented data transfer is used.

</t>
</section>
<section anchor="securityconsider" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   Since this document is only concerned with the IANA management of
   the Network Identifier (netid) and Universal Network Addresses
   (uaddrs) format registry, it raises no new security issues.

</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ianaconsider" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
This section uses terms that are defined in <xref target="RFC5226">RFC
    5226</xref>.
</t>

<section anchor="iananetids" title="IANA Considerations for Netids">

<t>
IANA has created a registry called "ONC RPC Netids". The remainder of this section describes the registry.
</t>

<t>
All assignments to the ONC RPC Netids registry are made on one of two bases:
<list style='symbols'>
<t>
A First Come First Served basis subregistry
per Section 4.1 of RFC 5226. 
</t>
<t>
A Standards Action basis subregistry
per Section 4.1 of RFC 5226.
</t>
</list>
The eXternal Data Representation (XDR) encoding allows netids to be up to 2^32 - 1 octets in length,
but the registry will only allow a much shorter length.
Assignments made on a Standards Action basis should be assigned
netids 1 to 8 octets long.  Assignments made on a First Come
First Served basis should be assigned netids 9 to
128 octets long.  Some exceptions are listed in <xref target="rfc_netids"/>.
</t>
<t>
Some portion of the netid name space is Reserved:
<list style='symbols'>

<t>
All netids, regardless of length, that
start with the prefixes "STDS" or "FCFS" are Reserved, in
order to extend the name space of either Standards Action or
First Come First Served bases.
</t>

<t>
To give the IESG the flexibility in the future to
permit Private and Experimental Uses, all netids with the
prefixes "PRIV" or "EXPE" are Reserved.
</t>

<t>
To prevent confusion with the control protocol by the same
name <xref target="RFC0792"/>, netids with the prefix "ICMP" are Reserved.
</t>

<t>
Since netids are not constructed in an explicit
hierarchical manner, this document does not provide for
Hierarchical Allocation of netids. Nonetheless, all netids containing
the octet "." are
Reserved for future possible provision of Hierarchical Allocation.
</t>

<t>
The zero length netid is Reserved.
</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>
A recommended convention for netids corresponding to transports that
work over the IPv6 protocol is to have "6" as the last character in the netid's name.
</t>

<t>
There are two subregistries of netids: one for Standards Action assignments
and one for First Come First Served assignments.
Each registry of netids is a list of assignments, each
containing five fields for each assignment.

<list style='numbers'>
<t>
  A US-ASCII string name that is the actual netid.
  The netid should be 1 to 8 octets long for the Standards Action subregistry, and
  9 to 128 octets long for the First Come First Served subregistry.
  The netid MUST NOT conflict with any other registered netid. Despite the fact that
  netids are case sensitive, the netid, when mapped to all upper case,
  MUST NOT conflict with the value of any other registered netid after
  the registered netid is mapped to upper case. In addition, when mapped to
  upper case, the prefix of the netid MUST NOT be equal to a Reserved prefix.
</t>

<t>
  A constant name that can be used for software programs
  that wish to use the transport protocol associated with
  the netid. 
The name of the constant typically has the
  prefix "NC_", and a suffix equal to the upper-case
  version of the netid. This constant name should be a
  constant that is valid in the 'C' programming language.
  This constant name MUST NOT conflict with any other netid
  constant name.  Constant names with the prefix "NC_STDS",
  "NC_FCFS", "NC_PRIV", "NC_EXPE", and "NC_ICMP" are Reserved.  Constant
  names with a prefix of "NC_" and a total length of 11
  characters or less should be for assignments made on the
  Standards Action basis. The constant "NC_" is Reserved. The constant
  name can be 1 to 131 octets long.

    <vspace blankLines='1' />
   Given the typical derivation of the constant name from the netid,
   the registration of the constant might be considered redundant.
   This is not always true. For example, a netid might use a
   character that is not valid in the programming language. The first
   entry of <xref target="fcfs_netids"/> provides such an example.
   


</t>

<t>
  A description and/or a reference to a description of 
  how the netid will be used.  For assignments made on a
  First Come First Served basis, the description should
  include, if applicable, a reference to the transport and
  network protocols corresponding to the netid.  For
  assignments made on a Standards Action basis, the
  description field must include the RFC numbers of the
  protocol associated with the netid, including, if
  applicable, RFC numbers of the transport and network
  protocols.

</t>

<t>
  A point of contact of the registrant.
  For assignments made on a First Come First
  Served basis: <list style="symbols">

  <t>the point of contact should include an email address.</t>

  <t>subject to authorization by a Designated
  Expert, the point of contact may be omitted for
  extraordinary situations, such as the registration of a
  commonly used netid where the owner is unknown.</t></list>  

For assignments made on a Standards Action basis, the point of
  contact is always determined by IESG.
</t>

<t>
  A numerical value, used to cross reference the netid
  assignment with an assignment in the uaddr format
  registry (see <xref target="ianauaddrs"/>). If the
  registrant is registering a netid that cross references an
  existing assignment in the uaddr format registry, then
  the registrant provides the actual value of the cross
  reference along with the date the registrant retrieved
  the cross reference value from the uaddr format registry.
  If the registrant is registering both a new netid and new
  uaddr format, then the registrant provides a value of
  TBD1 in the netid request, and uses TBD1 in the uaddr
  format request. IANA will then substitute TBD1 for the cross 
  reference number IANA allocates.
  Note that if a document requests multiple netid
  and uaddr assignments, each additional uaddr format cross reference will
  be identified as TBD2, TBD3, ..., etc.
</t>

</list>
</t>

<section title="Initial Registry">
<t>
  The initial list of netids is broken into two subregistries:
  those assigned on a First Come First Served basis in <xref
  target="fcfs_netids"/> and those assigned on a Standards
  Action basis in <xref target="rfc_netids"/>.
  These lists will change as IANA registers additional
  netids as needed, and the authoritative list of
  registered netids will always live with IANA.

</t>
<texttable title="Initial First Come First Served Netid Assignments" anchor='fcfs_netids'>

<ttcol>Netid</ttcol>
<ttcol>Constant Name</ttcol>
<ttcol>Description and/or Reference</ttcol>
<ttcol>PoC</ttcol>
<ttcol>CR</ttcol>

<c>
"-"
</c>
<c>
NC_NOPROTO 
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC1833">RFC1833</xref>,
<xref target="noproto_fmt"/> of RFC 5665
</c>
<c></c>
<c>1</c>

<c>
"ticlts"
</c>
<c>
NC_TICLTS
</c>
<c>
The loop back connectionless transport used in System V
Release 4 and other operating systems.

Although this assignment is made on a First Come First
Served basis and is fewer than nine characters long, the
exception is authorized.

See <xref target="ti-loop"/>.
</c>
<c>
</c>
<c>
0
</c>

<c>
"ticots" 
</c>
<c>
NC_TICOTS
</c>
<c>
The loop back connection-oriented transport used in System V
Release 4 and other operating systems.

See <xref target="ti-loop"/>.

Although this assignment is made on a First Come First
Served basis and is fewer than nine characters long, the
exception is authorized.

</c>
<c>
</c>
<c>
0
</c>

<c>
"ticotsord" 
</c>
<c>
NC_TICOTSORD
</c>
<c>
The loop back connection-oriented with orderly-release
transport used in System V Release 4 and other operating
systems.

See <xref target="ti-loop"/>.
</c>
<c>
</c>
<c>
0
</c>
</texttable>
<t>PoC: Point of Contact.</t>
<t>CR: Cross Reference to the Uaddr Format Registry.</t>

<texttable title="Initial Standards Action Netid Assignments" anchor='rfc_netids'>

<ttcol>Netid</ttcol>
<ttcol>Constant Name</ttcol>
<ttcol>RFC(s) and Description (if needed)</ttcol>
<ttcol>PoC</ttcol>
<ttcol>CR</ttcol>

<c>
"rdma" 
</c>
<c>
NC_RDMA
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC5666">RFC 5666</xref>,
<xref target="RFC0791">RFC 791</xref>
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>2</c>

<c>
"rdma6" 
</c>
<c>
NC_RDMA6
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC5666">RFC 5666</xref>,
<xref target="RFC2460">RFC 2460</xref>
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>3</c>

<c>
"sctp"
</c>
<c>
NC_SCTP
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC4960">RFC 4960</xref>,
<xref target="RFC0791">RFC 791</xref>,
<xref target="sctp_considerations"/> of RFC 5665
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>2</c>

<c>
"sctp6"
</c>
<c>
NC_SCTP6
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC4960">RFC 4960</xref>,
<xref target="RFC2460">RFC 2460</xref>,
<xref target="sctp_considerations"/> of RFC 5665
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>3</c>

<c>
"tcp" 
</c>
<c>
NC_TCP
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC0793">RFC 793</xref>,
<xref target="RFC0791">RFC 791</xref>,
Section 11 of <xref target="RFC5531">RFC 5531</xref>
<!-- [rfced] The IANA site lists RFC 1831 as the reference here.
Should this be updated to reflect RFC 5531 (where Section 10 is
"Authentication Protocols"), as this was a reference to
1831bis? 
[Eisler] Yes, IANA and this RFC should reference RFC 5531. In addition,
         the section number is now "Section 11" (The Record Marking
         Standard). I've made the edit.   -->

</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>2</c>

<c>
"tcp6" 
</c>
<c>
NC_TCP6
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC0793">RFC 793</xref>,
<xref target="RFC2460">RFC 2460</xref>,
Section 11 of <xref target="RFC5531">RFC 5531</xref>
<!-- [rfced] The IANA site lists RFC 1831 as the reference here.
Should this be updated to reflect RFC 5531 (where Section 10 is
"Authentication Protocols"), as this was a reference to
1831bis? 

   [Eisler] Yes same issue as the previous [rfced] and same resolution. -->

</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>3</c>

<c>
"udp" 
</c>
<c>
NC_UDP
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC0768">RFC 768</xref>,
<xref target="RFC0791">RFC 791</xref>
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>2</c>

<c>
"udp6" 
</c>
<c>
NC_UDP6
</c>
<c>
<xref target="RFC0768">RFC 768</xref>,
<xref target="RFC2460">RFC 2460</xref>
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>3</c>

</texttable>

</section>

<section title="Updating Registrations">
<t>
Per Section 5.2 of RFC 5226, the registrant
is always permitted to update a registration made
on a First Come First Served basis "subject to the same
constraints and review as with new registrations". The IESG or
a Designated Expert is permitted to update any registration
made on a First Come First Served basis, which normally is
done when the PoC cannot be reached in order to make
necessary updates. Examples where an update would be needed
include, but are not limited to: the email address or
other contact information becomes invalid; the reference to
the corresponding protocol becomes obsolete or unavailable;
RFC 1833 is updated or replaced in such a way that the scope of netids changes,
requiring additional fields in the assignment.
</t>

<t>
Only the IESG, on the advice of a Designated Expert, can update
a registration made on a Standards Action basis.
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor="ianauaddrs" title="IANA Considerations for Uaddr Formats">
<t>
IANA has created a registry called "ONC RPC Uaddr Format Registry"
(called the "format registry" for the remainder of this
document).

The remainder of this section describes the registry.

</t>

<t>
All assignments to the format registry are made on one of two bases:
<list style='symbols'>
<t>
First Come First Served basis
per Section 4.1 of RFC 5226. 
</t>
<t>
Standards Action
per Section 4.1 of RFC 5226.
</t>
</list>

</t>

<t>
The registry of formats
is a list of assignments, each containing four fields for
each assignment.

<list style='numbers'>
<t>
  The basis for the assignment, which can be either FCFS for First Come First
  Served assignments or STDS for Standards Action assignments.
</t>
<t>
  A description and/or reference to a description of the
  actual uaddr format.
  Assignments made on a Standards
  Action basis always have a reference to an RFC.

</t>

<t>
  For assignments made on a First Come First Served basis,
  a point of contact, including an email address.
  Subject to authorization by a Designated Expert, the
  point of contact may be omitted for extraordinary
  situations, such as the registration of a commonly used
  format where the owner is unknown.
  For assignments made on a Standards Action basis, the point of contact
  is always determined by the IESG.

</t>
<t>
  A numerical value, used to cross reference the format
  assignment with an assignment in the netid
  registry. The registrant provides a value of TBD1 for the cross reference
  field when requesting an assignment. IANA will assign TBD1 to a real value.
  Note that if a document requests multiple
  uaddr assignments, each additional uaddr format cross reference will
  be identified as TBD2, TBD3, ..., etc.
</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>
All requests for assignments to the format registry on a Standards Action
basis are only for Standards Track RFCs approved by the IESG.

</t>
<section title="Initial Registry">
<t>
  The initial list of formats is in <xref target="formats"/>.
  This list will change as IANA registers additional
  formats as needed, and the authoritative list of
  registered formats will always live with IANA.

</t>
<texttable anchor='formats' title="Initial Format Assignments">

<ttcol>Basis</ttcol>
<ttcol>Description and/or Reference</ttcol>
<ttcol>PoC</ttcol>
<ttcol>CR</ttcol>

<c>
FCFS
</c>
<c>
System V Release 4 loopback transport uaddr format. <xref target="loopback_fmt"/> of RFC 5665
</c>
<c>
</c>
<c>
0
</c>

<c>
FCFS
</c>
<c>
Uaddr format for NC_NOPROTO. <xref target="noproto_fmt"/> of RFC 5665
</c>
<c>
</c>
<c>
1
</c>

<c>
STDS
</c>
<c>
Uaddr format for IPv4 transports. <xref target="xprt_ip4_fmt"/> of RFC
5665
</c>
<c>
IESG
</c>
<c>
2
</c>

<c>
STDS
</c>
<c>
Uaddr format for IPv6 transports. <xref target="xprt_ip6_fmt"/> of RFC
5665
</c>
<c>IESG</c>
<c>
3
</c>

</texttable>

</section>

<section title="Updating Registrations">
<t>
The registrant is always permitted to update a registration
made on a First Come First Served basis "subject to the
same constraints and review as with new registrations."
The IESG is permitted to update any
registration made on a First Come First Served basis, which
normally is done when the PoC cannot be reached in order to
make necessary updates. Examples where an update would be
needed include, but are not limited to: the email address
or other contact information becomes invalid; the reference
to the format description becomes obsolete or unavailable;
RFC 1833 is updated or replaced in such a way that the scope of uaddr formats
changes, requiring additional fields in the assignment.

</t>

<t>
Only the IESG, on the advice of a Designated Expert, can update
a registration made on a Standards Action basis.

</t>

</section>

<section title="Uaddr Formats">

<section title="Uaddr Format for System V Release 4 Loopback Transports" anchor="loopback_fmt">
<t>
 Although RFC 1833 specifies the uaddr
as the XDR data type string (hence, limited to US-ASCII),
implementations of the System V Release 4 loopback
transports will use an opaque string of octets. Thus, the format of a 
loopback transport address is any non-zero length array of octets.
</t>

</section>


<section title='Uaddr Format for Netid "-"' anchor="noproto_fmt">
<t>
  There is no address format for netid "-". This netid is apparently
  for internal use for supporting some implementations of RFC 1833.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="xprt_ip4_fmt" title="Uaddr Format for Most IPv4 Transports">
       <t>
	Most transport protocols that operate over IPv4
	use 16-bit port numbers, including
        <xref target="RFC5666">RDMA</xref>,
        <xref target="RFC4960">SCTP</xref>,
	<xref target="RFC0793">TCP</xref>,
	and
	<xref target="RFC0768">UDP</xref>.
        The format of the uaddr
	for the above 16-bit port transports (when used over IPv4) is the
	US-ASCII string:

        <list style="empty">
	      <t>
		h1.h2.h3.h4.p1.p2
	      </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The prefix "h1.h2.h3.h4" is the standard textual form for
        representing an IPv4 address, which is always four octets
        long.  Assuming big-endian ordering, h1, h2, h3, and h4 are,
        respectively, the first through fourth octets each converted
        to ASCII-decimal.  The suffix "p1.p2" is a textual form for
        representing a service port.
        Assuming big-endian ordering, p1 and p2
        are, respectively, the first and second octets each converted
	to ASCII-decimal. For example, if a host, in
	big-endian order, has an address in hexadecimal of
	0xC0000207 and there is a service listening on, in
	big-endian order, port 0xCB51 (decimal 52049), then
	the complete uaddr is "192.0.2.7.203.81".

      </t>

</section>

<section anchor="xprt_ip6_fmt" title="Uaddr Format for Most IPv6 Transports">
       <t>
	Most transport protocols that operate over IPv6
	use 16-bit port numbers, including 
        <xref target="RFC5666">RDMA</xref>,
        <xref target="RFC4960">SCTP</xref>,
	<xref target="RFC0793">TCP</xref>,
	and
	<xref target="RFC0768">UDP</xref>.
        The format of the uaddr
	for the above 16-bit port transports (when used over IPv6) is the
	US-ASCII string:
        <list style="empty">

	      <t>
		x1:x2:x3:x4:x5:x6:x7:x8.p1.p2
	      </t>
        </list>

      </t>
      <t>
        The suffix "p1.p2" is the service port, and is computed the
        same way as with uaddrs for transports over IPv4 (see
        <xref target="xprt_ip4_fmt"/>).
        The prefix "x1:x2:x3:x4:x5:x6:x7:x8" is the preferred
        textual form for representing an IPv6 address as defined in
        Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC4291">RFC 4291</xref>.
        Additionally, the two alternative forms specified in Section
        2.2 of RFC 4291 are also acceptable.
      </t>
      </section>

<section title="Uaddr Format for ICMP over IPv4 and IPv6" anchor="icmp_fmt">
<t>
  As ICMP is not a true transport, there is no uaddr
  format for ICMP.  The netid assignments "icmp" and "icmp6" and their
  shared uaddr "format" are listed to prevent any registrant from allocating the
  netids "icmp" and "icmp6" for a purpose that would likely cause confusion.

</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>


<section title="Cross Referencing between the Netid and Format Registry" anchor="crossref">

<t>
The last field of the netids registry is used to cross reference with the last field of
the format registry. IANA is under no obligation to
maintain the same numeric values in cross references when updating each registry;
i.e., IANA is free to "re-number" these corresponding fields.
However, if IANA does so, both the netid and format registries must be updated atomically.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Port Assignment for NFS over SCTP">
<t>
Port 2049 is assigned to NFS over SCTP for the sctp and sctp6 netids.
</t>
</section>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">

    <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
      <front>
	<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
	<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
	  <organization>Harvard University</organization>
	  <address>
	    <postal>
	      <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
	      <street>Cambridge</street>
	    <street>MA 02138</street></postal>
	    <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
	<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
	<date year='1997' month='March' />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
      <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
      <format type='TXT' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt' />
    </reference>

    <reference anchor='RFC1833'>

    <front>
    <title>Binding Protocols for ONC RPC Version 2</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Srinivasan' fullname='Raj Srinivasan'>
    <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc., ONC Technologies</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>2550 Garcia Avenue</street>
    <street>M/S MTV-5-40</street>
    <city>Mountain View</city>
    <region>CA</region>
    <code>94043</code>
    <country>US</country></postal>
    <phone>+1 415 336 2478</phone>
    <facsimile>+1 415 336 6015</facsimile>
    <email>raj@eng.sun.com</email></address></author>
    <date year='1995' month='August' />
    <abstract>
    <t>This document describes the binding protocols used in conjunction with the ON
    C Remote Procedure Call (ONC RPC Version 2) protocols.</t></abstract></front>

    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1833' />
    <format type='TXT' octets='24449' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc1833.txt
    ' />
    </reference>



<reference anchor='RFC4291'>

<front>
<title>IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Hinden' fullname='R. Hinden'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Deering' fullname='S. Deering'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='February' />
<abstract>
<t>This specification defines the addressing architecture
of the IP Version 6 (IPv6) protocol. The document includes
the IPv6 addressing model, text representations of IPv6
addresses, definition of IPv6 unicast addresses, anycast
addresses, and multicast addresses, and an IPv6 node's
required addresses. This document obsoletes
RFC 3513, "IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture".
[STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>


<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4291' />
<format type='TXT' octets='52897' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4291.txt' />
</reference>

  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">

   <reference anchor='RFC5226'>

   <front>
   <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
   <author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'>
   <organization /></author>
   <author initials='H.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='H. Alvestrand'>
   <organization /></author>
   <date year='2008' month='May' />
   <abstract>
   <t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants and other well-known values. Even after a protocol has been defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or authentication transform for IPsec). To ensure that such quantities have consistent values and interpretations across all implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central authority. For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).&lt;/t>&lt;t> In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made. If IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace, IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that role. This document discusses issues that should be considered in formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and provides guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be included in documents that place demands on IANA.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This document obsoletes RFC 2434. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

   <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='26' />
   <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5226' />
   <format type='TXT' octets='66160' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5226.txt' />
   </reference>



<reference anchor='RFC5531'>

<front>
<title>RPC: Remote Procedure Call Protocol Specification Version
2</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Thurlow' fullname='R. Thurlow'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the Open Network Computing (ONC) Remote
Procedure Call (RPC) version 2 protocol as it is currently deployed
and accepted.  This document obsoletes RFC 1831. [STANDARDS
TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5531' />
<format type='TXT' octets='161720'
target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5531.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="RFC0793">
<front>
<title abbrev="Transmission Control Protocol">Transmission Control Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
<organization>
University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences Institute
</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
<city>Marina del Rey</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>90291</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
</address>
</author>
<date year="1981" day="1" month="September"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="STD" value="7"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="793"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="172710" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc793.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC0768">
<front>
<title>User Datagram Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
<organization>
University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences Institute
</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
<city>Marina del Rey</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>90291</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
</address>
</author>
<date year="1980" day="28" month="August"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="STD" value="6"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="768"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="5896" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc768.txt"/>
</reference>



<reference anchor="RFC5666">
<front>
<title>
Remote Direct Memory Access Transport for Remote Procedure Call
</title>
<author initials="T" surname="Talpey" fullname="Thomas  Talpey">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="B" surname="Callaghan" fullname="Brent Callaghan">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="January" year="2010"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5666"/>
<format type="TXT" />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC3530'>

<front>
<title>Network File System (NFS) version 4 Protocol</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Shepler' fullname='S. Shepler'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Callaghan' fullname='B. Callaghan'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Robinson' fullname='D. Robinson'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Thurlow' fullname='R. Thurlow'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Beame' fullname='C. Beame'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Eisler' fullname='M. Eisler'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Noveck' fullname='D. Noveck'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='April' />
<abstract>
<t>The Network File System (NFS) version 4 is a distributed filesystem protocol which owes heritage to NFS protocol version 2, RFC 1094, and version 3, RFC 1813.  Unlike earlier versions, the NFS version 4 protocol supports traditional file access while integrating support for file locking and the mount protocol.  In addition, support for strong security (and its negotiation), compound operations, client caching, and internationalization have been added.  Of course, attention has been applied to making NFS version 4 operate well in an Internet environment.  This document replaces RFC 3010 as the definition of the NFS version 4 protocol. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3530' />
<format type='TXT' octets='600988' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3530.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC0791">
<front>
<title abbrev="Internet Protocol">Internet Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
<organization>
University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences Institute
</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
<city>Marina del Rey</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>90291</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
</address>
</author>
<date year="1981" day="1" month="September"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="STD" value="5"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="791"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="97779" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc791.txt"/>
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC2460'>

<front>
<title abbrev='IPv6 Specification'>Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) Specification</title>
<author initials='S.E.' surname='Deering' fullname='Stephen E. Deering'>
<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<street>San Jose</street>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134-1706</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 408 527 8213</phone>
<facsimile>+1 408 527 8254</facsimile>
<email>deering@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='R.M.' surname='Hinden' fullname='Robert M. Hinden'>
<organization>Nokia</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>232 Java Drive</street>
<street>Sunnyvale</street>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94089</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 408 990 2004</phone>
<facsimile>+1 408 743 5677</facsimile>
<email>hinden@iprg.nokia.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1998' month='December' />
<area>Internet</area>
<keyword>internet protocol version 6</keyword>
<keyword>IPv6</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   This document specifies version 6 of the Internet Protocol (IPv6),
   also sometimes referred to as IP Next Generation or IPng.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2460' />
<format type='TXT' octets='85490' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2460.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='99496' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2460.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='93343' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2460.xml' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC0792">
<front>
<title>Internet Control Message Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
<organization>
University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences Institute
</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
<city>Marina del Rey</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>90291</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
</address>
</author>
<date year="1981" day="1" month="September"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="STD" value="5"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="792"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="30404" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc792.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4960'>

<front>
<title>Stream Control Transmission Protocol</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Stewart' fullname='R. Stewart' role='editor'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2007' month='September' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP). [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4960' />
<format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4960.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='ti-loop'>

<front>
<title>UNIX System V, Release 4 Programmer's Guide: Networking Interfaces, ISBN 0139470786</title>


<author fullname='American Telephone and Telegraph Company'>
<organization>American Telephone and Telegraph Company</organization>
</author>
<date year='1990' /></front>


</reference>
  </references>
<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments" >
<t>

Lisa Dusseault, Lars Eggert, Pasi Eronen, Tim Polk, Juergen Schoenwaelder, and Robert Sparks
reviewed the document and gave valuable feedback.

</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
