<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3032 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3032.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3270 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3270.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5129 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5129.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3272 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3272.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3443 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3443.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3469 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3469.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3564 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3564.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3985 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3985.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4182 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4182.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4364 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4379 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4379.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4448 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4448.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4761 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4761.xml">]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" number="5462" 
updates="3032, 3270, 3272, 3443, 3469, 3564,
	 3985, 4182, 4364, 4379, 4448, 4761, 5129">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS TC Field Definition">Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Stack Entry: "EXP"&nbsp;Field&nbsp;Renamed&nbsp;to&nbsp;"Traffic&nbsp;Class"&nbsp;Field</title>

    <author fullname="Loa Andersson"
            initials="L"
            surname="Andersson">
      <organization>Acreo AB</organization>

      <address>
        <email>loa@pi.nu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rajiv Asati"
            initials="R"
            surname="Asati">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>rajiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date month="January" year="2009" />


<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
    the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
      The early Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) documents defined the 
      form of the MPLS label stack entry.
      This includes a three-bit field called the "EXP 
      field".  The exact use of this 
      field was not defined by these documents, except to state that it was 
      to be "reserved for experimental use".
      </t>
      
      <t>
      Although the intended use of the EXP field was as a "Class of Service"
      (CoS) field, it was not named a CoS field by these 
      early documents because the use of such a CoS field was not considered 
      to be sufficiently defined. Today a number of standards documents define 
      its usage as a CoS field.
      </t>
      
      <t>
      To avoid misunderstanding about how this field may be used, it has become
      increasingly necessary to rename this field. This
      document changes the name of the field to the "Traffic Class field" ("TC
      field").  In doing
      so, it also updates documents that define the current use of the EXP
      field. 
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!-- section 1 -->

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
      The format of an MPLS label stack entry is defined by <xref
      target="RFC3032">RFC 3032</xref> to
      include a three-bit field called the "EXP field". The exact use of this 
      field is not defined by RFC 3032, except to state 
      that it is to be "reserved for experimental use".
      </t>
      
      <t>
      The EXP field, from the start, was intended to carry "Class of Service" 
      (CoS) information. The field was actually called the 
      "Class of Service field" in 
      early versions of the working group document that was published as 
      RFC 3032. However, at the time that RFC 3032 was published, the exact 
      usage of this 
      "Class of Service" field was not agreed upon and the field was designated 
      as "experimental use"; hence, the name has since been the "EXP field".
      </t>
      
      <t>
      The designation "for experimental use" has led other Standards
      Development Organizations (SDOs) and implementors to assume that
      it is possible to use the field for other purposes. This 
      document changes the name of the field to clearly indicate its use as
      a traffic classification field.
      </t>
      
      <t>
      At first, we discussed using the original "CoS field" as the name for
      the field, but it has been pointed out that this name does not cover 
      the following changes that have occurred with respect to its usage since RFC 3032 was 
      published.
          
      <list style="numbers">
      <t>
      The use of the EXP field was first defined in RFC 3270 [RFC3270],
      where a method to define a variant of Diffserv Label Switched Paths (LSP),
      called EXP-Inferred-PSC LSP (E-LSPs), was specified. PSC is a two-stage
      acronym that is expanded as PHB (Per Hop Behavior) Scheduling
      Class (PSC).
      </t>
      
      <t>
      The use of the EXP field as defined in RFC 3270 has been further
      extended in RFC 5129 [RFC5129], where methods for explicit congestion
      marking in MPLS are defined.
      </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>
      
      This document, hence, uses the name "Traffic Class field (TC field)",
      which better covers the potential use. The MPLS TC field relates to 
      an MPLS encapsulated packet the same way as the IPv6 TC field relates
      to an IPv6 encapsulated packet or the IPv4 Precedence field relates 
      to an IPv4 encapsulated packet.
      </t>
      
      <t>
      The definitions of how the EXP field is used are perfectly clear in
      RFC 3270 and RFC 5129.  However, these RFCs do not explicitly state
      they update RFC 3032, and this fact was not captured in the RFC
      repository until after work on this document was started.</t>

      <t>
      This document updates RFC 3032, RFC 3270, and RFC 5129
      to clarify the intended usage of the TC field. The changes to these RFCs requires some
      changes to the actual text in those
      documents; <xref target="chng"></xref> explains the changes.
      </t>

      <t>
      This document also updates several other RFCs; see
      <xref target="scope"></xref>. For these documents, the change is limited
      to changing the name of the Label Stack entry field.
      </t>

      <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
      </t>
      
    </section>

    <!-- end section 1 -->

   
    <!-- section 2 -->
    
    <section anchor="chng" title="Details of Change">
    <t>
    The three RFCs 3032, 3270, and 5129 are now updated according to the following.
    </t>
    
    <section anchor="3032" title="RFC 3032">
    <t>
    RFC 3032 states on page 4:
    <list>
    <t>
    3. Experimental Use
    </t>

    
    <t>
    This three-bit field is reserved for experimental use.
    </t>
    
    </list>

    </t>
    
    <t>
    This paragraph is now changed to:
    
     <list>
    <t>
    3. Traffic Class  (TC) field
    </t>
    
    <t>
    This three-bit field is used to carry Traffic Class information,
    and 
<!-- [rfced] Since the above "Traffic Class" is specifying the information
    type rather than the field name, should it be lowercase? -->

    the change of the name is applicable to all places it occurs in IETF RFCs
    and other IETF documents.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    RFC 3270 and RFC 5129 update the definition of the TC field and describe
    how to use the field.
    </t>
    
    </list>
    
    </t>
    
    <t>
    In Figure 1 on page 3 in RFC 3032, the format of a label stack entry is 
    specified as:

        <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Label
|                Label                  | Exp |S|       TTL     | Stack
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Entry

                    Label:  Label Value, 20 bits
                    Exp:    Experimental Use, 3 bits
                    S:      Bottom of Stack, 1 bit
                    TTL:    Time to Live, 8 bits
		    
		             Figure 1
             ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>
    Figure 1 in RFC 3032 is now changed to match the change of name to TC 
    field:

        <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Label
|                Label                  | TC  |S|       TTL     | Stack
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ Entry

                    Label:  Label Value, 20 bits
                    CoS:    Traffic Class field, 3 bits
                    S:      Bottom of Stack, 1 bit
                    TTL:    Time to Live, 8 bits

		              Figure 1 (new)
             ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
<!-- [rfced] Should the above CoS be instead TC? Or should the TC in
the figure be changed to CoS? -->      
    </t>

    <t>
    Note: The designation of the picture above as "Figure 1 (new)" is introduced
    as a way to distinguish the figures in this document. It will still be 
    "Figure 1" in RFC 3032.
    </t>
    </section>
    <!-- end section 2.1 -->
    
    <!-- section 2.2 -->
    
    <section anchor="3270" title="RFC 3270">
 
    <t>
    RFC 3270 says on page 6:
    </t>
    
    <t>
    1.2 EXP-Inferred-PSC LSPs (E-LSP)
    <list>
    <t>
    A single LSP can be used to support one or more OAs.  Such LSPs can
    support up to eight BAs of a given FEC, regardless of how many OAs
    these BAs span.  With such LSPs, the EXP field of the MPLS Shim
    Header is used by the LSR to determine the PHB to be applied to the
    packet.  This includes both the PSC and the drop preference.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    We refer to such LSPs as "EXP-inferred-PSC LSPs" (E-LSP), since the
    PSC of a packet transported on this LSP depends on the EXP field
    value for that packet.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The mapping from the EXP field to the PHB (i.e., to PSC and drop
    precedence) for a given such LSP, is either explicitly signaled at
    label set-up or relies on a pre-configured mapping.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Detailed operations of E-LSPs are specified in section 3 below.
    </t>
    </list>
   
    </t>
    <t>
    RFC 3270 is now updated like this:
    </t>
    <t>
    <list style="letters">
       <t>
       A new paragraph is added at the end of Section 1 "Introduction":
          <list style="empty">
          <t>
            The EXP field has been renamed the TC field, and thus all
            references in RFC 3270 to the EXP field now refer to
            the TC field.
          </t>
          </list>
       </t>

       <t>
       A new term is added to Section 1.1 "Terminology":
          <list style="empty">
          <t>
          TC&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Traffic Class (replaces the term EXP)
          </t>
          </list>
       </t>
       <t>
       In section 1.1 "Terminology", the acronym E-LSP is now understood to
       mean:
          <list style="empty">
         <t>
         E-LSP&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSP
         </t>
        </list>
       </t>
    </list>
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Section 1.2 on page 6 in RFC 3270 is now changed to:
    </t>
    <t>
    1.2 Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSPs (E-LSP)
    <list>
    
    <t>
    The EXP field has been renamed to the TC field, and thus all references 
    in RFC 3270 to EXP field now refer to the TC field. 
    However, we retain the acronym E-LSP (Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSP) as
    the acronym is in widespread use. 
    </t>
    <t>
    A single LSP can be used to support one or more OAs.  Such LSPs can
    support up to eight BAs of a given FEC, regardless of how many OAs
    these BAs span.  With such LSPs, the TC field of the MPLS Shim
    Header is used by the LSR to determine the PHB to be applied to the
    packet.  This includes both the PSC and the drop preference.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    We refer to such LSPs as "Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSPs" (E-LSPs), since the
    PSC of a packet transported on this LSP depends on the TC field
    (previously called the EXP field) value for that packet.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The mapping from the TC field to the PHB (i.e., to PSC and drop
    precedence) for a given such LSP is either explicitly signaled at
    label set-up or relies on a pre-configured mapping.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    This is an update to <xref target="RFC3032">RFC 3032</xref>, in line with
    the original intent of how this field in the MPLS Shim Header should be 
    used (as a TC field). RFC 3270 has 
    itself been updated by <xref target="RFC5129">RFC 5129</xref>.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Detailed operations of E-LSPs are specified in Section 3 of RFC 3270.
    </t>
    </list>
   
    </t>
    
    </section>
    <!-- end section 2.2 -->
    
    <section anchor="5129" title="RFC 5129">
    
    <t>
    RFC 5129 is now updated like this:
    </t>
        
    <t>
    A new paragraph is added at the end of Section 1.1 "Background":
    <list>
    <t>
    The EXP field has been renamed to the TC field, 
    and thus all references in RFC 5129 to the EXP field now 
    refer to the TC field.
    </t>
    </list>
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Section 2 (bullet 5) on page 7 of RFC 5129 says:
    </t>
    
    <t>
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      A third possible approach was suggested by [Shayman].  In this
      scheme, interior LSRs assume that the endpoints are ECN-capable,
      but this assumption is checked when the final label is popped.  If
      an interior LSR has marked ECN in the EXP field of the shim
      header, but the IP header says the endpoints are not ECN-capable,
      the edge router (or penultimate router, if using penultimate hop
      popping) drops the packet.  We recommend this scheme, which we
      call `per-domain ECT checking', and define it more precisely in
      the following section.  Its chief drawback is that it can cause
      packets to be forwarded after encountering congestion only to be
      dropped at the egress of the MPLS domain.  The rationale for this
      decision is given in Section 8.1.
    </t>
    </list>    
    
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Section 2 (bullet 5) of RFC 5129 is now updated to:
    </t>
    
    <t>
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>
      A third possible approach was suggested by [Shayman].  In this
      scheme, interior LSRs assume that the endpoints are ECN-capable,
      but this assumption is checked when the final label is popped.  If
      an interior LSR has marked ECN in the TC field of the shim
      header, but the IP header says the endpoints are not TC-capable,
      the edge router (or penultimate router, if using penultimate hop
      popping) drops the packet.  We recommend this scheme, which we
      call `per-domain ECT checking', and define it more precisely in
      the following section.  Its chief drawback is that it can cause
      packets to be forwarded after encountering congestion only to be
      dropped at the egress of the MPLS domain.  The rationale for this
      decision is given in Section 8.1. This scheme is an update to <xref 
      target="RFC3032">RFC 3032</xref> and 
      <xref target="RFC3270">RFC 3270</xref>.
    </t>
    </list>    
    
    </t>
       
    
    </section>
    
    <!-- end section 2.3 -->
    
    <!-- section 2.4 -->
    
     
    <section anchor="scope" title="The Scope of This Change">
    
    <t>
    There are several places in the RFCs that are explicitly updated by this
    document that reference the "Exp field", sometimes they refer to the field
     as "Exp bits", "EXP bits", or "EXP". In all those instances, the references
     now reference the TC field.
    </t>

    <t>
    There are also other RFCs, e.g., <xref target="RFC3272">RFC 3272</xref>,
    <xref target="RFC3443">RFC 3443</xref>, <xref target="RFC3469">RFC 3469</xref>, 
    <xref target="RFC3564">RFC 3564</xref>, <xref target="RFC3985">RFC 3985</xref>, 
    <xref target="RFC4182">RFC 4182</xref>, <xref target="RFC4364">RFC 4364</xref>, 
    <xref target="RFC4379">RFC 4379</xref>, <xref target="RFC4448">RFC 4448</xref>,
    and <xref target="RFC4761">RFC 4761 </xref>
    that reference the "Exp field"; sometimes they refer to the field
    as "Exp bits", "EXP bits", and "EXP". For all RFCs, including but not 
    limited to those mentioned in this paragraph, such references now reference the TC field.
    </t>
        
    </section>
    
    <!-- end section 2.4 -->

    </section>
    
    <!-- end section 2 -->
    
    <!-- section 3 -->
    
    <section anchor="rules" title="Use of the TC field">
    
    <t>
    Due to the limited number of bits in the TC field, their use for QoS
    and ECN (Explicit Congestion Notification) functions is intended
    to be flexible. These functions may rewrite all or some of the bits in the TC field.   
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Current implementations look at the TC field with and without label context,
    and the TC field may be copied to the label stack entries that are 
    pushed onto the
    label stack.  This is done to avoid label stack entries that are pushed
    onto an existing label stack having different TC fields from the rest of
    the label stack entries.
    </t>

    </section>
    <!-- end of section 3 -->
    
     <!-- section 5 -->
    
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    
    <t>
    This document only changes the name of one field in the MPLS Shim
    Header, and thus does not introduce any new security
    considerations.

<!-- [rfced] Please note that RFC 3270 is the only RFC (going back to
    RFC 2000) that capitalizes Shim Header. We have left it
    capitalized in portions of this document that update and quote RFC
    3270, but recommend lower-casing it here. -->
    </t>
    
    
    </section>
    <!-- end of section  -->
        
    <!-- section 6 -->
    
    <section anchor="acknowledgmetns" title="Acknowledgments">
    
    <t>
    The authors would like to thank Stewart Bryant, Bruce Davie, George
    Swallow, and Francois Le Faucheur for their input to and review
    of the current document.
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The authors would also like to thank George Swallow, Khatri Paresh, and Phil
    Bedard for their help with grammar and spelling; a special thanks to
    Adrian Farrel for his careful review and help trawling the RFC-sea for 
    RFCs that reference the EXP field.
    </t>
    
    </section>
    <!-- end of section  -->    
    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--references title="References" -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3032;
      &rfc3270;
      &rfc5129;
      &rfc3272;
      &rfc3443;
      &rfc3469;
      &rfc3564;
      &rfc3985;
      &rfc4182;
      &rfc4364;
      &rfc4379;
      &rfc4448;
      &rfc4761;
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
    
          <reference anchor="Shayman">
        <front>
          <title>Using ECN to Signal
                 Congestion Within an MPLS Domain</title>

          <author initials="M" surname="Shayman"
                 fullname="M. Shayman">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R" surname="Jaeger" fullname="R. Jaeger">
             <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2000">
          </date>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
