<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="5497" category="std">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Time TLV">Representing Multi-Value Time in Mobile Ad Hoc Networks (MANETs)</title>

    <author initials="T.H." surname="Clausen" fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen">
      <organization abbrev="LIX, Ecole Polytechnique">LIX, Ecole Polytechnique, France</organization>
      <address>
         <phone>+33 6 6058 9349</phone>
         <email>T.Clausen@computer.org</email>
         <uri>http://www.ThomasClausen.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="C.M." surname="Dearlove" fullname="Christopher Dearlove">
      <organization abbrev="BAE Systems ATC">BAE Systems Advanced Technology Centre</organization>
      <address>
         <phone>+44 1245 242194</phone>
         <email>chris.dearlove@baesystems.com</email>
         <uri>http://www.baesystems.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month='March' year='2009'/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Mobile Ad hoc Networking (MANET)</workgroup>

    <keyword>Routing Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>TLV</keyword>
    <keyword>Fisheye</keyword>
    <keyword>FSR</keyword>
    <keyword>Fuzzy-Sighted</keyword>
    <keyword>Hazy-Sighted</keyword>
    <keyword>extension</keyword>
    <keyword>packetbb</keyword>
    <keyword>RFC5444</keyword>

<note title="">
<t>
This document may contain material from IETF Documents or IETF
Contributions published or made publicly available before November 10,
2008.  The person(s) controlling the copyright in some of this material
may not have granted the IETF Trust the right to allow modifications
of such material outside the IETF Standards Process.  Without
obtaining an adequate license from the person(s) controlling the
copyright in such materials, this document may not be modified outside
the IETF Standards Process, and derivative works of it may not be
created outside the IETF Standards Process, except to format it for
publication as an RFC or to translate it into languages other than
English. 
</t>
</note>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	  This document describes a general and flexible TLV
        (type-length-value structure) for representing time-values, such as an
        interval or a duration, using the generalized Mobile Ad hoc NETwork (MANET)
        packet/message format. It defines two Message TLVs and two Address Block
        TLVs for representing validity and interval times for MANET routing protocols.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    </front>

    <middle>

<section anchor='introduction' title='Introduction'>

  <t>
    The generalized packet/message format <xref target="RFC5444"/>
    specifies a signaling format that MANET routing protocols can
    employ for exchanging protocol information. This format presents
    the ability to express and associate attributes to packets,
    messages, or addresses, by way of a general TLV (type-length-value)
    mechanism.
  </t>

  <t>
    This document specifies a general Time TLV structure, which can
    be used by any MANET routing protocol that needs to express
    either single time-values or a set of time-values with each time-value
    associated with a range of hop counts, as provided by the Message Header
    of <xref target="RFC5444"/>. This allows a receiving node to determine
    a single time-value if either it knows its hop count from the originator
    node or the Time TLV specifies a single time-value.
  </t>
  <t>
    A time-value is, in this context, not an "absolute point in time",
    but rather an interval or a duration. An instance of a Time TLV can,
    therefore, express an interval or a duration such as "10 seconds".
  </t>
  <t>
    This document also specifies two Message TLV Types, which use
    the TLV structure proposed. These TLV Types are INTERVAL_TIME
    and VALIDITY_TIME, specifying, respectively, the maximum time before
    another message of the same type as this message from the same
    originator should be received, and the duration for which the
    information in this message is valid after receipt. Note that,
    if both are present, then the latter will usually be greater
    than the former in order to allow for possible message loss.
  </t>

  <t>
    This document also specifies two Address Block TLV Types, which use
    the TLV structure proposed. These TLV Types are INTERVAL_TIME
    and VALIDITY_TIME, defined equivalently to the two Message TLVs
    with the same names.
  </t>

  <section title="Motivation and Rationale">

    <t>
      The Time TLV structure, specified in this document, is intended to be used
      as a component in a MANET routing protocol, e.g., to indicate the expected
      spacing between successive transmissions of a given Message Type, by
      including a Time TLV in transmitted messages.
    </t>

    <t>
      Some MANET routing protocols may employ very short spacing for some messages
      and very long spacing for others, or may change the message transmission rate
      according to observed behavior. For example, if a network is observed at some
      point in time to exhibit a highly dynamic topology, a very short (sub-second)
      message spacing could be appropriate, whereas if the network later is observed
      to stabilize, multi-hour message spacing may become appropriate. Different
      MANET routing protocols and different deployments of MANET routing protocols
      may have different granularity requirements and bounds on shortest and longest
      spacing between successive message transmissions.
    </t>

    <t>
      In addition, MANET routing protocol deployments typically use bandwidth-limited
      wireless network interfaces, and therefore prefer to trade off computational
      complexity for a saving in the number of bits transmitted. This is practical
      in this case, because the intended usages of Time TLVs, including the specified
      examples of message interval time and information validity time, do not require
      high-precision values of time.
    </t>

    <t>
      The Time TLV structure, specified in this document, caters to these characteristics by:
		
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          encoding time-values, such as an interval or a duration, in an 8-bit field; while
        </t>
        <t>
          allowing these time-values to range from "very small" (e.g., 1/1024 second)
          to "very long" (e.g., 45 days); and
        </t>
        <t>
          allowing a MANET routing protocol, or a deployment, to parameterize this
          (e.g., to attain finer granularity at the expense of a lower upper bound)
          through a single parameter, C.
        </t>
      </list>

    </t>

    <t>
      The parameter C must be the same for all MANET routers in the same deployment.
    </t>
    <t>
      The TLV mechanism as specified in <xref target="RFC5444"/> allows
      associating a "value" to either a packet, a message, or to addresses.
      The data structure for doing so -- the TLV -- is identical in each
      of the three cases; however, the TLV's position in a received packet
      allows determining if that TLV is a "Packet TLV" (it appears in the
      Packet Header, before any messages), a "Message TLV" (it appears in
      the TLV Block immediately following a Message Header), or an
      "Address Block TLV" (it appears in the TLV Block immediately following an
      Address Block).
    </t>

    <t>
      While TLVs may be structurally identical, that which they express may be
      different. This is determined from the kind (packet, message, or Address
      Block) and type of the TLV. For example, one TLV might associate a lifetime
      to an address, another a content sequence number to a message, and another
      a cryptographic signature to a packet. For this reason, <xref target="RFC5444"/>
      specifies separate registries for Packet TLV Types, Message TLV Types, and
      Address Block TLV Types, and it does not specify any structure in the
      TLV Value field.
    </t>

    <t>
      The TLVs defined in this document express, essentially, that "this
      information will be refreshed within X seconds" and that "this
      information is valid for X seconds after being received", each allowing
      the "X seconds" to be specified as a function of the number of hops
      from the originator of the information. This document specifies a
      general format allowing expressing and encoding this as the value
      field of a TLV. This representation uses a compact (8-bit) representation
      of time, as message size is an issue in many MANETs, and the offered
      precision and range is appropriate for MANET routing protocols.
    </t>

    <t>
      A TLV of this format may be used for packets, messages, or addresses.
      For example, a proactive MANET routing protocol periodically reporting
      link-state information could include a TLV of this format as a Message TLV. 
      This may indicate a different periodicity in different scopes (possibly
      frequently up to a few hops, less frequently beyond that) because some
      messages may be sent with limited scope, as specified in
      <xref target="RFC5444"/>. A reactive MANET routing protocol could
      include a TLV of this format as an Address Block TLV for reporting the
      lifetime of routes to individual addresses.
    </t>

    <t>
      In addition to defining the general format as outlined above, this document
      requests IANA assignments for INTERVAL_TIME and VALIDITY_TIME TLVs. These
      IANA assignments are requested in this document in order to avoid
      interdependencies between otherwise unrelated MANET protocols and in order
      to not exhaust the TLV Type spaces by having different protocols request
      types for essentially identical data structures. Only Message TLVs
      and Address Block TLVs are requested, as these are those for which a need
      has been demonstrated.
    </t>

  </section>

</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

  <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
    Additionally, this document uses terminology from <xref target="RFC5444"/>, and
    introduces the following terminology:

    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">
 
      <t hangText="hop count">
        - the number of hops from the message originator to the message
        recipient. This is defined to equal the &lt;msg-hop-count&gt; field
        in the &lt;msg-header&gt; element defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>,
        if present, after it is incremented on reception. If the &lt;msg-hop-count&gt;
        field is not present, or in a Packet TLV, then hop count is defined to
        equal 255.
      </t>

      <t hangText="time-value">
        - a time, measured in seconds.
      </t>

      <t hangText="time-code">
        - an 8-bit field, representing a time-value.
      </t>

    </list>

  </t>

</section>

<section anchor="applicability" title="Applicability Statement">  
  
  <t>
    The TLV structure described in this document is applicable whenever a
    single time-value, or a time-value that varies with the number of hops
    from the originator of a message, is required in a protocol
    using the generalized MANET packet/message format
    <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
    Examples of time-values that may be included in a protocol
    message are:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
        The maximum time interval until the next message of the same
        type is to be generated by the message's originator node.
      </t>
      <t>
        The validity time of the information with which the time-value
        is associated.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    Either of these may vary with the hop count between the originating
    and receiving nodes, e.g., if messages of the same type are sent with
    different hop limits as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>. 
  </t>
  
  <t>
    Parts of this document have been generalized from material in the
    proactive MANET routing protocol OLSR (Optimized Link State
    Routing Protocol) <xref target="RFC3626"/>.
  </t>

</section>
<section anchor="functioning" title="Protocol Overview and Functioning">

  <t>
    This document does not specify a protocol nor does it mandate specific
    node or protocol behavior. Rather, it outlines mechanisms for encoding
    time-values using the TLV mechanism of <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
  </t>

</section>
<section anchor="time" title="Representing Time">

  <t>
    This document specifies a TLV structure in which time-values
    are each represented in an 8-bit time-code, one or more of which
    may be used in a TLV's &lt;value&gt; field. Of these 8 bits, the
    least significant 3 bits represent the mantissa (a), and the most
    significant 5 bits represent the exponent (b), so that:

  <list style="symbols">
    <t>time-value := (1 + a/8) * 2^b * C</t>
    <t>time-code := 8 * b + a</t>
  </list>
</t>
  <t>
    All nodes in the MANET MUST use the same value of the constant C, which
    will be specified in seconds, hence so will be all time-values. C MUST be
    greater than 0 seconds. Note that ascending values of the time-code
    represent ascending time-values; time-values may thus be compared by
    comparison of time-codes.
  </t>

  <t>
    An algorithm for computing the time-code representing the smallest
    representable time-value not less than the time-value t is:

  <list style="numbers">
    <t>find the largest integer b such that t/C &gt;= 2^b;</t>
    <t>set a := 8 * (t / (C * 2^b) - 1), rounded up to the nearest integer;</t>
    <t>if a = 8, then set b := b + 1 and set a := 0;</t>
    <t>if 0 &lt;= a &lt;= 7, and 0 &lt;= b &lt;= 31, then the required
       time-value can be represented by the time-code 8 * b + a,
       otherwise it cannot.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    The minimum time-value that can be represented in this manner is C.
    The maximum time-value that can be represented in this manner is
    15 * 2^28 * C, or about 4.0 * 10^9 * C.  If, for example,
    C = 1/1024 second, then this is about 45 days.
  </t>

  <t>
    A protocol using this time representation MUST define the value of C.
    A protocol using this specification MAY specify that the all-bits zero
    time-value (0) represents a time-value of zero and/or that the all-bits
    one time-value (255) represents an indefinitely large time-value.
  </t>

</section>
<section anchor="timetlv" title="General Time TLV Structure">
	
  <t>
    The following data structure allows the representation of a single time-value,
    or of a default time-value plus pairs of (time-values, hop counts) for when
    hop-count-dependent time-values are required. The time-values are represented
    as time-codes as defined in <xref target="time"/>. This &lt;time-data&gt;
    data structure is specified, using the regular expression syntax of
    <xref target="RFC5444"/>, by:
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
    &lt;time-data&gt; = (&lt;time-code&gt;&lt;hop-count&gt;)*&lt;time-code&gt;
    </artwork>	 
  </figure>

  <t>
    where:
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="&lt;time-code&gt;">
	  is an 8-bit unsigned integer field containing a time-code as defined in
        <xref target="time"/>.
      </t>

      <t hangText="&lt;hop-count&gt;">
	  is an 8-bit unsigned integer field specifying a hop count from the message
        originator.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    A &lt;time-data&gt; structure thus consists of an odd number of octets;
    with a repetition factor of n for the (time, hop count) pairs in the
    regular expression syntax, it contains 2n+1 octets. On reception, n is
    determined from the length.
  </t>

  <t>
    A &lt;time-data&gt; field may be thus represented by:
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
    &lt;t_1&gt;&lt;d_1&gt;&lt;t_2&gt;&lt;d_2&gt; ... &lt;t_i&gt;&lt;d_i&gt; ...  &lt;t_n&gt;&lt;d_n&gt;&lt;t_default&gt;
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    &lt;d_1&gt;, ... &lt;d_n&gt;, if present, MUST be a strictly increasing sequence,
    with &lt;d_n&gt; &lt; 255. Then, at the receiving node's hop count from the originator
    node, the time-value indicated is that represented by the time-code:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>
	  &lt;t_1&gt;, if n > 0 and hop count &lt;= &lt;d_1&gt;;
      </t>
      <t>
	  &lt;t_i+1&gt;, if n > 1 and &lt;d_i&gt; &lt; hop count &lt;= &lt;d_i+1&gt; for some
        i such that 1 &lt;= i &lt; n;
      </t>
      <t>
        &lt;t_default&gt; otherwise, i.e. if n = 0 or hop count > &lt;d_n&gt;.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

   <t>
    If included in a message without a &lt;msg-hop-count&gt; field in its Message
    Header, or in a Packet TLV, then the form of this data structure with a
    single time-code in &lt;time-data&gt; (i.e., n = 0) SHOULD be used.
  </t>
  
  <section title="Single-Value Time TLVs">

    <t>
      The purpose of a single value Time TLV is to allow a single time-value
      to be determined by a node receiving an entity containing the Time TLV,
      based on its hop count from the entity's originator. The Time TLV may
      contain information that allows that time-value to be a function of
      the hop count; thus, different receiving nodes may determine different
      time-values.
    </t>

    <t>
      A single-value Time TLV may be a Packet TLV, a Message TLV, or
      an Address Block TLV.
    </t>

    <t>
      A Time TLV that has the tismultivalue flag cleared ('0') in its &lt;tlv-flags&gt;
      field, as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>, contains a single &lt;time-data&gt;,
      as defined above, in its &lt;value&gt; field. For such a Time TLV:
		
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>	
          The &lt;length&gt; field in the TLV MUST contain the value 2n+1, with n being
          the number of (time-value, hop count) pairs in the Time TLV.
        </t>
        <t>
          The number of (time-value, hop count) pairs MUST be identified by inspecting
          the &lt;length&gt; field in the TLV. The number of such pairs, n, is:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>n := (&lt;length&gt; - 1) / 2</t>
          </list>
          This MUST be an integer value.
        </t>
      </list>

    </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Value Time TLVs">

    <t>
      The purpose of a multi-value Time TLV is to associate a set of &lt;time-data&gt; structures
      to an identically sized set of addresses, as described in <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
      For each of these &lt;time-data&gt; structures, a single time-value can be determined by a
      node receiving an entity containing the Time TLV, based on its hop count from the entity's
      originator. The Time TLV may contain information that allows that time-value to be a function
      of the hop count, and thus different receiving nodes may determine different time-values. 
    </t>

    <t>
      Multi-value Time TLVs MUST be Address Block TLVs. A multi-value Time TLV MUST NOT be a Packet
      TLV or Message TLV.
    </t>

    <t>
      A Time TLV that has the tismultivalue flag set ('1') in its &lt;tlv-flags&gt; field,
      as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>, contains a sequence of &lt;time-data&gt;
      structures, as defined above, in its &lt;value&gt; field. For such a Time TLV:
		
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          The &lt;length&gt; field in the TLV MUST contain the value m * (2n+1), with n
          being the number of (time-value, hop count) pairs in the Time TLV, and m being
          number-values as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The number of &lt;time-data&gt; structures included in the &lt;value&gt; field
          is equal to number-values as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The number of (time-value, hop count) pairs in each &lt;time-data&gt; structure
          MUST be the same, and MUST be identified by inspecting the &lt;length&gt; field
          in the TLV and using number-values as defined in <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
          The number of such pairs in each &lt;time-data&gt; structure, n, is:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>n := ((&lt;length&gt; / number-values) - 1) / 2</t>
          </list>
          This MUST be an integer value. The lists of hop count values MAY be different.
        </t>
      </list>

    </t>

  </section>

</section>
<section anchor="message TLVs" title="Message TLVs">

  <t>
    Two Message TLVs are defined, for signaling message interval
    (INTERVAL_TIME) and message validity time (VALIDITY_TIME).
  </t>

  <section anchor="interval time" title="INTERVAL_TIME TLV">

    <t>
      An INTERVAL_TIME TLV is a Message TLV that defines
      the maximum time before another message of the same type
      as this message from the same originator should be received.
      This interval time MAY be specified to depend on the hop count
      from the originator. (This is appropriate if messages are sent
      with different hop limits so that receiving nodes at greater
      hop counts have an increased interval time.)
    </t>

    <t>
      A message MUST NOT include more than one INTERVAL_TIME TLV.
    </t>

    <t>
      An INTERVAL_TIME TLV is an example of a Time TLV specified
      as in <xref target="time"/>.
    </t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="validity time" title="VALIDITY_TIME TLV">

    <t>
      A VALIDITY_TIME TLV is a Message TLV that defines the
      validity time of the information carried in the message
      in which the TLV is contained. After this time, the
      receiving node MUST consider the message content to no
      longer be valid (unless repeated in a later message).
      The validity time of a message MAY be specified to depend
      on the hop count from its originator. (This is appropriate
      if messages are sent with different hop limits so that
      receiving nodes at greater hop counts receive information
      less frequently and must treat is as valid for longer.)
    </t>

    <t>
      A message MUST NOT include more than one VALIDITY_TIME TLV.
    </t>

    <t>
      A VALIDITY_TIME TLV is an example of a Time TLV specified
      as in <xref target="time"/>.
    </t>

  </section>

</section>

<section anchor="address block TLVs" title="Address Block TLVs">

  <t>
    Two Address Block TLVs are defined, for signaling address
    advertisement interval (INTERVAL_TIME) and address validity time
    (VALIDITY_TIME).
  </t>

  <section anchor="address block interval time" title="INTERVAL_TIME TLV">

    <t>
      An INTERVAL_TIME TLV is an Address Block TLV that defines the maximum
      time before this address from the same originator should be received
      again. This interval time MAY be specified to depend on the hop count
      from the originator. (This is appropriate if addresses are contained in
      messages sent with different hop limits so that receiving nodes at greater
      hop counts have an increased interval time.)
    </t>

    <t>
      A protocol using this TLV and the same named Message TLV MUST specify
      how to interpret the case when both are present (typically, that the former
      overrides the latter for those addresses that are covered by the former).
    </t>

    <t>
      An INTERVAL_TIME TLV is an example of a Time TLV specified
      as in <xref target="time"/>.
    </t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="address block validity time" title="VALIDITY_TIME TLV">

    <t>
      A VALIDITY_TIME TLV is an Address Block TLV that defines the
      validity time of the addresses to which the TLV is associated.
      After this time, the receiving node MUST consider the addresses to no
      longer be valid (unless these are repeated in a later message).
      The validity time of an address MAY be specified to depend
      on the hop count from its originator. (This is appropriate
      if addresses are contained in messages sent with different hop limits
      so that receiving nodes at greater hop counts receive information
      less frequently and must treat is as valid for longer.)
    </t>

    <t>
      A protocol using this TLV and the same named Message TLV MUST specify
      how to interpret the case when both are present (typically, that the former
      overrides the latter for those addresses that are covered by the former).
    </t>

    <t>
      A VALIDITY_TIME TLV is an example of a Time TLV specified
      as in <xref target="time"/>.
    </t>

  </section>

</section>
<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

  <t>
    This specification defines two Message TLV Types, which
    have been allocated from the "Assigned Message TLV Types"
    repository of <xref target="RFC5444"/> as specified in
    <xref target="msgtlvtypesiana"/>, and two Address Block TLV Types,
    which have been allocated from the "Assigned Address Block TLV Types"
    repository of <xref target="RFC5444"/> as specified in
    <xref target="addrblocktlvtypesiana"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
    IANA has assigned the same numerical value to the Message TLV Type
    and Address Block TLV Type with the same name.
  </t>

  <section title="Expert Review: Evaluation Guidelines">

    <t>
      For the registries for TLV Type Extensions where an Expert Review is required,
      the designated expert SHOULD take the same general recommendations into
      consideration as are specified by <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
    </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Message TLV Types">

    <texttable anchor="msgtlvtypesiana">
      <ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="center">Type</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="center">Type Extension</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
      <c>INTERVAL_TIME</c><c>0</c><c>0</c>
        <c>The maximum time before another message of the same type
           as this message from the same originator should be received</c>
      <c>Unassigned</c><c>0</c><c>1-223</c><c>Expert Review</c>
      <c></c><c></c><c>224-255</c><c>Experimental Use</c>
      <c>VALIDITY_TIME</c><c>1</c><c>0</c>
        <c>The time from receipt of the message during which the information
           contained in the message is to be considered valid</c>
      <c>Unassigned</c><c>1</c><c>1-223</c><c>Expert Review</c>
      <c></c><c></c><c>224-255</c><c>Experimental Use</c>
    </texttable>	

  </section>

  <section title="Address Block TLV Types">

    <texttable anchor="addrblocktlvtypesiana">
      <ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="center">Type</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="center">Type extension</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
      <c>INTERVAL_TIME</c><c>0</c><c>0</c>
        <c>The maximum time before another message of the same type
           as this message from the same originator and containing this address should be received</c>
      <c>Unassigned</c><c>0</c><c>1-223</c><c>Expert Review</c>
      <c></c><c></c><c>224-255</c><c>Experimental Use</c>
      <c>VALIDITY_TIME</c><c>1</c><c>0</c>
        <c>The time from receipt of the address during which the information
           regarding this address is to be considered valid</c>
      <c>Unassigned</c><c>0</c><c>1-223</c><c>Expert Review</c>
      <c></c><c></c><c>224-255</c><c>Experimental Use</c>
    </texttable>	

  </section>

</section>
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

  <t>
    This document specifies how to add data structures (TLVs) that provide timing
    information  to packets and messages specified using <xref target="RFC5444"/>.
    In particular, information validity durations and reporting intervals may be added.
  </t>

  <t>
    The general security threats that apply are those general to
    <xref target="RFC5444"/> and described therein, problems of
    integrity and confidentiality. With regard to the former,
    modification of a Time TLV can cause information to have an
    invalid validity time, or expected interval time. This may cause
    incorrect protocol performance. Modification or addition of
    timed information can add to a protocol's workload (especially
    if a short validity time is specified) and storage requirements
    (especially if a long validity time is specified).
  </t>

  <t>
    To counter these threats, the security suggestions in
    <xref target="RFC5444"/>, for the use of authentication and
    encryption, are appropriate.
  </t>

</section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Normative References">

  <reference anchor="RFC2119">
    <front>
      <title abbrev="RFC2119">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
        <organization abbrev="HU">Harvard University</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="March" year="1997"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
  </reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5444'>

<front>

<title>Generalized Mobile Ad Hoc Network (MANET) Packet/Message Format</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Clausen' fullname='T. Clausen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Dearlove' fullname='C. Dearlove'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Dean' fullname='J. Dean'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Adjih' fullname='C. Adjih'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='February' />

<abstract>
  <t>
    This document specifies a packet format capable of carrying multiple messages
    that may be used by mobile ad hoc network routing protocols. [STANDARDS TRACK]
  </t>
</abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5444' />
<format type='TXT' octets='139048' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5444.txt' />
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

  <reference anchor="RFC3626">
    <front>
      <title>The Optimized Link State Routing Protocol</title>
      <author initials="T.H." surname="Clausen" fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen (ed.)">
        <organization abbrev="X">Ecole Polytechnique, France</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Jacquet" fullname="Philippe Jacquet (ed.)">
        <organization abbrev="INRIA">Project Hipercom, INRIA Rocquencourt, France</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="October" year="2003"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3626"/>
  </reference>

</references>
<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

  <t>
    The authors would like to thank Brian Adamson and Justin Dean (both NRL)
    and Ian Chakeres (Motorola) for their contributions, and Alan Cullen (BAE Systems)
    and Jari Arkko (Ericsson, Finland) for their careful reviews of this specification.
  </t>

</section>

  </back>

</rfc>
