<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="5711" category="std" updates="3209">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Node Behavior with RSVP PathErr">Node Behavior upon
    Originating and Receiving Resource Reservation Protocol (RSVP) Path Error
    Messages</title>

    <author fullname="JP Vasseur" initials="JP." role="editor"
            surname="Vasseur">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Avenue</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <code>01719</code>

          <region>MA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jpv@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Swallow" initials="G" surname="Swallow">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Avenue</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <code>01719</code>

          <region>MA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>swallow@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I" surname="Minei">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Mathilda Ave.</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <code>94089</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ina@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2009" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->
<keyword>example</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
      The aim of this document is to describe a common practice with
      regard to the behavior of nodes that send and receive a Resource
      Reservation Protocol (RSVP) Traffic Engineering (TE) Path Error
      messages for a preempted Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS)
      or Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) Traffic Engineering Label Switched
      Path (TE LSP).  (For reference to the notion of TE LSP
      preemption, see RFC 3209.)   This
   document does not define any new protocol extensions.
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The aim of this document is to describe a common practice with regard
      to the behavior of a node sending a Resource Reservation Protocol (RSVP)
      Traffic Engineering (TE) Path Error message and to the behavior of a
      node receiving an RSVP Path Error message for a preempted Multiprotocol
      Label Switching (MPLS) and Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) Traffic Engineering
      Label Switched Path (TE LSP).  (For reference to the notion of TE LSP
      preemption, see <xref target="RFC3209"></xref>).</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC2205"></xref> defines two RSVP error message types:
      PathErr and ResvErr that are generated when an error occurs. Path Error
      messages (PathErr) are used to report errors and travel upstream toward
      the head-end of the flow. Resv Error messages (ResvErr) travel
      downstream toward the tail-end of the flow.</t>

      <t>This document describes only PathErr message processing for the
      specific case of a preempted TE
      LSP, where the term preemption is defined in <xref
      target="RFC3209"></xref>.</t>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Behavior">
      <t>PathErr messages are routed hop-by-hop using the path state
      established when a Path message is routed through the network from the
      head-end to its tail-end.</t>

      <t>As stated in <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>, PathErr messages do not
      modify the state of any node through which they pass; they are only
      reported to the head-end of the TE LSP (Traffic Engineering Label
      Switched Path).</t>

      <t>The format of the PathErr message is defined in Section 3. of <xref
      target="RFC2205"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The ERROR_SPEC object includes the IP address of the node
      that detected the error (Error Node Address), and specifies the
      error through two fields. The Error Code field encodes the
      category of the error, for example, Policy Control Failure or
      Unknown object class. The Error Value field qualifies the error
      code to indicate the error with more
      precision. <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> extends RSVP as
      defined in
      <xref target="RFC2205"></xref> for the management of MPLS-TE
      LSPs. <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> specifies several additional
      conditions that trigger the sending of a RSVP PathErr message for which
      new error codes and error values have been defined that extend the list
      defined in <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>. The exact circumstances under
      which a TE LSP is preempted and such PathErr messages are sent are
      defined in <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> and will not be repeated
      here.</t>

      <t>Values for the Error Code and Error Value fields defined in <xref
      target="RFC2205"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3209"></xref>, and other
      documents are maintained in a registry by the IANA.</t>

      <t>The error conditions fall into two categories: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Fatal errors represent disruptive conditions for a TE
          LSP.</t>

          <t>Non-fatal errors are non-disruptive conditions that have
          occurred for this TE LSP.</t>

        </list>PathErr messages may be used in two circumstances: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>during TE LSP establishment, and</t>

          <t>after a TE LSP has been successfully established.</t>

        </list>Nodal behavior is dependent on which combination of the four
      cases listed above applies. The following sections describe the expected
      behavior at nodes that perform a preemption action for a TE LSP (and
      therefore report using error PathErr messages), and at nodes that
      receive PathErr messages. This text is a clarification and restatement
      of the procedures set out in <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> and does not
      define any new behavior.</t>

      <section title="Behavior at Detecting Nodes">

        <t>In the case of fatal errors ("Hard Preemption"; see Section 4.7.3 of <xref target="RFC3209"/> ), the detecting node MUST send a PathErr
        message reporting the error condition, and MUST clear the
        corresponding Path and Resv (control plane) states. A direct
        implication is that the data-plane resources of such a TE LSP are also
        released, thus resulting in traffic disruption. It should be noted,
        however, that in fatal error cases, the LSP has usually already failed
        in the data plane, and traffic has already been disrupted. When the
        error arises during LSP establishment, the implications are different
        to when it arises on an active LSP since no traffic flows until the
        LSP has been fully established. In the case of non-fatal errors, the
        detecting node should send a PathErr message, and must not clear
        control plane or data plane state.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Behavior at Receiving Nodes">
        <t>Nodes that receive PathErr messages are all of the nodes along the
        path of the TE LSP upstream of the node that detected the error. This
        includes the head-end node. In accordance with Section 3.7.1
        of <xref
        target="RFC2205"></xref>, a node receiving a PathErr message takes no
        action upon it, and consequently the node must not clear Path or
        Resv control-plane or data-plane state. 

This is true regardless of whether the
        error condition reported by the PathErr is fatal or non-fatal. RSVP
        states should only be affected upon receiving a PathTear or ResvTear
        message, or in the event of a Path or Resv state timeout. Further
        discussion of the processing of these events is outside the scope of
        this document. </t>
	
        <t>Note that <xref target="RFC3473"></xref> defines a
        Path_State_Removed flag in the ERROR_SPEC object carried on a PathErr
        message. This field may be set to change the behavior of upstream
        nodes that receive the PathErr message. When set, the flag indicates
        that the message sender has removed Path state (and any associated
        Resv and data-plane state) for the TE LSP. The message receiver should
        do likewise before forwarding the message, but may retain state and
        clear the flag before forwarding the message.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Data-Plane Behavior">
        <t>Any node clearing either or both the Path or the Resv state of a TE
        LSP MUST also free up the data-plane resources allocated to the
        corresponding TE LSP.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="RSVP PathErr Messages for a Preempted TE LSP">
      <t>Two Error Codes have been defined to report a preempted TE LSP:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC2750"></xref>: Error Code=2:
          "Policy Control Failure", Error Value=5: "Flow was preempted"</t>

          <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>, Error Code=12:
          "Service preempted"</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>They are both fatal errors.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not define any new procedures, but clarifies those
      defined in other documents where security considerations are already
      specified in <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC3473"></xref>. This document does not raise specific security
      issues beyond those of existing MPLS-TE. By clarifying the procedures,
      this document reduces the security risk introduced by non-conformant
      implementations. See <xref
      target="SEC_FMWK"></xref> for
      further discussion of MPLS security issues.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Carol Iturralde, Ashok Narayanan, Rom
      Reuther, and Reshad Rahman.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3209'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2750'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3473'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2205'?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
 
<!-- draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework -->

<reference anchor='SEC_FMWK'>
<front>
<title>Security Framework for MPLS and GMPLS Networks</title>

<author initials='L' surname='Fang' fullname='Luyuan Fang' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='25' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress"/>

</reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
