<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'[

<!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>

<!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>

<!ENTITY RFC5844 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5844.xml'>



<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-integrated PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-integrated.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC5447 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5447.xml'>

<!ENTITY Dime-Split PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC5778 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5778.xml'>

<!ENTITY DHCP-Option PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mip6-hiopt.xml'> 

<!ENTITY DIME-PMIPv6 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-pmip6.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC5779 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5779.xml'>

<!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'> 



<!ENTITY rfc5026 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5026.xml'> 

<!ENTITY rfc4877 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4877.xml'> 

<!ENTITY rfc2136 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC2865 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC2866 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2866.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC2869 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2869.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC3579 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC3748 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC5149 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5149.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC6097 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6097.xml'> 

<!ENTITY RFC4372 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4372.xml'> 

] >



<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6572">


<front> 
    <!----Title -->
    <title abbrev="RADIUS PMIPv6"> 
    RADIUS Support for Proxy Mobile IPv6 
    </title>
    <!----End of Title-->

    <!----Author information -->
       
    <author initials='F' surname='Xia' fullname="Frank Xia">
    <organization>Huawei USA</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>1700 Alma Dr., Suite 500</street>
    <street></street>
    <city>Plano</city> <region>TX</region> <code>75075</code>
    </postal>
    <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>
    <email>xiayangsong@huawei.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>   

    <author initials="B" surname="Sarikaya" fullname="Behcet Sarikaya">
    <organization>Huawei USA</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>1700 Alma Dr., Suite 500</street>
    <city>Plano</city> <region>TX</region> <code>75075</code>
    </postal>
    <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>
    <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
    </address>
    </author>   

    <author role="editor" initials="J" surname="Korhonen" fullname="Jouni Korhonen">
    <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
    <city>Espoo</city> <code>FI-02600</code> <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>   

    <author initials="S" surname="Gundavelli" fullname="Sri Gundavelli">
    <organization>Cisco</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
    <city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region> <code>95134</code>
    </postal>
    <email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>   

    <author initials="D" surname="Damic" fullname="Damjan Damic">
    <organization>Siemens</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>Heinzelova 70a</street>
    <city>Zagreb</city> <code>10000</code> <country>Croatia</country>
    </postal>
    <email>damjan.damic@siemens.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>   

<!----End of Author information -->

   <date  month="June" year="2012"/>

   <workgroup>netext</workgroup>


<abstract>
   <t>
This document defines new attributes to facilitate Proxy Mobile IPv6 operations using
      the RADIUS infrastructure. 
      The protocol defined in this document uses RADIUS-based interfaces of the  mobile access gateway  and the local mobility anchor with the AAA server for authentication, authorization, and policy functions.
      The RADIUS interactions between the mobile access gateway and 
	  the RADIUS-based AAA server take place when the mobile node (MN) attaches, authenticates, and
	  authorizes to a Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain. Furthermore, this document defines the
	  RADIUS-based interface between the local mobility anchor and the AAA RADIUS server for
	  authorizing received Proxy Binding Update messages for the mobile node's mobility session.
	  In addition to the interactions related to mobility session setup, this document defines the
      baseline for the mobile access gateway and the local mobility anchor
      generated accounting.
   </t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>
<section title='Introduction'>
   <t>Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5213"/> is a network-based mobility
      management protocol that allows IP mobility support for a mobile node without
	  requiring the mobile node's participation in any mobility-related signaling. The
	  mobile management elements in the network, the mobile access gateway (MAG) and the
	  local mobility anchor (LMA), are the two key functions in this network-based mobility
	  system. The mobile access gateway is responsible for detecting the mobile node's movements
	  in the network and for initiating the needed mobility management signaling with the local
	  mobility anchor (LMA). Both the mobility management agents make use of the AAA infrastructure
	  to retrieve the mobile node's policy profile and for performing service authorization.</t>
      
   <t>This document defines a RADIUS-based <xref target="RFC2865"/> profile and
      corresponding attributes to be used on the AAA interface between the MAG
      and the AAA RADIUS server. This interface is used to carry the per-MN
      policy profile from the remote policy store to the MAG.
	  Furthermore, this document also defines a RADIUS-based
	  interface between the LMA and the AAA RADIUS server for authorization of the received
      Proxy Mobile IPv6 signaling messages.
	  The AAA procedures defined in this document cover the following two scenarios:	  
	  <list style="symbols">
      <t>a mobile node connects to the Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain from the home network</t>
	  <t>a mobile node connects to the Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain from a visited network</t>
      </list>
   </t>
   
</section> <!----end of introduction -->

<section title='Terminology'>

   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
      are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.
   </t>


   <t>All the mobility-related terms used in this document are to be interpreted as defined in
   the Proxy Mobile IPv6 specifications <xref target="RFC5213"/> and  <xref target="RFC5844"/>.
   Additionally, this document uses the following abbreviations: </t>

	<t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Network Access Server (NAS):">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/> A function that provides authorization services for a
		  device/user access to the network as defined in <xref target="RFC2865"/>. 
		  This document makes an assumption that the NAS
function is co-located with the MAG. In scenarios where the NAS
function and MAG are decoupled, the messaging interface needed between
them for the operation of PMIP6 is beyond the scope of this document.
		
          </t>

          <t hangText="Home AAA (HAAA):">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>An Authentication, Authorization, and 
          Accounting (AAA) server located in the MN's home network. This sever has 
		  access to the mobile node's policy profiles.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="Visited AAA (VAAA):">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>An Authentication, Authorization, and 
          Accounting (AAA) server located in the MN's visited network. The VAAA server
		  takes the role of a proxy-server, forwarding the received AAA service 
		  request to the HAAA server in the mobile node's home network and relaying
		  the response to the requesting node, after applying any local access network
		  policies.
          </t>   
          <t hangText="Local AAA (LAAA):">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>An Authentication, Authorization, and 
          Accounting proxy located in the local network. In a roaming case,
          the local AAAA has the visited AAA role.
          </t>
      </list></t>  
           
</section>




<section anchor="Solution Overview" title="Solution Overview">
   <t>This document defines the RADIUS-based AAA interactions with the two mobility
   management elements in the Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain.</t>
   
   <t>
   <list style="symbols">
   <t> Interactions between a MAG and a RADIUS-based AAA server </t>
   <t> Interactions between a LMA and a RADIUS-based AAA server </t>
   </list>
   </t>
   
   <t>
   The mobile node's policy profile <xref target="RFC5213"/> is present in a policy store
   and is needed by the PMIPv6 mobility management elements for authorizing the mobile node
   for mobility management service and for obtaining various service-related parameters.
   This policy store could be locally co-located with the mobility management agents enabling
   direct local access or could be available from a AAA server through a RADIUS-based AAA interface.
   </t>
   
   <t>When a mobile
node attaches to an access network, the NAS on that access network
   may activate the network access authentication procedure. The choice of the
   authentication mechanism is specific to the access network
   deployment; however, it is typically based on the Extensible Authentication
   Protocol (EAP) <xref target="RFC3748"/>. The NAS performs
   the network access authentication and queries the HAAA using AAA protocol, such as RADIUS.
   If the network access authentication succeeds, the MN's  policy profile is
   obtained as part of the RADIUS message exchange with the AAA server.
   </t>
   
   <t>
   The mobile node may be an IPv4-only node, IPv6-only node, or a dual-
   stack (IPv4/v6) node. Based on the policy specified in the policy profile, the
   network access authentication procedure SHOULD provide the unambiguous indication of 
   the type of address(es) to be assigned for the MN in the network and with
   all other service-related and policy parameters relevant to the mobility service.
   </t>
   
   <t>After the successful network access authentication and  obtaining the mobile
   node's policy profile, the MAG sends a Proxy Binding Update (PBU) to the LMA. Upon
   receiving the PBU, the LMA interacts with the HAAA to obtain the mobile node's
   policy profile, which is
required for authorizing and activating mobility service.
   </t>
   
   <t>This document adds support for three distinct PMIPv6 mobility use cases, taking into account
   the administrative domains to which the MAG and the LMA belong. The following are the
   three relevant deployment models.</t>
 
   <t>
   <list style="numbers">
   <t>the MAG and LMA are both in the home network,</t>
   <t>the MAG and LMA are both in the visited network,</t>
   <t>the MAG is in the visited network while the LMA is in the home network.</t>
   </list>
   </t>
   
   
   <t><xref target="both-home"/> shows participating network entities for
   the PMIPv6 mobility session, which is located in the home network.
   The MAG and LMA interact only with the HAAA.
   </t>

    <figure anchor='both-home' title="The MAG and LMA Are Both in the Home Network"  >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
    +--------+
    | HAAA & |  RADIUS  +-----+
    | Policy |<-------->| LMA |
    | Profile|          +-----+
    +--------+             | <--- LMA-Address
         ^                 |
         |               // \\
     +---|------------- //---\\----------------+
    (    |  IPv4/IPv6  //     \\                )
    (    |   Network  //       \\               )
     +---|-----------//---------\\-------------+
         |          //           \\
       RADIUS      // <- Tunnel1  \\ <- Tunnel2
         |        //               \\
         |        |- MAG1-Address   |- MAG2-Address
         |     +----+             +----+
         +---->|MAG1|             |MAG2|
               +----+             +----+
                  |                 |
                  |                 |
                 MN1               MN2
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
    
   <t><xref target="both-visited"/> shows both the LMA and MAG
   are in the visited network. The MAG and LMA exchange 
   signaling with the HAAA through the VAAA, which acts as a Proxy. The
   visited network may append additional information to the HAAA replies
   in order to reflect the local policy.
   </t>
   
   
    <figure anchor='both-visited' title="The MAG and LMA Are Both in the Visited/Local Network"  >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
                    +---------------+
                    |    HAAA &     |
         +----------| Policy Profile|
         |          +---------------+
         |
    +---------+
    |[VL]AAA &| RADIUS  +-----+
    | Policy  |<------->| LMA |
    | Profile |         +-----+
    +---------+            | <--- LMA-Address
         ^               // \\
     +---|------------- //---\\----------------+
    (    |  IPv4/IPv6  //     \\                )
    (    |   Network  //       \\               )
     +---|-----------//---------\\-------------+
         |          //           \\
       RADIUS      // <- Tunnel1  \\ <- Tunnel2
         |        //               \\
         |        |- MAG1-Address   |- MAG2-Address
         |     +----+             +----+
         +---->|MAG1|             |MAG2|
               +----+             +----+
                  |                 |
                 MN1               MN2
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>    
   
   <t><xref target="MAG-Only-visited"/> illustrates a topology where the MAG resides 
   in the visited network while the associated LMA is in MN's home network.
   Any message between the MAG and the HAAA passes through the VAAA, which acts
   as a Proxy. During the network authentication, the visited network's
   specific policy may also be propagated from the VAAA to the MAG.
   The LMA has a direct access to the HAAA.</t>

    <figure anchor='MAG-Only-visited' title="Visited MAG and Home LMA Topology"  >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
                    +---------------+
                    |    HAAA &     |
         +----------| Policy Profile|
         |          +---------------+
         |                 |
         |               RADIUS
    +---------+            | 
    |[VL]AAA &|         +-----+
    | Policy  |         | LMA |
    | Profile |         +-----+
    +---------+            | <--- LMA-Address
         ^               // \\
     +---|------------- //---\\----------------+
    (    |  IPv4/IPv6  //     \\                )
    (    |   Network  //       \\               )
     +---|-----------//---------\\-------------+
         |          //           \\
       RADIUS      // <- Tunnel1  \\ <- Tunnel2
         |        //               \\
         |        |- MAG1-Address   |- MAG2-Address
         |     +----+             +----+
         +---->|MAG1|             |MAG2|
               +----+             +----+
                  |                 |
                 MN1               MN2
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>   
</section>

<section title="Attribute Definitions">

      <section title="MIP6-Feature-Vector" anchor="capability">
        <t>Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/> reserves AVP Code space 1-255
        as RADIUS attribute compatibility space. The MIP6-Feature-Vector 
        attribute
        (Type value 124) defined in <xref target="RFC5447"/> is of type OctetString 
        and contains a 64&nbhy;bit flags field of supported mobility capabilities.
        This document reserves two new capability bits according to the rules in
        <xref  target="RFC5447"/>, and reuses the PMIPv6 capability bits defined by 
        <xref target="RFC5779"/>. The following capability 
        flag bits are used or defined in this document:
		</t>
		<t>
		<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="PMIP6_SUPPORTED (0x0000010000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> This capability bit is used as defined in 
             <xref target="RFC5779"/>. 
          </t>

          <t hangText="IP4_HOA_SUPPORTED (0x0000020000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/>This capability bit is used as defined in 
             <xref target="RFC5779"/>. Assignment of the IPv4-HoA (Home Address) is defined by
			 <xref target="RFC5844"/>.
          </t>

          <t hangText="LOCAL_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED (0x0000040000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> This capability bit is used as defined in 
             <xref target="RFC5779"/>.
          </t>
          
             <t hangText="IP4_TRANSPORT_SUPPORTED (0x0000800000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> This capability bit is used
			 for negotiation of the IPv4 transport support between the MAG and
             AAA. When the MAG sets this flag bit in the MIP6-Feature-Vector, 
             it indicates the ability of the MAG to provide IPv4 transport (i.e., IPv4-based encapsulation)
			 for carrying IP traffic between the MAG and the LMA. If this flag
             bit is unset in the returned MIP6-Feature-Vector attribute, the
             AAA does not authorize the use of IPv4 transport on the MAG-to-LMA tunnel.
          </t>
		  
		     <t hangText="IP4_HOA_ONLY_SUPPORTED (0x0001000000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> This capability bit is used
			 for determination of the authorized PMIPv6 mobility mode. When this
			 bit is set by the AAA, it indicates PMIPv6 mobility with IPv4 support
			 has only been authorized for the MN. As a result,
			 the RADIUS Access-Accept SHOULD NOT carry the IPv6 Home Network Prefix (IPv6 HNP).
			 When this bit is set, the PMIP6_SUPPORTED flag MUST also be set
			 and the IP4_HOA_SUPPORTED flag MUST NOT be set.
          </t>

      </list></t>
<t>  To summarize the use of the MIP6-Feature-Vector the following capability
  bit combination settings mean:
<list>
  <t>PMIP6-SUPPORTED bit set - only IPv6 mobility is supported and authorized.</t>
  <t>PMIP6-SUPPORTED and IP4-ONLY-HOA-SUPPORTED bits set - only IPv4 mobility
     is supported and authorized.</t>
  <t>PMIP6-SUPPORTED and IP4-HOA-SUPPORTED bits set - both IPv6 and IPv4
     mobility are supported and authorized.</t></list></t>

      <t>The MIP6-Feature-Vector attribute is also used on 
         the LMA to the RADIUS AAA interface.
         This capability announcement attribute enables direct capability
		 negotiation between the LMA and the AAA. The capabilities that are
		 announced by both parties in the MIP6-Feature-Vector are known to
		 be mutually supported. The LMA may use this mechanism during
		 authorization of the received PBU against the AAA to check individual PMIPv6 feature permissions for a particular MN.
	   </t>
	   <t>If the RADIUS Access-Accept contains a contradicting combination of
  the capability flag bits such as both the IP4_HOA_ONLY_SUPPORTED and
  the IP4_HOA_SUPPORTED flags being set, then the RADIUS client MUST
  treat the Access-Accept as an Access-Reject and SHOULD
        log the event. Similarly, if the RADIUS Access-Request contains
        a contradicting combination of the capability flag bits, then the
        RADIUS server MUST reply with an Access-Reject message and SHOULD
        log the event.
	   </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Mobile-Node-Identifier" anchor="mni">
      <t>The Mobile-Node-Identifier attribute (Type value 145) is of type String and contains the mobile node identifier (MN-Identifier), see <xref
         target="RFC5213"/>, in a form of a Network Access Identifier (NAI) <xref target="RFC4282"/>. This
		 identifier and the identifier used for access authentication may be 
		 different; however, there needs to be a mapping between the two identities
		 as specified in Section 6.6 of <xref target="RFC5213"/>.
         This attribute is used on the interface between the MAG and the AAA server. 
         The Mobile-Node-Identifier attribute is designed for deployments where 
         the identity used during network access authentication and the identity used for
		 mobility management is decoupled. It may also be the case where the MAG
		 does not have means to find out the MN identity that could be 
         used in subsequent PBU and Proxy Binding Acknowledgement (PBA) exchanges (e.g., due to identity hiding during 
         the network access authentication) or when the HAAA wants to assign periodically 
         changing identities to the MN.</t>
         
      <t>The Mobile-Node-Identifier attribute MAY be returned by the HAAA in the RADIUS Access-Accept
		 message that completes a successful authentication and authorization
         exchange between the MAG and the HAAA. The MAG  MUST use the received MN-Identifier.
      </t>
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |   Mobile Node Identifier...   ~  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  Mobile-Node-Identifier 145.

Length:
   In octets, including Type and Length fields (>= 3).

Mobile Node Identifier:
   This field is of type String and contains the MN-Identifier
   of the MN to be used in the PBU/PBA exchange.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section title="Service-Selection">
    <t>The Service-Selection attribute (Type value 146) is of type UTF-8 text and contains the name of the service
	or the external network with which the mobility service for the particular MN
	SHOULD be associated <xref target="RFC5149"/>. The identifier MUST be unique within the PMIPv6 Domain when normalized using the selected normalization form <xref target="UNF"/> for the particular PMIPv6 Domain deployment. For instance, <xref target="RFC5149"/> uses the Normalization Form KC (NFKC).</t>
	   
	   <t>
	   The MAG MUST include the Service-Selection attribute in the Access-Request sent to
	   the AAA if the information was acquired, e.g., by operator-specific configuration. The AAA MAY include the Service-Selection attribute in the
       Access-Accept response message to the MAG even if it was not included
       in the Access-Request as a means of indicating the MN's default service.
	   </t>
	   
	   <t>
	   The Service Selection mobility option defined in <xref target="RFC5149"/> can be used in PBU/PBA messages between the MAG and LMA.
	   On the LMA-to-AAA interface, the LMA MAY populate the Service-Selection
       attribute in the Access-Request message using the service information
	   found in the received PBU, if such a mobility option were included. The
	   Service-Selection identifier should be used to assist the PBU
	   authorization, the assignment of the MN-HNP, and the IPv4-MN-HoA
	   as described in <xref target="RFC5149"/> and <xref target="RFC5779"/>.
    </t>
    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |    Service Identifier...      ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   Service-Selection 146.

Length:
   In octets, including Type and Length fields (>= 3).

Text:
   This field is of type UTF-8 text and contains the Service
   Identifier with which the MN is associated.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address attribute (Type value 147) is of type IPv6 address and is used to deliver the IPv6 address of the LMA located in the home network.</t>
<t>Before the MAG can initiate Proxy Mobile IPv6 signaling, 
   it must be aware of the LMA's IP address.
   </t>
   <t>When the LMA is assigned to the MN from the home network,
   this attribute MAY be sent by the HAAA to the MAG in the 
   RADIUS Access-Accept message.</t>

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |    Home LMA IPv6 address      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                       Home LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                       Home LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                       Home LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    Home LMA IPv6 address       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address 147.

Length:
   = 18 octets

Home LMA IPv6 address:
   128-bit IPv6 address of the assigned home LMA IPv6 address.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>   
  </section>

  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address attribute (Type value 148) is of type 
   IPv6 address and is used to propose a particular LMA in the visited network 
   and to authorize the use of the LMA in the visited/local network. 
   </t>
   <t>
   PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address attribute MAY be included by the MAG
   in the RADIUS Access-Request message. The LMA in the visited/local 
   network may be assigned by the [VL]AAA as the result of
   retrieved policy  profile.  
   If included by the [VL]AAA in the RADIUS Access-Accept sent to the MAG, 
   the use of the LMA in the visited/local network is authorized and the
   attribute SHALL carry the IPv6 address of the LMA assigned
   for the particular MN. See Section 4.2.5 of <xref target="RFC5447"/> how
   the MIP6-Feature-Vector attribute and LOCAL_HOME_AGENT_ASSIGNMENT
   capability flag is used with the LMA (Home Agent) assignment.
   </t>
   <!--t>   
   The attribute SHOULD NOT be included if the use of LMA in the home network
   is authorized (the PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address attribute is already present). 
   However, if the VAAA local policy allows both home and visited LMA addresses 
   to be delivered to the MAG, then the MAG has to select either the visited or 
   home network LMA based on its local policy.
   </t-->
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |   Visited LMA IPv6 address     
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                     Visited LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                     Visited LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                     Visited LMA IPv6 address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   Visited LMA IPv6 address     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address 148.

Length:
   = 18 octets

Visited LMA IPv6 address:
   128-bit IPv6 address of the assigned visited LMA IPv6 address.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>   
   
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address">
    <t>The PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address attribute (Type value 149)
	is of type IPv4 address and contains the IPv4 address of the LMA assigned by 
	the HAAA. The <xref target="RFC5844"/> supports
    Proxy Mobile IPv6 signaling exchange between MAG and LMA  
    using the IPv4 transport.
	</t>
    <t>When the LMA is located in the home network,
    this attribute MAY be sent by the HAAA to the MAG in the RADIUS 
    Access-Accept 
    message.
	</t>
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Home LMA IPv4 address        
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    Home LMA IPv4 address       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address 149.

Length:
   = 6 octets

Home LMA IPv4 address:
   32-bit IPv4 address of the assigned LMA.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>   
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address">
    <t>The PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address attribute (Type value 150) is of type IPv4 address and is used to propose a particular LMA in the visited network and to authorize the use of the LMA in the visited network.
   </t>
   <t>
   PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address attribute MAY be included by the MAG
   in the RADIUS Access-Request message. The LMA in the visited/local 
   network may be assigned by the [VL]AAA as the result of
   retrieved policy  profile.  
   If included by the [VL]AAA in the RADIUS Access-Accept sent to the MAG, 
   the use of the LMA in the visited/local network is authorized and the
   attribute SHALL carry the IPv4 address of the LMA assigned
   for the particular MN. See Section 4.2.5 of <xref target="RFC5447"/> how
   the MIP6-Feature-Vector attribute and LOCAL_HOME_AGENT_ASSIGNMENT
   capability flag is used with the LMA (Home Agent) assignment.
   </t> 
   <!--t>
   The PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address attribute MAY be included by the MAG 
   in the RADIUS Access-Request packet sent to the VAAA as a proposal to allocate the particular LMA
   to the MN. The LMA in the visited network may be assigned by
   the visited AAA as the result of retrieved policy profile.  
   If included by the VAAA in the RADIUS Access-Accept sent to the MAG, 
   the use of the LMA in the visited network is authorized and the
   attribute SHALL carry the IPv4 address of the assigned visited LMA.
   </t>
   <t>
   The attribute SHOULD NOT be included if the use of LMA in the home network
   is authorized (the PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address attribute is already present). However, if the VAAA local policy allows both home and visited LMA addresses to be delivered to the MAG, then the MAG has to select either the visited or home  network LMA based on its local policy.
   </t-->
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |    Visited LMA IPv4 address   
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   Visited LMA IPv4 address     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address 150.

Length:
   = 6 octets

IPv4 LMA address:
   32-bit IPv4 address of the assigned LMA.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>   
  </section>
 
  <section title="PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix">
  <t>The PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix attribute (Type value 151) is of type IPv6 prefix. It contains the Mobile Node - Home Network Prefix (MN&nbhy;HNP), which is the IPv6 prefix assigned to the link between the MN and the MAG. The MN configures its IP interface  from its home network prefix(es). When the LMA is located in the home network, the PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix attribute is used to deliver the MN-HNP from the HAAA to the MAG.
   </t>
   
  <t> The PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix attribute is also used on the LMA-to-HAAA
   interface containing the prefix assigned to the MN. If the
   LMA delegates the MN-HNP assignment to the HAAA, the attribute MUST
   contain all zeroes in the address of (i.e., '::') the Access-Request message. The attribute
   MUST be present in the RADIUS Access-Accept message if the prior request already included one and SHOULD carry the MN-HNP the HAAA assigned to the MN.</t>

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length   |    Reserved     | Prefix-Length |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Home MN-HNP                            
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                         Home MN-HNP                            
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                         Home MN-HNP                            
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                         Home MN-HNP                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix 151.

Length:
   = at least 4 and no larger than 20.

Reserved:
   Reserved for future use.  The bits MUST be set to zero by the
   sender and MUST be ignored by the receiver. 

Prefix-Length:
   The 8-bit unsigned integer indicating the prefix length of
   the home network prefix (at least 0 and no larger than 128).
   If the home network prefix contains an address of all zeroes 
   (i.e., '::'), then the Prefix-Length MUST be set to 128.

Home Network Prefix:
   The home network prefix for the MN's IPv6 address configuration.
   The Prefix field is up to 16 octets in length.  Bits outside of
   the Prefix-Length, if included, must be zero.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>    
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix">
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix attribute (Type value 152) is of type IPv6 prefix. It contains the Mobile Node - Home Network Prefix (MN-HNP), which is the IPv6 prefix assigned to the link between the MN and the MAG. The MN configures its IP interface  from its home network prefix(es). When the LMA is located in the visited network, the PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix attribute is used to deliver the MN-HNP from the VAAA to the MAG.
  </t>   
  <t> The PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix attribute is also used on the LMA-to-VAAA
   interface containing the IPv6 prefix assigned to the MN. If the
   LMA delegates the assignment of the MN-HNP to the VAAA, the attribute MUST
   contain an address of all zeroes (i.e., '::') in the RADIUS Access-Request message. The attribute MUST be present in Access-Accept message if the prior request already included one and SHOULD
   carry the MN-HNP the VAAA assigned to the MN.</t>
      <t>
   The attribute SHOULD NOT be included if the use of LMA in the home network
   is authorized (the PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix and/or PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address attributes are already present). However, if the VAAA local policy allows both home and visited LMA addresses to be delivered to the MAG, then this attribute MAY also be included.
   </t>

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length   |    Reserved     | Prefix-Length |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Visited MN-HNP                          
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                        Visited MN-HNP                          
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                        Visited MN-HNP                          
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                        Visited MN-HNP                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix 152.

Length:
   = at least 4 and no larger than 20.

Reserved:
   Reserved for future use.  The bits MUST be set to zero by the
   sender and MUST be ignored by the receiver. 

Prefix-Length:
   The 8-bit unsigned integer indicating the prefix length of
   the Visited MN-HNP (at least 0 and no larger than 128).  If
   the visited home network prefix contains an address of all zeroes 
   (i.e., '::'), then the Prefix-Length MUST be set to 128.

Visited Home Network Prefix:
   The home network prefix for the MN's IPv6 address configuration.
   The Prefix field is up to 16 octets in length.  Bits outside of
   the Prefix-Length, if included, must be zero.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>    
  </section>  

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID">
  <t>The PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID attribute (Type value 153) is of type
  String and contains the MN's interface identifier. The selection of the
  interface identifier SHOULD NOT allow the tracking of individual MNs or users
  between PMIPv6 mobility sessions for privacy reasons. This attribute
  is applicable in network systems and link technologies, where the
  network explicitly delivers an interface identifier to the MN during
  the link setup. Third Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) and PPP link technologies are examples of such.
  </t>

  <t>This attribute MAY be sent by the LMA or the MAG to the HAAA in the
  RADIUS Access-Request packet as a proposal. This attribute MAY be sent
  by the HAAA to the LMA or to the MAG in an Access-Accept packet; however, it
  MUST be present if the prior request already included one. 
  </t>      

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Home Interface Identifier    
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                    Home Interface Identifier                   
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  Home Interface Identifier     |                                 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID 153.

Length:
   = 10 octets.

Home Interface Identifier:
   The 64-bit long interface identifier (8 octets).
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>    
   
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID">
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID attribute (Type value 154) is of type
  String and contains the MN's interface identifier. The selection of the
  interface identifier SHOULD NOT allow the tracking of individual MNs or users
  between PMIPv6 mobility session for privacy reasons. This attribute
  is applicable in network systems and link technologies, where the
  network explicitly delivers an interface identifier to the MN during
  the link setup. 3GPP and PPP link technologies are examples of such.
  </t>

  <t>This attribute MAY be sent by the LMA or the MAG to the VAAA in the
  RADIUS Access-Request packet as a proposal. This attribute MAY be sent
  by the VAAA to the LMA or to the MAG in an Access-Accept packet; however, it
  MUST be present if the prior request already included one.
  </t>

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Visited Interface Identifier             
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                    Visited Interface Identifier                
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  Visited Interface Identifier  |                                 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID 154.

Length:
   = 10 octets.

Visited Interface Identifier:
   The 64-bit long interface identifier (8 octets).
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>    
   
  </section>
  

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA">
    <t><xref target="RFC5844"/> specifies 
    extensions to Proxy Mobile IPv6 protocol that enable IPv4 home address 
    mobility support to the MN. The PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA attribute (Type value 155) is of type Address and contains the IPv4 Home Address of the MN. The primary use of 
    this attribute is to deliver the assigned IPv4-HoA from HAAA to the MAG.</t>
   
   <t> The PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA is also used on the LMA-to-HAAA
   interface. If the LMA in the home network delegates the assignment of 
   the IPv4&nbhy;HoA to the HAAA, the attribute MUST contain an address of all zeroes 
   (i.e., 0.0.0.0) in the Access-Request message. The attribute MUST be included in by HAAA in the Access-Accept message if the previous request included it, and it contains the IPv4-HoA
   assigned to the MN.</t>
   <t>
   </t>
    
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |     Reserved      |Prefix-Len |  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Home IPv4 HoA                           | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA 155.

Length:
   = 8 octets

Reserved
   The 10-bit field reserved for future use.  The value MUST be
   initialized to zero by sender and MUST be ignored by the
   receiver.   
   
Prefix-Len
   The 6-bit unsigned integer indicating the prefix length of the
   IPv4 HoA.  If the Home IPv4 HoA contains an address of all zeroes
   (i.e., '0.0.0.0'), then the Prefix-Len MUST be set to 32.

Home IPv4 HoA:
   This field is of type Address and contains the IPv4 home
   address of the MN in the home network.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA">
    <t>When both the MAG and the LMA are in the visited network, the 
    PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA attribute (Type value 156) is of type Address and is
    used to exchange information
	between the VAAA and the MAG on the assignment of the IPv4 Home Address to 
	the MN being present in the visited network.</t>
   
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA is also used on the LMA-to-VAAA
   interface. If the LMA delegates the assignment of the IPv4-HoA to 
   the VAAA, the attribute MUST contain an address of all zeroes (i.e., 0.0.0.0)
   in the  RADIUS Access-Request message. The Access-Accept message MUST have 
   the attribute present if the prior request to the VAAA already included one.
   </t>
   <t>The attribute SHOULD NOT be included if the use of the LMA in the home 
   network is authorized (the PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA and/or 
   PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address attributes are already present). However, if the 
   VAAA local policy allows both home and visited LMA addresses to be delivered 
   to the MAG, then this attribute MAY also be included.
   </t>

    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |     Reserved      |Prefix-Len | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Visited IPv4 HoA                         | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>   
</figure>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Type:">
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
   PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA 156.
</t>
<t hangText="Length:">
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
   = 8 octets
</t>	
<t hangText="Reserved:">
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
   The 10-bit field reserved for future use.  The value MUST be
   initialized to zero by the sender and MUST be ignored by the
   receiver.
</t>  
<t hangText="Prefix-Len:">
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
   6-bit unsigned integer indicating the prefix length of the
   IPv4 HoA.  If the Visited IPv4 HoA contains an address of all zeroes 
   (i.e., '0.0.0.0'), then the Prefix-Len MUST be set to 32.
</t>   
<t hangText="Visited IPv4 HoA:">
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
   This field is of type Address and contains the IPv4 home
   address of the MN in the visited network.   
</t>
</list></t>
  </section>
  

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-DHCP4-Server-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Home-DHCP4-Server-Address (Type value 157) is of type Address and contains the
   IPv4 address of the DHCPv4 server in the home network. The particular
   DHCP server address is indicated to the MAG that serves the concerning MN.
   The HAAA MAY assign a DHCP server to the MAG in deployments where the MAG acts
   as a DHCP Relay, as defined in <xref target="RFC5844"/>. </t>
    
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Home DHCPv4 server address    
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   Home DHCPv4 server address   | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Home-DHCP4-Server-Address 157.

Length:
   = 6 octets.

Home DHCPv4 server address:
   This field is of type Address and contains a 4-octet IPv4 address
   of the DHCP server.
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-DHCP4-Server-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-DHCP4-Server-Address attribute (Type value 158)
   is of type Address and delivers the IPv4 address of the DHCPv4 server from the visited network to the MAG. When both  the MAG and the LMA are in the visited network, the VAAA MAY assign a DHCPv4 server to the MAG in
   deployments where the MAG acts as a DHCP Relay, as defined in
   <xref target="RFC5844"/>.
  </t>
    
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      | Visited DHCPv4 server address  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  Visited DHCPv4 server address | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


Type:
   PMIP6-Visited-DHCP4-Server-Address 158.

Length:
   = 6 octets

Visited DHCPv4 server address:
   This field is of type Address and contains a 4-octet IPv4 address
   of the DHCPv4 server.  
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-DHCP6-Server-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Home-DHCP6-Server-Address (Type value 159) is of type IPv6 address and contains the IPv6 address of the 
   DHCPv6 server in the home network indicated by the HAAA to the MAG that serves the MN. The HAAA MAY assign a DHCPv6 server to the 
   MAG in deployments where the MAG acts as a DHCP Relay, as defined in
   <xref target="RFC5213"/>. </t>
    
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Home DHCPv6 server address   
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                  Home DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                  Home DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                  Home DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   Home DHCPv6 server address   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Home-DHCP6-Server-Address 159.

Length:
   = 18 octets

Home DHCPv6 server address:
   This field is of type Address and contains 16-octet IPv6 address
   of the DHCPv6 server.   
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>  

  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-DHCP6-Server-Address">
   <t>The PMIP6-Visited-DHCP6-Server-Address attribute (Type value 160) is of type IPv6 address and contains the IPv6 address of the DHCPv6 server in the visited network indicated by the VAAA to the MAG that serves 
   the MN. When both MAG and the LMA are located in the visited network, the VAAA MAY assign a DHCPv6 server to the MAG in deployments where the MAG acts as a DHCP Relay, as defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/>.
   </t>
    
    <figure>   
    <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      | Visited DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                 Visited DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                 Visited DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                 Visited DHCPv6 server address
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  Visited DHCPv6 server address |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
  PMIP6-Visited-DHCP6-Server-Address 160.

Length:
   = 18 octets

Visited DHCPv6 server address:
   This field is of type Address and contains the 16-octet IPv6
   address of the DHCPv6 server.   
    ]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section title="Calling-Station-Id">
    <t> The Calling-Station-Id attribute (Type value 31) is of type String. When used within PMIPv6 deployments, the attribute contains the MN Link-Layer Identifier option of the MN as defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/>, Sections 2.2 and 8.6.
    </t>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Chargeable-User-Identity">
    <t>The Chargeable-User-Identity attribute, or CUI, (Type value 89) is a unique,
	temporary handle used as means to, for example, correlate authentication,
	accounting, and bill post-processing for a particular chargeable subscriber.
	The CUI format and use follows guidelines defined by <xref target="RFC4372"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	In the scope of this document, the CUI attribute MAY be
	present in the Access-Request. The CUI MAY also be present in the Access-Accept.
	The CUI MUST be present in the Access-Accept if it was
	present in the Access-Request. If the use of the Chargeable-User-Identity attribute is supported, then the MAG and/or the LMA commits to include
	the Chargeable-User-Identity attribute in all subsequent RADIUS Accounting packets they
	send for the given user.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway">
    <t><xref target="RFC5844"/> specifies 
    extensions to Proxy Mobile IPv6 protocol that enable IPv4 home address 
    mobility support to the MN. The PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway attribute (Type value 161) is of type Address and contains the default gateway IPv4 address for the MN. This address is populated into the PMIPv6
    IPv4 Default-Router Address Option <xref target="RFC5844"/>. The address
    MUST belong to the subnet defined in the PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA attribute.
    </t>
   
    <figure >   
    <artwork>
    <![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |   Home IPv4 default gateway  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            address             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway 161.

Length:
   = 6 octets

Home IPv4 default gateway address:
   This field is of type Address and contains a 4-octet IPv4 default
   gateway address. 
    ]]>                                                          
    </artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>


  <section title="PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway">
    <t><xref target="RFC5844"/> specifies 
    extensions to Proxy Mobile IPv6 protocol that enable IPv4 home address 
    mobility support to the MN. The PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway attribute (Type value 162) is of type Address and contains the default gateway IPv4 address for the MN. This address is populated into the PMIPv6
    IPv4 Default-Router Address Option <xref target="RFC5844"/>. The address
    MUST belong to the subnet defined in the PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA attribute.
    </t>
    <figure >   
    <artwork>
    <![CDATA[  
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Visited IPv4 default gateway  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            address             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type:
   PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway 162.

Length:
   = 6 octets

Visited IPv4 default gateway address:
   This field is of type Address and contains a 4-octet IPv4 default
   gateway address.
    ]]>                                                          
    </artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>

</section>

<section title="MAG to RADIUS AAA Interface">
  <section title="Interface Operations">
    <t>The MAG to the AAA RADIUS server interface is used for
       retrieval of the policy profile  when an MN tries to attach, authenticate,
       and authorize to a PMIPv6 domain. Depending on the policies
	   and network capabilities, the MAG may retrieve different sets of PMIPv6-session-related parameters:
	    <list style="symbols">
		<t> Configuration attributes for home or visited network access scenario, depending on the location and attachment point of the MN,</t>
		<t> The IPv6 or IPv4 address of the designated LMA, depending on the access network's actual IP topology,</t>
		<t> The IPv6 or IPv4 configuration parameters for the MN, depending on the utilized IP configuration method and individual MN's service Policy,</t>
		<t> The DHCP Relay support attributes (IPv4 or IPv6) in case such functionality is supported in the network.</t>
		</list>
	</t>
	<t>In addition to PMIPv6-specific attributes, other RADIUS attributes
    are to be used on the MAG-to-AAA interface.
    </t>
    <t>
    The User-Name attribute MUST be present in the Access-Request.
    It MUST carry a correctly formed identifier that SHOULD correspond to an MN identity unless the identity is being
    suppressed for policy reasons, for example, when identity hiding
    is in effect.  The MN identity, if available, MUST be in Network
    Access Identifier (NAI) <xref target="RFC4282"/> format.  At minimum,
    the home realm of the MN MUST be available at the MAG when the network
    access authentication takes place.  Otherwise, the MAG is not able to
    route RADIUS request messages towards the correct HAAA.  The MN
    identity used on the MAG-to-HAAA interface and in the User-Name
    attribute MAY entirely be related to the network access
    authentication and, therefore, not be suitable to be used as the
    MN-Identifier mobility option value in the subsequent PBU/PBA messages.
    In this case, the HAAA MUST provide the MN-Identifier for PBU/PBA
    messages using the Mobile-Node-Identifier attribute (see
    <xref target="mni"/>).
    </t>
    <t>At least one of the NAS-IP-Address, NAS-IPv6-Address, or
    NAS&nbhy;Identifier attributes MUST be present in the Access-Request.
    The Service-Type attribute SHOULD be set to value 1 (Login) and the NAS-Port-Type
    attribute SHOULD be present in the Access-Request.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Table of Attributes">
    <t>The following table provides a guide to attributes that may be found
       in authentication and authorization RADIUS messages between the MAG and the AAA server.
	   </t>
    <figure>   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
Request Accept Reject Challenge #  Attribute

1       0-1    0      0         1  User-Name
0-1     0      0      0         4  NAS-IP-Address
0-1     0-1    0      0         5  NAS-Port
0-1     0-1    0      0         6  Service-Type
0-1     0-1    0      0-1      24  State
0       0-1    0      0        25  Class
0       0-1    0      0-1      27  Session-Timeout
0-1     0      0      0        31  Calling-Station-Id
0-1     0      0      0        32  NAS-Identifier
0+      0+     0+     0+       33  Proxy-State
0-1     0      0      0        69  NAS-Port-Type
0+      0+     0+     0+       79  EAP-Message
1       1      1      1        80  Message-Authenticator
0-1     0-1    0      0        89  Chargeable-User-Identity
0-1     0      0      0        95  NAS-IPv6-Address
0-1     0-1    0      0       124  MIP6-Feature-Vector
0       1      0      0       145  Mobile-Node-Identifier
0-1     0-1    0      0       146  Service-Selection
0       0-1    0      0       147  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address
0-1     0-1    0      0       148  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address
0       0-1    0      0       149  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address
0-1     0-1    0      0       150  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address
0       0+     0      0       151  PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix
0       0+     0      0       152  PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix
0       0-1    0      0       153  PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID
0       0-1    0      0       154  PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID
0       0-1    0      0       155  PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA
0       0-1    0      0       156  PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA
0       0-1    0      0       157  PMIP6-Home-DHCP4-Server-Address
0       0-1    0      0       158  PMIP6-Visited-DHCP4-Server-Address
0       0-1    0      0       159  PMIP6-Home-DHCP6-Server-Address
0       0-1    0      0       160  PMIP6-Visited-DHCP6-Server-Address
0       0-1    0      0       161  PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway
0       0-1    0      0       162  PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway
]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>


</section>

<section title="LMA to RADIUS AAA Interface">
  <section title="Interface Operations">
  <t>
  The LMA-to-HAAA interface may be used for multiple purposes.  These
  include the authorization of the incoming PBU, updating the LMA
  address to the HAAA, delegating the assignment of the MN-HNP or the
  IPv4-HoA to the HAAA, and accounting and PMIPv6 session
  management.  The primary purpose of this interface is to update the
  HAAA with the LMA address information in case of dynamically
  assigned LMA and to exchange the MN address assignment information
  between the LMA and the HAAA.
  </t>
  <t>
  Whenever the LMA sends an Access-Request message to the HAAA, the
  User-Name attribute SHOULD contain the MN's identity.  The LMA-provided
  identity in the User-Name attribute is strongly RECOMMENDED to
  be the same as the MN's identity information in the PBU MN-Identifier
  mobility option.  The identity SHOULD also be the same as used on the
  MAG-to-HAAA interface; however, in case those identities differ, the HAAA
  MUST have a mechanism of mapping the MN identity used on the MAG-to-HAAA interface to the identity used on the LMA-to-HAAA interface.
  </t>
  <t>
  If the PBU contains the MN Link-Layer Identifier option, the Calling-
  Station-Id attribute SHOULD be included in the request message containing
  the received MN Link-Layer Identifier option.  Furthermore, if the PBU contains
  the Service Selection mobility option <xref target="RFC5149"/>, the Service-Selection
  attribute SHOULD be included in the request message containing the
  received service identifier.  Both the MN Link-Layer Identifier option
  and the service selection can be used to provide more information for
  the PBU authorization step in the HAAA.
  </t>
  <t>
  The Service-Type attribute MUST be set to the value 17 (Authorize Only).
  If the HAAA is not able to authorize the subscriber's mobility service
  session, then the Access-Reject message to the LMA MAY contain the
  Reply-Message attribute describing the reason for rejecting the
  authorization. A failed authorization obviously results in a rejection
  of the PBU, and a PBA with an appropriate error Status Value MUST be
  sent back to the MAG.
  </t>
  <t>
  The authorization step MUST be performed at least for the initial PBU
  session up to a mobility session, when the LMA-to-HAAA interface is
  deployed.  For the subsequent re-registration and handover of PBUs, the
  authorization step MAY be repeated (in this case, the LMA-to-HAAA
  interface should also maintain an authorization session state).
  </t>
  <t>
  In case of a dynamic LMA discovery and assignment <xref target="RFC6097"/>, the
  HAAA and the remote policy store may need to be updated with the
  selected LMA address information.  The update can be done during the
  PBU authorization step using the LMA-to-HAAA interface.  This
  specification uses the PMIP6-*-LMA-*-Address attribute for carrying
  the LMA's address information from the LMA to the HAAA.  The LMA address
  information in the request message MUST contain the IP address of the
  LMA, the Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) uniquely identifying 
  the LMA, or both.  The LMA address information refers to the PMIPv6
  part of the LMA, not necessarily the LMA part interfacing with the
  AAA infrastructure.
  </t>
  <t>
  The LMA and the HAAA use the PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix/PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix attributes  to exchange the MN-HNP
  when appropriate.  Similarly, the LMA and the HAAA use the PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA/PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA
  attributes to exchange the IPv4-MN-HoA when appropriate. The MN
  address information exchange is again done during the PBU
  authorization step.  The HAAA MAY also use the LMA-provided MN
  address information as a part of the information used to authorize
  the PBU.
  </t>
  <t>
  Which entity is actually responsible for the address management is
  deployment specific within the PMIPv6 Domain and MUST be pre-agreed
  on per deployment basis.  When the LMA is responsible for the address
  management, the PMIP6-*-HN-Prefix/PMIP6-*-IPv4-HoA attributes are used to inform the HAAA and the remote policy store of the MN-HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA
  assigned to the MN. 
  It is also possible that the LMA delegates the address management to
  the HAAA.  In this case, the MN&nbhy;HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA are set to undefined
  addresses in the Access-Request message sent from the LMA to the HAAA.
  The LMA expects to receive the HAAA assigned HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA in the
  corresponding Access-Accept message.
  </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Table of Attributes">
    <t>The following table provides a guide to which attributes may be found
       in authorization process between LMA and the AAA.</t>
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[
Request Accept Reject Challenge #   Attribute

1       0-1    0      0         1   User-Name
0-1     0-1    0      0         4   NAS-IP-Address   
0-1     0-1    0      0         5   NAS-Port
1       0-1    0      0         6   Service-Type
0       0-1    0      0        25   Class
0       0-1    0      0-1      27   Session-Timeout
0-1     0      0      0        31   Calling-Station-Id
1       0      0      0        32   NAS-Identifier
0+      0+     0+     0+       33   Proxy-State
1       0      0      0        69   NAS-Port-Type
1       1      1      1        80   Message-Authenticator
0-1     0-1    0      0        89   Chargeable-User-Identity
0-1     0-1    0      0        95   NAS-IPv6-Address   
0-1     0-1    0      0       124   MIP6-Feature-Vector
1       0      0      0       145   Mobile-Node-Identifier       
0-1     0-1    0      0       146   Service-Selection
0-1     0      0      0       147   PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address
0-1     0      0      0       148   PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address
0-1     0      0      0       149   PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address   
0-1     0      0      0       150   PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address
0+      0+     0      0       151   PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix
0+      0+     0      0       152   PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix    
0-1     0-1    0      0       153   PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID
0-1     0-1    0      0       154   PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID
0-1     0-1    0      0       155   PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA
0-1     0-1    0      0       156   PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA   
0-1     0-1    0      0       161   PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway
0-1     0-1    0      0       162   PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway
]]></artwork>   
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>


<section anchor="Accounting" title="Accounting">
	<t>
	Radius-based interfaces at the MAG and LMA with the AAA server enables the metering of
traffic associated with the MN, commonly called "accounting". If accounting is turned on in the mobile node's policy profile, the local routing SHOULD NOT be enabled <xref target="RFC5213"/>.
	</t>
  <section anchor="Accounting at LMA" title="Accounting at LMA">
    <t>The accounting at the LMA to AAA server interface is based on <xref target="RFC2865"/> and
    <xref target='RFC2866'/>. This interface MUST support the transfer of accounting
   records needed for service control and charging. These records should include (but
   may not be limited to) the following: time of binding cache entry creation and
   deletion, number of the octets sent and received by the MN over the bi-directional
   tunnel, etc.</t>
  
  </section>  <!---end of Accounting at LMA -->        
    
  <section anchor="Accounting at MAG" title="Accounting at MAG">
    <t>The accounting at the MAG to AAA server interface is based on <xref target="RFC2865"/> and
    <xref target='RFC2866'/>. The interface MUST also support the transfer of accounting
   records that should include the following: time of binding cache entry creation and
   deletion, number of the octets sent and received by the MN over the bi-directional
   tunnel, etc.
   </t>
   <t>If there is data traffic between a visiting MN and a
   correspondent node that is locally attached to an access link
   connected to the same MAG, the mobile access gateway MAY
   optimize on the delivery efforts by locally routing the packets instead of
   using reverse tunneling to the mobile node's LMA.
   In this case, the local data traffic too MUST be reported to AAA Accounting servers
   by means of RADIUS protocol.</t>
  </section>  <!---end of Accounting at MAG -->        

  <section title='Table of Attributes'>
  <t>The following table provides a list of attributes that may be included
   in the RADIUS Accounting messages. These attributes are to complement the
   set of accounting attributes already required by <xref target="RFC2866"/>
   and <xref target="RFC2869"/>.
   </t>
    <figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
Accounting  
Request       #  Attribute

0-1         145  Mobile-Node-Identifier
0-1         146  Service-Selection
0-1         147  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address
0-1         148  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address
0-1         149  PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address
0-1         150  PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address            
0+          151  PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix
0+          152  PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix      
0-1         155  PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA
0-1         156  PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA
0-1          31  Calling-Station-Id
0-1          80  Message-Authenticator
0-1          89  Chargeable-User-Identity
0-1         124  MIP6-Feature-Vector
   ]]></artwork>   
   </figure>   
  </section> 
  <!---end of Table of Attributes -->  

</section>  <!---end of Accounting -->           
    
<section title='Security Considerations'>
  <t>The RADIUS messages may be transported between the MAG and/or the LMA to the
     RADIUS server via one or more AAA brokers or RADIUS proxies. In
     this case, the communication between the LMA and the RADIUS AAA server relies on the
     security properties of the intermediate AAA brokers and RADIUS proxies.
  </t>
  <t>Regarding the privacy threats associated with sending MN-specific
  information between the MAG and AAA server and between the LMA and
  AAA server, considerations of the RADIUS Base protocol
  <xref target="RFC2865"/>, RADIUS Accounting <xref target="RFC2866"/>, and the RADIUS EAP
  application <xref target="RFC3579"/> are applicable to this document.
  The MAG, LMA, and AAA server SHOULD avoid including attributes containing
  personally identifying information such as a MN's Interface ID, link-layer address, or NAI, except as needed and SHOULD pay special attention if identity hiding is desired.
  
  </t>
</section> 
   <!---end of Security Considerations -->

<section title='IANA Consideration'>
<section title='Attribute Type Codes'>
<t>This specification defines the following new RADIUS attribute type
   values:</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[  
        Mobile-Node-Identifier              145
        Service-Selection                   146
        PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv6-Address         147   
        PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv6-Address      148
        PMIP6-Home-LMA-IPv4-Address         149
        PMIP6-Visited-LMA-IPv4-Address      150
        PMIP6-Home-HN-Prefix                151
        PMIP6-Visited-HN-Prefix             152
        PMIP6-Home-Interface-ID             153
        PMIP6-Visited-Interface-ID          154
        PMIP6-Home-IPv4-HoA                 155
        PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-HoA              156
        PMIP6-Home-DHCP4-Server-Address     157
        PMIP6-Visited-DHCP4-Server-Address  158
        PMIP6-Home-DHCP6-Server-Address     159
        PMIP6-Visited-DHCP6-Server-Address  160
        PMIP6-Home-IPv4-Gateway             161
        PMIP6-Visited-IPv4-Gateway          162

   ]]></artwork></figure>   
</section>
<!---end of Attribute Type Codes -->

<section title='Namespaces'>
<t>This specification defines new values to the Mobility Capability
   registry (see <xref target="RFC5447"/>) for use with the MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP:</t>

<figure >   
    <artwork><![CDATA[  
  Token                             | Value                             
  ----------------------------------+--------------------            
  IP4_TRANSPORT_SUPPORTED           | 0x0000800000000000
  IP4_HOA_ONLY_SUPPORTED            | 0x0001000000000000
   ]]></artwork>   
</figure>
   
</section>
<!---end of Namespaces -->

</section>
<!---end of IANA consideration -->

<section title='Acknowledgements'>
  <t> First of all, the authors would like to acknowledge
  the standardization work and people of the WiMAX Forum that
  have set the foundation for this document.
</t><t>
  The authors would like to thank Basavaraj Patil, Glen Zorn, Avi Lior, Alan DeKok, Dhananjay Patki and Pete McCann for reviewing the document and providing valuable input. The authors also thank Elwyn Davies, Pete Resnick, Bernard Aboba, Jari Arkko, and Stephen Farrell for their reviews on the document during the IESG process.
</t><t>
  The authors would also like to thank the authors of <xref target="RFC5779"/>
  as this document reuses some procedural ideas of that specification.</t>
</section>
<!---end of Acknowledgements -->  

 </middle>

 <back>

 <references title='Normative References'> 
  &RFC2119;
  &RFC2865;
  &RFC5213;
  &RFC4282;
  &RFC5447;
  &RFC3588;
  &RFC5844;
  &RFC5779;
  &RFC4372;
  </references>

 <references title='Informative References'>
  &RFC3579;
  &RFC2866;
  &RFC2869;  
  &RFC3748;
  &RFC5149;
  &RFC6097;


<reference anchor="UNF" target="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr15/">
 <front>
   <title>Unicode Standard Annex #15: Unicode Normalization Forms</title>
   <author initials="M." surname="Davis" fullname="Mark Davis" role="editor"/>
   <author initials="K." surname="Whistler" fullname="Ken Whistler" role="editor"/>
   <date month='January' year='2012' />
 </front>
</reference>
</references>
 
 </back> 
 
 </rfc>
