<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" number="6758" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Tunneling of Message Transfer Priorities">
      Tunneling of SMTP Message Transfer Priorities
    </title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
      <organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
          <street>36 Station Road</street>
          <city>Hampton</city>
          <region>Middlesex</region>
          <code>TW12 2BX</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
      
    <author initials="K." surname="Carlberg" fullname="Ken Carlberg">
      <organization>G11</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1601 Clarendon Blvd, #203</street>
          <city>Arlington</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>22209</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>carlberg@g11.org.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2012"/>
    
    <keyword>SMTP</keyword>
    <keyword>Priority</keyword>
    <keyword>MMHS</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
   This memo defines a mechanism for tunneling of SMTP (Simple Mail Transfer
   Protocol) Message Transfer Priority values through MTAs (Message Transfer
   Agents) that don't support the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

<t>
  The SMTP Message Transfer Priorities extension <xref target="RFC6710"/>
  specifies a mechanism to allow messages to be given a label to
  indicate preferential handling, to enable mail handling nodes to take
  this into account for onward processing. However, as with all SMTP
  extensions, all SMTP Message Transfer Agents (MTAs) between the
  source and the destination must support the extension in order for it
  to be successfully used. This document describes an application-layer
  tunneling of message priority, to convey the priority of the messages
  through MTAs that do not support the Message Transfer Priorities extension.
  The tunneling is done by adding a new message header field to the Internet
  Message Format specified in <xref target="RFC5322"/>.
</t>

<t>
  A number of other header fields are already in use, mostly in
   Message User Agents (MUAs), to convey meanings related to importance
   or priority of messages.
   Examples of such header fields are Importance <xref target="RFC2156"/>,
   Priority <xref target="RFC2156"/>, and X-Priority (undocumented).
   Considering sometimes subtle and sometimes significant differences in the meaning of these header fields
   and widely different syntax, this document defines a new header field.
</t>

<t>This document is motivated by 2 main deployment scenarios: (1) an MUA
   talking to a non-MT-PRIORITY-aware Message Submission Agent (MSA), and
   (2) the use of an unextended MUA to talk to an MT-PRIORITY-aware MSA.
   These 2 use cases are discussed in more detail below.</t>

<!--////Add ASCII art?-->

<t>Use case (1) is about an MT-PRIORITY-capable MUA talking to a
   non&nbhy;MT&nbhy;PRIORITY-capable MSA <xref target="RFC6409"/>,
   which in turn is talking to an MT-PRIORITY-capable
   MTA <xref target="RFC5321"/>. Both the MSA and MTA are within the same
   ADministrative Management Domain (ADMD) and are on a fast network;
   however, some recipients are accessible via the MTA that is talking over
   a slow link to the next MTA. Communications over that slow link can benefit
   from the use of the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension.</t>

<t>In use case (2), a widely deployed client (such as a desktop client) is
   talking to an MT-PRIORITY-capable MSA. The client might be extendable via a
   plug-in API provided by the client developers; however, existing APIs
   frequently allow easy manipulation of email header fields, while not
   allowing for addition of SMTP protocol features. In such a case, installing
   a plug-in on the client that can set the MT-Priority header field could
   provide easier and earlier deployment of the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension in
   an organization without requiring changes to desktop clients.</t>

<t>
We note that the above use cases are not exhaustive and that other use cases --
variations of the above --
may exist.  The purpose of this document is not to consider every scenario, but
rather examples
that reinforce the need to consider a tunneling mechanism that can deal with
SMTP-capable devices
that do not support <xref target="RFC6710"/>.
</t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
            this document are to be interpreted as described in
            <xref target="RFC2119"/> when they appear in ALL CAPS.
      These words also appear in this document in lower case as plain
      English words, absent their normative meanings.</t>
      
      <t>The formal syntax uses the <xref target="RFC5234">Augmented
         Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)</xref> notation, including the core rules
         defined in Appendix B of <xref target="RFC5234">RFC 5234</xref>.
      </t>

<t>
In examples, "C:" and "S:" indicate lines sent by the client and
server, respectively.  Line breaks that do not start with a new "C:" or
"S:" exist for editorial reasons and are not a part of the protocol.
</t>

<t>
  This document uses the term "priority" specifically in relation to
  the internal treatment of a message by the server. Messages with
  higher priorities may be given expedited handling, and those with
  lower priorities may be handled only as resources become available.
</t>

    </section>


    <section title="Handling of Messages Received via SMTP">
      
        <t>
  The subsections of this section update the corresponding subsections
  of Section 4 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>.
        </t>

        
        <section title="Handling of the MT-PRIORITY Parameter by the Receiving SMTP Server" anchor="message-pri">

            <t>
        This specification inserts the following between steps 4 and 5
        in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>:

        <list style="format 4%c.">

                <t>If the sending SMTP client hasn't specified the MT-PRIORITY parameter to the MAIL FROM command,
                but the message has a single syntactically valid MT-Priority header field (see <xref target="mt-priority"/>),
                then the value of this header field is the message priority.</t>

          <t>
    In the absence of both the MT-PRIORITY MAIL FROM parameter and the MT-Priority header field,
    other message header fields, such as Priority <xref target="RFC2156"/> and X-Priority,
    MAY be used for determining the priority under this "Priority Message Handling" SMTP extension.
    Note, however, that the Importance <xref target="RFC2156"/> header field MUST NOT be used for determining
    the priority under this "Priority Message Handling" SMTP extension, as it has different semantics:
    the Importance header field is aimed at the user recipient and not at the nodes responsible for transferring the message.
          </t>

      </list>

            </t>

        </section>

        <section title="Relay of Messages to Other Conforming SMTP/LMTP Servers" anchor="relay-conform">
            
            <t>
      This specification inserts the following between steps 1 and 2
      in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>.

<list style="format 1%c.">
    
                <t>
    Note that rule 1 also applies to messages that didn't have any priority
    explicitly specified using the MT-PRIORITY MAIL FROM parameter or the MT-Priority header field.
    </t>

</list>

            </t>

        </section>

        <section title="Relay of Messages to Non-Conforming SMTP/LMTP Servers" anchor="relay-non-conform">

           <t>
     This specification appends the following after step 1
     in Section 4.3 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>:

         <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">

    <t hangText="2.">
    The relaying MTA MUST first remove any and all existing MT&nbhy;Priority
    header fields from the message. (Please see <xref target="seccons"/>
    for additional considerations related to removal of the MT-Priority
    header field.)
  </t>
  
    <t hangText="3.">
    If the incoming message had an MT-PRIORITY parameter specified in the MAIL FROM
    command *or* there was an MT-Priority header field
    removed in step 2 above, then the relaying MTA MUST add its own
    MT-Priority header field with the value determined by the
    procedure in <xref target="message-pri"/>.
    The syntax of the MT-Priority header field is specified in <xref target="mt-priority"/>.
                </t>
</list>
</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Mailing Lists and Aliases">

    <t>
    This specification makes no changes to Section 4.4 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>.
    </t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Gatewaying a Message into a Foreign Environment">
            
          <t>
   This specification inserts the following between steps 1 and 2
   in Section 4.5 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>.

<list style="format 1%c.">

        <t>
  Note that if the destination environment doesn't support the transport
  of an arbitrary header field, the requirement in <xref target="relay-non-conform"/>
  to add an MT-Priority header field doesn't apply.
        </t>
    
</list>

          </t>
        
        </section>

        <section title="Interaction with the DSN SMTP Extension">

           <t>
     This specification makes no changes to Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC6710"/>.
           </t>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Header Field: MT-Priority" anchor="mt-priority">
      <figure><artwork>
Applicable protocol: mail [RFC5322]
Status: standard
Author/change controller: Alexey Melnikov / IESG (iesg@ietf.org)
   on behalf of the IETF
Specification document(s): RFC 6758
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>
        The MT-Priority header field conveys message transfer priority when relaying
        a message through MTAs that don't support the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension.
      </t>

      <t>
      The ABNF for this header field is defined as follows:
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
   priority-header-field = "MT-Priority:"
                           [CFWS] priority-value [CFWS] CRLF
]]>  </artwork></figure>

      <t>where "priority-value" is defined in <xref target="RFC6710"/>.</t>
      
      <figure><artwork>
Example:
MT-Priority: -3

Example:
MT-Priority: 4 (ultra)
      </artwork></figure>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Example">

     <t>
     Note that the following example of an SMTP transaction with 2
     recipients is also making use of the STARTTLS <xref target="RFC3207"/> and
     Delivery Status Notification (DSN) <xref target="RFC3461"/> SMTP
     extensions, even though there is no requirement
     that these other extensions are to be supported when the MT-PRIORITY
     SMTP extension is implemented.
     </t>
        
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
     S: 220 example.net SMTP server here
     C: EHLO example.com
     S: 250-example.net
     S: 250-DSN
     S: 250-STARTTLS
     S: 250 MT-PRIORITY STANAG4406
     C: STARTTLS
     [...TLS negotiation...]
     C: MAIL FROM:<eljefe@example.com> ENVID=QQ314159
         MT-PRIORITY=3
     S: 250 <eljefe@example.com> sender ok
     C: RCPT TO:<topbanana@example.net>
     S: 250 <topbanana@example.net> recipient ok
     C: RCPT TO:<Dana@Ivory.example.net> NOTIFY=SUCCESS,FAILURE
         ORCPT=rfc822;Dana@Ivory.example.net
     S: 250 <Dana@Ivory.example.net> recipient ok
     C: DATA
     S: 354 okay, send message
     C:  (message goes here)
     C: .
     S: 250 message accepted
     C: QUIT
     S: 221 goodbye
]]></artwork></figure>
   
           <t>
           Here, the receiving SMTP server supports the "STANAG4406" Priority Assignment Policy
     <xref target="RFC6710"/> with 6 priority levels, so it will use the priority value
     4 internally (the next supported priority higher or equal to 3)
     and will communicate the priority value 3 when relaying it to the next hop (if necessary).
     When relaying the message to the next hop that doesn't support the MT-PRIORITY SMTP
     extension, the transaction might look like this:
           </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
     S: 220 example.org SMTP server here
     C: EHLO example.net
     S: 250-example.org
     S: 250-DSN
     S: 250-STARTTLS
     S: 250 SIZE
     C: STARTTLS
     [...TLS negotiation...]
     C: MAIL FROM:<eljefe@example.com> ENVID=QQ314159
     S: 250 <eljefe@example.com> sender ok
     C: RCPT TO:<topbanana@example.net>
     S: 250 <topbanana@example.net> recipient ok
     C: RCPT TO:<Dana@Ivory.example.net> NOTIFY=SUCCESS,FAILURE
         ORCPT=rfc822;Dana@Ivory.example.net
     S: 250 <Dana@Ivory.example.net> recipient ok
     C: DATA
     S: 354 okay, send message
     C: MT-Priority: 3
     C:  (the rest of the message goes here)
     C: .
     S: 250 message accepted
     C: QUIT
     S: 221 goodbye
]]>  </artwork> </figure>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-regs">

      <t>IANA has added the following list of header field names to
      the "Permanent Message Header Field Names" registry (in
      <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/message-headers/perm-headers.html"/>):</t>

      <figure><artwork>
Header field: MT-Priority
Applicable protocol: mail
Status: standard
Author/change controller: Alexey Melnikov / IESG (iesg@ietf.org)
   on behalf of the IETF
Specification document(s): RFC 6758
      </artwork></figure>
        
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="seccons">
        
        <t>This document allows a message priority to be tunneled through MTAs
        that don't support the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension by specifying how it can be
        represented in the message itself (using the MT-Priority header field).
        Thus, it is important to ensure that an MTA receiving a message containing
        the MT-Priority header field can trust that it was set by an authorized agent.

  The use of technologies such as DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM)
  <xref target="RFC6376"/> or S/MIME
  to sign the MT&nbhy;Priority header field value can enable a recipient to verify
  whether the specified priority value was generated by a trusted agent.
  In particular, DKIM signing allows a recipient to verify that the
  specified priority value was present when the message was
  signed, and to verify who signed the message. Note, however, that the DKIM
  signer might not be the same agent that generated the MT-Priority header
  field.
        </t>

  <t>
  MSAs ought to only accept message transfer
  priorities (whether by using the MT-PRIORITY parameter to the MAIL FROM command or
        the MT&nbhy;Priority header field in the message itself)
  from users (or only certain groups of such users) who are authenticated and authorized
  in some way that's acceptable to the MSA.  As part of this policy, they can also
  restrict maximum priority values that different groups of users can
  request and can override the priority values specified by MUAs.
  When relaying to non-MT-PRIORITY-capable SMTP/LMTP (Local Mail
Transfer Protocol) servers, such MSAs are required to replace any MT&nbhy;Priority
header field values that don't satisfy this policy.
  See <xref target="dkim"/> for more details on what the consequences of such
changes might be.
  </t>

        <t>
  Similarly, MTAs ought to only accept message transfer priorities
  (whether by using the MT-PRIORITY parameter to the MAIL FROM command or
        the MT-Priority header field in the message itself) from senders
  (or only certain groups of such senders) who are authenticated and authorized
  in some way that's acceptable to the MTA.  As part of this policy, they can also
  restrict maximum priority values that different groups of senders can
  request and can override the priority values specified by them.
  When relaying to non-MT-PRIORITY-capable SMTP/LMTP servers, such MTAs are
  required to replace any MT-Priority header field values that don't satisfy
  this policy.
  See <xref target="dkim"/> for more details on what the consequences of such
changes might be.
        </t>
      
        <t>
        In the absence of the policy enforcement mentioned above, an SMTP server (whether an MSA or an MTA)
  implementing the MT-PRIORITY SMTP extension might be susceptible to a
  denial-of-service attack. For example,
        malicious clients (MUAs/MSAs/MTAs) can try to abuse this feature by always
  requesting priority 9.
        </t>

        <t>
        To protect the MT-Priority header field from modification or insertion,
        MUAs, MSAs, and MTAs inserting it into messages SHOULD use a message
header protection
        mechanism such as DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"/>; however,
see <xref target="dkim"/> for more information.
        </t>

      <section title="Modification of the MT-Priority Header Field and DKIM" anchor="dkim">

<t>An MSA/MTA that receives a message with an MT-Priority header field
protected by DKIM and that wants to change the message priority due to its
policy is forced to choose between

     <list style="letters">

       <t>breaking DKIM signatures (by replacing the MT-Priority header value),</t>
       
       <t>leaving the message as is (and using the MT-PRIORITY MAIL FROM
       parameter), relying on the fact that all downstream MTAs are compliant
       with this specification, and</t>
       
       <t>rejecting the message.</t>
       
      </list>
  
None of these choices are perfect.  They work in a particular situation, so these choices
should be carefully considered during implementation and deployment.
</t>

<t>
If the MSA/MTA decides to alter the message, it SHOULD re-sign the message with DKIM.
</t>

      </section>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>

  <?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
    <references title="Normative References">
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?> <!-- Keywords -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3461"?> <!-- SMTP DSN -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?> <!-- ABNF -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5321"?> <!-- SMTP -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322"?> <!-- Email -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6409"?> <!-- Submission Service -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6710"?> <!-- SMTP Priorities -->

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2156"?> <!-- MIXER -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3207"?> <!-- SMTP STARTTLS -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6376"?> <!-- DKIM -->

<!-- draft-schmeing-smtp-priorities (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='SMTP-PRI-OLD'>
<front>
<title>SMTP Service Extension for Priority Message Handling</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Schmeing' fullname='Michael Schmeing'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Brendecke' fullname='J. Brendecke'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Carlberg' fullname='K. Carlberg'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='August' year='2006' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

    </references>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
        
      <t>
      This document copies lots of text from "SMTP Service Extension
   for Priority Message Handling" <xref target="SMTP-PRI-OLD"/>.
   Therefore, the authors of this document would like to acknowledge
   contributions made by the authors of that document: Michael Schmeing
   and Jan-Wilhelm Brendecke.
      </t>

      <t>
      Many thanks for input provided by Steve Kille, David Wilson,
      John Klensin, Dave Crocker, Graeme Lunt, Alessandro Vesely,
      Barry Leiba, Bill McQuillan, Murray Kucherawy, SM,
      Glenn Parsons, Pete Resnick, Chris Newman, Ned Freed, Claudio Allocchio,
      Martin Thomson, and Joseph Yee.
      </t>

      <t>
      Special thanks to Barry Leiba for agreeing to shepherd this document.
      </t>
 
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
