<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC1958 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1958.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3756 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3756.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3819 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3819.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4593 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4593.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4944 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4944.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4919 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4919.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5548 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5548.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5556 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5556.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5673 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5673.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5706 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5706.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5826 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5826.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5867 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5867.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5996 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5996.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC6282 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6282.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC6434 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6434.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" number="6606" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

        <front>
                <title abbrev="6LoWPAN Routing Requirements">
                        Problem Statement and Requirements for IPv6&nbsp;over&nbsp;Low&nbhy;Power&nbsp;Wireless&nbsp;Personal&nbsp;Area&nbsp;Network&nbsp;(6LoWPAN)&nbsp;Routing
                </title>

                <author initials="E." surname="Kim" fullname="Eunsook Eunah Kim">
                        <organization>ETRI</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>161 Gajeong-dong</street>
                                        <street>Yuseong-gu</street>
                                        <city>Daejeon</city>
                                        <code>305-700</code>
                                        <country>Korea</country>
                                </postal>
                                <phone>+82-42-860-6124</phone>
                                <email>eunah.ietf@gmail.com</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author initials="D." surname="Kaspar" fullname="Dominik Kaspar">
                        <organization>Simula Research Laboratory</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>Martin Linges v 17</street>
                                        <city>Fornebu</city>
                                        <code>1364</code>
                                        <country>Norway</country>
                                </postal>
                                <phone>+47-6782-8223</phone>
                                <email>dokaspar.ietf@gmail.com</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author initials="C." surname="Gomez" fullname="Carles Gomez">
                        <organization>Universitat Politecnica de
Catalunya/Fundacio i2CAT</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>Escola d'Enginyeria de
Telecomunicacio i Aeroespacial</street>
                                        <street>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;de Castelldefels</street>
                                        <street>C/Esteve Terradas, 7</street>
                                        <city>Castelldefels</city>
                                        <code>08860</code>
                                        <country>Spain</country>
                                </postal>
                                <phone>+34-93-413-7206</phone>
                                <email>carlesgo@entel.upc.edu</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author initials="C." surname="Bormann" fullname="Carsten Bormann">
                        <organization>Universitaet Bremen TZI</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>Postfach 330440</street>
                                        <city>Bremen</city>
                                        <code>D-28359</code>
                                        <country>Germany</country>
                                </postal>
                                <phone>+49-421-218-63921</phone>
                                <email>cabo@tzi.org</email>
                        </address>
                </author>

                <date month="May" year="2012" />

                <area>General</area>
                <workgroup>6LoWPAN Working Group</workgroup>

        <keyword>WSN for Wireless Sensor Network</keyword>
        <keyword>L3 Mesh for Layer 3 Mesh Network</keyword>
        <keyword>Routing Protocol</keyword>
        <keyword>Subnet Routing</keyword>
        <keyword>ieee 802.15.4</keyword>

        <keyword>LLN</keyword>
        <keyword>Low Power</keyword>
        <keyword>radio 802.15.4</keyword>
        <keyword>powerline</keyword>
        <keyword>ISA100.11a</keyword>
        <keyword>RFC 4944</keyword>

                <abstract>
                        <t>
                IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Networks (6LoWPANs)
are formed by devices that are compatible with the IEEE 802.15.4
                standard. However, neither the IEEE 802.15.4 standard nor the 6LoWPAN format
                specification defines how mesh topologies could be obtained and maintained.
                Thus, it should be considered how 6LoWPAN formation and multi-hop routing could be supported.</t>

                <t>
This document provides the problem statement and design space for 6LoWPAN routing.
                It defines the routing requirements for 6LoWPANs, considering the low-power
                and other particular characteristics of the devices and links.
                The purpose of this document is not to recommend specific solutions
                but to provide general, layer-agnostic guidelines about the
design of 6LoWPAN routing that can lead to further analysis and protocol
design.
                This document is intended as input to groups working on routing
                protocols relevant to 6LoWPANs, such as the IETF ROLL WG.
                        </t>
                </abstract>
        </front>

        <middle>

<!--================ PROBLEM STATEMENT===============-->

                <section anchor="problems" title="Problem Statement">
                        <t>
                6LoWPANs are formed by devices that are compatible with the IEEE 802.15.4
                standard <xref target="IEEE802.15.4"/>. 
                Most of the LoWPAN devices are distinguished by their low bandwidth,
                short range, scarce memory capacity, limited processing capability, and other attributes of
                inexpensive hardware.  The characteristics of nodes
                participating in LoWPANs are assumed to be those described in 
                the 6LoWPAN problem statement <xref target="RFC4919"/>,
                and in the IPv6 over IEEE 802.15.4 document <xref target="RFC4944"/>, which has specified
                how to carry IPv6 packets over IEEE 802.15.4 and similar networks. 
                Whereas IEEE 802.15.4 distinguishes two types of devices called 
                full-function devices (FFDs) and reduced-function devices (RFDs), 
                this distinction is based on some features of the Medium Access Control (MAC) layer that are not always in use. 
                Hence, the distinction is not made in this document. 
                Nevertheless, some 6LoWPAN nodes may limit themselves to the role of hosts only, 
                whereas other 6LoWPAN nodes may take part in routing. 
                This host/router distinction can correlate with the processing and storage 
                capabilities of the device and power available in a similar way to the idea of RFDs and FFDs.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                IEEE 802.15.4 networks support star and mesh topologies.
                However, neither the IEEE 802.15.4 standard nor the 6LoWPAN format
                specification (<xref target="RFC4944"/>) define
                how mesh topologies could be obtained and maintained. Thus, 6LoWPAN
                formation and multi-hop routing can be supported either 
                below the IP layer (the adaptation layer or Logical Link
Control (LLC)) or the IP layer. 
                (Note that in the IETF, the term "routing" usually, but not 
                always <xref target="RFC5556"/>, refers exclusively to the formation of paths 
                and the forwarding at the IP layer.  In this document, we distinguish 
                the layer at which these services are performed by the terms "route-over" and "mesh-under".  
                See Sections <xref target="terminology" format="counter"/>
 and <xref target="designspace" format="counter"/>.) 
                A number of IP routing protocols have been developed in various
                IETF working groups. However, these existing routing protocols may not
                satisfy the requirements of multi-hop routing in 6LoWPANs, for the following
                reasons:
                <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                        6LoWPAN nodes have special types and roles, such as nodes drawing their power from primary batteries,
                        power-affluent nodes, mains-powered and high-performance gateways,
                        data aggregators, etc. 6LoWPAN routing protocols should support multiple device types
                        and roles.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        More stringent requirements apply to LoWPANs, as
opposed to higher-performance or non-battery-operated networks. &nbsp;6LoWPAN
nodes are characterized by small memory sizes and
                        low processing power, and they run on very limited power supplied
                        by primary non-rechargeable batteries (a few KB of RAM,
                        a few dozen KB of ROM/flash memory, and a few MHz of CPU is
                        typical). A node's lifetime is usually defined by the
 lifetime of its battery.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Handling sleeping nodes is very critical in LoWPANs,
more so than in
                        traditional ad hoc networks. LoWPAN nodes might stay in sleep mode
                        most of the time. Taking advantage of appropriate times for
                        transmissions is important for efficient packet forwarding.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Routing in 6LoWPANs might possibly translate to a simpler problem
                        than routing in higher-performance networks. LoWPANs might be either
                        transit networks or stub networks.  Under the assumption that LoWPANs
                        are never transit networks (as implied by <xref target="RFC4944"/>),
                        routing protocols may be drastically simplified.
                        This document will focus on the requirements for stub
                        networks. Additional requirements may apply to transit networks.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Routing in LoWPANs might possibly translate to a harder problem
                        than routing in higher-performance networks. Routing in LoWPANs
                        requires power optimization, stable operation in lossy environments,
                        etc.  These requirements are not easily
                        satisfiable all at once <xref target="ROLL-PROTOCOLS"/>.
                        </t>
                </list>

                These properties create new challenges for the design of routing within LoWPANs.
                        </t>

                        <t>
                The 6LoWPAN problem statement <xref target="RFC4919"/>
                briefly mentions four requirements for routing protocols:
                <list>
                        <t>(a) low overhead on data packets</t>
                        <t>(b) low routing overhead</t>
                        <t>(c) minimal memory and computation requirements</t>
                        <t>(d) support for sleeping nodes (consideration of
                               battery savings)</t>
                </list>
                These four high-level requirements describe the basic requirements for 6LoWPAN routing.
                Based on the fundamental features of 6LoWPANs, more detailed
routing requirements, which can lead to further analysis and protocol design,
                are presented in this document.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                Considering the problems above, detailed 6LoWPAN routing requirements must be defined.
                Application-specific features affect the design of 6LoWPAN routing requirements and
                corresponding solutions. However, various applications can be profiled by similar technical
                characteristics, although the related detailed requirements might differ (e.g., a few dozen
                nodes in a home lighting system need appropriate scalability
for the system's applications, while
                millions of nodes for a highway infrastructure system also need appropriate scalability).
                        </t>
                        <t>
                This routing requirements document states the routing requirements of 6LoWPAN applications in
                general, providing examples for different cases of routing. It
does not imply that a single routing
                solution will be favorable for all 6LoWPAN applications, and
there is no requirement for different
                routing protocols to run simultaneously.
                        </t>
                </section>

<!--=============== TERMINOLOGY ====================-->

                <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
                        <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                Readers are expected to be familiar with all the terms and concepts
                that are discussed in <xref target="RFC4919">"IPv6 over Low-Power
                Wireless Personal Area Networks (6LoWPANs): Overview, Assumptions,
                Problem Statement, and Goals"</xref> and <xref target="RFC4944">
                "Transmission of IPv6 Packets over IEEE 802.15.4 Networks"</xref>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            This specification makes use of the terminology
defined in <xref target="6LoWPAN-ND"/>.

                        </t>
                </section>

<!--=============== DESIGN SPACE ==============-->

                <section anchor="designspace" title="Design Space">
                        <t>
                Apart from a wide variety of conceivable routing algorithms for 6LoWPANs,
                it is possible to perform routing in the IP layer (using a route-over approach)
                or below IP, as defined by the
                6LoWPAN format document <xref target="RFC4944"/> (using the mesh-under approach). See <xref target="NetworkStack"/>.
                        </t>

                        <t>
                The route-over approach relies on IP routing and therefore supports
                routing over possibly various types of interconnected links.
                <vspace/>
                Note: The ROLL WG is now working on route-over approaches for Low-power
                and Lossy Networks (LLNs), not specifically for 6LoWPANs.
                This document focuses on 6LoWPAN-specific requirements; it may be used in
                conjunction with the more application-oriented requirements defined by the ROLL WG.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                The mesh-under approach performs the multi-hop communication below the IP link.
                The most significant consequence of the mesh-under mechanism is that
                the characteristics of IEEE 802.15.4 directly affect the 6LoWPAN routing mechanisms,
                including the use of 64-bit (or 16-bit short) link-layer addresses instead of IP
                addresses.  A 6LoWPAN would therefore be seen as a single IP link.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                Most statements in this document consider both the route-over and mesh-under cases.
                        </t>

                        <figure anchor='NetworkStack' title="Mesh-Under Routing
(Left) and Route-Over Routing (Right)">
                <preamble>
                        <xref target="NetworkStack"/> shows the place of 6LoWPAN routing in the entire network stack.
                </preamble>
                <artwork>
 +---------------------------+  +-----------------------------+
 |      Application Layer    |  |      Application Layer      |
 +---------------------------+  +-----------------------------+
 | Transport Layer (TCP/UDP) |  |  Transport Layer (TCP/UDP)  |
 +---------------------------+  +-----------------------------+
 |     Network Layer (IPv6)  |  |  Network       +---------+  |
 +---------------------------+  |  Layer         | Routing |  |
 |  6LoWPAN                  |  |  (IPv6)        +---------+  |
 |  Adaptation               |  +-----------------------------+
 |  Layer       +----------+ |  |  6LoWPAN Adaptation Layer   |
 +--------------| Routing* |-+  +-----------------------------+
 | 802.15.4 MAC +----------+ |  |        802.15.4 MAC         |
 +---------------------------+  +-----------------------------+
 |         802.15.4 PHY      |  |        802.15.4 PHY         |
 +---------------------------+  +-----------------------------+
  * Here, "Routing" is not equivalent to IP routing,
    but includes the functionalities of path computation and
    forwarding under the IP layer.
    The term "Routing" is used in the figure in order to
    illustrate which layer handles path computation and
    packet forwarding in mesh-under as compared to route-over.
                </artwork>
                <postamble/>
                        </figure>

                        <t>
                In order to avoid packet fragmentation and the overhead for reassembly,
                routing packets should fit into a single IEEE 802.15.4 physical frame,
                and application data should not be expanded to an extent that they
                no longer fit.
                        </t>

                <!--================================-->
        <section title="Reference Network Model">
                        <t>
                For multi-hop communication in 6LoWPANs, when a route-over mechanism is in use,
                all routers (i.e., 6LoWPAN Border Routers (6LBRs) and 6LoWPAN
    Routers (6LRs)) perform IP routing within the stub network (see <xref target="x6LoWPAN-rover-conf"/>).
                In this case, the link-local scope covers the set of nodes within symmetric radio range of a node.
                        </t>
                        <t> 
                 When a LoWPAN follows the mesh-under configuration,
                 the 6LBR is the only IPv6 router in the LoWPAN (see <xref target="x6LoWPAN-mesh-conf"/>).
                 This means that the IPv6 link-local scope includes all nodes in the LoWPAN.
                 For this, a mesh-under mechanism MUST be provided to support multi-hop transmission.
                        </t>

                    <figure anchor='x6LoWPAN-rover-conf' title="An Example of a Route-Over LoWPAN">
                <preamble></preamble>
                <artwork>
     h   h
    /    |                     6LBR: 6LoWPAN Border Router
6LBR -- 6LR --- 6LR --- h       6LR: 6LoWPAN Router
        / \                       h: Host
       h  6LR --- h
           |
          / \
       6LR - 6LR -- h
                 </artwork>
                        </figure>
                        <figure anchor='x6LoWPAN-mesh-conf' title="An Example of a Mesh-Under LoWPAN">
                <preamble></preamble>
                <artwork>
     h   h
    /    |                    6LBR: 6LoWPAN Border Router
6LBR --- m --- m --- h           m: mesh-under forwarder
        / \                      h: Host
       h   m --- h
           |
          / \
         m - m -- h
                 </artwork>
                        </figure>
                        <t>
     Note than in both mesh-under and route-over networks, there is no
     expectation of topologically based address assignment in the 6LoWPAN.
     Instead, addresses are typically assigned based on the EUI-64
     addresses assigned at manufacturing time to nodes, or based on a
     (from a topological point of view) more or less random process
     assigning 16-bit MAC addresses to individual nodes.
     Within a 6LoWPAN, there is therefore no opportunity for
     aggregation or summarization of IPv6 addresses beyond the sharing
     of (one or more) common prefixes.
   </t>
   <t>
    Not all devices that are within radio range of each other need to be
    part of the same LoWPAN.
                When multiple LoWPANs are formed with globally unique IPv6 addresses
                in the 6LoWPANs, and device (a) of LoWPAN [A] wants to communicate
                with device (b) of LoWPAN [B], the normal IPv6 mechanisms will be employed.
                For route-over, the IPv6 address of (b) is set as the destination of the packets, and
                the devices perform IP routing to the 6LBR for these outgoing packets.
                For mesh-under, there is one IP hop from device (a) to the 6LBR of [A],
                no matter how many radio hops they are apart from each other. This, of course, assumes
                the existence of a mesh-under routing protocol in order to reach the 6LBR.
                Note that a default route to the 6LBR could be inserted into the 6LoWPAN routing system 
                for both route-over and mesh-under.
                        </t>
                </section>

                </section> 

    <!--========================================================-->
        <!-- start of section 4.scenario and parameters -->
                <section anchor="scenarios" title="Scenario Considerations and Parameters for 6LoWPAN Routing">
                        <t>
                IP-based LoWPAN technology is still in its early stage of
                development, but the range of conceivable usage scenarios is
                tremendous.  The numerous possible applications of sensor networks
                make it obvious that mesh topologies will be prevalent in LoWPAN
                environments and robust routing will be a necessity for expedient
                communication.  Research efforts in the area of sensor networking
                have put forth a large variety of multi-hop routing algorithms
                <xref target="Bulusu"/>.
                Most related work focuses on optimizing
                routing for specific application scenarios, which can be realized using
                several modes of communication, including the following <xref target="Watteyne"/>:

                <list style="symbols">
                   <t>Flooding (in very small networks)</t>
                   <t>Hierarchical routing</t>
                   <t>Geographic routing</t>
                   <t>Self-organizing coordinate routing</t>
                </list>

                Depending on the topology of a LoWPAN and the application(s) running over it,
                different types of routing may be used. However, this document abstracts from
                application-specific communication and describes general routing requirements
                valid for overall routing in LoWPANs.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                The following parameters can be used to describe specific scenarios
                in which the candidate routing protocols could be evaluated.
                        </t>
      <t>
                        <list style="letters">
                <t>Network Properties:
                <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                        Number of Devices, Density, and Network Diameter: <vspace/>
                        These parameters usually affect the routing state directly
                        (e.g., the number of entries in a routing table or neighbor
                        list).  Especially in large and dense networks, policies must
                        be applied for discarding "low-quality" and stale routing
                        entries in order to prevent memory overflow.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Connectivity: <vspace/>
                        Due to external factors or programmed disconnections, a LoWPAN
                        can be in several states of connectivity -- anything in the
                        range from "always connected" to "rarely connected".  This
                        poses great challenges to the dynamic discovery of routes
                        across a LoWPAN.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Dynamicity (including mobility): <vspace/>
                        Location changes can be induced by unpredictable external
                        factors or by controlled motion, which may in turn cause route
                        changes.  Also, nodes may dynamically be introduced into a
                        LoWPAN and removed from it later.  The routing state and the
                        volume of control messages may heavily depend on the number
                        of moving nodes in a LoWPAN and their speed, as well as how
                        quickly and frequently environmental characteristics influencing radio propagation change.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Deployment: <vspace/>
                        In a LoWPAN, it is possible for nodes to be scattered randomly
                        or to be deployed in an organized manner.  The deployment can
                        occur at once, or as an iterative process, which may also
                        affect the routing state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Spatial Distribution of Nodes and Gateways: <vspace/>
                        Network connectivity depends on the spatial distribution of the nodes and on other factors,
                        such as device number, density, and transmission range. For instance, nodes can be placed on a
                        grid, or randomly located in an area (as can be modeled by a two-dimensional Poisson distribution), etc.
                        Assuming a random spatial distribution, an average of 7 neighbors per node are required for
                        approximately 95% network connectivity (10 neighbors
per node are needed for 99% connectivity) <xref target="Kuhn"/>.
                        In addition, if the LoWPAN is connected to other networks through infrastructure nodes called
                        gateways, the number and spatial distribution of
these gateways affect network congestion and available
                        data rate, among other things.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Traffic Patterns, Topology, and Applications: <vspace/>
                        The design of a LoWPAN and the requirements for its application
                        have a big impact on the network topology and the most efficient routing type to be
                        used.  For different traffic patterns (point-to-point,
                        multipoint-to-point, point-to-multipoint) and network
                        architectures, various routing mechanisms have been
                        developed, such as data-centric, event-driven, address-centric,
                        and geographic routing.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Classes of Service: <vspace/>
                        For mixing applications of different criticality on one LoWPAN, support of
                        multiple classes of service may be required in resource-constrained LoWPANs and may
                        require a new routing protocol functionality.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Security: <vspace/>
                        LoWPANs may carry sensitive information and require a high
                        level of security support where the availability, integrity,
                        and confidentiality of data are of prime relevance.  Secured messages
                        cause overhead and affect the power consumption of LoWPAN
                        routing protocols.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of network parameters-->
        </t>
                <t>Node Parameters:
                <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                        Processing Speed and Memory Size: <vspace/>
                        These basic parameters define the maximum size of the routing state and the
                        maximum complexity of its processing. LoWPAN nodes may have different
                        performance characteristics, queuing strategies, and queue buffer sizes.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Power Consumption and Power Source: <vspace/>
                        The number of battery- and mains-powered nodes and their positions in the topology created by them in
                        a LoWPAN affect routing protocols in their selection of
                        paths that optimize network lifetime.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Transmission Range: <vspace/>
                        This parameter affects routing.  For example, a
                        high transmission range may cause a dense network, which in
                        turn results in more direct neighbors of a node, higher
                        connectivity, and a larger routing state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Traffic Pattern: <vspace/>
                        This parameter affects routing, since highly loaded nodes (either
                        because they are the source of packets to be transmitted or due
                        to forwarding) may contribute to higher delivery
                        delays and may consume more energy than lightly loaded nodes.
                        This applies to both data packets and routing control messages.
                        </t>
                </list> <!--end of node parameters-->
                </t>
                <t>Link Parameters:
                        <vspace/>
                        This section discusses link parameters that apply
                        to IEEE 802.15.4 legacy mode (i.e., not making use of improved modulation schemes).
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>
                        Throughput:
                            <vspace/>
                        The maximum user data throughput of a bulk data transmission between a single sender and
                        a single receiver through an unslotted IEEE 802.15.4
2.4 GHz channel in ideal conditions is
                        as follows <xref target="Latre"/>:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t>16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         151.6 kbit/s </t>
                <t>16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         139.0 kbit/s </t>
                <t>64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         135.6 kbit/s </t>
                <t>64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     124.4 kbit/s </t>
                        </list>
                <vspace/>
                Throughput for the 915 MHz band is as follows:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         31.1 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         28.6 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         27.8 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     25.6 kbit/s </t>
                        </list>

                            <vspace/>
                        Throughput for the 868 MHz band is as follows:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         15.5 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         14.3 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         13.9 kbit/s </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     12.8 kbit/s </t>
                        </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>
                        Latency: <vspace/>
                        Latency ranges -- depending on payload size -- 
of a frame transmission between a single sender and
                        a single receiver through an unslotted IEEE 802.15.4
2.4 GHz channel in ideal conditions
                        are as shown below <xref target="Latre"/>. For unreliable mode, the actual latency is provided. For reliable mode,
                        the round-trip time, including transmission of a Layer-2 acknowledgment, is provided:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [1.92 ms, 6.02 ms] </t>
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         [2.46 ms, 6.56 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [2.75 ms, 6.02 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     [3.30 ms, 6.56 ms] </t>
                        </list>
                        <vspace/>
                        Latency ranges for the 915 MHz band are as follows:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [5.85 ms, 29.35 ms] </t>
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         [8.35 ms, 31.85 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [8.95 ms, 29.35 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     [11.45 ms, 31.82 ms] </t>
                        </list>
                        <vspace/>
                        Latency ranges for the 868 MHz band are as follows:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [11.7 ms, 58.7 ms] </t>
                <t> 16-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:         [16.7 ms, 63.7 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, unreliable mode:         [17.9 ms, 58.7 ms] </t>
                <t> 64-bit MAC addresses, reliable mode:     [22.9 ms, 63.7 ms] </t>
                        </list>
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of link parameters-->
          </t>
                        </list> <!-- end of parameter list-->
      </t>
                        <t>        Note that some of the parameters presented in this section may be used as link or node evaluation metrics. However, multi-criteria routing may be too expensive for 6LoWPAN nodes. Rather, various single-criteria metrics are available and can be selected to suit the environment or application.</t>
                </section> <!-- end of Section 4: Scenarios and Parameters-->

 <!--==============================================-->
 <!--==============================================-->

    <!-- start of section 5.routing requirements -->
                <section anchor="Requirements" title="6LoWPAN Routing Requirements">
                        <t>
                This section defines a list of requirements for 6LoWPAN routing.
                An important design property specific to low-power networks is that LoWPANs
                have to support multiple device types and roles, such as
                <list style="symbols">
                        <t>host nodes drawing their power from primary
batteries or using energy harvesting (sometimes called "power-constrained
nodes")</t>
                        <t>mains-powered host nodes (an example of what we call "power-affluent nodes")</t>
                        <t>power-affluent (but not necessarily mains-powered) high-performance gateway(s)</t>
                        <t>nodes with various functionality (data aggregators, relays, local manager/coordinators, etc.)</t>
                </list>

                        Due to these different device types and roles, LoWPANs need to consider
                        the following two primary attributes:

                <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                        Power conservation: some devices are mains-powered, but many are
                        battery-operated and need to last several months to a few years
                        with a single AA battery. Many devices are mains-powered most of
                        the time but still need to function on batteries
for possibly extended periods (e.g., on a construction site before building power
                        is switched on for the first time).
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Low performance: tiny devices, small memory sizes, low-performance
                        processors, low bandwidth, high loss rates, etc.
                        </t>
                </list>
                These fundamental attributes of LoWPANs affect the design of routing
                solutions. Whether existing routing specifications are
                simplified and modified, or new solutions are introduced in order to
                fit the low-power requirements of LoWPANs, they need to meet the requirements
                described below.
                        </t>

        <!--====================================-->
                <!-- start of Section 5.1: Device -->
                        <section anchor="reqs1" title="Support of 6LoWPAN Device Properties">
                <t>
                        The general objectives listed in this section should be met
                        by 6LoWPAN routing protocols. The importance of each requirement is
                        dependent on what node type the protocol is running on and what
                        the role of the node is. The following requirements consider the presence of battery-powered nodes in LoWPANs.
                </t>
                <t>
                    [R01] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD allow implementation with small code size
                        and require low routing state to fit the typical 6LoWPAN node capacity.
                        Generally speaking, the code size is bounded by available flash memory size, and the routing table is bounded by RAM size, possibly limiting it to less than 32 entries.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t> <!-- R01: small code-->
            The RAM size of LoWPAN nodes often ranges between 4 KB and 10 KB (2 KB
minimum),
                        and program flash memory normally consists of 48 KB to
128 KB. &nbsp;(For example, in the current market, MICAz has 128 KB program flash,
                        4 KB EEPROM, and 512 KB external flash ROM; TIP700CM has 48 KB program
                        flash, 10 KB RAM, and 1 MB external flash ROM.)
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Due to these hardware restrictions, code SHOULD
                        fit within a small memory size -- no more than 48 KB to 128 KB of flash memory, including
                        at least a few tens of KB of application code size.
                        (As a general observation, a routing protocol of low
            complexity may help achieve
                        the goal of reducing power consumption, improves robustness,
                        requires lower routing state, is easier to analyze, and may be
                        less prone to security attacks.)
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        In addition, operation with limited amounts of routing state (such as routing tables and neighbor lists)
                        SHOULD be maintained, since some typical memory sizes preclude storing
                        state of a large number of nodes. For instance, industrial monitoring applications
                        may need to support a maximum of 20 hops <xref target="RFC5673"/>.

                        Small networks can be designed to support a smaller number of hops.
                        While the need for this is highly dependent on the network architecture,
                        there should be at least one mode of operation that can
                        function with 32 forwarding entries or less.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R01-->
        </t>
                <t> <!-- R02: minimal power -->
                    [R02] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD cause minimal power
                        consumption by efficiently using control packets
                        (e.g., minimizing expensive IP multicast, which causes link broadcast to the entire
                        LoWPAN) and by efficiently routing data packets.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        One way of optimizing battery lifetime is by achieving a minimal
                        control message overhead. Compared to such functions as
                        computational operations or taking sensor samples, radio communication
                        is by far the dominant factor of power consumption <xref target="Doherty"/>.
                        Power consumption of transmission and/or reception depends linearly
                        on the length of data units and        on the frequency of transmission
                        and reception of the data units <xref target="Shih"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The energy consumption of two
                        example radio frequency (RF) controllers for low-power nodes is shown in <xref target="Hill"/>.
                        The TR1000 radio consumes 21 mW when transmitting at
0.75 mW,
                        and 15 mW during reception (with a receiver sensitivity of
-85 dBm).
                        The CC1000 consumes 31.6 mW when transmitting at
0.75 mW, and 20 mW during reception (with a receiver sensitivity
                        of -105 dBm). Power endurance under the concept of
                        an idealized power source is explained in <xref target="Hill"/>.
                        Based on the energy of an idealized AA battery,
                        the CC1000 can transmit for approximately 4 days straight or receive
                        for 9 consecutive days. Note that availability for reception consumes
                        power as well.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        As multicast may cause flooding in the LoWPAN, a 6LoWPAN routing
                        protocol SHOULD minimize the control cost by multicasting routing packets.
          </t>
          <t>
                        Control cost of routing protocols in low-power and lossy
            networks is discussed in more detail in <xref target="ROLL-PROTOCOLS"/>.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R03-->
        </t>
                        </section> <!-- end of section 5.1 -->

                <!--==================================-->
                <!-- start of section 5.2 : Link -->
                        <section anchor="reqs2" title="Support of 6LoWPAN Link Properties">
                <t>
                        6LoWPAN links have the characteristics of low data rate and possibly high loss rates.
                        The routing requirements described in this section are derived from
                        the link properties.
                </t>

                <t> <!-- R03: no fragmentation-->
                 [R03] 6LoWPAN routing protocol control messages SHOULD NOT exceed a single IEEE 802.15.4 frame size,
                 in order to avoid packet fragmentation and the overhead for reassembly.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                  <t>
                  In order to save energy, routing overhead should be minimized
to
                  prevent fragmentation of frames. Therefore, 6LoWPAN routing
                  should not cause packets to exceed the IEEE 802.15.4 frame
size.
                  This reduces the energy required for transmission, avoids
                  unnecessary waste of bandwidth, and prevents the need for
packet
                  reassembly. The <xref target="IEEE802.15.4"/>
                  standard specifies an MTU of
                  127&nbsp;bytes, yielding about 80 octets of actual MAC
                  payload with security enabled, some of which is
                  taken for the (typically compressed) IP header <xref
target="RFC6282"/>.
                  Avoiding fragmentation at the adaptation layer may imply the
use of semantic fragmentation and/or
     algorithms that can work on small increments of routing information.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R03: no fragmentation-->
                </t>
                <t> <!-- start of R04: NEWLY added on Nov. 3, by EUNAH-->
                        [R04] The design of routing protocols for LoWPANs must consider the fact that
                        packets are to be delivered        with sufficient probability according to application requirements.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Requirements for a successful end-to-end packet delivery ratio
                        (where delivery may be bounded within certain latency levels) vary, depending
                        on the application. In industrial applications, some non-critical monitoring
                        applications may tolerate a successful delivery ratio of less than 90%
                        with hours of latency; in some other cases, a delivery ratio of 99.9%
                        is required <xref target="RFC5673"/>. In building automation applications,
                        application-layer errors must be below 0.01% <xref target="RFC5867"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Successful end-to-end delivery of packets in an IEEE 802.15.4 mesh
                        depends on the quality of the path selected by the routing protocol and
                        on the ability of the routing protocol to cope with short-term and long-term quality variation.
                        The metric of the routing protocol strongly influences performance of
                        the routing protocol in terms of delivery ratio.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The quality of a given path depends on the individual qualities of the links
                        (including the devices) that compose that path. IEEE 802.15.4 settings affect
                        the quality perceived at upper layers. In particular, in IEEE 802.15.4 reliable mode,
                        if an acknowledgment frame is not received after a given period,
                        the originator retries frame transmission up to a maximum number of times.
                        If an acknowledgment frame is still not received by the sender
                        after performing the maximum number of transmission attempts,
                        the MAC layer assumes that the transmission has failed and notifies the next
                        higher layer of the failure. Note that excessive retransmissions may be detrimental;
                        see RFC 3819 <xref target="RFC3819"/>.
                        </t>
                </list>
        </t>
                <t> <!-- start of R05: NEWLY added on Nov. 17 -->
                        [R05] The design of routing protocols for LoWPANs must consider the
                        latency requirements of applications and IEEE 802.15.4 link latency characteristics.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Latency requirements may differ -- e.g., from a
few hundred milliseconds to minutes --
                        depending on the type of application.
                        Real-time building automation applications usually need response times
                        below 500 ms between egress and ingress, while
                        forced-entry security alerts must be routed to one or more fixed or mobile user devices
                        within 5 seconds <xref target="RFC5867"/>.
                        Non-critical closed-loop applications for industrial automation
                        have latency requirements that can be as low as 100 ms,
but many control loops are
                        tolerant of latencies above 1&nbsp;s <xref
target="RFC5673"/>.  In contrast,

                        urban monitoring applications allow latencies smaller than the typical intervals used for
                        reporting sensed information -- for instance, on the order of seconds to
                        minutes <xref target="RFC5548"/>.
                    </t>
                        <t>
                        The range of latencies of a frame transmission between a single
                        sender and a single receiver through an ideal unslotted IEEE 802.15.4
                        2.4 GHz channel is between 2.46 ms and
6.02 ms with 64&nbhy;bit MAC addresses in
                        unreliable mode, and between 2.20 ms and 6.56 ms with
64-bit MAC addresses in reliable
                        mode.  The range of latencies of the 868 MHz band is from 11.7 ms to
                        63.7 ms, depending on the address type and mode used
(reliable or unreliable). Note that the latencies may be larger than that,
depending on channel load, the MAC-layer settings,
                        and the choice of reliable or unreliable mode.
                        Note that MAC approaches other than legacy 802.15.4 may be used (e.g., TDMA).
                        Duty cycling may further affect latency (see [R08]). 
                        Depending on the routing path chosen and the network diameter, 
                        multiple hops may contribute to the end-to-end latency
that an application may experience.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Note that a tradeoff exists between [R05] and [R04].
                        </t>
                </list>        <!-- end of R05-->
                </t>
                <t> <!-- start of R06-->
                    [R06] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD be robust to dynamic loss caused by link failure
                    or device unavailability either in the short term
(approx. 30 ms) -- due to Received Signal Strength Indication (RSSI)
                    variation, interference variation, noise, and asynchrony --
or in the long term, due
                    to a depleted power source, hardware breakdown, operating system misbehavior, etc.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        An important trait of 6LoWPAN devices is their
unreliability, which can be due to
                        limited system capabilities and possibly being closely
                        coupled to the physical world with all its unpredictable variations.
                        In harsh environments, LoWPANs easily suffer from
                        link failure. Collisions or link failures easily increase send
                        and receive queues and can lead to queue overflow and
                        packet losses.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        For home applications, where users expect feedback
after carrying out certain actions
                        (such as handling a remote control while moving around), routing protocols must converge
                        within 2 seconds if the destination node of the packet has moved and must converge within
                        0.5 seconds if only the sender has moved <xref target="RFC5826"/>.
                        The tolerance of the recovery time can vary, depending on the application; however, the
                        routing protocol must provide the detection of short-term unavailability and long-term
                        disappearance. The routing protocol has to exploit network resources (e.g., path redundancy)
                            to offer good network behavior despite node failure.
     </t>
     <t>
         Different routing protocols may exhibit different scaling
         characteristics with respect to the recovery/convergence time
         and the computational resources to achieve recovery after a
         convergence; see also [R01] and [R10].
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R06-->
        </t>
                <t>
                        [R07] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD be designed to correctly operate in the presence of link asymmetry.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Link asymmetry occurs when the probability of successful transmission
                        between two nodes is significantly higher in one direction than in
                        the other. This phenomenon has been reported in a large number of
                        experimental studies, and it is expected that 6LoWPANs will exhibit
                        link asymmetry.
                        </t>
                </list>
        </t>
                        </section>
                <!-- end of section 5.2: link -->

            <!--======================================-->
                <!-- start of section 5.3 : Network-->
                        <section anchor="reqs3" title="Support of 6LoWPAN Characteristics">
                <t>
                        6LoWPANs can be deployed in different sizes and topologies,
                        adhere to various models of mobility, be exposed to various levels of interference, etc.
                        In any case, LoWPANs must maintain low energy consumption.
                        The requirements described in this subsection are derived
                        from the network attributes of 6LoWPANs.
                </t>

                <t> <!-- R08: sleep node-->

                    [R08] The design of 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD take into account that some nodes
                    may be unresponsive during certain time intervals, due to periodic hibernation.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Many nodes in LoWPAN environments might periodically hibernate (i.e., disable their
                        transceiver activity) in order to save energy. Therefore, routing protocols must ensure
                        robust packet delivery despite nodes frequently shutting off their radio transmission
                        interface. Feedback from the lower IEEE 802.15.4 layer may be considered to enhance the
                        power awareness of 6LoWPAN routing protocols.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        CC1000-based nodes must operate at a duty cycle of approximately 2% to survive for one year
                        from an idealized AA battery power source <xref target="Hill"/>. For home automation purposes,
                        it is suggested that the devices have to maximize the sleep phase with a duty cycle lower
                        than 1% <xref target="RFC5826"/>, while in building automation applications,
                        batteries must be operational for at least 5 years when the sensing devices are transmitting
                        data (e.g., 64 bytes) once per minute <xref target="RFC5867"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Depending on the application in use, packet rates may range from one per second to one per day,
                        or beyond. Routing protocols may take advantage of knowledge about the packet transmission rate
                        and utilize this information in calculating routing paths. In many IEEE 802.15.4 deployments, and
                        in other wireless low-power technologies, forwarders are mains-powered devices (and hence do not
                        need to sleep). However, it cannot be assumed that all forwarders are mains-powered.
                        A routing protocol that addresses this case
                        SHOULD provide a mode in which power
                        consumption is a metric.  In addition, using
                        nodes in power-saving modes for forwarding may
                        increase delay and reduce the probability of
                        packet delivery, which in this case also should be
                        available as an input into the path computation.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R08-->
                </t>
                <t> <!-- R09: metrics -->
                    [R09] The metric used by 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD
        provide some flexibility with respect to the inputs provided
        by the lower layers and other measures to optimize path
        selection, considering energy balance and link qualities.
                </t>
        <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        In homes, buildings, or infrastructure, some nodes will be installed
                        with mains power. Such power-installed nodes MUST be
considered
                        as relay points for a prominent role in packet
delivery. &nbsp;6LoWPAN routing protocols MUST know the power constraints of the nodes.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Simple hop-count-only mechanisms may be inefficient in 6LoWPANs.
                        There is a Link Quality Indication (LQI) and/or RSSI
from
                        IEEE 802.15.4 that may be taken into account for better
metrics.
                        The metric to be used (and its goal) may depend on
                        applications and requirements.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The numbers in <xref target="LDR"/> represent the Link Delivery Ratio (LDR)
                        of each pair of nodes. There are studies that show a
piecewise linear dependence between the LQI and the
                        LDR <xref target="Chen"/>.

                        <figure anchor='LDR' title="An Example Network"><artwork>
                                  0.6
                               A-------C
                                \     /
                             0.9 \   / 0.9
                                  \ /
                                   B
                        </artwork></figure>
</t>
                        <t>
                        In this simple example, there are two options in routing from node&nbsp;A
                        to node C, with the following features:

                        <list style="letters">
                        <t>Path AC:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t>(1/0.6) = 1.67 avg. transmissions needed for each packet
(confirmed link-layer delivery with retransmissions and negligible ACK loss
have been assumed) </t>

                <t>one-hop path</t>

                <t>good energy consumption and end-to-end latency of data
packets, poor delivery ratio (0.6)</t>

                <t>poor probability of route reconfigurations</t>
                        </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>Path ABC:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t>(1/0.9)+(1/0.9) = 2.22 avg. transmissions needed for each
packet (under the same assumptions as above) </t>

                <t>two-hop path</t>

                <t>poor energy consumption and end-to-end latency of data
packets, good delivery ratio (0.81)</t>
                        </list>
                        </t>
                        </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>
                        If energy consumption of the network must be minimized,
                        path AC is the best (this path would be chosen based on a hop-count
                        metric). However, if the delivery ratio in that case is not sufficient,
                        the best path is ABC (it would be chosen by an LQI-based metric).
                        Combinations of both metrics can be used.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The metric also affects the probability of route reconfiguration.
                        Route reconfiguration, which may be triggered by packet losses,
                        may require transmission of routing protocol messages.
                        It is possible to use a metric aimed at selecting the
path with a low route
                        reconfiguration rate by using the LQI as an input to the metric.
                        Such a path has good properties, including stability and low control message overhead.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R09:metrics-->
                          </t>
                        <t>
                        Note that a tradeoff exists between [R09] and [R01].
                        </t>
                <t> <!-- R10-->
                        [R10] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD be designed to
achieve both
                       scalability -- from a few nodes to maybe millions of
nodes -- and minimal use of system resources.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                         A LoWPAN may consist of just a couple of nodes (for
instance, in
                         a body-area network), but may also contain much higher numbers of
                         devices (e.g., monitoring of a city infrastructure or a highway).
                         For home automation applications, it is envisioned that the routing protocol
                         must support 250 devices in the network <xref target="RFC5826"/>,
                         while routing protocols for metropolitan-scale sensor networks must be capable of clustering
                         a large number of sensing nodes into regions
                         containing on the order of 10^2 to 10^4 sensing nodes each <xref target="RFC5548"/>.
                         It is therefore necessary that routing mechanisms are designed
                         to be scalable for operation in networks of various
sizes. However,
                         due to a lack of memory size and computational power, 6LoWPAN
                         routing might limit forwarding entries to a small number, such
                         as a maximum of 32 routing table entries. Particularly
in large networks, the routing mechanism MUST be designed in such a way that the number of routers is smaller than the number of hosts.
                        </t>
                </list> <!--end of R10-->
                </t>
                <t> <!--R11 -->
                        [R11] The procedure of route repair and related control messages
                        SHOULD NOT harm overall energy consumption from the routing protocols.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Local repair improves throughput and end-to-end latency, especially
                        in large networks. Since routes are repaired quickly, fewer data
                        packets are dropped, and a smaller number of routing protocol
                        packet transmissions are needed, since routes can be repaired without
                        source-initiated route discovery <xref target="Lee"/>.
                        One important consideration here may be to avoid premature
                        energy depletion, even if that impairs other requirements.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R11-->
                </t>
                <t> <!-- R12-->
                    [R12] 6LoWPAN routing protocols SHOULD allow for dynamically adaptive
                        topologies and mobile nodes. When supporting dynamic topologies and
                        mobile nodes, route maintenance should keep in mind the goal of
                        a minimal routing state and routing protocol message overhead.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        Topological node mobility may be the result of physical
                        movement and/or a changing radio environment, making it very
                        likely that mobility needs to be handled even in a network with
                        physically static nodes. &nbsp;6LoWPANs do not make
use of a separate protocol to maintain
                        connectivity to moving nodes but expects the routing protocol to
                        handle it.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        In addition, some nodes may move from one 6LoWPAN to another and are
                        expected to become functional members of the latter 6LoWPAN in a
                        limited amount of time.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Building monitoring applications, for instance, have a number of
                        requirements with respect to recovery and settling time for
                        mobility that range between 5 and 20 seconds (Section 5.3.1 of <xref target="RFC5867"/>).
                        For more interactive applications such as those used in home automation systems, where users provide input
                        and expect instant feedback, mobility requirements are also stricter and,
                        for moves within a network,
                        a convergence time below 0.5 seconds is commonly required
                        (Section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC5826"/>).
                        In industrial environments, where mobile equipment
(e.g., cranes) moves around, the routing protocol needs to support vehicular
speeds of up to 35&nbsp;km/h <xref target="RFC5673"/>.

                        Currently, 6LoWPANs are not normally being used for such fast mobility,
                        but dynamic association and disassociation MUST be supported in 6LoWPANs.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        There are several challenges that should be addressed by a 6LoWPAN
                              routing protocol in order to create robust routing in dynamic environments:
                        <list style="symbols">
                <t> Mobile Nodes Changing Their Location inside a LoWPAN:
                    <vspace/>
                        If the nodes' movement pattern is unknown, mobility cannot
                        easily be detected or distinguished by the routing protocols.
                        Mobile nodes can be treated as nodes that disappear and reappear
                        in another place. The tracking of movement patterns
increases complexity and can be
                        avoided by handling moving nodes using reactive route updates.
                </t>
                <t> Movement of a LoWPAN with Respect to Other (Inter)Connected LoWPANs:
                    <vspace/>
                        Within each stub network, (one or more) relatively powerful 
                        gateway nodes (6LBRs) need to be configured to handle moving LoWPANs.
                </t>
                <t> Nodes Permanently Joining or Leaving the LoWPAN:
                    <vspace/>
                        In order to ease routing table updates, reduce the size
of these updates, and minimize error
                        control messages, nodes leaving the network may announce their disassociation to
                the closest edge router or to a specific node (if any) that
takes charge of
                        local association and disassociation.
                </t>
                        </list> <!--end of symbol list-->
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R12-->
                </t>
                <t> <!-- R13: traffic pattern -->
                    [R13] A 6LoWPAN routing protocol SHOULD support various
traffic patterns --
                        point-to-point, point-to-multipoint, and
multipoint-to-point --
                        while avoiding excessive multicast traffic in a LoWPAN.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        6LoWPANs often have point-to-multipoint or multipoint-to-point
                        traffic patterns. Many emerging applications include point-to-point
                        communication as well. &nbsp;6LoWPAN routing protocols should
                        be designed with the consideration of forwarding packets from/to
                        multiple sources/destinations. Current documents of the ROLL WG
                        explain that the workload or traffic pattern of use cases for
                        LoWPANs tends to be highly structured, unlike the any-to-any data
                        transfers that dominate typical client and server workloads. In many
                        cases, exploiting such structure may simplify difficult problems
                        arising from resource constraints or variation in connectivity.
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R13-->
                </t>
                        </section>
                <!-- end of section 5.3-->

        <!--======================================-->
                <!-- start of section :5.4 security -->
                        <section anchor="reqs4" title="Support of Security">
                <t>
                        The routing requirement described in this subsection allows secure
                        transmission of routing messages. 

                        As in traditional networks, routing mechanisms in 6LoWPANs
                        present another window from which an attacker might disrupt and
                        significantly degrade the overall performance of the
6LoWPAN.  Attacks
                        against non-secure routing aim mainly to contaminate
WPANs with
                        false routing information, resulting in routing inconsistencies.  A
                        malicious node can also snoop packets and then launch replay attacks
                        on the 6LoWPAN nodes.  These attacks can cause harm, especially when
                        the attacker is a high-power device, such as a laptop.  It can also
                        easily drain the batteries of 6LoWPAN devices by
sending broadcast messages,
                        redirecting routes, etc.

                </t>
                <t> <!-- R14: security-->
                    [R14] 6LoWPAN routing protocols MUST support
confidentiality, authentication, and 
                        integrity services as required for secure delivery of control messages.
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        A general set of requirements that may apply to these services
                        can be found in <xref target="KARP-THREATS"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Security is very important for designing robust routing
                        protocols, but it should not cause significant transmission
                        overhead.
                        The security aspect, however, seems to be a bit of a
tradeoff in a 6LoWPAN,
                        since security is always a costly function. A 6LoWPAN poses unique challenges to which traditional security techniques 
                        cannot be applied directly.
                        For example, public key cryptography primitives are typically avoided
                        (as being too expensive), as are relatively heavyweight conventional
                        encryption methods.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Consequently, it becomes questionable whether the 6LoWPAN devices can
                        support IPsec as it is.  While <xref target="RFC6434"/>
makes support of the IPsec architecture a SHOULD for all IPv6 nodes,
                        considering the power constraints and limited processing capabilities of 
                        IEEE 802.15.4-capable devices, IPsec is computationally
expensive.
                        Internet Key Exchange (IKEv2) messaging as described in
RFC 5996 <xref target="RFC5996"/> will not work well
                        in 6LoWPANs, as we want to minimize the amount of signaling in these
                        networks. IPsec supports the Authentication Header (AH)
for authenticating the IP
                        header and the Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) for
authenticating and encrypting the payload.  The
                        main issues of using IPsec are two-fold: (1) processing power and (2)
                        key management.  Since these tiny 6LoWPAN devices do not process huge
                        amounts of data or communicate with many different
nodes, whether complete implementation of a Security Association
Database (SAD), policy database, and dynamic key-management protocol
are appropriate for these small battery-powered devices or not is not well
understood.
                        </t>

                        <t>
                        Bandwidth is a very scarce resource in 6LoWPAN environments.  The
                        fact that IPsec additionally requires another header (AH or ESP) in
                        every packet makes its use problematic in 6LoWPAN environments.
                        IPsec requires two communicating peers to share a secret key that is
                        typically established dynamically with IKEv2.  Thus, it has an additional packet overhead
                        incurred by the exchange of IKEv2 packets.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Given existing constraints in 6LoWPAN environments, IPsec may not be
                        suitable for use in such environments, especially since
a 6LoWPAN node
                        may not be capable of operating all IPsec algorithms on its own.
                        Thus, a 6LoWPAN may need to define its own keying management
                        method(s) that require minimum overhead in packet size
and in the number
                        of signaling messages that are exchanged.  IPsec will provide authentication
                        and confidentiality between end-nodes and across
multiple LoWPAN 
                        links, and may be useful only when two nodes want to apply security
                        to all exchanged messages.  However, in most cases, the security may
                        be requested at the application layer as needed, while other messages
                        can flow in the network without security overhead.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Security threats within LoWPANs may be different from existing
                        threat models in ad hoc network environments.  If IEEE 802.15.4 security is not used, 
                        Neighbor Discovery (ND) in IEEE 802.15.4 links is susceptible to threats. 
                        These include Neighbor Solicitation/Neighbor
Advertisement (NS/NA) spoofing, a malicious router, a default router that is "killed", 
                        a good router that goes bad, a spoofed redirect, replay attacks,
and remote ND DoS
                        <xref target="RFC3756"/>. However, if IEEE 802.15.4 security is used, 
                        no other protection is needed for ND, as long as none of the nodes become compromised, 
                        because the Corporate Intranet Model of RFC&nbsp;3756 can be assumed 
                        <xref target="6LoWPAN-ND"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        Bootstrapping may also impose additional threats. For example, a malicious node can 
                        obtain initial configuration information in order to appear as a legitimate node 
                        and then carry out various types of attacks. Such a node can also keep legitimate 
                        nodes busy by broadcasting authentication/join requests. 
                        One option for mitigating such threats is the use of mutual authentication schemes 
                        based on the use of pre-shared keys <xref target="Ikram"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The IEEE 802.15.4 MAC provides an AES-based security mechanism. Routing protocols may
                        define how this mechanism (in conjunction with IPsec whenever available) 
                        can be used to obtain the intended security, either for
                        the routing protocol alone or in conjunction with the security used for the data.
                        Byte overhead of the mechanism, which depends on the security services selected, must
                        be considered. In the worst case in terms of overhead, the mechanism consumes 21 bytes
                        of MAC payload.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The IEEE 802.15.4 MAC security is typically supported by crypto
                        hardware, even in very simple chips that will be used in a 6LoWPAN.
                        Even if the IEEE 802.15.4 MAC security mechanisms are not used,
                        this crypto hardware is usually available for use by application
                        code running on these chips.  A security protocol outside IEEE
                        802.15.4 MAC security SHOULD therefore provide a mode of
                        operation that is covered by this crypto hardware.
                        </t>

                        <t>
                        IEEE 802.15.4 does not specify protection for acknowledgment frames.
                        Since the sequence numbers of data frames are sent in the clear,
                        an adversary can forge an acknowledgment for each data frame.
                        Exploitation of this weakness can be combined with targeted jamming to prevent delivery of
                        selected packets. Consequently, IEEE 802.15.4 acknowledgments cannot be relied upon.
                        In applications that require high security, the routing protocol must not exploit
                        feedback from acknowledgments (e.g., to keep track of neighbor connectivity, see [R16]).
                        </t>
                </list> <!-- end of R14 -->
                </t>
                        </section>
                <!-- end of section: 5.4 security -->

                <!--==========================================-->
                <!-- start of section: 5.5 mesh-under -->
                        <section anchor="reqs5" title="Support of Mesh-Under Forwarding">
                <t>
                    One LoWPAN may be built as one IPv6 link. In this case, mesh-under forwarding
                    mechanisms must be supported. 

                        While this document provides general, layer-agnostic guidelines 
                        about the design of 6LoWPAN routing,

                        the requirements in this section are specifically
related to Layer 2. 
                        These requirements are directed to bodies that might consider 
                        working on mesh-under routing, such as the IEEE. 
                        The requirements described in this subsection allow
                    optimization and correct operation of routing solutions, taking into account the specific
                    features of the mesh-under configuration.
                </t>
                <t>
                    [R15] Mesh-under requires the development of a routing protocol
                        operating below IP. This protocol MUST support 16-bit short and
                        64&nbhy;bit extended MAC addresses. 
                </t>
                <t>
                        [R16] In order to perform discovery and maintenance of neighbors
                        (i.e., neighborhood discovery as opposed to ND-style neighbor discovery),
                        LoWPAN nodes SHOULD avoid sending separate "Hello" messages.
                        Instead, link-layer mechanisms (such as acknowledgments) MAY be utilized
                        to keep track of active neighbors.
                </t>
                <t>
                   <list>
                        <t>
                        Reception of an acknowledgment after a frame transmission may render
                        unnecessary the transmission of explicit Hello messages, for example.
                        In a more general view, any frame received by a node may be used as an input
                        to evaluate the connectivity between the sender and receiver of that frame.
                        </t>
                </list>
                </t>

                <t>
                        [R17] If the routing protocol functionality includes enabling IP multicast,
                        then it MAY employ structure in the network for efficient
                        distribution in order to minimize link-layer broadcast.
                </t>
                        </section>
                <!-- end of mesh-under req -->

        <!--========================================-->

<!--==========================================-->
                <!-- start of section: 5.6 management -->
                        <section anchor="reqs6" title="Support of Management">
                <t>
                    When a new protocol is designed, the operational environment and
manageability of the protocol should be considered from the start
<xref target="RFC5706"/>. This subsection provides a requirement for the manageability of 6LoWPAN routing protocols.
                </t>
                <t>
                    [R18] A 6LoWPAN routing protocol SHOULD be designed according to the guidelines for operations and management stated in <xref target="RFC5706"/>. 
                </t>
                <t>
                <list>
                        <t>
                        The management operations that a 6LoWPAN routing protocol implementation can support depend
         on the memory and processing capabilities of the 6LoWPAN devices used, which are typically constrained.
         However, 6LoWPANs may benefit significantly from supporting such 6LoWPAN routing protocol management
         operations as configuration and performance monitoring.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                        The design of 6LoWPAN routing protocols should take
into account that, according to "Architectural Principles of the Internet"
<xref target="RFC1958"/>, "options and parameters should be configured or
negotiated dynamically rather than manually".
 This is especially important for 6LoWPANs, which can be composed of a large
         number of devices (and, in addition, these devices may not have an appropriate user interface). Therefore,
         parameter autoconfiguration is a desirable property for a 6LoWPAN routing protocol, although some subset
         of routing protocol parameters may allow other forms of configuration as well.
                        </t>
                              <t>
                        In order to verify the correct operation of the 6LoWPAN routing protocol and the network itself, a 6LoWPAN routing
         protocol should allow monitoring of the status and/or value of 6LoWPAN routing protocol parameters and 
         data structures such as routing table entries. In order to enable fault management, further monitoring of the
         6LoWPAN routing protocol operation is needed. For this, faults can be reported via error log messages. These 
         messages may contain information such as the number of times a packet could not be sent to a 
         valid next hop, the duration of each period without connectivity, memory overflow and its causes, etc.
                        </t>
                              <t>
                        <xref target="RFC5706"/> -- in particular its
Section 3 -- provides a comprehensive
guide to properly designing the management solution for a 6LoWPAN
routing protocol.
                        </t>


                </list>
                </t>
                        </section>
                <!-- end of management req -->
                </section>
        <!-- end of  Requirement section-->

        <!--========================================-->


    <!--========================================-->

                <section title="Security Considerations">
                        <t>
                Security issues are described in <xref target="reqs4"/>.
 The security considerations
                in RFC 4919 <xref target="RFC4919"/>, RFC 4944 <xref target="RFC4944"/>, and RFC&nbsp;4593 <xref target="RFC4593"/> apply as well.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                The use of wireless links renders a 6LoWPAN susceptible to attacks
                like any other wireless network.
                In outdoor 6LoWPANs, the physical exposure of the nodes
                allows an adversary to capture, clone, or tamper with these devices.
                In ad hoc 6LoWPANs that are dynamic in both their topology and node memberships,
                a static security configuration does not suffice.
                Spoofed, altered, or replayed routing information might occur,
 while
                multihopping could delay the detection and treatment of attacks.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                This specification expects that the link layer is sufficiently protected,
                either by means of physical or IP security for the backbone link, or with
                MAC-sublayer cryptography.
                However, link-layer encryption and authentication may not be sufficient
                to provide confidentiality, authentication,  integrity, and freshness to both data and routing protocol packets.
                Time synchronization, self-organization, and secure localization
                for multi-hop routing are also critical to support.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                For secure routing protocol operation, it may be necessary to consider authenticated
                broadcast (and multicast) and bidirectional link verification.
                On the other hand, secure end-to-end data delivery can be assisted by the routing protocol. For example, multi-path routing could be considered for increasing security
                to prevent selective forwarding.
                However, the challenge is that 6LoWPANs already have high resource constraints,
                so that 6LBR and LoWPAN nodes may require different security solutions.
                        </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The authors of this document highly appreciate the authors
of "IPv6 over Low Power WPAN Security Analysis" <xref target="6LoWPAN-SEC"/>.
Although their security analysis work is not ongoing at the time of this
writing, the valuable information and text in that document are used in
<xref target="reqs4"/> of this document,
per advice received during IESG review procedures. Thanks to their work,
<xref target="reqs4"/> is much improved.
The authors also thank S. Chakrabarti, who gave valuable comments
regarding mesh-under requirements, and A. Petrescu for significant review.
            </t>

            <t>
            Carles Gomez has been supported in part by FEDER and by the Spanish
            Government through projects TIC2006-04504 and TEC2009-11453.
            </t>
                </section>
        </middle>

<back>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
        <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC2119;

<reference anchor='RFC3756'>
<front>
<title>IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) Trust Models and Threats</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Nikander' fullname='P. Nikander' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Kempf' fullname='J. Kempf'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Nordmark' fullname='E. Nordmark'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2004' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3756' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC3819'>
<front>
<title>Advice for Internet Subnetwork Designers</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Karn' fullname='P. Karn' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Bormann' fullname='C. Bormann'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Fairhurst' fullname='G. Fairhurst'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Grossman' fullname='D. Grossman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Ludwig' fullname='R. Ludwig'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Mahdavi' fullname='J. Mahdavi'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Montenegro' fullname='G. Montenegro'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Touch' fullname='J. Touch'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Wood' fullname='L. Wood'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2004' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='89' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3819' />
</reference>

&RFC4919;
&RFC4944;

<reference anchor='RFC5548'>
<front>
<title>Routing Requirements for Urban Low-Power and Lossy Networks</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Dohler' fullname='M. Dohler' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Watteyne' fullname='T. Watteyne' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Winter' fullname='T. Winter' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Barthel' fullname='D. Barthel' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5548' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5673'>
<front>
<title>Industrial Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy Networks</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Pister' fullname='K. Pister' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Thubert' fullname='P. Thubert' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Dwars' fullname='S. Dwars'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Phinney' fullname='T. Phinney'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='October' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5673' />
</reference>

&RFC4593;
                <reference anchor="IEEE802.15.4">
                         <front>
                           <title>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area
Networks -- Part 15.4: Low-Rate Wireless Personal Area Networks (LR-WPANs)</title>
                           <author><organization>IEEE Computer Society</organization></author>
                           <date month="September" year="2011"/>
                          </front>
                      <seriesInfo name="IEEE Std." value="802.15.4-2011"/>
                </reference>

         </references>

        <references title='Informative References'>

<!-- draft-daniel-6lowpan-security-analysis (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='6LoWPAN-SEC'>
<front>
<title>IPv6 over Low Power WPAN Security Analysis</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Park' fullname='Soohong Daniel Park'>
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Kim' fullname='Ki-Hyung Kim'>
</author>
<author initials='W' surname='Haddad' fullname='Wassim Haddad' role="editor">
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Chakrabarti' fullname='Samita Chakrabarti'>
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Laganier' fullname='Julien Laganier'>
</author>
<date month='March' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-karp-threats-reqs (Waiting for AD Go-Ahead::AD Followup) -->
<reference anchor='KARP-THREATS'>
<front>
<title>Keying and Authentication for Routing Protocols (KARP) Overview, Threats, and Requirements</title>
<author initials='G' surname='Lebovitz' fullname='Gregory Lebovitz'>
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Bhatia' fullname='Manav Bhatia'>
</author>
<date month='May' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

                <reference anchor="Bulusu">
                        <front>
                <title>Wireless Sensor Networks: A Systems Perspective</title>
                <author initials="N." surname="Bulusu" fullname="Nirupama
Bulusu" role="editor">
        </author>
                <author initials="S." surname="Jha" fullname="Sanjay Jha" role="editor">
        </author>
                <date month="July" year="2005"/>
                        </front>
<seriesInfo name="Artech" value="House"/>
<seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781580538671" />
                </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-6lowpan-nd (IESG Evaluation::Revised ID Needed) -->
<reference anchor='6LoWPAN-ND'>
<front>
<title>Neighbor Discovery Optimization for Low Power and Lossy Networks (6LoWPAN)</title>
<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby' role="editor">
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Chakrabarti' fullname='Samita Chakrabarti'>
</author>
<author initials='E' surname='Nordmark' fullname='Erik Nordmark'>
</author>
<date month='October' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>
                
  <reference anchor="Doherty">
    <front>
      <title>Energy and Performance Considerations for Smart Dust</title>
        <author initials="L." surname="Doherty" fullname="">
        </author>
        <author initials="B.A." surname="Warneke" fullname="">
        </author>
        <author initials="B.E." surname="Boser" fullname="">
        </author>
        <author initials="K.S.J." surname="Pister" fullname="">
        </author>
        <date year="2001"/>
      </front>
     <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Parallel and Distributed
Systems and Networks," value="Vol. 4, No. 3"/>
   </reference>

                <reference anchor="Hill">
                   <front>
                           <title>System Architecture for Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
                           <author initials="J." surname="Hill" fullname="Jason
Lester Hill">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date year="2003"/>
                   </front>
<seriesInfo name="Ph.D. Thesis," value="UC Berkeley"/>
                </reference>

                <reference anchor="Lee">
                   <front>
                           <title>Scalability Study of the Ad Hoc On-Demand Distance-Vector Routing Protocol</title>
                           <author initials="S. J." surname="Lee" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="E. M." surname="Belding-Royer" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="C. E." surname="Perkins" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date month="March" year="2003"/>
                   </front>
<seriesInfo name="International Journal of Network" value="Management"/>
<seriesInfo name="Vol." value="13"/>
<seriesInfo name="pp." value="97-114"/>

                </reference>


                <reference anchor="Shih">
                   <front>
                           <title>Physical Layer Driven Protocols and Algorithm Design for Energy-Efficient Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
                           <author initials="E." surname="Shih" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="S." surname="Cho" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="N." surname="Ickes" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="R." surname="Min" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="A." surname="Sinha" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="A." surname="Wang" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="A." surname="Chandrakasan" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date month="July" year="2001"/>
                   </front>

<seriesInfo name="MobiCom '01:" value="Proceedings of the 7th ACM Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking"/>
                </reference>

                <reference anchor="Chen">
                   <front>
                           <title>Ad-Hoc Multicast Routing on Resource-Limited Sensor Nodes</title>
                           <author initials="B." surname="Chen" fullname="">
        </author>
                           <author initials="K. K." surname="Muniswamy-Reddy" fullname="">
        </author>
                           <author initials="M." surname="Welsh" fullname="">
        </author>
                           <date month="May" year="2006"/>
                   </front>
                 <seriesInfo name="Proc. 2nd International Workshop on
Multi-hop" value="Ad Hoc Networks"/>
                </reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1958'>
<front>
<title>Architectural Principles of the Internet</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Carpenter' fullname='Brian E. Carpenter' role="editor">
</author>
<date year='1996' month='June' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1958' />
</reference>

  &RFC5826;

<reference anchor='RFC5867'>
<front>
<title>Building Automation Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy Networks</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Martocci' fullname='J. Martocci' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='De Mil' fullname='P. De Mil'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Riou' fullname='N. Riou'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Vermeylen' fullname='W. Vermeylen'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='June' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5867' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-roll-protocols-survey (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='ROLL-PROTOCOLS'>
<front>
<title>Overview of Existing Routing Protocols for Low Power and Lossy Networks</title>
<author initials='P' surname='Levis' fullname='P Levis'>
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Tavakoli' fullname='Arsalan Tavakoli'>
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Dawson-Haggerty' fullname='Stephen Dawson-Haggerty'>
</author>
<date month='April' year='2009' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

  &RFC5556;
  &RFC5706;
  &RFC5996;

<reference anchor='RFC6282'>
<front>
<title>Compression Format for IPv6 Datagrams over IEEE 802.15.4-Based Networks</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Hui' fullname='J. Hui' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Thubert' fullname='P. Thubert'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6282' />
</reference>

                 <reference anchor="Latre">
                   <front>
                           <title>Throughput and Delay Analysis of Unslotted IEEE 802.15.4</title>
                           <author initials="B." surname="Latre" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="P." surname="De Mil" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="I." surname="Moerman" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="B." surname="Dhoedt" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="P." surname="Demeester" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date month="May" year="2006"/>
                   </front>
                  <seriesInfo name="Journal of Networks," value="Vol. 1, No. 1"/>
                </reference>

                 <reference anchor="Watteyne" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/articleDetails.jsp?arnumber=5581105">
                   <front>
                       <title>From MANET To IETF ROLL Standardization: A
Paradigm Shift in WSN Routing Protocols</title>
                       <author initials="T." surname="Watteyne" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                       <author initials="A." surname="Molinaro" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                       <author initials="M.G." surname="Richichi" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                       <author initials="M." surname="Dohler" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date year="2011"/>
                   </front>
<seriesInfo name="IEEE Communications" value="Surveys and Tutorials"/>
<seriesInfo name="Vol." value="13"/>
<seriesInfo name="Issue" value="4"/>
<seriesInfo name="pp." value="688-707"/>
                </reference>

                <reference anchor="Ikram">
                   <front>
                           <title>A Simple Lightweight Authentic Bootstrapping Protocol for IPv6-based Low Rate Wireless Personal Area Networks (6LoWPANs)</title>
                 <author initials="M." surname="Ikram" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="A." surname="Chowdhury" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="B." surname="Zafar" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="H." surname="Cha" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="K." surname="Kim" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="S." surname="Yoo" fullname="">
        </author>
                 <author initials="D." surname="Kim" fullname="">
        </author>
                           <date month="June" year="2009"/>
                   </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proc. International Conference on Wireless
Communications and Mobile" value="Computing"/>
                </reference>


<reference anchor="Kuhn">
                   <front>
                           <title>Worst-Case Optimal and Average-Case Efficient Ad-Hoc Geometric Routing</title>
                           <author initials="F." surname="Kuhn" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="R." surname="Wattenhofer" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <author initials="A." surname="Zollinger" fullname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
                           <date month="June" year="2003"/>
                   </front>
<seriesInfo name="MobiHoc '03:" value="Proceedings of the 4th ACM International
Symposium on Mobile Ad Hoc Networking and Computing"/>
                </reference>

&RFC6434;
        </references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
</back>
</rfc>
