<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.2869__g60i1uxb SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2869.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" number="6519"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DS-Lite RADIUS Extensions">RADIUS Extensions for Dual-Stack
    Lite</title>

    <author fullname="Roberta Maglione" initials="R." surname="Maglione">
      <organization abbrev="">Telecom Italia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Reiss Romoli 274</street>
          <city>Torino</city>
          <code>10148</code>
          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>
        <email>roberta.maglione@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alain Durand" initials="A." surname="Durand">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Mathilda Avenue</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089-1206</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>adurand@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2012" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>softwire</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Dual-Stack Lite is a solution to offer both IPv4 and IPv6
      connectivity to customers that are addressed only with an IPv6 prefix.
      Dual-Stack Lite requires pre-configuration of the Dual-Stack Lite Address
      Family Transition Router (AFTR) tunnel information on the Basic Bridging
      BroadBand (B4) element. In many networks, the customer profile
      information may be stored in Authentication, Authorization, and
      Accounting (AAA) servers, while client configurations are mainly
      provided through the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP).
      This document specifies a new Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service
      (RADIUS) attribute to carry the Dual-Stack Lite AFTR tunnel name; the
      RADIUS attribute is defined based on the equivalent DHCPv6
      OPTION_AFTR_NAME option. This RADIUS attribute is meant to be used
      between the RADIUS server and the Network Access Server (NAS); it is not
      intended to be used directly between the B4 element and the
      RADIUS server.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Dual-Stack Lite <xref target="RFC6333"></xref> is a solution to offer
      both IPv4 and IPv6 connectivity to customers that are addressed only
      with an IPv6 prefix (no IPv4 address is assigned to the attachment
      device). One of its key components is an IPv4-over-IPv6 tunnel, but a
      Dual-Stack-Lite Basic Bridging BroadBand (B4) element will not know if
      the network to which it is attached offers Dual-Stack Lite support.
      Even if the B4 did know, it would not know the remote end of the tunnel
      to which it could establish a connection.</t>

      <t>To inform the B4 element of the location of the Address Family
      Transition Router (AFTR), a Fully Qualified Domain Name
      (FQDN) may be used. Once this information is conveyed, the presence of
      the configuration indicating the AFTR's location also informs a host to
      initiate Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite) service and become a Softwire
      Initiator.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6334"></xref> specifies a DHCPv6 option that is
      meant to be used by a DS&nbhy;Lite client (B4 element) to discover its AFTR
      name. In order to be able to populate such an option, the DHCPv6 server
      must be pre-provisioned with the AFTR name.</t>

      <t>In broadband environments, a customer profile may be managed by
      Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) servers, together
      with AAA for users. The Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service
      (RADIUS) protocol <xref target="RFC2865"></xref> is usually used by
      AAA servers to communicate with network elements. <xref
      target="RADIUS-IPv6"></xref> describes a typical
      broadband network scenario in which the Network Access Server (NAS) acts
      as the access gateway for the users (hosts or Customer Premises
      Equipment (CPE) devices) and also embeds a
      DHCPv6 server function that allows it to locally handle any DHCPv6
      requests issued by the clients.</t>

      <t>Since the DS-Lite AFTR information can be stored in AAA servers and
      the client configuration is mainly provided through DHCP running
      between the NAS and the requesting
      clients, a new RADIUS attribute is needed to send AFTR information from
      the AAA server to the NAS.</t>

      <t>This document defines a new RADIUS attribute to be used for
      carrying the DS-Lite Tunnel Name, based on the equivalent DHCPv6 option
      already specified in <xref target="RFC6334"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- intro -->

    <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The terms DS-Lite Basic Bridging BroadBand element (B4) and the
      DS&nbhy;Lite Address Family Transition Router element (AFTR) are defined
      in <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DS-Lite Configuration with RADIUS and DHCPv6">
      <t><xref target="fig1"></xref> illustrates how the RADIUS protocol
      and DHCPv6 work together to accomplish DS-Lite configuration on the B4
      element when a PPP session is used to provide connectivity to the
      user.</t>

      <t>The NAS operates as a client of RADIUS and as
      a DHCP Server. The NAS initially sends a RADIUS Access-Request message
      to the RADIUS server, requesting authentication. Once
      the RADIUS server receives the request, it validates the sending client,
      and if the request is approved, the AAA server replies with an
      Access-Accept message including a list of attribute-value pairs that
      describe
      the parameters to be used for this session. This list MAY also contain
      the AFTR tunnel name. When the NAS receives a DHCPv6 client request
      containing the DS-Lite tunnel option, the NAS SHALL use the name
      returned in the RADIUS DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute to populate the
      DHCPv6 OPTION_AFTR_NAME option in the DHCPv6 reply message.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig1" height=""
          title="RADIUS and DHCPv6 Message Flow for a PPP Session">
          <artwork><![CDATA[    B4                                NAS                     AAA
    |                                  |                     Server
    |                                  |                        |
    |----PPP LCP Config-Request------> |                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |                                  |----Access-Request ---->|
    |                                  |                        |
    |                                  |<---- Access-Accept-----|
    |                                  | (DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name)  |
    |<-----PPP LCP Config-ACK  ------- |                        |
    |                                  |                        | 
    |                                  |                        |   
    |--- PPP IPv6CP Config-Request --->|                        |
    |                                  |                        |     
    |<----- PPP IPv6CP Config-ACK -----|                        |
    |                                  |                        |  
    |-------  DHCPv6 Solicit  -------->|                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |<-------DHCPv6 Advertisement -----|                        |
    |      (DHCPv6 OPTION_AFTR_NAME)   |                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |-------  DHCPv6 Request  -------->|                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |<-------- DHCPv6 Reply ---------- |                        |
    |      (DHCPv6 OPTION_AFTR_NAME)   |                        |
                        
                DHCPv6                         RADIUS 
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><xref target="fig2"></xref> illustrates how the RADIUS protocol
      and DHCPv6 work together to accomplish DS-Lite configuration on the B4
      element when an IP session is used to provide connectivity to the
      user.</t>

      <t>The only difference between this message flow and the previous one is
      that in this scenario, the interaction between the NAS and the
      AAA/RADIUS server
      is triggered by the DHCPv6 Solicit message received by the NAS from the
      B4 acting as a DHCPv6 client, while in the case of a PPP session,
      the trigger
      is the PPP Link Control Protocol (LCP) Config-Request message
      received by the NAS.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig2" height=""
              title="RADIUS and DHCPv6 Message Flow for an IP Session">
        <artwork><![CDATA[    B4                                NAS                      AAA
    |                                  |                      Server
    |------ DHCPv6 Solicit --------->  |                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |                                  |----Access-Request ---->|
    |                                  |                        |
    |                                  |<---Access-Accept-------|
    |                                  | (DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name)  |
    |                                  |                        |
    |<-------DHCPv6 Advertisement------|                        |
    |     (DHCPv6 OPTION_AFTR_NAME)    |                        |
    |                                  |                        |
    |-------  DHCPv6 Request  -------->|                        |
    |                                  |                        |    
    |                                  |                        |
    |<----- DHCPv6 Reply ------------- |                        |
    |     (DHCPv6 OPTION_AFTR_NAME)    |                        |
                        
                DHCPv6                         RADIUS 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>In the scenario depicted in <xref target="fig2"></xref>, the
      Access-Request packet contains a Service-Type attribute with the value
      Authorize Only (17); thus, according to <xref target="RFC5080"></xref>,
      the Access-Request packet MUST contain a State attribute.</t>

      <t>After receiving the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute in the
      initial Access-Accept packet,
      the NAS MUST store the received AFTR tunnel name locally. When the B4
      sends a DHCPv6 Renew message to request an extension of the lifetimes
      for the assigned address or prefix, the NAS does not have to initiate a
      new Access-Request packet towards the AAA server to request the AFTR
      tunnel name. The NAS retrieves the previously stored AFTR tunnel name
      and uses it in its reply.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>, if the DHCPv6 server to
      which the DHCPv6 Renew message was sent at time T1 has not responded,
      the DHCPv6 client initiates a Rebind/Reply message exchange with any
      available server. In this scenario, the NAS receiving the DHCPv6 Rebind
      message MUST initiate a new Access-Request message towards the AAA
      server. The NAS MAY include the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute in its
      Access-Request message.</t>

      <t>If the NAS does not receive the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute in the
      Access-Accept message, it MAY fall back to a pre-configured default
      tunnel name,
      if any. If the NAS does not have any pre-configured default tunnel name
      or if the NAS receives an Access-Reject message, the IPv4-over-IPv6
      tunnel cannot be established; thus, the B4 element has only IPv6
      connectivity.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- term -->

    <!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->

    <section anchor="Attrib" title="RADIUS Attribute">
      <t>This section specifies the format of the new RADIUS attribute.</t>

      <section anchor="DSLITE-Name" title="DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name">

        <t>The DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name RADIUS attribute contains an FQDN
        that refers to the AFTR to which the client is requested to
        establish a connection. The NAS SHALL use the name returned in
        the RADIUS DS&nbhy;Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute to populate the DHCPv6
        OPTION_AFTR_NAME option <xref target="RFC6334"></xref>.</t>

        <t>This attribute MAY be used in Access-Request packets as a hint to
        the RADIUS server; for example, if the NAS is pre-configured with a
        default tunnel name, this name MAY be inserted in the attribute. The
        RADIUS server MAY ignore the hint sent by the NAS, and it MAY assign a
        different AFTR tunnel name.</t>

        <t>If the NAS includes the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute, but the AAA
        server does not recognize it, this attribute MUST be ignored by the
        AAA server.</t>

        <t>If the NAS does not receive the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute in the
        Access-Accept message, it MAY fall back to a pre-configured default
        tunnel name,
        if any. If the NAS does not have any pre-configured default tunnel
        name, the tunnel cannot be established.</t>

        <t>If the NAS is pre-provisioned with a default AFTR tunnel name and
        the AFTR tunnel name received in the Access-Accept message is
        different from the
        configured default, then the AFTR tunnel name received in the
        Access-Accept message MUST be used for the session.</t>

        <t>If the NAS cannot support the received AFTR tunnel name for any
        reason, the tunnel SHOULD NOT be established.</t>

        <t>When the Access-Request message is triggered by a DHCPv6 Rebind
        message, if the AFTR tunnel name received in the Access-Accept
        message is different from
        the currently used one for that session, the NAS MUST force the B4 to
        re-establish the tunnel using the new AFTR name received in the
        Access-Accept message.</t>

        <t>If an implementation includes Change-of-Authorization (CoA)
        messages <xref target="RFC5176"></xref>, they could be used to modify
        the current established DS&nbhy;Lite tunnel. When the NAS receives
        a CoA
        Request message containing the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute, the NAS
        MUST send a Reconfigure message to a B4 to inform the B4 that the NAS
        has new or updated configuration parameters and that the B4 is to
        initiate a Renew/Reply or Information-Request/Reply transaction with
        the NAS in order to receive the updated information.</t>

        <t>Upon receiving an AFTR tunnel name different from the currently
        used one, the B4 MUST terminate the current DS-Lite tunnel, and the B4
        MUST establish a new DS-Lite tunnel with the specified AFTR.</t>

        <t>The DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name RADIUS attribute MAY be present in
        Accounting-Request records where the Acct-Status-Type is set to Start,
        Stop, or Interim-Update. The DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name RADIUS attribute MUST
        NOT appear more than once in a message.</t>

        <t>A summary of the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name RADIUS attribute format is
        shown below. The fields are transmitted from left to right.</t>

        <figure>
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |    Length     |  DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name (FQDN)...
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>Type:</t>

        <t><list counter="1" hangIndent="5">
            <t>144 for DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name.</t>
          </list>Length: <list counter="1" hangIndent="5">
            <t>This field indicates the total length in octets of this
            attribute including the Type and Length fields, and the length in
            octets of the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name field.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name:<list counter="1" hangIndent="5">
            <t>This field contains a single FQDN of the remote tunnel
            endpoint, located at the DS-Lite AFTR.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>As the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name attribute is used to populate the DHCPv6
        OPTION_AFTR_NAME option, the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name field is formatted as
        required in DHCPv6 (Section 8 of <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> --
        "Representation and Use of Domain Names"). Briefly, the format
        described is using a single octet noting the length of one DNS label
        (limited to at most 63 octets), followed by the label contents. This
        repeats until all labels in the FQDN are exhausted, including a
        terminating zero-length label. Any updates to Section 8 of <xref
        target="RFC3315"></xref> also apply to the encoding of this field.</t>

        <t>The data type of the DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name RADIUS attribute is a
        string with opaque encapsulation, according to <xref target="RFC2865">
        Section 5 of </xref>.</t>

        <!-- ProvSnd -->

        <!-- ProvRecv -->
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Table of Attributes">
      <t>The following tables provide a guide to which attributes may be found
      in which kinds of packets, and in what quantity.</t>

      <texttable style="none">
        <ttcol>Access- Request</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Access- Accept</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Access- Reject</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Challenge</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Accounting Request</ttcol>

        <ttcol>#</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Attribute</ttcol>

        <c>0-1</c>

        <c>0-1</c>

        <c>0</c>

        <c>0</c>

        <c>0-1</c>

        <c>144</c>

        <c>DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name</c>
      </texttable>

      <texttable align="left" style="none">
        <ttcol>CoA-Request</ttcol>

        <ttcol>CoA-ACK</ttcol>

        <ttcol>CoA-NACK</ttcol>

        <ttcol>#</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Attribute</ttcol>

        <c>0-1</c>

        <c>0</c>

        <c>0</c>

        <c>144</c>

        <c>DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>The following table defines the meaning of the above table
      entries.</t>

      <texttable style="none" suppress-title="true">
        <ttcol></ttcol>

        <ttcol></ttcol>

        <c>0</c>

        <c>This attribute MUST NOT be present in the packet.</c>

        <c>0+</c>

        <c>Zero or more instances of this attribute MAY be present in the
        packet.</c>

        <c>0-1</c>

        <c>Zero or one instance of this attribute MAY be present in the
        packet.</c>
      </texttable>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="seccons" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document has no additional security considerations beyond those
      already identified in <xref target="RFC2865"></xref> for the RADIUS
      protocol and in <xref target="RFC5176"></xref> for CoA messages.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6333"></xref> discusses security issues
      related to Dual-Stack Lite.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Per this document, IANA has allocated a new RADIUS attribute type
      from the IANA registry "Radius Attribute Types" located at
      http://www.iana.org/assignments/radius-types.</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>DS-Lite-Tunnel-Name - 144</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6333'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6334'?>

      &rfc2865;

<reference anchor='RFC3315'>
<front>
<title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Droms' fullname='R. Droms' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Bound' fullname='J. Bound'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Volz' fullname='B. Volz'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Lemon' fullname='T. Lemon'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Perkins' fullname='C. Perkins'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Carney' fullname='M. Carney'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' /></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3315' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5080'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!-- draft-ietf-radext-ipv6-access ("I-D Exists") -->
<reference anchor='RADIUS-IPv6'>
<front>
<title>RADIUS attributes for IPv6 Access Networks</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Lourdelet' fullname='Benoit Lourdelet'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='W' surname='Dec' fullname='Wojciech Dec' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='B' surname='Sarikaya' fullname='Behcet Sarikaya'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='G' surname='Zorn' fullname='Glen Zorn'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Miles' fullname='David Miles'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='November' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5176'?>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
