<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902" number="6127" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<front>

<title abbrev="IPv4 and IPv6 Co-Existence">IPv4 Run-Out and IPv4-IPv6 Co-Existence Scenarios</title>

<author initials="J" surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
<organization>Ericsson</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street/>
<city>Jorvas</city> <code>02420</code>
<country>Finland</country>
</postal>
<email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="M" surname="Townsley" fullname="Mark Townsley">
<organization>Cisco</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street/>
<city>Paris</city><code>75006</code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>townsley@cisco.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="May" year="2011"/>

<abstract>

<t>
When IPv6 was designed, it was expected that the transition from
IPv4 to IPv6 would occur more smoothly and expeditiously than
experience has revealed.  The growth of the IPv4 Internet and predicted
depletion of the free pool of IPv4 address blocks on a foreseeable horizon
has highlighted an urgent need to revisit IPv6 deployment models.  This
document provides an overview of deployment scenarios with the goal of
helping to understand what types of additional tools the industry
needs to assist in IPv4 and IPv6 co-existence and transition.</t>

<t> This document was originally created as input to the Montreal
co-existence interim meeting in October 2008, which led to the
rechartering of the Behave and Softwire working groups to take on new
IPv4 and IPv6 co-existence work.  This document is published as a
historical record of the thinking at the time, but hopefully will
also help readers understand the rationale behind current IETF tools for
co-existence and transition.</t>
</abstract>

</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t> This document was originally created as input to the Montreal
co&nbhy;existence interim meeting in October 2008, which led to the
rechartering of the Behave and Softwire working groups to take on new
IPv4 and IPv6 co-existence work.  This document is published as a
historical record of the thinking at the time, but hopefully will also
help readers understand the rationale behind current IETF tools for
co-existence and transition.</t>

<t>When IPv6 was designed, it was expected that IPv6 would be enabled,
in part or in whole, while continuing to run IPv4 side-by-side on the
same network nodes and hosts.  This method of transition is referred to
as "dual-stack" <xref target="RFC4213"/> and has been the prevailing
method driving the specifications and available tools for IPv6 to
date.</t>

<t> Experience has shown that large-scale deployment of IPv6 takes
time, effort, and significant investment.  With IPv4 address pool
depletion on the foreseeable horizon <xref target="HUSTON-IPv4"/>,
network operators and Internet Service Providers are being forced to
consider network designs that no longer assume the same
level of access to unique global IPv4
addresses.  IPv6 alone does not alleviate this
concern given the basic assumption that all hosts and nodes will be
dual-stack until the eventual sunsetting of IPv4-only equipment.  In
short, the time-frames for the growth of the IPv4 Internet, the
universal deployment of dual-stack IPv4 and IPv6, and the final
transition to an IPv6-dominant Internet are not in alignment with what
was originally expected.</t>

<t>While dual-stack remains the most well-understood approach to
deploying IPv6 today, current realities dictate a re-assessment of the
tools available for other deployment models that are likely to
emerge.  In particular, the implications of deploying multiple layers
of IPv4 address translation need to be considered, as well as those
associated with translation between IPv4 and IPv6, which led to the
deprecation of <xref target="RFC2766"/> as detailed in
<xref target="RFC4966"/>.  This document outlines some of the scenarios
where these address and protocol translation mechanisms could be
useful, in addition to methods where carrying IPv4 over IPv6 may be
used to assist in transition to IPv6 and co-existence with IPv4.  We
purposefully avoid a description of classic dual-stack methods, as
well as IPv6-over-IPv4 tunneling.  Instead, this document focuses on
scenarios that are driving tools we have historically not been
developing standard solutions around.</t>

<t>It should be understood that the scenarios in this document
represent new deployment models and are intended to complement, and not
replace, existing ones.  For instance, dual-stack continues to be the
most recommended deployment model.  Note that dual-stack is not limited
to situations where all hosts can acquire public IPv4 addresses.  A
common deployment scenario is running dual-stack on the IPv6 side with
public addresses, and on the IPv4 side with just one public address
and a traditional IPv4 NAT.  Generally speaking, offering native
connectivity with both IP versions is preferred over the use of
translation or tunneling mechanisms when sufficient address space is
available.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="scenarios" title="Scenarios">

<t>This section identifies five deployment scenarios that we believe
have a significant level of near-to-medium-term demand somewhere on the
globe.  We will discuss these in the following sections, while walking
through a bit of the design space to get an understanding of the types
of tools that could be developed to solve each.  In particular, we want
the reader to consider for each scenario what type of new equipment must be
introduced in the network, and where; which nodes
must be changed in some way; and which nodes must work together in an
interoperable manner via a new or existing protocol.

<t>The five scenarios are:</t>

<list style="symbols">

<t>Reaching the IPv4 Internet with less than one global IPv4
address per subscriber or subscriber household available
(<xref target="scenario-outofv4"/>).</t>

<t>Running a large network needing more addresses than those available in
private RFC 1918 address space
(<xref target="scenario-outofnet10"/>).</t>

<t>Running an IPv6-only network for operational simplicity as compared
to dual-stack, while still needing access to the global IPv4 Internet for 
some, but not all, connectivity
(<xref target="scenario-simpleops"/>).</t>

<t>Reaching one or more privately addressed IPv4-only servers via IPv6
(<xref target="scenario-net10servers"/>).</t>

<t>Accessing IPv6-only servers from IPv4-only clients
(<xref target="scenario-v6onlyservers"/>).</t>

</list></t>


<section anchor="scenario-outofv4" title="Reaching the IPv4 Internet">

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                 +----+                       +---------------+
IPv4 host(s)-----+ GW +------IPv4-------------| IPv4 Internet |
                 +----+                       +---------------+

<---private v4--->NAT<--------------public v4----------------->

         Figure 1: Accessing the IPv4 Internet Today

]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Figure 1 shows a typical model for accessing the IPv4 Internet
today, with the gateway device implementing a Network Address and Port
Translation (NAPT, or more simply referred to in this document as
NAT).  The NAT function serves a number of purposes, one of which is to
allow more hosts behind the gateway (GW) than there are IPv4 addresses
presented to the Internet.  This multiplexing of IP addresses comes at
great cost to the original end-to-end model of the Internet, but
nonetheless is the dominant method of access today, particularly to
residential subscribers.</t>

<t>Taking the typical residential subscriber as an example, each
subscriber line is allocated one global IPv4 address for it to use
with as many devices as the NAT GW and local network can handle.  As
IPv4 address space becomes more constrained and without substantial
movement to IPv6, it is expected that service providers will be
pressured to assign a single global IPv4 address to multiple
subscribers.  Indeed, in some deployments this is already the case.</t>

<section title="NAT444">

<t>When there is less than one address per subscriber at a given time,
address multiplexing must be performed at a location where visibility
to more than one subscriber can be realized.  The most obvious place for this
is within the service provider network itself, requiring the service
provider to acquire and operate NAT equipment to allow sharing of
addresses across multiple subscribers.  For deployments where the GW is
owned and operated by the customer, however, this becomes
operational overhead for
the Internet Service Provider (ISP), for which the ISP will no longer be
able to rely on the customer and the seller of the GW device.</t>

<t>This new address translation node has been termed a "Carrier Grade
NAT", or CGN <xref target="NISHITANI-CGN"/>.  The CGN's insertion
into the ISP network is shown in Figure 2.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+
IPv4 host(s)-----+ GW +------IPv4---------+CGN+--+IPv4 Internet|
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+

<---private v4--->NAT<----private v4------>NAT<----public v4--->

             Figure 2: Employing Two NAT Devices: NAT444
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>This approach is known as "NAT444" or "Double-NAT" and
is discussed further in
<xref target="NAT-PT"/>.</t>

<t>It is important to note that while multiplexing of IPv4
addresses is occurring here at multiple levels, there is no aggregation of
NAT state between the GW and the CGN.  Every flow that is originated in the
subscriber home is represented as duplicate state in the GW and the
CGN.  For example, if there are 4 PCs in a subscriber home, each with
25 open TCP sessions, both the GW and the CGN must track 100 sessions each
for that subscriber line.</t>

<t>NAT444 has the enticing property that it seems, at first glance,
that the CGN can be deployed without any change to the GW device or
other node in the network.  While it is true that a GW that can accept
a lease for a global IPv4 address would very likely accept a
translated IPv4 address as well, the CGN is neither transparent to the
GW nor to the subscriber.  In short, it is a very different service model
to offer a translated IPv4 address versus a global IPv4 address to a
customer.  While many things may continue to work in both environments,
some end-host applications may break, and GW port-mapping
functionality will likely cease to work reliably.  Further, if
addresses between the subscriber network and service provider network
overlap <xref target="ISP-SHARED-ADDR"/>, ambiguous routes in the GW
could lead to misdirected or black-holed traffic.  Resolving this overlap
through allocation of new private address space is difficult, as many
existing devices rely on knowing what address ranges represent private
addresses
<xref target="IPv4-SPACE-ISSUES"/>.</t>

<t>Network operations that had previously been tied to a single IPv4
address for a subscriber would need to be considered when deploying
NAT444 as well.  These may include troubleshooting, operations,
accounting, logging and legal intercept, Quality of Service (QoS)
functions, anti-spoofing and security, backoffice systems, etc.
Ironically, some of these
considerations overlap with the kinds of considerations one needs to
perform when deploying IPv6. </t>

<t> Consequences aside, NAT444 service is already being deployed in
some networks for residential broadband service.  It is safe to assume
that this trend will likely continue in the face of tightening IPv4
address availability.  The operational considerations of NAT444 need to
be well-documented.</t>

<t>NAT444 assumes that the global IPv4 address offered to a
residential subscriber today will simply be replaced with a single
translated address.  In order to try and circumvent performing NAT
twice, and since the address being offered is no longer a global
address, a service provider could begin offering a subnet of
translated IPv4 addresses in hopes that the subscriber would route
IPv4 in the GW rather than NAT.  The same would be true if the GW was
known to be an IP-unaware bridge.  This makes assumptions on whether
the ISP can enforce policies, or even identify specific capabilities,
of the GW.  Once we start opening the door to making changes at the GW,
we have increased the potential design space considerably.  The next
section covers the same problem scenario of reaching the IPv4 Internet
in the face of IPv4 address depletion, but with the added wrinkle that
the GW can be updated or replaced along with the deployment of a CGN
(or CGN-like) node.</t>

</section>

<section title="Distributed NAT">

<t>Increasingly, service providers offering "triple-play" services own
and manage a highly functional GW in the subscriber home.  These
managed GWs generally have rather tight integration with the service
provider network and applications.  In these types of deployments, we
can begin to consider what other possibilities exist besides NAT444 by
assuming cooperative functionality between the CGN and the GW.</t>

<t>If the connection between the GW and the CGN is a point-to-point
link (a common configuration between the GW and the "IP edge"
in a number of access architectures), NAT-like
functionality may be "split" between the GW and the CGN rather than
performing NAT444 as described in the previous section.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
              one frac addr            one public addr
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+
IPv4 host(s)-----+ GW +-----p2p link------+CGN+--+IPv4 Internet|
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+

<---private v4--->            NAT             <----public v4--->
                          (distributed, 
                        over a p2p link)

            Figure 3: Distributed-NAT Service
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>In this approach, multiple GWs share a common public IPv4 address,
but with separate, non-overlapping port ranges.  Each such
address/port range pair is defined as a "fractional address".  Each
home gateway can use the address as if it were its own public address,
except that only a limited port range is available to the gateway.  The
CGN is aware of the port ranges, which may be assigned in different ways,
for instance during DHCP lease acquisition or dynamically
when ports are needed
<xref target="v6OPS-APBP"/>.  The CGN directs traffic to
the fractional address towards that subscriber's GW device.  This
method has the advantage that the more complicated aspects of the NAT
function (Application Level Gateways (ALGs), port mapping, etc.) remain in the GW, augmented only
by the restricted port range allocated to the fractional address for
that GW.  The CGN is then free to operate in a fairly stateless manner,
forwarding traffic based on IP address and port ranges and not tracking any
individual flows from within the subscriber network.  There are obvious
scaling benefits to this approach within the CGN node, with the
tradeoff of complexity in terms of the number of nodes and protocols
that must work together in an interoperable manner.  Further, the GW is
still receiving a global IPv4 address, albeit only a "portion" of one
in terms of available port usage.  There are still outstanding
questions in terms of how to handle protocols that run directly over
IP and cannot use the divided port number ranges, and how to handle
fragmented packets, but the benefit is
that we are no longer burdened by two layers of NAT as in NAT444. </t>

<t>Not all access architectures provide a natural
point-to-point link between the GW and the CGN to tie into.  Further, the
CGN may not be incorporated into the IP edge device in 
networks that do have point-to-point links.  For
these cases, we can build our own point-to-point link using a tunnel.  A
tunnel is essentially a point-to-point link that we create when
needed <xref target="INTAREA-TUNNELS"/>.  This is illustrated in Figure 4.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
              one frac addr            one public addr
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+
IPv4 host(s)-----+ GW +======tunnel=======+CGN+--+IPv4 Internet|
                 +----+                   +---+  +-------------+

<---private v4--->            NAT             <----public v4--->
                         (distributed, 
                         over a tunnel)

       Figure 4: Point-to-Point Link Created through a Tunnel
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Figure 4 is essentially the same as Figure 3, except the data link
is created with a tunnel.  The tunnel could be created in any number of
ways, depending on the underlying network. </t>

<t>At this point, we have used a tunnel or point-to-point link with
coordinated operation between the GW and the CGN in order to keep most of
the NAT functionality in the GW.</t>

<t>Given the assumption of a point-to-point link between the GW and the CGN,
the CGN could perform the NAT function, allowing private, overlapping
space to all subscribers.  For example, each subscriber GW may be
assigned the same 10.0.0.0/8 address space (or all RFC 1918 <xref
target="RFC1918"/> space for that matter).  The GW then becomes a
simple "tunneling router", and the CGN takes on the full NAT role.  One
can think of this design as effectively a layer-3 VPN, but with
Virtual-NAT tables rather than Virtual-Routing tables.</t>

</section>

<section title="Recommendation">

<t>This section deals strictly with the problem of reaching the IPv4
Internet with limited public address space for each device in a
network.  We explored combining NAT functions and tunnels between the
GW and the CGN to obtain similar results with different design
tradeoffs.  The methods presented can be summarized as:

<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="a.">Double-NAT (NAT444)</t>
<t hangText="b.">Single-NAT at CGN with a subnet and routing at the GW</t>
<t hangText="c.">Tunnel/link + fractional IP (NAT at GW, port-routing at CGN)</t>
<t hangText="d.">Tunnel/link + Single-NAT with overlapping RFC 1918 ("Virtual NAT" tables and routing at the GW)</t>
</list></t>

<t>In all of the methods above, the GW could be logically moved into a single
host, potentially eliminating one level of NAT by that action alone.  As
long as the hosts themselves need only a single IPv4 address, methods
b and d obviously are of little interest.  This leaves methods a and c
as the more interesting methods in cases where there is no analogous
GW device (such as a campus network).</t>

<t>This document recommends the development of new guidelines and
specifications to address the above methods.  Cases where the
home gateway both can and cannot be modified should be addressed.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor="scenario-outofnet10" title="Running Out of IPv4 Private Address Space">

<t>In addition to public address space depletion, very large privately addressed
networks are reaching exhaustion of RFC 1918 space on local networks as well.  Very large
service provider networks are prime candidates for this.  Private address
space is used locally in ISPs for a variety of things, including:

<list style="symbols">

<t>Control and management of service provider devices in subscriber
premises (cable modems, set-top boxes, and so on).</t>

<t>Addressing the subscriber's NAT devices in a Double-NAT arrangement.</t>

<t>"Walled garden" data, voice, or video services.</t>

</list></t>

<t>Some providers deal with this problem by dividing their network
into parts, each on its own copy of the private space.  However, this
limits the way services can be deployed and what management systems
can reach what devices.  It is also operationally complicated in the
sense that the network operators have to understand which private
scope they are in.</t>

<t> Tunnels were used in the previous section to facilitate
distribution of a single global IPv4 address across multiple endpoints
without using NAT, or to allow overlapping address space to GWs or
hosts connected to a CGN.  The kind of tunnel or link was not specified.  If
the tunnel used carries IPv4 over IPv6, the portion of the IPv6 network
traversed naturally need not be IPv4-capable, and need not utilize
IPv4 addresses, private or public, for the tunnel traffic to traverse
the network.  This is shown in Figure 5.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                         IPv6-only network
                 +----+                     +---+  +-------------+
IPv4 host--------+ GW +=======tunnel========+CGN+--+IPv4 Internet|
                 +----+                     +---+  +-------------+

<---private v4---->  <-----  v4 over v6 ----->  <---public v4---->

        Figure 5: Running IPv4 over an IPv6-Only Network
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t> Each of the four approaches (a, b, c, and d) from the
<xref target="scenario-outofv4"/> scenario could be applied here, 
and for brevity each iteration is not specified in full here.  The
models are essentially the same, just that the tunnel is over 
an IPv6 network and carries IPv4 traffic.  Note that while there
are numerous solutions for carrying IPv6 over IPv4, this reverse 
mode is somewhat of an exception (one notable exception being
the Softwire working group, as seen in <xref target="RFC4925"/>).</t>

<t> Once we have IPv6 to the GW (or host, if we consider
the GW embedded in the host), enabling IPv6 and IPv4 over the IPv6 tunnel
allows for dual-stack operation at the host or network behind the GW
device.  This is depicted in Figure 6:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                +----+                               +-------------+
  IPv6 host-----+    |            +------------------+IPv6 Internet|
                |    +---IPv6-----+                  +-------------+
dual-stack host-+ GW |
                |    |                        +---+  +-------------+
  IPv4 host-----+    +===v4-over-v6 tunnel====+CGN+--+IPv4 Internet|
                +----+                        +---+  +-------------+
         
<-----------private v4 (partially in tunnel)-->NAT<---public v4---->
<-----------------------------public v6---------------------------->

  Figure 6: "Dual-Stack Lite" Operation over an IPv6-Only Network
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>In <xref target="DUAL-STACK-LITE"/>, this is referred to
as "dual-stack lite", bowing to the fact that it is dual-stack at the
gateway, but not at the network.  As introduced in
<xref target="scenario-outofv4"/>, if the CGN here is a full
functioning NAT, hosts behind a dual-stack lite gateway can support
IPv4-only and IPv6-enabled applications across an IPv6-only network
without provisioning a unique IPv4 address to each gateway.  In fact,
every gateway may have the same address.</t>

<t>While the high-level problem space in this scenario is how to alleviate
local usage of IPv4 addresses within a service provider network, the
solution direction identified with IPv6 has interesting operational
properties that should be pointed out.  By tunneling IPv4 over IPv6
across the service provider network, the separate problems of
transitioning the service provider network to IPv6, deploying IPv6 to
subscribers, and continuing to provide IPv4 service can all be decoupled.
The service provider could deploy IPv6 internally, turn off IPv4
internally, and
still carry IPv4 traffic across the IPv6 core for end users.  In the
extreme case, all of that IPv4 traffic need not be provisioned with
different IPv4 addresses for each endpoint, as there is not IPv4
routing or forwarding within the network.  Thus, there are no issues
with IPv4 renumbering, address space allocation, etc. within the
network itself.</t>

<t>It is recommended that the IETF develop tools to address this
scenario for both a host and the GW.  It is assumed that both endpoints of
the tunnel can be modified to support these new tools.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="scenario-simpleops" title="Enterprise IPv6-Only Networks">

<t>This scenario is about allowing an IPv6-only host or a host that
has no interfaces connected to an IPv4 network to reach servers on
the IPv4 Internet.  This is an important scenario for what we sometimes
call "greenfield" deployments.  One example is an enterprise network
that wishes to operate only IPv6 for operational simplicity, but still
wishes to reach the content in the IPv4 Internet.  For instance, a new
office building may be provisioned with IPv6 only.  This is shown in
Figure 7.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                          +----+                  +-------------+
                          |    +------------------+IPv6 Internet+
                          |    |                  +-------------+
IPv6 host-----------------+ GW |
                          |    |                  +-------------+
                          |    +------------------+IPv4 Internet+
                          +----+                  +-------------+

<-------------------------public v6----------------------------->
<-------public v6--------->NAT<----------public v4-------------->

          Figure 7: Enterprise IPv6-Only Network
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Other cases that have been mentioned include "greenfield" wireless service
provider networks and sensor networks.  This enterprise IPv6-only scenario
bears a striking resemblance to the <xref target="scenario-outofnet10"/>
scenario as well, if one considers a particularly large enterprise network
that begins to resemble a service provider network.</t>

<t>In the <xref target="scenario-outofnet10"/> scenario, we dipped
into design space enough to illustrate that the service provider was
able to implement an IPv6-only network to ease their addressing
problems via tunneling.  This came at the cost of touching two devices
on the edges of this network; both the GW and the CGN have to support
IPv6 and the tunneling mechanism over IPv6.  The greenfield enterprise
scenario is different from that one in the sense that there is only
one place that the enterprise can easily modify: the border between
its network and the IPv4 Internet.  Obviously, the IPv4 Internet
operates the way it already does.  But in addition, the hosts in the
enterprise network are commercially available devices, personal
computers with existing operating systems.  While we consider in this
scenario that all of the devices on the network are "modern"
dual-stack-capable devices, we do not want to have to rely upon
kernel-level modifications to these operating systems.  This
restriction drives us
to a "one box" type of solution, where IPv6 can be translated into
IPv4 to reach the public Internet.  This is one situation where new
or improved IETF specifications could have
an effect on the user experience in these networks.  In fairness, it
should be noted that even a network-based solution will take time
and effort to deploy.  This is essentially, again, a tradeoff between
one new piece of equipment in the network, or a cooperation between
two.</t>

<t>One approach to deal with this environment is to provide an
application-level proxy at the edge of the network (GW).  For instance,
if the only application that needs to reach the IPv4 Internet is the
web, then an HTTP/HTTPS proxy can easily convert traffic from IPv6 into
IPv4 on the outside.</t>

<t>Another more generic approach is to employ an IPv6-to-IPv4
translator device.  Different types of translation schemes are
discussed in <xref target="NAT-PT"/>,
<xref target="RFC6144"/>, <xref target="RFC6145"/>,
and <xref target="RFC6052"/>.  NAT64 is one example of a translation
scheme falling under this category <xref target="RFC6147"/>
<xref target="RFC6146"/>.</t>

<t>Translation will in most cases have some negative consequences for
the end-to-end operation of Internet protocols.  For instance, the
issues with Network Address Translation - Protocol Translation
(NAT-PT) <xref target="RFC2766"/> have been described
in <xref target="RFC4966"/>.
It is important to note that the choice of translation solution, and
the assumptions about the network in which it is used, impact the
consequences.  A translator for the general case has a number of issues
that a translator for a more specific situation may not have at
all.</t>

<t>It is recommended that the IETF develop tools to address
this scenario.  These tools need to allow existing IPv6 hosts
to operate unchanged.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="scenario-net10servers" title="Reaching Private IPv4-Only Servers">

<t>This section discusses the specific problem of IPv4-only-capable
server farms that no longer can be allocated a sufficient number of
public addresses.  It is expected that for individual servers,
addresses are going to be available for a long time in a reasonably
easy manner.  However, a large server farm may require a large enough
block of addresses that it is either not feasible to allocate one
or it becomes economically desirable to use the addresses for other
purposes.</t>

<t>Another use case for this scenario involves a service provider that
is capable of acquiring a sufficient number of IPv4 addresses, and has
already done so.  However, the service provider also simply wishes to
start to offer an IPv6 service but without yet touching the server
farm (that is, without upgrading the server farm to IPv6).</t>

<t>One option available in such a situation is to move those servers
and their clients to IPv6.  However, moving to IPv6 involves not just the
cost of the IPv6 connectivity, but the cost of moving the application
itself from IPv4 to IPv6.  So, in this case, the server farm is IPv4-only,
there is an increasing cost for IPv4 connectivity, and there is an
expensive bill for moving server infrastructure to IPv6.
What can be done?</t>

<t>If the clients are IPv4-only as well, the problem is a hard one.
This issue is dealt with in more depth in
<xref target="scenario-v6onlyservers"/>.  However, there are important
cases where large sets of clients are IPv6-capable.  In these cases, it
is possible to place the server farm in private IPv4 space and arrange
some of the gateway service from IPv6 to IPv4 to reach the servers.  This
is shown in Figure 8.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
                                  +----+
IPv6 host(s)-------(Internet)-----+ GW +------Private IPv4 servers
                                  +----+

<---------public v6--------------->NAT<------private v4---------->

       Figure 8: Reaching Servers in Private IPv4 Space
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>One approach to implement this is to use NAT64 to translate IPv6
into private IPv4 addresses.  The private IPv4 addresses are mapped
into IPv6 addresses within one or more known prefixes.  The GW at the edge of
the server farm is aware of the mapping, as is the Domain Name System (DNS).
AAAA records for
each server name are given an IPv6 address that corresponds to the
mapped private IPv4 address.  Thus, each privately addressed IPv4
server is given a public IPv6 presentation.  No Application Level Gateway
for DNS (DNS-ALG) is needed in this case,
contrary to what NAT-PT would require, for instance.</t>

<t>This is very similar to the <xref target="scenario-simpleops"/>
scenario where
we typically think of a small site with IPv6 needing to reach the
public IPv4 Internet.  The difference here is that we assume not a
small IPv6 site, but the whole of the IPv6 Internet needing to reach a
small IPv4 site.  This example was driven by the enterprise network
with IPv4 servers, but could be scaled down to the individual
subscriber home level as well.  Here, the same technique could be used
to, say, access an IPv4 webcam in the home from the IPv6 Internet.  All
that is needed is the ability to update AAAA records appropriately, an
IPv6 client (which could use Teredo <xref target="RFC4380"/> or some
other method to obtain IPv6 reachability), and the NAT64 mechanism.  In
this sense, this method looks much like a "NAT/firewall bypass"
function.</t>

<t>An argument could be made that since the host is likely dual-stack,
existing port-mapping services or NAT traversal techniques could be
used to reach the private space instead of IPv6.  This would have to be
done anyway if the hosts are not all IPv6-capable or connected.
However, in cases where the hosts are all IPv6-capable, the alternative
techniques force
additional limitations on the use of port numbers.  In the case of
IPv6-to-IPv4 translation, the full port space would be available for each
server, even in the private space.</t>

<t>It is recommended that the IETF develop tools to address this
scenario.  These tools need to allow existing IPv4 servers to operate
unchanged.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="scenario-v6onlyservers" title="Reaching IPv6-Only Servers">

<t>This scenario is predicted to become increasingly important as IPv4
global connectivity sufficient for supporting server-oriented content
becomes significantly more difficult to obtain than global IPv6
connectivity.  Historically, the expectation has been that for
connectivity to IPv6-only devices, devices would either need to be
IPv6-connected, or dual-stack with the ability to set up an
IPv6-over-IPv4 tunnel in order to access the IPv6 Internet.  Many
"modern" device
stacks have this capability, and for them this scenario does not
present a problem as long as a suitable gateway to terminate the
tunnel and route the IPv6 packets is available.  But, for the server
operator, it may be a difficult proposition to leave all IPv4-only
devices without reachability.  Thus, if a solution for IPv4-only
devices to reach IPv6-only servers were realizable, the benefits would
be clear.  Not only could servers move directly to IPv6 without
trudging through a difficult dual-stack period, but they could do so
without risk of losing connectivity with the IPv4-only Internet. </t>

<t>Unfortunately, realizing this goal is complicated by the fact that IPv4 to IPv6 is
considered "hard" since of course IPv6 has a much larger address
space than IPv4.  Thus, representing 128 bits in 32&nbsp;bits is not possible, barring
the use of techniques similar to NAT64, which uses IPv6 addresses to
represent IPv4 addresses as well.</t>

<t>The main questions regarding this scenario are about timing and
priority.  While the expectation that this scenario may be of
importance one day is readily acceptable, at the time of this writing,
there are few or no IPv6-only servers of importance (beyond some
contrived cases) that the authors are aware of.  The difficulty of
making a decision about this case is that, quite possibly, when
there is sufficient pressure on IPv4 such that we see IPv6-only servers,
the vast majority of hosts will either have IPv6 connectivity or
the ability to tunnel IPv6 over IPv4 in one way or another.</t>

<t>This discussion makes assumptions about what a "server" is as well.
For the majority of applications seen on the IPv4 Internet to date,
this distinction has been more or less clear.  This clarity is
perhaps in no small part due to the overhead today in creating a
truly end-to-end application in the face of the fragmented
addressing and reachability brought on by the various NATs and
firewalls employed today.  However, current notions of a
"server" are beginning to shift, as we see more and
more pressure to connect people to one another in an
end-to-end fashion -- with peer-to-peer techniques, for instance --
rather than simply content server to client.  Thus, if we consider
an "IPv6-only server" as what we classically consider an
"IPv4 server" today, there may not be a lot of demand for this
in the near future.  However, with a more distributed
model of the Internet in mind, there may be more
opportunities to employ IPv6-only "servers" that we would
normally extrapolate from based on past experience with
applications.</t>

<t>It is recommended that the IETF address this scenario, though perhaps
with a slightly lower priority than the others.  In any case, when
new tools are developed to support this, it should be obvious that we
cannot assume any support for updating legacy IPv4 
hosts in order to reach the IPv6-only servers.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t>Security aspects of the individual solutions are discussed in more
depth elsewhere, for instance in
<xref target="DUAL-STACK-LITE"/>,
<xref target="RFC6144"/>,
<xref target="RFC6147"/>,
<xref target="RFC6145"/>,
<xref target="RFC6146"/>,
<xref target="NAT-PT"/>, and
<xref target="RFC4966"/>.  This document highlights just three issues:

<list style="symbols">

<t>Any type of translation may have an impact on how certain protocols
can pass through.  For example, IPsec needs support for NAT traversal,
and the proliferation of NATs implies an even higher reliance on these
mechanisms.  It may also require additional support for new types of
translation.</t>

<t>Some solutions have a need to modify results obtained from
DNS.  This may have an impact on DNS security, as discussed in
<xref target="RFC4966"/>.  Minimization or even elimination of such
problems is essential, as discussed in
<xref target="RFC6147"/>.</t>

<t>Tunneling solutions have their own security issues, for instance
the need to secure tunnel endpoint discovery or to avoid opening up
denial-of-service or reflection vulnerabilities <xref target="RFC6169"/>.</t>

</list></t>

</section>

<section anchor="conc" title="Conclusions">

<t>The authors believe that the scenarios outlined in this document
are among the top of the list of those that should be addressed by
the IETF community in short order.  For each scenario, there are
clearly different solution approaches with implementation, operations,
and deployment tradeoffs.  Further, some approaches rely on existing or
well-understood technology, while some require new protocols and
changes to established network architecture.  It is essential that these
tradeoffs be considered, understood by the community at large, and in
the end well-documented as part of the solution design. </t>

<t>After writing the initial version of this document, the Softwire working group was rechartered
to address the <xref target="scenario-outofnet10"/> scenario with a
combination of existing tools (tunneling, IPv4 NATs) and some minor
new ones (DHCP options)
<xref target="DUAL-STACK-LITE"/>.  Similarly, the Behave working group was rechartered
to address scenarios from
Sections <xref target="scenario-simpleops" format="counter" />,
<xref target="scenario-net10servers" format="counter" />, and
<xref target="scenario-v6onlyservers" format="counter" />.
At the time this document is being published, proposals to address
scenarios from <xref target="scenario-outofv4"/>
are still under consideration for new IETF work items.</t>

<t>This document set out to list scenarios that are important for the
Internet community.  While it introduces some design elements in order
to understand and discuss tradeoffs, it does not list detailed
requirements.  In large part, the authors believe that exhaustive and
detailed requirements would not be helpful at the expense of embarking
on solutions, given our current state of affairs.  We do not expect any
of the solutions to be perfect when measured from all vantage
points.  When looking for opportunities to deploy IPv6, reaching too
far for perfection could result in losing these opportunities if we are
not attentive.  Our goal with this document is to support the development of
tools to help minimize the tangible problems that we are experiencing
now, as well as those problems that we can best anticipate down the road, in
hopes of steering the Internet on its best course from here.
</t>

</section>

</middle> 
<back>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor='RFC1918'>
<front>
<title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>
<author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Yakov Rekhter'>
<organization>Cisco systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134-1706</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 914 528 0090</phone>
<facsimile>+1 408 526 4952</facsimile>
<email>yakov@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Moskowitz' fullname='Robert G. Moskowitz'>
<organization>Chrysler Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>25999 Lawrence Ave</street>
<city>Center Line</city>
<region>MI</region>
<code>48015</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 810 758 8212</phone>
<facsimile>+1 810 758 8173</facsimile>
<email>rgm3@is.chrysler.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='Daniel Karrenberg'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>Daniel.Karrenberg@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='de Groot' fullname='Geert Jan de Groot'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>GeertJan.deGroot@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Lear' fullname='Eliot Lear'>
<organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2011 N. Shoreline Blvd.</street>
<street>Mail Stop 15-730</street>
<city>Mountain View</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94043-1389</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 960 1980</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 961 9584</facsimile>
<email>lear@sgi.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1996' month='February' /></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='5' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1918' />
<format type='TXT' octets='22270'
target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1918.txt' />
</reference>

  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4213.xml"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2766.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4380.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4925.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4966.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6052.xml"?>

<reference anchor='NAT-PT'>
<front>
<title>A Comparison of Proposals to Replace NAT-PT</title>
<author initials='D' surname='Wing' fullname='Dan Wing'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Ward' fullname='David Ward'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Durand' fullname='Alain  Durand'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='September' year='2008' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='DUAL-STACK-LITE'>
<front>
<title>Dual-Stack Lite Broadband Deployments Following IPv4 Exhaustion</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Durand' fullname='Alain Durand'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Droms' fullname='Ralph Droms'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Woodyatt' fullname='James Woodyatt'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='May' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6144'>
<front>
<title>Framework for IPv4/IPv6 Translation</title>
<author initials='F' surname='Baker' fullname='Fred Baker'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='X' surname='Li' fullname='Xing Li'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Bao' fullname='Congxiao Bao'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Yin' fullname='Kevin Yin'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6144'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6145'>
<front>
<title>IP/ICMP Translation Algorithm</title>
<author initials='X' surname='Li' fullname='Xing Li'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Bao' fullname='Congxiao Bao'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='F' surname='Baker' fullname='Fred Baker'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6145' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6146'>
<front>
<title>Stateful NAT64: Network Address and Protocol Translation from IPv6
Clients to IPv4 Servers</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='P' surname='Matthews' fullname='Philip Matthews'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='van Beijnum' fullname='Iljitsch van Beijnum'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6146' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6147'>
<front>
<title>DNS64: DNS Extensions for Network Address Translation from IPv6 Clients
to IPv4 Servers</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Sullivan' fullname='Andrew Sullivan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='P' surname='Matthews' fullname='Philip Matthews'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='van Beijnum' fullname='Iljitsch van Beijnum'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6147' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='INTAREA-TUNNELS'>
<front>
<title>Tunnels in the Internet Architecture</title>
<author initials='J' surname='Touch' fullname='Joseph Touch'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Townsley' fullname='Mark Townsley'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2010' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='v6OPS-APBP'>
<front>
<title>A Scalable IPv4-IPv6 Transition Architecture Need for an
Address-Port-Borrowing-Protocol (APBP)</title>
<author initials='R' surname='Despres' fullname='Remi Despres'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2008' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='HUSTON-IPv4'>
<front>
<title>IPv4 Address Report</title>
<author initials='G' surname='Huston' fullname='Geoff Huston'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' year='2010' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='available at' value='http://www.potaroo.net' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='NISHITANI-CGN'>
<front>
<title>Common Requirements for IP Address Sharing Schemes</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Perreault' fullname='Simon Perreault'
role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='Yamagata' fullname='Ikuhei Yamagata'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Miyakawa' fullname='Shin Miyakawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Nakagawa' fullname='Akira Nakagawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Ashida' fullname='Hiroyuki Ashida'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='ISP-SHARED-ADDR'>
<front>
<title>ISP Shared Address</title>
<author initials='I' surname='Yamagata' fullname='Ikuhei Yamagata'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Miyakawa' fullname='Shin Miyakawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Nakagawa' fullname='Akira Nakagawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Yamaguchi' fullname='Jiro Yamaguchi'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Ashida' fullname='Hiroyuki Ashida'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='September' year='2010' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='IPv4-SPACE-ISSUES'>
<front>
<title>Issues Associated with Designating Additional Private IPv4 Address Space</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Azinger' fullname='Marla Azinger'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='L' surname='Vegoda' fullname='Leo Vegoda'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='January' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6169'>
<front>
<title>Security Concerns with IP Tunneling</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Krishnan' fullname='Suresh Krishnan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Hoagland' fullname='James Hoagland'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6169' />
<format type='TXT'/>
</reference>

</references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

<t>Discussions with a number of people including Dave Thaler, Thomas
Narten, Marcelo Bagnulo, Fred Baker, Remi Despres, Lorenzo Colitti, Dan
Wing, and Brian Carpenter, and feedback during the Internet Area open
meeting at IETF 72, were essential to the creation of the content in
this document.</t>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
