<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

]>
<rfc submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" number="6843"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>



  <front>
    <title abbrev="RTCP XR Delay">RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended Report
    (XR) Block for Delay Metric Reporting</title>

    <author fullname="Alan Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
      <organization abbrev="Telchemy">Telchemy Incorporated</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2905 Premiere Parkway, Suite 280</street>

          <city>Duluth</city>

          <region>GA</region>

          <code>30097</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>alan.d.clark@telchemy.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kevin Gross" initials="K." surname="Gross">
      <organization>AVA Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <email>kevin.gross@avanw.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2013" />

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure Area</area>

    <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Working Group</workgroup>


    <keyword>Real Time Control Protocol</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines an RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended Report
      (XR) block that allows the reporting of delay metrics for use in a range
      of Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP) applications.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <section title="Packet Delay Metrics Block">
        <t>This document defines a new block type to augment those defined in
        [RFC3611] for use in a range of RTP applications. The new block type
        supports the reporting of the mean, minimum, and maximum values of the
        network round-trip delay between RTP interfaces in peer RTP end
        systems as measured, for example, using the RTCP method described in
        <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. It also supports reporting of the
        component of the round- trip delay internal to the local RTP
        system.</t>

        <t>The network metrics belong to the class of transport metrics
        defined in <xref target="RFC6792"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RTCP and RTCP XR Reports">
        <t>The use of RTCP for reporting is defined in <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref>. <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> defined an
        extensible structure for reporting using an RTCP Extended Report (XR).
        This document defines a new Extended Report block for use with <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref> and <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Performance Metrics Framework">
        <t>The Performance Metrics Framework <xref target="RFC6390"></xref>
        provides guidance on the definition and specification of performance
        metrics. The RTP Monitoring Architectures <xref
        target="RFC6792"></xref> provides guidelines for reporting block format
        using RTCP XR. The metrics block described in this document is in
        accordance with the guidelines in <xref target="RFC6390"></xref> and
        <xref target="RFC6792"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
        <t>These metrics are applicable to a range of RTP applications in
        which this report block would be useful, such as multimedia
        conferencing and streaming audio and video. Knowledge of the
        round-trip delay and delay characteristics can aid other receivers in
        sizing their receive buffers and selecting a playout delay. The same
        information is also valuable to network managers in troubleshooting
        network and user experience issues.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <section title="Standards Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Delay Block">
      <t>Metrics in this block report on packet delay in the stream arriving
      at the RTP system. The measurement of these metrics is made either at
      the receiving end of the RTP stream or at the sending end of the RTP
      stream. Instances of this metrics block refer by synchronization source
      (SSRC) to the separate auxiliary Measurement Information block <xref
      target="RFC6776"></xref>, which contains measurement periods (see <xref target="RFC6776" />, Section 4.2). This metrics block relies on the measurement period in the
      Measurement Information block indicating the span of the report and
      SHOULD be sent in the same compound RTCP packet as the Measurement
      Information block. If the measurement period is not received in the same
      compound RTCP packet as this metrics block, this metrics block MUST be
      discarded.</t>

      <section title="Report Block Structure">
        <t>Delay metrics block<figure title="Figure 1: Report Block Structure">
            <artwork>
       0               1               2               3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |    BT=16      | I |   resv.   |      block length = 6         |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                           SSRC of Source                      |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                  Mean Network Round-Trip Delay                |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                   Min Network Round-Trip Delay                |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                   Max Network Round-Trip Delay                |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |               End System Delay - Seconds (bit 0-31)           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |              End System Delay - Fraction (bit 0-31)           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>



      <section title="Definition of Fields in Delay Metrics Report Block">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Block type (BT): 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />A
            Delay Report Block is identified by the constant 16.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /><vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>



            <t hangText="Interval Metric flag (I): 2 bit"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />This field is used to indicate whether the delay
            metrics are Sampled, Interval or Cumulative metrics: <list>
                <t>I=10: Interval Duration - the reported value applies to the
                most recent measurement interval duration between successive
                metrics reports.</t>

                <t>I=11: Cumulative Duration - the reported value applies to
                the accumulation period characteristic of cumulative
                measurements.</t>

                <t>I=01: Sampled Value - the reported value is a sampled
                instantaneous value.</t>
              </list><vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved (resv): 6 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />These bits are reserved. They MUST be set to zero
            by senders and ignored by receivers (see <xref target="RFC6709" />, Section
            4.2).<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>



            <t hangText="block length: 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" /> The
            length of this report block in 32-bit words, minus one. For the
            delay block, the block length is equal to 6.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="SSRC of source: 32 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />As
            defined in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Mean Network Round-Trip Delay: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The Mean Network Round-Trip Delay is the mean
            value of the RTP-to-RTP interface round-trip delay over the
            measurement period, expressed in units of 1/65536 seconds. This value is typically

     determined using "the NTP timestamp field" in the RTCP sender report

     (SR) and "the last SR (LSR) field","delay since last SR (DLSR) field"

     in the RTCP receiver report (RR) (see <xref target="RFC3550" />, Section 6.4.1 and Figure 2).      
     It

     also can be determined using "the NTP timestamp field" in the RTCP

     Receiver Reference Time Report Block and "last RR (LRR) field",

     "delay since last RR (DLRR) field" in the DLRR Report Block (see

     <xref target="RFC3611" />, Section 4.5). <vspace blankLines="1" /> If only one measurement of
            Round-Trip Delay is available for the time span of the report
            (i.e., the measurement period) (whether Interval or Cumulative),
            this single value SHOULD be reported as the mean value.<vspace
            blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable, the value of
            this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be reported.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Min Network Round-Trip Delay: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The Min Network Round Trip Delay is the minimum
            value of the RTP-to-RTP interface round-trip delay over the
            measurement period, expressed in units of 1/65536 seconds. This
            value is typically determined using the NTP timestamp field in the
            RTCP SR and LSR field and DLSR field in the RTCP RR. It also can
            be determined using the NTP timestamp field in the RTCP Receiver
            Reference Time Report Block and LRR field and DLRR field in the
            DLRR Report Block. <vspace blankLines="1" /> If only one
            measurement of Round Trip Delay is available for the time span of
            the report (i.e., the measurement period) (whether Interval or
            Cumulative), this single value SHOULD be reported as the minimum
            value.<vspace blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable,
            the value of this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be
            reported.</t>

            <t hangText="Max Network Round-Trip Delay: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The Max Network Round-Trip Delay is the maximum
            value of the RTP-to-RTP interface round-trip delay over the
            measurement period, expressed in units of 1/65536 seconds. This
            value is typically determined using the NTP timestamp field in the
            RTCP SR and LSR field and DLSR field in the RTCP RR. It also can
            be determined using the NTP timestamp field in the RTCP Receiver
            Reference Time Report Block and LRR field and DLRR field in the
            DLRR Report Block. <vspace blankLines="1" /> If only one
            measurement of Round-Trip Delay is available for the time span of
            the report (i.e.,the measurement period) (whether Interval or
            Cumulative), this single value SHOULD be reported as the maximum
            value.<vspace blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable,
            the value of this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be
            reported.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="End System Delay: 64 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The End System Delay is the internal round-trip
            delay within the reporting endpoint, calculated using the nominal
            value of the jitter buffer delay plus the accumulation/encoding
            and decoding/playout delay associated with the codec being used.
            The value of this field is represented using a 64-bit NTP-format
            timestamp as defined in <xref target="RFC5905"></xref>, which is
            a 64-bit unsigned fixed-point number with the integer part in the
            first 32 bits and the fractional part in the last 32 bits. <vspace
            blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable, the value of
            this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be reported.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SDP Signaling">
      <t><xref target="RFC3611" /> defines the use of SDP (Session Description Protocol) <xref
      target="RFC4566"></xref> for signaling the use of XR blocks. XR blocks
      MAY be used without prior signaling.</t>

      <section title="SDP rtcp-xr-attrib Attribute Extension">
        <t>This section augments the SDP <xref target="RFC4566"></xref>
        attribute "rtcp-xr" defined in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> by
        providing an additional value of "xr-format" to signal the use of the
        report block defined in this document.<figure>
            <artwork>
xr-format =/ xr-delay-block
   
xr-delay-block ="delay"
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Offer/Answer Usage">
        <t>When SDP is used in offer/answer context, the SDP Offer/Answer
        usage defined in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> applies.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>New block types for RTCP XR are subject to IANA registration. For
      general guidelines on IANA considerations for RTCP XR, refer to <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="New RTCP XR Block Type Value">
        <t>This document assigns the block type value 16 in the IANA "RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR) Block Type Registry" to the "Delay Metrics Block".</t>

      </section>

      <section title="New RTCP XR SDP Parameter">
        <t>This document also registers a new parameter "delay" in the "RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR) Session Description Protocol (SDP) Parameters" registry.</t>


      </section>

      <section title="Contact Information for Registrations">

        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
   The contact information for the registrations is:

   Qin Wu (sunseawq@huawei.com)
   Huawei
   101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District
   Nanjing, Jiangsu  210012
   China
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>It is believed that this proposed RTCP XR report block introduces no
      new security considerations beyond those described in <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>. This block does not provide per-packet
      statistics, so the risk to confidentiality documented in Section 7,
      paragraph 3, of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> does not apply.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>Geoff Hunt wrote the initial version of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors gratefully acknowledge the comments and contributions
      made by Bruce Adams, Philip Arden, Amit Arora, Bob Biskner, Kevin
      Connor, Claus Dahm, Randy Ethier, Roni Even, Jim Frauenthal, Albert
      Higashi, Tom Hock, Shane Holthaus, Paul Jones, Rajesh Kumar, Keith
      Lantz, Mohamed Mostafa, Amy Pendleton, Colin Perkins, Mike Ramalho, Ravi
      Raviraj, Albrecht Schwarz, Tom Taylor, and Hideaki Yamada, Jing
      Zhao, Kevin Gross, Colin Perkins, Charles Eckel, Glen Zorn, Shida
      Schubert, Barry Leiba, Sean Turner, Robert Sparks, Benoit Claise, and Stephen
      Farrell.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
  


<reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17970' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='RFC3550'>

<front>
<title>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Casner' fullname='S. Casner'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Frederick' fullname='R. Frederick'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='V. Jacobson'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This memorandum describes RTP, the real-time transport protocol.  RTP provides end-to-end network transport functions suitable for applications transmitting real-time data, such as audio, video or simulation data, over multicast or unicast network services.  RTP does not address resource reservation and does not guarantee quality-of- service for real-time services.  The data transport is augmented by a control protocol (RTCP) to allow monitoring of the data delivery in a manner scalable to large multicast networks, and to provide minimal control and identification functionality.  RTP and RTCP are designed to be independent of the underlying transport and network layers.  The protocol supports the use of RTP-level translators and mixers.  Most of the text in this memorandum is identical to RFC 1889 which it obsoletes.  There are no changes in the packet formats on the wire, only changes to the rules and algorithms governing how the protocol is used.  The biggest change is an enhancement to the scalable timer algorithm for calculating when to send RTCP packets in order to minimize transmission in excess of the intended rate when many participants join a session simultaneously. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='64' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3550' />
<format type='TXT' octets='259985' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.txt' />
<format type='PS' octets='630740' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.ps' />
<format type='PDF' octets='504117' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.pdf' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC3611'>

<front>
<title>RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Friedman' fullname='T. Friedman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Caceres' fullname='R. Caceres'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='A. Clark'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines the Extended Report (XR) packet type for the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP), and defines how the use of XR packets can be signaled by an application if it employs the Session Description Protocol (SDP).  XR packets are composed of report blocks, and seven block types are defined here.  The purpose of the extended reporting format is to convey information that supplements the six statistics that are contained in the report blocks used by RTCP's Sender Report (SR) and Receiver Report (RR) packets.  Some applications, such as multicast inference of network characteristics (MINC) or voice over IP (VoIP) monitoring, require other and more detailed statistics.  In addition to the block types defined here, additional block types may be defined in the future by adhering to the framework that this document provides.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3611' />
<format type='TXT' octets='126736' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3611.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC4566'>

<front>
<title>SDP: Session Description Protocol</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='M. Handley'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='V. Jacobson'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Perkins' fullname='C. Perkins'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo defines the Session Description Protocol (SDP).  SDP is intended for describing multimedia sessions for the purposes of session announcement, session invitation, and other forms of multimedia session initiation. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4566' />
<format type='TXT' octets='108820' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4566.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC5905'>

<front>
<title>Network Time Protocol Version 4: Protocol and Algorithms Specification</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Mills' fullname='D. Mills'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Martin' fullname='J. Martin'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Burbank' fullname='J. Burbank'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Kasch' fullname='W. Kasch'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is widely used to synchronize computer clocks in the Internet.  This document describes NTP version 4 (NTPv4), which is backwards compatible with NTP version 3 (NTPv3), described in RFC 1305, as well as previous versions of the protocol.  NTPv4 includes a modified protocol header to accommodate the Internet Protocol version 6 address family.  NTPv4 includes fundamental improvements in the mitigation and discipline algorithms that extend the potential accuracy to the tens of microseconds with modern workstations and fast LANs.  It includes a dynamic server discovery scheme, so that in many cases, specific server configuration is not required.  It corrects certain errors in the NTPv3 design and implementation and includes an optional extension mechanism. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5905' />
<format type='TXT' octets='241096' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5905.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC6709'>

<front>
<title>Design Considerations for Protocol Extensions</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Carpenter' fullname='B. Carpenter'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Aboba' fullname='B. Aboba'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Cheshire' fullname='S. Cheshire'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='September' />
<abstract>
<t>This document discusses architectural issues related to the extensibility of Internet protocols, with a focus on design considerations.  It is intended to assist designers of both base protocols and extensions.  Case studies are included.  A companion document, RFC 4775 (BCP 125), discusses procedures relating to the extensibility of IETF protocols.  This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6709' />
<format type='TXT' octets='103913' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6709.txt' />
</reference>



    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!--draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-22 updated to RFC 6792 -->


<reference anchor='RFC6792'>

<front>
<title>Guidelines for Use of the RTP Monitoring Framework</title>
<author initials='Q.' surname='Wu' fullname='Q. Wu'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Hunt' fullname='G. Hunt'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Arden' fullname='P. Arden'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo proposes an extensible Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP) monitoring framework for extending the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) with a new RTCP Extended Reports (XR) block type to report new metrics regarding media transmission or reception quality.  In this framework, a new XR block should contain a single metric or a small number of metrics relevant to a single parameter of interest or concern, rather than containing a number of metrics that attempt to provide full coverage of all those parameters of concern to a specific application.  Applications may then "mix and match" to create a set of blocks that cover their set of concerns.  Where possible, a specific block should be designed to be reusable across more than one application, for example, for all of voice, streaming audio, and video.  This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6792' />
<format type='TXT' octets='42473' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6792.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC6390'>

<front>
<title>Guidelines for Considering New Performance Metric Development</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='A. Clark'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Claise' fullname='B. Claise'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes a framework and a process for developing Performance Metrics of protocols and applications transported over IETF-specified protocols.  These metrics can be used to characterize traffic on live networks and services.  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='170' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6390' />
<format type='TXT' octets='49930' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6390.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC6776'>

<front>
<title>Measurement Identity and Information Reporting Using a Source Description (SDES) Item and an RTCP Extended Report (XR) Block</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='A. Clark'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='Q.' surname='Wu' fullname='Q. Wu'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines an RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Source Description (SDES) item and an RTCP Extended Report (XR) block carrying parameters that identify and describe a measurement period to which one or more other RTCP XR blocks may refer. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6776' />
<format type='TXT' octets='17259' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6776.txt' />
</reference>



</references>
  </back>
</rfc>
