<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6245" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<front>

<title abbrev="GRE Key Ext. for MIP4">Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) Key Extension for Mobile IPv4</title>

<author initials="P" surname="Yegani" fullname="Parviz Yegani">
    <organization abbrev="Juniper Networks">Juniper Networks</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>1194 North Mathilda Ave.</street>
        <city>Sunnyvale</city>
        <region>California</region>
        <code>94089</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1 408-759-1973</phone>
      <email>pyegani@juniper.net</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials="K" surname="Leung" fullname="Kent Leung">
    <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems Incorporated</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>California</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1 408 526 5030</phone>
      <email>kleung@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
</author>
        
<author initials="A" surname="Lior" fullname="Avi Lior">
    <organization abbrev="Bridgewater Systems">Bridgewater Systems Corporation</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>303 Terry Fox Drive</street>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <region>Ontario</region>
        <code>K2K 3J1</code>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1 613-591-6655</phone>
      <email>avi@bridgewatersystems.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="K.C" surname="Chowdhury" fullname="Kuntal Chowdhury">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems Incorporated</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>California</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>kchowdhu@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

<author initials="J.N" surname="Navali" fullname="Jay Navali">
       <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems Incorporated</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>California</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>jnavali@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>
    
<date month="May" year="2011"/>

<abstract>

<t>The Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) specification contains a Key field, which MAY contain a 
value that is used to identify a particular GRE data stream. This 
specification defines a new Mobile IP extension that is used to 
exchange the value to be used in the GRE Key field. This extension 
further allows the Mobility Agents to set up the necessary protocol 
interfaces prior to receiving the mobile node traffic. 

The new extension 
allows a Foreign Agent to request GRE tunneling without 
disturbing the Home Agent behavior specified for Mobile IPv4. 
GRE tunneling with the Key field allows the operators to have 
home networks that consist of multiple Virtual Private Networks (VPNs), 
which may have overlapping home addresses.  When the tuple &lt;Care of 
Address, Home Address, and Home Agent Address&gt; is the same across 
multiple subscriber sessions, GRE tunneling will provide a means for 
the Foreign Agent and Home Agent to identify data streams for the individual sessions 
based on the GRE key.  In the absence of this key identifier, the data 
streams cannot be distinguished from each other -- a significant 
drawback when using IP-in-IP tunneling.</t>
     
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>This document specifies a new extension for use by a Foreign Agent (FA)
operating Mobile IP for IPv4.  The new extension allows a 
Foreign Agent to request Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE)
<xref target="RFC2784"/> tunneling without disturbing the 
Home Agent (HA) behavior specified for Mobile IPv4 <xref target="RFC5944"/>. 
This extension contains the GRE key <xref target="RFC2890"/> 
required for establishing a GRE tunnel between the FA and the HA.</t>

<t>GRE tunneling with the Key field allows the operators to have 
home networks that consist of multiple Virtual Private Networks (VPNs), 
which may have overlapping home addresses.  When the tuple 
&lt;Care of Address, Home Address, and Home Agent Address&gt; is the same 
across multiple subscriber sessions, GRE tunneling will provide a 
means for the FA and the HA to identify data streams for the individual 
sessions based on the GRE key.  In the absence of this key identifier, 
the data streams cannot be distinguished from each other -- a significant 
drawback when using IP-in-IP tunneling.</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", 
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.  
Other terminology is used as already defined in 
<xref target="RFC5944"/>.</t>
</section>


<section title="GRE Key Extension">

<t>The format of the GRE Key Extension conforms to the extension format
specified for Mobile IPv4 <xref target="RFC5944"/>.
This extension option is used by
the Foreign Agent to supply GRE key and other necessary information to
the Home Agent to establish a GRE tunnel between the FA and the HA.</t>
</section>

<section title="Operation and Use of the GRE Key Extension">

<section title="Foreign Agent Requirements for GRE Tunneling Support">

<t>The FA MUST support IP-in-IP tunneling of datagrams for Mobile IPv4 
<xref target="RFC5944"/>.  The FA may support GRE tunneling that can be 
used, for example, to allow for overlapping private home IP addresses 
(Section&nbsp;4.2.2.5 of <xref target="X.S0011-E"/>).

 If the FA is capable of supporting GRE encapsulation, it 
should set the 'G' (GRE encapsulation) bit in the Flags field in the Agent Advertisement 
message sent to the Mobile Node (MN) during the Mobile IP session establishment.</t>

<t>If the MN does not set the 'G' bit, the FA MAY fall back to using 
IP-in-IP encapsulation for the session per <xref target="RFC5944"/>.</t>

<t>If the MN does not set the 'G' bit and does not set the 'D' (Decapsulation by mobile node)
bit (i.e.,
the mobile node does not request GRE tunneling and is not using
a co-located care-of address), and the local policy allows 
the FA to override the 'G' bit setting received from the MN, the FA MUST 
include the GRE Key Extension as defined in this memo in the Registration 
Request (RRQ) that it propagates to the HA.  The presence of this extension is
a request for GRE encapsulation that takes precedence over the setting of 
the 'G' bit in the Registration Request.  The FA MUST NOT modify the 'G' 
bit in the Registration Request because it is protected by the Mobile-Home 
Authentication extension.
</t>

<t>If the FA does not support GRE encapsulation, the FA MUST reset the 
'G' bit in the Agent Advertisement message.  In this case, if the MN 
sets the 'G' bit in the Registration Request message, the FA returns a 
Registration Reply (RRP) message to the MN with code 'requested encapsulation 
unavailable' (72) per <xref target="RFC5944"/>.</t>

<t>If the FA allows GRE encapsulation, and either the MN requested GRE
encapsulation or local policy dictates using GRE encapsulation for
the session, and the 'D' bit is not set (i.e., the mobile node is not using
a co-located care-of address), the FA MUST include the GRE Key in the
GRE Key Extension in all Mobile IP Registration Requests (including initial,
renewal, and de-registration requests) before forwarding the request to the
HA.  The FA may include a GRE key of value zero in the GRE Key
Extension to signal that the HA assigns GRE keys in both directions.
The GRE key assignment in the FA and the HA is outside the scope of
this memo.</t>


<t>The GRE Key Extension SHALL follow the format defined in 
<xref target="RFC5944"/>.  This extension SHALL be added after the 
MN-HA and MN-FA Challenge and MN-AAA (Mobile Node - Authentication,
Authorization, and Accounting) extensions (if any) and before
the FA-HA Auth extension (if any). </t>

</section>

<section title="Home Agent Requirements for GRE Tunneling Support">

<t>The HA MUST follow the procedures specified in <xref target="RFC5944"/> in 
processing this extension in Registration Request messages.</t>

<t>If the HA receives the GRE Key Extension in a Registration Request
and does not recognize this non-skippable extension, it MUST
silently discard the message.  The HA MUST use other alternative
forms of encapsulation (e.g., IP-in-IP tunneling), when requested
by the mobile node per <xref target="RFC5944"/>.</t>

<t>If the HA receives the GRE Key Extension in a Registration Request 
and recognizes the GRE Key Extension but is not configured to support 
GRE encapsulation, it MUST send an RRP with code 'requested 
encapsulation unavailable (139)' <xref target="RFC3024"/>.</t>

<t>If the HA receives a Registration Request with a GRE Key Extension 
but without the 'G' bit set, the HA SHOULD treat this as if the 'G' bit is 
set in the Registration Request; i.e., the presence of a GRE Key Extension 
indicates a request for GRE encapsulation.</t>

<t>If the HA receives the GRE Key Extension in a Registration Request,
and it recognizes the GRE Key Extension as well as supports GRE 
encapsulation, the following procedures should apply:

<list style="symbols">
<t>The HA SHOULD accept the RRQ and send an RRP with code 
'registration accepted (0)'.</t>

<t>The HA MUST assign a GRE key and include the GRE Key Extension in
the RRP before sending it to the FA.</t>

<t>The HA MUST include the GRE Key Extension in all RRPs in response
to any RRQ that included the GRE Key Extension, when a GRE key is
available for the registration.</t></list></t>

<t>
If the HA receives the GRE Key Extension in the initial Registration Request
and recognizes the GRE Key Extension carrying a GRE key value of zero, 
it SHOULD accept the RRQ and send an RRP with code
'registration accepted (0)', and the following procedures apply:

<list style="symbols">
<t>The HA MUST assign GRE keys for both directions and include these
keys in the GRE Key Extension in the RRP before sending it to the FA.</t>

<t>The HA MUST include the GRE Key Extension in the RRP in response
to the initial RRQ that included the GRE Key Extension, when a
GRE key is available for the registration. </t></list></t>

</section>

<section title="Mobile Node Requirements for GRE Tunneling Support">

<t>If the MN is capable of supporting GRE encapsulation, it SHOULD set 
the 'G' bit in the Flags field in the Registration Request per 
<xref target="RFC5944"/>.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="GRE Key Extension and Tunneling Procedures">

<t>GRE tunneling support for Mobile IP will permit asymmetric GRE keying;
i.e., the FA assigns a GRE key for use in encapsulated traffic, and the 
HA can assign its own GRE key. Once the GRE keys have been exchanged, 
the FA uses the HA-assigned key in the encapsulating GRE header for 
reverse tunneling, and the HA uses the FA-assigned key in the 
encapsulating GRE header. </t>

<t>The format of the GRE Key Extension is as shown below. </t>

<t>The GRE Key Extension MAY be included in Registration Requests or Registration
Replies <xref target="RFC5944"/>. The GRE Key Extension is used to inform the 
recipient of the Mobile IP request of the value to be used in the GRE
Key field. </t>

<figure anchor="Figure 1" title="GRE Key Extension">
<artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |     Type      |   Sub-Type    |            Length             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                        Key Identifier                         |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>
      Type
      <list style="empty">
        <t>
         48 - An 8-bit identifier of the GRE Key Extension type (non-skippable)
      </t>
      </list>
      </t>

        <t>
      Sub-Type
        <list style="empty">
        <t>
         0
        </t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>
      Length
        <list style="empty">
        <t>
         4
        </t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>
      Key Identifier  
        <list style="empty">
        <t>
         This is a four-octet value assigned during registration and 
         inserted in every GRE packet of the user traffic.
        </t>
        </list>
        </t>


</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>The GRE Key Extension defined in this memo is a Mobile IP extension as
defined in <xref target="RFC5944"/>. IANA has assigned a Type value (48) for this
extension from the non-skippable range (0-127).
</t>
<t>
The GRE Key Extension introduces a new sub-type numbering space, where the
value 0 has been assigned from the range 0 to 255.  Approval of new GRE
Key Extension sub-type values is to be made through Expert Review with
Specification Required.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>This specification does not introduce any new security 
considerations, beyond those described in <xref target="RFC5944"/>.
</t>

<t>
   Despite its name, the GRE Key Extension has little to do with
   security.  The word "Key" here is not used in the cryptographic
   sense of a shared secret that must be protected but rather in
   the sense of an "index" or demultiplexing value that can
   be used to distinguish packets belonging to a given flow within a GRE tunnel.

</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">

<t>Thanks to Jun Wang, Gopal Dommety, and Sri Gundavelli for their helpful
comments, offline discussions, and review of the initial draft version of this document.  Also, Pete McCann and Simon Mizikovsky provided valuable review comments.
</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?>
 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2784.xml'?>
 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2890.xml'?>
 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3024.xml'?>
 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5944.xml'?>

 <reference anchor="X.S0011-E" target="http://www.3gpp2.org/Public_html/specs/X.S0011-002-E_v1.0_091116.pdf">
 <front>
  <title>cdma2000 Wireless IP Network Standard: Simple IP and Mobile IP Access Services</title>
  <author fullname="3rd Generation Partnership Project 2">
   <organization>3rd Generation Partnership Project 2</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="November" year="2009"/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="3GPP2 X.S0011-002&nbhy;E" value="Version 1.0"/>
 </reference>

</references>

</back>
</rfc>
