<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC6180 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6180.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1918 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2460 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3056 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3056.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3068 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3068.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6724 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4380 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4380.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4942 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4942.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5569 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5569.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5969 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5969.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6092 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6092.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6144 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6144.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6146 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6169 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6169.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6264 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6264.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6269 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6269.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6333 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6333.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6343 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6343.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6540 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6540.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6586 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6586.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6598 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6598.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6732 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6732.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" number="6782" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Wireline Incremental IPv6">Wireline Incremental
    IPv6</title>

    <author fullname="Victor Kuarsingh" initials="V." role="editor"
            surname="Kuarsingh">
      <organization>Rogers Communications</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8200 Dixie Road</street>
          <city>Brampton</city>
          <region>Ontario</region>
          <code>L6T 0C1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>victor.kuarsingh@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.rogers.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lee Howard" initials="L." surname="Howard">
      <organization>Time Warner Cable</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13820 Sunrise Valley Drive</street>
          <city>Herndon</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20171</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>lee.howard@twcable.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.timewarnercable.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2012"/>

    <area>Ops Area</area>

    <workgroup>v6ops</workgroup>

    <keyword>transition</keyword>
    <keyword>IPv6 transition</keyword>
    <keyword>operator</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Operators worldwide are in various stages of preparing for or
      deploying IPv6 in their networks. These operators often face difficult
      challenges related to IPv6 introduction, along with those related to
      IPv4 run-out. Operators will need to meet the simultaneous needs of IPv6
      connectivity and continue support for IPv4 connectivity for legacy
      devices with a stagnant supply of IPv4 addresses. The IPv6 transition
      will take most networks from an IPv4-only environment to an
      IPv6-dominant environment with long transition periods varying by
      operator. This document helps provide a framework for wireline
      providers who are faced with the challenges of introducing IPv6
      along with meeting the legacy needs of IPv4 connectivity, utilizing
      well-defined and commercially available IPv6 transition technologies.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document sets out to help wireline operators in planning their
      IPv6 deployments while ensuring continued support for IPv6-incapable
      consumer devices and applications. This document identifies which
      technologies can be used incrementally to transition from IPv4-only
      to an IPv6-dominant environment with support for Dual Stack operation.
      The end state or goal for most operators will be IPv6-only,
      but the path to this
      final state will depend heavily on the amount of legacy equipment
      resident in end networks and management of long-tail IPv4-only content.
      Although no single plan will work for all operators, options listed
      herein provide a baseline that can be included in many plans.</t>

      <t>This document is intended for wireline environments that include cable,
      DSL, and/or fiber as the access method to the end consumer. This document
      attempts to follow the principles laid out in <xref target="RFC6180"/>,
      which provides
      guidance on using IPv6 transition mechanisms. This document will focus
      on technologies that enable and mature IPv6 within the operator's
      network, but it will also include a cursory view of IPv4 connectivity
      continuance. This document will focus on transition technologies that
      are readily available in off-the-shelf Customer Premises Equipment
      (CPE) devices and commercially available network equipment.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Operator Assumptions">
   <?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?> 
      <t>For the purposes of this document, the authors assume the following:

    <list style="symbols">
          <t>The operator is considering deploying IPv6 or is in the
          process of deploying IPv6.</t>

          <t>The operator has a legacy IPv4 subscriber base that will
          continue to exist for a period of time.</t>

          <t>The operator will want to minimize the level of disruption to
          the existing and new subscribers.</t>

          <t>The operator may also want to minimize the number of
          technologies and functions that are needed to mediate any given set
          of subscribers' flows (overall preference for native IP flows).</t>

          <t>The operator is able to run Dual Stack in its own core
          network and is able to transition its own services to support
          IPv6.</t>
        </list></t>
   <?rfc text-list-symbols="o*+-"?> 

      <t>Based on these assumptions, an operator will want to utilize
      technologies that minimize the need to tunnel, translate, or mediate
      flows to help optimize traffic flow and lower the cost impacts of
      transition technologies. Transition technology selections should be made
      to mediate the non-dominant IP family flows and allow native routing
      (IPv4 and/or IPv6) to forward the dominant traffic whenever possible.
      This allows the operator to minimize the cost of IPv6 transition
      technologies by minimizing the transition technology deployment
      size.</t>

      <t>An operator may also choose to prefer more IPv6-focused models where
      the use of transition technologies is based on an effort to enable IPv6
      at the base layer as soon as possible. Some operators may want to
      promote IPv6 early on in the deployment and have IPv6 traffic perform
      optimally from the outset. This desire would need to be weighed against
      the cost and support impacts of such a choice and the quality of
      experience offered to subscribers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Reasons and Considerations for a Phased Approach">
      <t>When faced with the challenges described in the introduction,
      operators may want to consider a phased approach when adding IPv6 to an
      existing subscriber base. A phased approach allows the operator to add
      in IPv6 while not ignoring legacy IPv4 connection requirements. Some of
      the main challenges the operator will face include the following:
     <?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
     <list style="symbols">
          <t>IPv4 exhaustion may occur long before all traffic is able to be
          delivered over IPv6, necessitating IPv4 address sharing.</t>

          <t>IPv6 will pose operational challenges, since some of the
          software is quite new and has had short run time in large production
          environments and organizations are also not acclimatized to
          supporting IPv6 as a service.</t>

          <t>Connectivity modes will move from IPv4-only to Dual Stack in
          the home, changing functional behaviors in the consumer network and
          increasing support requirements for the operator.</t>

          <t>Although IPv6 support on CPEs is a newer phenomenon, there is a
          strong push by operators and the industry as a whole to enable IPv6
          on devices. As demand grows, IPv6 enablement will no longer be
          optional but will be necessary on CPEs.
          Documents like <xref target="RFC6540"/> provide
          useful tools in the short term to help vendors and implementors
          understand what "IPv6 support" means.</t>
        </list></t>
   <?rfc text-list-symbols="o*+-"?>

      <t>These challenges will occur over a period of time, which means that
      the operator's plans need to address the ever-changing requirements of
      the network and subscriber demand. Although phases will be presented in
      this document, not all operators may need to enable each discrete phase.
      It is possible that characteristics in individual networks may allow
      certain operators to skip or jump to various phases.</t>

      <section title="Relevance of IPv6 and IPv4">
        <t>The delivery of high-quality unencumbered Internet service should
        be the primary goal for operators. With the imminent exhaustion of
        IPv4, IPv6 will offer the highest quality of experience in the long
        term. Even though the operator may be focused on IPv6 delivery, it
        should be aware that both IPv4 and IPv6 will play a role in the
        Internet experience during transition. The Internet is made of many
        interconnecting systems, networks, hardware, software, and content
        sources -- all of which will support IPv6 at different rates.</t>

        <t>Many subscribers use older operating systems and hardware that
        support IPv4-only operation. Internet subscribers don't buy IPv4 or
        IPv6 connections; they buy Internet connections, which demand the
        need to support both IPv4 and IPv6 for as long as the subscriber's
        home network demands such support. The operator may be able to
        leverage one or the other protocol to help bridge connectivity on the
        operator's network, but the home network will likely demand both IPv4
        and IPv6 for some time.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv4 Resource Challenges">
        <t>Since connectivity to IPv4-only endpoints and/or content will
        remain common, IPv4 resource challenges are of key concern to
        operators. The lack of new IPv4 addresses for additional devices means
        that meeting the growth in demand of IPv4 connections in some networks
        will require address sharing.</t>

        <t>Networks are growing at different rates, including those in emerging
        markets and established networks based on the proliferation of
        Internet-based services and devices. IPv4 address constraints will
        likely affect many, if not most, operators at some point, increasing
        the benefits of IPv6. IPv4 address exhaustion is a consideration when
        selecting technologies that rely on IPv4 to supply IPv6 services,
        such as 6rd (IPv6 Rapid Deployment on IPv4 Infrastructures) <xref
        target="RFC5969"/>. Additionally, if native Dual Stack is considered
        by the operator, challenges related to IPv4 address exhaustion remain a
        concern.</t>

        <t>Some operators may be able to reclaim small amounts of IPv4 addresses
        through addressing efficiencies in the network, although this will
        have few lasting benefits to the network and will not meet
        longer-term
        connectivity needs. Secondary markets for IPv4 addresses have also
        begun to arise, but it's not well understood how this will complement
        overall demand for Internet growth. Address transfers will also be
        subject to market prices and transfer rules governed by the Regional
        Registries.</t>

        <t>The lack of new global IPv4 address allocations will therefore
        force operators to support some form of IPv4 address sharing and may
        impact technological options for transition once the operator runs out
        of new IPv4 addresses for assignment.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 Introduction and Operational Maturity">
        <t>The introduction of IPv6 will require new operational practices.
        The IPv4 environment we have today was built over many years and
        matured by experience. Although many of these experiences are
        transferable from IPv4 to IPv6, new experience and practices specific
        to IPv6 will be needed.</t>

        <t>Engineering and operational staff will need to develop experience
        with IPv6. Inexperience may lead to early IPv6 deployment instability,
        and operators should consider this when selecting technologies for
        initial transition. Operators may not want to subject their mature
        IPv4 service to a "new IPv6" path initially while it may be going
        through growing pains. Dual Stack Lite (DS&nbhy;Lite)
        <xref target="RFC6333"/> and NAT64 <xref target="RFC6146"/> are both
        technologies that require IPv6 to support connectivity to IPv4
        endpoints or content over an IPv6-only access network.</t>

        <t>Further, some of these transition technologies are new and require
        refinement within running code. Deployment experience is required to
        expose bugs and stabilize software in production environments. Many
        supporting systems are also under development and have newly developed
        IPv6 functionality, including vendor implementations of DHCPv6,
        management tools, monitoring systems, diagnostic systems, and logging,
        along with other elements.</t>

        <t>Although the base technological capabilities exist to enable and
        run IPv6 in most environments, organizational experience is low. Until
        such time as each key technical member of an operator's organization
        can identify IPv6 and can understand its relevance to the IP service
        offering, how it operates, and how to troubleshoot it, the deployment
        needs to mature and may be subject to events that impact subscribers.
        This fact should not incline operators to delay their IPv6 deployment
        but should drive them to deploy IPv6 sooner, to gain much-needed
        experience before IPv6 is the only viable way to connect new hosts to
        the network.</t>

        <t>It should also be noted that although many transition technologies
        may be new, and some code related to access environments may be new,
        there is a large segment of the networking fabric that has had IPv6
        available for a long period of time and has had extended exposure in
        production. Operators may use this to their advantage by first
        enabling IPv6 in the core network and then working outward towards
        the subscriber edge.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Service Management">
        <t>Services are managed within most networks and are often based on
        the gleaning and monitoring of IPv4 addresses assigned to endpoints.
        Operators will need to address such management tools, troubleshooting
        methods, and storage facilities (such as databases) to deal with not
        only new address types containing 128-bit IPv6 addresses <xref target="RFC2460"/>
        but often both IPv4 and IPv6 at the same time. Examination of address
        types, and recording delegated prefixes along with single address
        assignments, will likely require additional development.</t>

        <t>With any Dual Stack service -- whether native, 6rd-based, DS-Lite,
        NAT64, or some other service -- two address families may need to be managed
        simultaneously to help provide the full Internet experience. This
        would indicate that IPv6 management is not just a simple add-in but
        needs to be well integrated into the service management
        infrastructure. In the early transition phases, it's quite likely that
        many systems will be missed, and that IPv6 services will go
        unmonitored and impairments will go undetected.</t>

        <t>These issues may be worthy of consideration when selecting technologies
        that require IPv6 as the base protocol to deliver IPv4 connectivity.
        Instability of the IPv6 service in such a case would impact IPv4
        services.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Suboptimal Operation of Transition Technologies">
        <t>Native delivery of IPv4 and IPv6 provides a solid foundation for
        delivery of Internet services to subscribers, since native IP paths are
        well understood and networks are often optimized to send such traffic
        efficiently. Transition technologies, however, may alter the normal
        path of traffic or reduce the path MTU, removing many network
        efficiencies built for native IP flows. Tunneling and translation
        devices may not be located on the most optimal path in line with the
        natural traffic flow (based on route computation) and therefore may
        increase latency. These paths may also introduce additional points of
        failure.</t>

        <t>Generally, the operator will want to deliver native IPv6 as soon as
        possible and utilize transition technologies only when required.
        Transition technologies may be used to provide continued access to
        IPv4 via tunneling and/or translation or may be used to deliver IPv6
        connectivity. The delivery of Internet or internal services should be
        considered by the operator, since supplying connections using a
        transition technology will reduce overall performance for the
        subscriber.</t>

        <t>When choosing between various transition technologies, operators
        should consider the benefits and drawbacks of each option. Some
        technologies, like Carrier-Grade NAT (CGN)/NAT444, utilize many
        existing addressing and management practices.
        Other options, such as DS-Lite and NAT64, remove
        the IPv4 addressing requirement to the subscriber premises device but
        require IPv6 to be operational and well supported.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Future IPv6 Network">
        <t>An operator should also be aware that longer-term plans may include
        IPv6-only operation in all or much of the network. The IPv6-only
        operation may be complemented by technologies such as NAT64 for
        long-tail IPv4 content reach. This longer-term view may be distant to
        some but should be considered when planning out networks, addressing,
        and services. The needs and costs of maintaining two IP stacks will
        eventually become burdensome, and simplification will be desirable.
        Operators should plan for this state and not make IPv6 inherently
        dependent on IPv4, as this would unnecessarily constrain the
        network.</t>

        <t>Other design considerations and guidelines for running an IPv6
        network should also be considered by the operator. Guidance on
        designing an IPv6 network can be found in <xref target="IPv6-DESIGN"/>
        and <xref target="IPv6-ICP-ASP-GUIDANCE"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IPv6 Transition Technology Analysis">
      <t>Operators should understand the main transition technologies for IPv6
      deployment and IPv4 run-out. This document provides a brief description
      of some of the mainstream and commercially available options.
      This analysis is focused on the applicability of technologies to deliver
      residential services and less focused on commercial access, wireless, or
      infrastructure support.</t>

      <t>This document focuses on those technologies that are
      commercially available and in deployment.</t>

      <section title="Automatic Tunneling Using 6to4 and Teredo">
        <t>Even when operators may not be actively deploying IPv6, automatic
        mechanisms exist on subscriber operating systems and CPE hardware.
        Such technologies include 6to4 <xref target="RFC3056"/>, which is most commonly used
        with anycast relays <xref target="RFC3068"/>. Teredo <xref target="RFC4380"/> is also used widely by
        many Internet hosts.</t>

        <t>Documents such as <xref target="RFC6343"/> have been written to help operators
        understand observed problems with 6to4 deployments and provide
        guidelines on how to improve their performance. An operator may want to
        provide local relays for 6to4 and/or Teredo to help improve the
        protocol's performance for ambient traffic utilizing these IPv6
        connectivity methods. Experiences such as those described in
        <xref target="COMCAST-IPv6-EXPERIENCES"/> show that local relays have
        proved beneficial to 6to4 protocol performance.</t>

        <t>Operators should also be aware of breakage cases for 6to4 if
        non-<xref target="RFC1918"/> addresses are used within CGN/NAT444 zones. Many
        off-the-shelf CPEs and operating systems may turn on 6to4 without a
        valid return path to the originating (local) host. This particular use
        case can occur if any space other than <xref target="RFC1918"/> is used, including
        Shared Address Space <xref target="RFC6598"/> or space registered to another
        organization (squat space). The operator can use
        6to4 Provider Managed Tunnels (6to4-PMT)
        <xref target="RFC6732"/> or attempt to block
        6to4 operation entirely by blocking the anycast ranges associated with
        <xref target="RFC3068"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Carrier-Grade NAT (NAT444)">
        <t>Carrier-Grade NAT (CGN), specifically as deployed in a NAT444
        scenario <xref target="CGN-REQS"/>, may prove beneficial for
        those operators who offer Dual Stack services to subscriber endpoints
        once they exhaust their pools of IPv4 addresses. CGNs, and address
        sharing overall, are known to cause certain challenges for the IPv4
        service <xref target="RFC6269"/> <xref target="NAT444-IMPACTS"/> but may be necessary,
        depending on how an operator has chosen to deal with IPv6 transition
        and legacy IPv4 connectivity requirements.</t>

        <t>In a network where IPv4 address availability is low, CGN/NAT444
        may provide continued access to IPv4 endpoints. Some of the advantages
        of using CGN/NAT444 include similarities in provisioning and
        activation models. IPv4 hosts in a CGN/NAT444 deployment will likely
        inherit the same addressing and management procedures as legacy IPv4
        globally addressed hosts (i.e., DHCPv4, DNS (v4), TFTP, TR-069, etc.).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="6rd">
        <t>6rd <xref target="RFC5969"/> provides a way of offering IPv6 connectivity to
        subscriber endpoints when native IPv6 addressing on the access network
        is not yet possible. &nbsp;6rd provides tunneled connectivity for IPv6 over
        the existing IPv4 path. As the access edge is upgraded and subscriber
        premises equipment is replaced, 6rd can be replaced by native IPv6
        connectivity. &nbsp;6rd can be delivered on top of a CGN/NAT444 deployment,
        but this would cause all traffic to be subject to some type of
        transition technology.</t>

        <t>6rd may also be advantageous during the early transition period while IPv6
        traffic volumes are low. During this period, the operator can gain
        experience with IPv6 in the core network and improve the operator's
        peering framework
        to match those of the IPv4 service. &nbsp;6rd scales by adding relays to the
        operator's network. Another advantage of 6rd is that the operator
        does not need a DHCPv6 address assignment infrastructure and does not
        need to support IPv6 routing to the CPE to support a delegated prefix
        (as it's derived from the IPv4 address and other configuration
        parameters).</t>

        <t>Client support is required for 6rd operation and may not be
        available on deployed hardware. &nbsp;6rd deployments may require the
        subscriber or operator to replace the CPE. &nbsp;6rd will also require
        parameter configuration that can be powered by the operator through
        DHCPv4, manually provisioned on the CPE, or automatically
        provisioned through some
        other means. Manual provisioning would likely limit deployment
        scale.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Native Dual Stack">
        <t>Native Dual Stack is often referred to as the "gold standard" of
        IPv6 and IPv4 delivery. It is a method of service delivery that is
        already used in many existing IPv6 deployments. Native Dual Stack
        does, however, require that native IPv6 be delivered through the
        access network to the subscriber premises. This technology option is
        desirable in many cases and can be used immediately if the access
        network and subscriber premises equipment support native IPv6.</t>

        <t>An operator who runs out of IPv4 addresses to assign to subscribers
        will not be able to provide traditional native Dual Stack connectivity
        for new subscribers. In Dual Stack deployments where sufficient IPv4
        addresses are not available, CGN/NAT444 can be used on the IPv4
        path.</t>

        <t>Delivering native Dual Stack would require the operator's core and
        access networks to support IPv6. Other systems, like DHCP, DNS, and
        diagnostic/management facilities, need to be upgraded to support IPv6
        as well. The upgrade of such systems may often be non-trivial and
        costly.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DS-Lite">
        <t>DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/> is based on a native IPv6
        connection model where IPv4 services are supported. DS-Lite provides
        tunneled connectivity for IPv4 over the IPv6 path between the
        subscriber's network device and a provider-managed gateway
        (Address Family Transition Router (AFTR)).</t>

        <t>DS-Lite can only be used where there is a native IPv6 connection
        between the AFTR and the CPE. This may mean that the technology's use
        may not be viable during early transition if the core or access
        network lacks IPv6 support. During the early transition period, a
        significant amount of content and services may by IPv4-only. Operators
        may be sensitive to this and may not want the newer IPv6 path to be
        the only bridge to IPv4 at that time, given the potential impact. The
        operator may also want to make sure that most of its internal services
        and a significant amount of external content are available over IPv6
        before deploying DS-Lite. The availability of services on IPv6 would
        help lower the demand on the AFTRs.</t>

        <t>By sharing IPv4 addresses among multiple endpoints, like
        CGN/NAT444, DS-Lite can facilitate continued support of legacy IPv4
        services even after IPv4 address run-out. There are some functional
        considerations to take into account with DS-Lite, such as those
        described in <xref target="NAT444-IMPACTS"/> and in
        <xref target="DSLITE-DEPLOYMENT"/>.</t>

        <t>DS-Lite requires client support on the CPE to function. The ability
        to utilize DS-Lite will be dependent on the operator providing
        DS&nbhy;Lite-capable CPEs or retail availability of the supported
        client for subscriber-acquired endpoints.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT64">
        <t>NAT64 <xref target="RFC6146"/> provides the ability to connect IPv6-only connected
        clients and hosts to IPv4 servers without any tunneling. NAT64
        requires that the host and home network support IPv6-only modes of
        operation. Home networks do not commonly contain equipment that is
        100% IPv6-capable. It is also not anticipated that common home
        networks will be ready for IPv6-only operation for a number of years.
        However, IPv6-only networking can be deployed by early adopters or
        highly controlled networks <xref target="RFC6586"/>.</t>

        <t>Viability of NAT64 will increase in wireline networks as consumer
        equipment is replaced by IPv6-capable versions. There are incentives
        for operators to move to IPv6-only operation, when feasible; these
        include the simplicity of a single-stack access network.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IPv6 Transition Phases">
      <t>The phases described in this document are not provided as a rigid set
      of steps but are considered a guideline that should be analyzed by
      operators planning their IPv6 transition. Operators may choose to skip
      steps based on technological capabilities within their specific
      networks (residential/corporate, fixed/mobile), their business
      development perspectives (which may affect the pace of migration towards
      full IPv6), or a combination thereof.</t>

      <t>The phases are based on the expectation that IPv6 traffic volume may
      initially be low, and operator staff will gain experience with IPv6 over
      time. As traffic volumes of IPv6 increase, IPv4 traffic volumes will
      decline (in percentage relative to IPv6), until IPv6 is the dominant
      address family used. Operators may want to keep the traffic flow for the
      dominant traffic class (IPv4 vs. IPv6) native to help manage costs
      related to transition technologies. The cost of using multiple
      technologies in succession to optimize each stage of the transition
      should also be compared against the cost of changing and upgrading
      subscriber connections.</t>

      <t>Additional guidance and information on utilizing IPv6 transition
      mechanisms can be found in <xref target="RFC6180"/>. Also, guidance on
      incremental CGN
      for IPv6 transition can be found in <xref target="RFC6264"/>.</t>

      <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation">
        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: Training">
          <t>Training is one of the most important steps in preparing an
          organization to support IPv6. Most people have little experience
          with IPv6, and many do not even have a solid grounding in IPv4. The
          implementation of IPv6 will likely produce many challenges due to
          immature code on hardware, and the evolution of many applications
          and systems to support IPv6. To properly deal with these impending
          or current challenges, organizations must train their staff on
          IPv6.</t>

          <t>Training should also be provided within reasonable timelines from
          the actual IPv6 deployment. This means the operator needs to plan in
          advance as it trains the various parts of its organization. New
          technology and engineering staff often receive little training
          because of their depth of knowledge but must at least be provided
          opportunities to read documentation, architectural white papers, and
          RFCs. Operations personnel who support the network and other systems
          need to be trained closer to the deployment timeframes so that they
          immediately use their newfound knowledge before forgetting.</t>

          <t>Subscriber support staff would require much more basic but
          large-scale training, since many organizations have massive
          call centers to
          support the subscriber base. Tailored training will also be required
          for marketing and sales staff to help them understand IPv6 and build
          it into the product development and sales process.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: System Capabilities ">
          <t>An important component with any IPv6 network architecture and
          implementation is the assessment of the hardware and operating
          capabilities of the deployed equipment (and software). The
          assessment needs to be conducted irrespective of how the operator
          plans to transition its network. The capabilities of the install
          base will, however, impact what technologies and modes of operation
          may be supported and therefore what technologies can be considered
          for the transition. If some systems do not meet the needs of the
          operator's IPv6 deployment and/or transition plan, the operator may
          need to plan for replacement and/or upgrade of those systems.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: Routing">
          <t>The network infrastructure will need to be in place to support
          IPv6. This includes the routed infrastructure, along with addressing
          principles, routing principles, peering policy, and related network
          functions. Since IPv6 is quite different from IPv4 in several ways,
          including the number of addresses that are made available, careful
          attention to a scalable and manageable architecture is needed.
          One such change is the notion of a delegated prefix, which
          deviates from the common single-address phenomenon in IPv4-only
          deployments. Deploying prefixes per CPE can load the routing tables
          and require a routing protocol or route gleaning to manage
          connectivity to the subscriber's network. Delegating prefixes can be
          of specific importance in access network environments where
          downstream subscribers often move between access nodes, raising the
          concern of frequent renumbering and/or managing movement of routed
          prefixes within the network (common in cable-based networks).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: Network Policy and Security">
          <t>Many, but not all, security policies will map easily from IPv4 to
          IPv6. Some new policies may be required for issues specific to IPv6
          operation. This document does not highlight these specific issues
          but raises the awareness that they are to be taken into
          consideration and should be
          addressed when delivering IPv6 services. Other IETF documents, such
          as <xref target="RFC4942"/>, <xref target="RFC6092"/>, and <xref target="RFC6169"/>, are excellent resources.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: Transition Architecture">
          <t>Operators should plan out their transition architecture in
          advance (with room for flexibility) to help optimize how they will
          build out and scale their networks. Should operators consider
          multiple technologies, like CGN/NAT444, DS-Lite, NAT64, and 6rd, they
          may want to plan out where network resident equipment may be located
          and potentially choose locations that can be used for all
          functional roles (i.e., placement of a NAT44 translator, AFTR, NAT64
          gateway, and 6rd relays). Although these functions are not inherently
          connected, additional management, diagnostic, and monitoring
          functions can be deployed alongside the transition hardware without
          the need to distribute these functions to an excessive or divergent
          number of locations.</t>

          <t>This approach may also prove beneficial if traffic patterns
          change rapidly in the future, as operators may need to evolve
          their transition infrastructure faster than originally anticipated.
          One such example may be the movement from a CGN/NAT44 model (Dual
          Stack) to DS-Lite. Since both traffic sets require a translation
          function (NAT44), synchronized pool management, routing, and
          management system positioning can allow rapid movement (the
          technological means to re-provision the subscriber notwithstanding).</t>

          <t>Operators should inform their vendors of what technologies they
          plan to support over the course of the transition to make sure the
          equipment is suited to support those modes of operation. This is
          important for both network gear and subscriber premises
          equipment.</t>

          <t>Operators should also plan their overall strategy to meet the
          target needs of an IPv6-only deployment. As traffic moves to IPv6,
          the benefits of only a single stack on the access network may
          eventually justify the removal of IPv4 for simplicity. Planning for
          this eventual model, no matter how far off this may be, will help
          operators embrace this end state when needed.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Phase 0 - Foundation: Tools and Management">
          <t>The operator should thoroughly analyze all provisioning and
          management systems to develop requirements for each phase. This will
          include concepts related to the 128-bit IPv6 address, the notation
          of an assigned IPv6 prefix (Prefix Delegation), and the ability to
          detect either or both address families when determining if a
          subscriber has full Internet service.</t>

          <t>If an operator stores usage information, this would need to be
          aggregated to include both IPv4 and IPv6 information as both address
          families are assigned to the same subscriber. Tools that verify
          connectivity may need to query the IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Phase 1 - Tunneled IPv6">
        <t>Tunneled access to IPv6 can be regarded as an early-stage
        transition option by operators. Many network operators can deploy
        native IPv6 from the access edge to the peering edge fairly quickly
        but may not be able to offer IPv6 natively to the subscriber edge
        device. During this period of time, tunneled access to IPv6 is a
        viable alternative to native IPv6. It is also possible that operators
        may be rolling out IPv6 natively to the subscriber edge, but the time
        involved may be long, due to logistics and other factors. Even while
        carefully rolling out native IPv6, operators can deploy relays for
        automatic tunneling technologies like 6to4 and Teredo. Where native
        IPv6 to the access edge is a longer-term project, operators can
        consider 6rd <xref target="RFC5969"/> as an option to offer
        in-home IPv6 access. Note that 6to4 and Teredo have different
        address selection <xref target="RFC6724"/> behaviors than
        6rd. Additional guidelines on deploying and supporting 6to4
        can be found in <xref target="RFC6343"/>.</t>

        <t>The operator can deploy 6rd relays into the network and scale them
        as needed to meet the early subscriber needs of IPv6. Since 6rd
        requires the upgrade or replacement of CPE devices, the operator may
        want to ensure that the CPE devices support not just 6rd but native
        Dual Stack and other tunneling technologies, such as DS-Lite, if
        possible <xref target="IPv6-CE-RTR-REQS"/>. &nbsp;6rd clients are
        becoming available
        in some retail channel products and within the original equipment
manufacturer (OEM) market. Retail
        availability of 6rd is important, since not all operators control or
        have influence over what equipment is deployed in the consumer home
        network. The operator can support 6rd access with unmanaged devices
        using DHCPv4 Option 212 (OPTION_6RD) <xref target="RFC5969"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" title="6rd Basic Model" anchor="figure_1">
          <artwork align="center">
                             +--------+         -----
                             |        |       /       \
             Encap IPv6 Flow |  6rd   |      |  IPv6   |
                      - - -&gt; | Relay  | &lt;- &gt; |   Net   |
+---------+         /        |        |       \       /
|         |        /         +--------+         -----
|   6rd   + &lt;-----                              -----
|         |                                   /       \
|  Client |         IPv4 Flow                |  IPv4   |
|         + &lt; - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -&gt; |   Net   |
|         |                                   \       /
+---------+                                     -----
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>6rd used as an initial transition technology also provides the
        added benefit of a deterministic IPv6 prefix based on the IPv4
        assigned address. Many operational tools are available or have been
        built to identify what IPv4 (often dynamic) address was assigned to a
        subscriber CPE. So, a simple tool and/or method can be built to help
        identify the IPv6 prefix using the knowledge of the assigned IPv4
        address.</t>

        <t>An operator may choose to not offer internal services over IPv6 if
        tunneled access to IPv6 is used, since some services generate a large
        amount of traffic. Such traffic may include video content, like IPTV.
        By limiting how much traffic is delivered over the 6rd connection (if
        possible), the operator can avoid costly and complex scaling of the
        relay infrastructure.</t>

        <section title="6rd Deployment Considerations">
          <t>Deploying 6rd can greatly speed up an operator's ability to
          support IPv6 to the subscriber network if native IPv6 connectivity
          cannot be supplied. The speed at which 6rd can be deployed is
          highlighted in <xref target="RFC5569"/>.</t>

          <t>The first core consideration is deployment models. &nbsp;6rd requires
          the CPE (6rd client) to send traffic to a 6rd relay. These relays
          can share a common anycast address or can use unique addresses.
          Using an anycast model, the operator can deploy all the 6rd relays
          using the same IPv4 interior service address. As the load increases
          on the deployed relays, the operator can deploy more relays into the
          network. The one drawback is that it may be difficult to manage the
          traffic volume among additional relays, since all 6rd traffic will
          find the nearest (in terms of IGP cost) relay. The use of
          multiple relay
          addresses can help provide more control but has the disadvantage of
          being more complex to provision. Subsets of CPEs across the network
          will require and contain different relay information. An alternative
          approach is to use a hybrid model using multiple anycast service IP
          addresses for clusters of 6rd relays, should the operator anticipate
          massive scaling of the environment. Thus, the operator has multiple
          vectors by which to scale the service.</t>

          <figure title="6rd Multiple IPv4 Service Address Model" anchor="figure_2">  <artwork align="center">
                               +--------+
                               |        |
                 IPv4 Addr.X   |  6rd   |
                      - - - &gt;  | Relay  |
+-----------+        /         |        |
| Client A  | &lt;- - -           +--------+
+-----------+
              Separate IPv4 Service Addresses
+-----------+
| Client B  | &lt; - -            +--------+
+-----------+       \          |        |
                      - - - &gt;  |  6rd   |
                 IPv4 Addr.Y   | Relay  |
                               |        |
                               +--------+
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <figure title="6rd Anycast IPv4 Service Address Model" anchor="figure_3">  <artwork align="center">
                               +--------+
                               |        |
                 IPv4 Addr.X   |  6rd   |
                      - - - &gt;  | Relay  |
+-----------+        /         |        |
| Client A  |- - - -           +--------+
+-----------+
          Common (Anycast) IPv4 Service Addresses
+-----------+
| Client B  | - - -            +--------+
+-----------+       \          |        |
                      - - - &gt;  |  6rd   |
                 IPv4 Addr.X   | Relay  |
                               |        |
                               +--------+
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Provisioning of the 6rd endpoints is affected by the deployment
          model chosen (i.e., anycast vs. specific service IP addresses). Using
          multiple IP addresses may require more planning and management, as
          subscriber equipment will have different sets of data to be
          provisioned into the devices. The operator may use DHCPv4, manual
          provisioning, or other mechanisms to provide parameters to subscriber
          equipment.</t>

          <t>If the operator manages the CPE, support personnel will need
          tools able to report the status of the 6rd tunnel. Usage information
          can be collected on the operator edge, but if source/destination
          flow details are required, data must be collected after the 6rd relay
          (the IPv6 side of the connection).</t>

          <t>6rd <xref target="RFC5969"/>, like any tunneling option, is subject to a reduced
          MTU, so operators need to plan to manage this type of environment.</t>

          <figure title="6rd Tools and Flow Management" anchor="figure_4">
            <artwork align="center">
+---------+  IPv4 Encapsulation  +------------+
|         +- - - - - - - - - - - +            |
|   6rd   +----------------------+     6rd    +------------
|         |   IPv6 Packet        |    Relay   | IPv6 Packet
| Client  +----------------------+            +------------
|         +- - - - - - - - - - - +            |      ^
+---------+  ^                   +------------+      |
             |                                       |
             |                                       |
      IPv4 (Tools/Mgmt)                     IPv6 Flow Analysis
</artwork> </figure>

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Phase 2 - Native Dual Stack">
        <t>Either as a follow-up phase to "tunneled IPv6" or as an initial
        step, the operator may deploy native IPv6 down to the CPEs. This phase
        would then allow both IPv6 and IPv4 to be natively accessed by the
        subscriber home network without translation or tunneling. The native
        Dual Stack phase can be rolled out across the network while the
        tunneled IPv6 service remains operational, if used. As areas begin to
        support native IPv6, subscriber home equipment will generally prefer
        using the IPv6 addresses derived from the delegated IPv6 prefix versus
        tunneling options as defined in <xref target="RFC6724"/>, such as
        6to4 and Teredo. Specific care is needed when moving to native
        Dual Stack from 6rd, as documented in <xref target="6rd-SUNSETTING"/>.</t>

        <t>Native Dual Stack is the best option at this point in the
        transition and should be sought as soon as possible. During this
        phase, the operator can confidently move both internal and external
        services to IPv6. Since there are no translation devices needed for
        this mode of operation, it transports both protocols (IPv6 and IPv4)
        efficiently within the network.</t>

        <section title="Native Dual Stack Deployment Considerations">
          <t>Native Dual Stack is a very desirable option for the IPv6
          transition, if feasible. The operator must enable IPv6 on the
          network core and peering edge before attempting to turn on native
          IPv6 services. Additionally, provisioning and support systems such
          as DHCPv6, DNS, and other functions that support the subscriber's
          IPv6 Internet connection need to be in place.</t>

          <t>The operator must treat IPv6 connectivity with the same
          operational importance as IPv4. A poor IPv6 service may be worse
          than not offering an IPv6 service at all, as it will negatively
          impact the subscriber's Internet experience. This may cause users or
          support personnel to disable IPv6, limiting the subscriber from the
          benefits of IPv6 connectivity as network performance improves.
          New code and IPv6 functionality may cause instability at first. The
          operator will need to monitor, troubleshoot, and resolve issues
          promptly.</t>

          <t>Prefix assignment and routing are new for common residential
          services. Prefix assignment is straightforward (DHCPv6 using
          Identity Associations for Prefix Delegation (IA_PDs)),
          but installation and propagation of routing information for
          the prefix, especially during access layer instability, are often
          poorly understood. The operator should develop processes for
          renumbering subscribers who move to new access nodes.</t>

          <t>Operators need to keep track of the dynamically assigned
          IPv4 address along with the IPv6 address and prefix. Any additional
          dynamic elements, such as auto-generated host names, need to be
          considered and planned for.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Intermediate Phase for CGN">
        <t>Acquiring more IPv4 addresses is already challenging, if not
        impossible; therefore, address sharing may be required on the IPv4 path
        of a Dual Stack deployment. The operator may have a preference to move
        directly to a transition technology such as DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/> or may
        use Dual Stack with CGN/NAT444 to facilitate IPv4 connections.</t>

        <t>CGN/NAT444 requires IPv4 addressing between the subscriber premises
        equipment and the operator's translator; this may be facilitated by
        shared addresses <xref target="RFC6598"/>, private addresses <xref target="RFC1918"/>, or another address
        space. CGN/NAT444 is only recommended to be used alongside IPv6 in a
        Dual Stack deployment and not on its own. <xref target="figure_5"/>
        provides a
        comparative view of a traditional IPv4 path versus one that uses
        CGN/NAT444.</t>

        <figure title="Overlay CGN Deployment" anchor="figure_5">
          <artwork align="center">
                             +--------+         ----- 
                             |        |       /       \ 
                   IPv4 Flow |  CGN   |      |         |
                      - - -&gt; +        + &lt; -&gt; |         |
+---------+         /        |        |      |         |
|   CPE   | &lt;- - - /         +--------+      |  IPv4   |
|---------+                                  |   Net   |
                                             |         |
+---------+         IPv4 Flow                |         |
|   CPE   | &lt;- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - &gt; |         |
|---------+                                   \       /
                                                ----- 
</artwork> </figure>

        <t>In the case of native Dual Stack, CGN/NAT444 can be used to assist
        in extending connectivity for the IPv4 path while the IPv6 path
        remains native. For endpoints operating in an IPv6+CGN/NAT444 model,
        the native IPv6 path is available for higher-quality connectivity,
        helping host operation over the network. At the same time, the CGN
        path may offer less than optimal performance. These points are also
        true for DS-Lite.</t>

        <figure title="Dual Stack with CGN" anchor="figure_6">
          <artwork align="center">
                             +--------+         ----- 
                             |        |       /       \
                   IPv4 Flow |  CGN   |      |  IPv4   |
                      - - -&gt; +        + &lt; -&gt; |   Net   |
+---------+         /        |        |       \       /
|         | &lt;- - - /         +--------+        -------
|   Dual  |                                  
|  Stack  |                                     ----- 
|   CPE   |         IPv6 Flow                 / IPv6  \
|         | &lt;- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - &gt; |   Net   |
|---------+                                   \       /
                                                ----- 
</artwork>  </figure>

        <t>CGN/NAT444 deployments may make use of a number of address options,
        which include <xref target="RFC1918"/> or Shared Address Space <xref target="RFC6598"/>. It is also
        possible that operators may use part of their own Regional Internet
Registry (RIR) assigned address
        space for CGN zone addressing if <xref target="RFC1918"/> addresses pose technical
        challenges in their networks. It is not recommended that operators use
        'squat space', as it may pose additional challenges with filtering and
        policy control <xref target="RFC6598"/>.</t>

        <section title="CGN Deployment Considerations">
          <t>CGN is often considered undesirable by operators but is required
          in many cases. An operator who needs to deploy CGN capabilities
          should
          consider the impacts of the function on the network. CGN is often
          deployed in addition to running IPv4 services and should not
          negatively impact the already working native IPv4 service. CGNs will
          be needed on a small scale at first and will grow to meet the
          demands based on traffic and connection dynamics of the
          subscriber, content, and network peers.</t>

          <t>The operator may want to deploy CGNs more centrally at first and
          then scale the system as needed. This approach can help conserve the
          costs of the system, limiting the deployed base and scaling it based
          on actual traffic demand. The operator should use a deployment model
          and architecture that allow the system to scale as needed.</t>

          <figure title="CGN Deployment: Centralized vs. Distributed" anchor="figure_7">
            <artwork align="center">
                             +--------+         ----- 
                             |        |       /       \ 
                             |  CGN   |      |         |
                      - - -&gt; +        + &lt; -&gt; |         |
+---------+         /        |        |      |         |
|   CPE   | &lt;- - - /         +--------+      |  IPv4   |
|         |                      ^           |         |
|---------+                      |           |   Net   |
                 +--------+    Centralized   |         |
+---------+      |        |       CGN        |         |
|         |      |  CGN   |                  |         |
|   CPE   | &lt;- &gt; +        + &lt;- - - - - - - &gt; |         |
|---------+      |        |                   \       /
                 +--------+                     -----
                     ^
                     |
                 Distributed CGN
</artwork>  </figure>

          <t>The operator may be required to log translation information
          <xref target="CGN-REQS"/>. This logging may require
          significant investment in external systems that ingest, aggregate,
          and report such information <xref target="DETERMINISTIC-CGN"/>.</t>

          <t>Since CGN has noticeable impacts on certain applications
          <xref target="NAT444-IMPACTS"/>, operators may deploy CGN only for those
          subscribers who may be less affected by CGN (if possible).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Phase 3 - IPv6-Only">
        <t>Once native IPv6 is widely deployed in the network and
        well supported by tools, staff, and processes, an operator may
        consider supporting only IPv6 to all or some subscriber endpoints.
        During this final phase, IPv4 connectivity may or may not need to be
        supported, depending on the conditions of the network, subscriber
        demand, and legacy device requirements. If legacy IPv4 connectivity is
        still demanded (e.g., for older nodes), DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/> may be used
        to tunnel the traffic. If IPv4 connectivity is not required but
        access to legacy IPv4 content is, then NAT64 <xref target="RFC6144"/>
        <xref target="RFC6146"/> can be used.</t>

        <section title="DS-Lite">
          <t>DS-Lite allows continued access for the IPv4 subscriber base
          using address sharing for IPv4 Internet connectivity but with only
          a single layer of translation, as compared to CGN/NAT444. This mode
          of operation also removes the need to directly supply subscriber
          endpoints with an IPv4 address, potentially simplifying the
          connectivity to the customer (single address family) and supporting
          IPv6-only addressing to the CPE.</t>

          <t>The operator can also move Dual Stack endpoints to DS-Lite
          retroactively to help optimize the IPv4 address-sharing deployment
          by removing the IPv4 address assignment and routing component. To
          minimize traffic needing translation, the operator should have
          already moved most content to IPv6 before the IPv6-only phase is
          implemented.</t>

          <figure align="center" title="DS-Lite Basic Model" anchor="figure_8">
            <artwork align="center">                             +--------+      -----
                             |        |    /       \
             Encap IPv4 Flow |  AFTR  |   |  IPv4   |
                      -------+        +---+   Net   |
+---------+         /        |        |    \       /
|         |        /         +--------+      -----
| DS-Lite +-------                           -----
|         |                                /       \
|  Client |         IPv6 Flow             |  IPv6   |
|         +-------------------------------|   Net   |
|         |                                \       /
+---------+                                  ----- </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>If the operator had previously decided to enable a CGN/NAT444
          deployment, it may be able to co-locate the AFTR and CGN/NAT444
          processing functions within a common network location to simplify
          capacity management and the engineering of flows. This case may be
          evident in a later transition stage, when an operator chooses to
          optimize its network and IPv6-only operation is feasible.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DS-Lite Deployment Considerations">
          <t>The same deployment considerations associated with native IPv6
          deployments apply to DS-Lite and NAT64. IPv4 will now be dependent
          on IPv6 service quality, so the IPv6 network and services must be
          running well to ensure a quality experience for the end subscriber.
          Tools and processes will be needed to manage the encapsulated IPv4
          service. If flow analysis is required for IPv4 traffic, this may be
          enabled at a point beyond the AFTR (after decapsulation) or where
          DS-Lite-aware equipment is used to process traffic midstream.</t>

          <figure align="center" title="DS-Lite Tools and Flow Analysis" anchor="figure_9">
            <artwork align="center">
+---------+  IPv6 Encapsulation  +------------+
|         + - - - - - - - - - - -+            |
|  AFTR   +----------------------+    AFTR    +------------
|         |   IPv4 Packet        |            | IPv4 Packet
| Client  +----------------------+            +------------
|         + - - - - - - - - - - -+            |      ^
+---------+  ^               ^   +------------+      |
             |               |                       |
             |               |                       |
      IPv6 (Tools/Mgmt)      |           IPv4 Packet Flow Analysis
                             |
        Midstream IPv4 Packet Flow Analysis (Encapsulation Aware)
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/> also requires client support on the subscriber
          premises device. The operator must clearly articulate to vendors
          which technologies will be used at which points, how they interact
          with each other at the CPE, and how they will be provisioned. As an
          example, an operator may use 6rd in the outset of the transition,
          then move to native Dual Stack followed by DS-Lite.</t>

          <t>DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/>, like any tunneling option,
          is subject to a reduced MTU, so operators need to plan to manage
          this type of environment.
          Additional considerations for DS-Lite deployments can be found
          in <xref target="DSLITE-DEPLOYMENT"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="NAT64 Deployment Considerations">
          <t>The deployment of NAT64 assumes that the network assigns an IPv6
          address to a network endpoint that is translated to an IPv4 address
          to provide connectivity to IPv4 Internet services and content.
          Experiments such as the one described in <xref target="RFC6586"/> highlight issues
          related to IPv6-only deployments due to legacy IPv4 APIs and IPv4
          literals. Many of these issues will be resolved by the eventual
          removal of this undesirable legacy behavior. Operational deployment
          models, considerations, and experiences related to NAT64 have been
          documented in <xref target="NAT64-EXPERIENCE"/>.</t>

          <figure align="center" title="NAT64/DNS64 Basic Model" anchor="figure_10">
            <artwork align="center">
                             +--------+      -----
                             |        |    /       \
                   IPv6 Flow | NAT64  |   |  IPv4   |
                      -------+ DNS64  +---+   Net   |
+---------+         /        |        |    \       /
|         |        /         +--------+      -----
|  IPv6   +-------                           -----
|         |                                /       \
|  Only   |         IPv6 Flow             |  IPv6   |
|         +-------------------------------|   Net   |
|         |                                \       /
+---------+                                  ----- 
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>To navigate some of the limitations of NAT64 when dealing
          with legacy IPv4 applications, the operator may choose to implement
          464XLAT <xref target="464XLAT"/> if possible. As support for IPv6 on
          subscriber equipment and content increases, the efficiency of NAT64
          increases by reducing the need to translate traffic. NAT64
          deployments would see an overall decline in translator usage
          as more traffic is promoted to IPv6-to-IPv6 native communication.
          NAT64 may play an important part in an operator's late-stage
          transition, as it removes the need to support IPv4 on the
          access network and provides a solid go-forward networking model.</t>

          <t>It should be noted, as with any technology that utilizes address
          sharing, that the IPv4 public pool sizes (IPv4 transport addresses
          per <xref target="RFC6146"/>) can pose limits to IPv4 server
          connectivity for the subscriber base. Operators should be aware
          that some IPv4 growth in the near term is possible, so IPv4
          translation pools need to be monitored.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Operators should review the documentation related to the technologies
      selected for IPv6 transition. In those reviews, operators should
      understand what security considerations are applicable to the chosen
      technologies. As an example, <xref target="RFC6169"/> should be reviewed to understand
      security considerations related to tunneling technologies.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Special thanks to Wes George, Chris Donley, Christian Jacquenet, and
      John Brzozowski for their extensive review and comments.</t>

      <t>Thanks to the following people for their textual contributions,
      guidance, and comments: Jason Weil, Gang Chen, Nik Lavorato, John
      Cianfarani, Chris Donley, Tina TSOU, Fred Baker, and Randy Bush.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
 <?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6180'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1918'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2460'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3056'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3068'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6724'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4380'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4942'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5569'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5969'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6092'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6144'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6146'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6169'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6264'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6269'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6333'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6343'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6540'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6586'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6598'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements (RFC-EDITOR/MISSREF) -->
      <reference anchor="CGN-REQS">
        <front>
          <title>Common requirements for Carrier Grade NATs (CGNs)</title>
          <author fullname="Simon Perreault" initials="S" surname="Perreault" role="editor">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Ikuhei Yamagata" initials="I" surname="Yamagata">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Shin Miyakawa" initials="S" surname="Miyakawa">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Akira Nakagawa" initials="A" surname="Nakagawa">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Hiroyuki Ashida" initials="H" surname="Ashida">
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2012"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

<!-- draft-jjmb-v6ops-comcast-ipv6-experiences (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='COMCAST-IPv6-EXPERIENCES'>
<front>
<title>Comcast IPv6 Trial/Deployment Experiences</title>
<author initials='J' surname='Brzozowski' fullname='John Brzozowski'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Griffiths' fullname='Chris Griffiths'>
</author>
<date month='October' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-donley-nat444-impacts (ISR) -->
      <reference anchor="NAT444-IMPACTS">
<front>
<title>Assessing the Impact of Carrier-Grade NAT on Network Applications</title>
<author initials='C' surname='Donley' fullname='Chris Donley' role="editor">
</author>
<author initials='L' surname='Howard' fullname='Lee Howard'>
</author>
<author initials='V' surname='Kuarsingh' fullname='Victor Kuarsingh'>
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Berg' fullname='John Berg'>
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Doshi' fullname='Jinesh Doshi'>
</author>
<date month='October' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- RFC 6732 / Pub. Sep 2012 (was draft-kuarsingh-v6ops-6to4-provider-managed-tunnel)  -->
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6732'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-v6ops-464xlat ("Publication Requested") -->
<reference anchor='464XLAT'>
<front>
<title>464XLAT: Combination of Stateful and Stateless Translation</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Mawatari' fullname='Masataka Mawatari'>
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Kawashima' fullname='Masanobu Kawashima'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Byrne' fullname='Cameron Byrne'>
</author>
<date month='September' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-v6ops-nat64-experience
(replaces draft-chen-v6ops-nat64-experience) (I-D Exists) -->
      <reference anchor="NAT64-EXPERIENCE">
<front>
<title>NAT64 Operational Experiences</title>
<author initials='G' surname='Chen' fullname='Gang Chen'>
</author>
<author initials='Z' surname='Cao' fullname='Zhen Cao'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Byrne' fullname='Cameron Byrne'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Xie' fullname='Chongfeng Xie'>
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Binet' fullname='David Binet'>
</author>
<date month='August' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-donley-behave-deterministic-cgn (I-D Exists) -->
      <reference anchor="DETERMINISTIC-CGN">
<front>
<title>Deterministic Address Mapping to Reduce Logging in Carrier Grade NAT Deployments</title>
<author initials='C' surname='Donley' fullname='Chris Donley'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Grundemann' fullname='Chris Grundemann'>
</author>
<author initials='V' surname='Sarawat' fullname='Vikas Sarawat'>
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Sundaresan' fullname='Karthik Sundaresan'>
</author>
<date month='July' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-softwire-dslite-deployment (IESG Evaluation::Revised ID Needed) -->
      <reference anchor="DSLITE-DEPLOYMENT">
<front>
<title>Deployment Considerations for Dual-Stack Lite</title>
<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Maglione' fullname='Roberta Maglione'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Williams' fullname='Carl Williams'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Jacquenet' fullname='Christian Jacquenet'>
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohamed Boucadair'>
</author>
<date month='August' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-v6ops-6204bis (MISSREF) -->
      <reference anchor="IPv6-CE-RTR-REQS">
<front>
<title>Basic Requirements for IPv6 Customer Edge Routers</title>
<author initials='H' surname='Singh' fullname='Hemant Singh'>
</author>
<author initials='W' surname='Beebee' fullname='Wes Beebee'>
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Donley' fullname='Chris Donley'>
</author>
<author initials='B' surname='Stark' fullname='Barbara Stark'>
</author>
<date month='October' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-townsley-v6ops-6rd-sunsetting (Expired) -->
      <reference anchor="6rd-SUNSETTING">
<front>
<title>6rd Sunsetting</title>
<author initials='W' surname='Townsley' fullname='Mark Townsley'>
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Cassen' fullname='Alexandre Cassen'>
</author>
<date month='November' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-matthews-v6ops-design-guidelines (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='IPv6-DESIGN'>
<front>
<title>Design Guidelines for IPv6 Networks</title>
<author initials='P' surname='Matthews' fullname='Philip Matthews'>
</author>
<date month='October' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-v6ops-icp-guidance ("Publication Requested") -->
<reference anchor='IPv6-ICP-ASP-GUIDANCE'>
<front>
<title>IPv6 Guidance for Internet Content and Application Service Providers</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Carpenter' fullname='Brian Carpenter'>
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Jiang' fullname='Sheng Jiang'>
</author>
<date month='September' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

    </references>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
  </back>
</rfc>
