<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [ 
<!ENTITY rfc2418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2418.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4287 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="6292" ipr="trust200902" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<front> <title abbrev="WG Charter Tool Reqs"> Requirements for a
Working Group Charter Tool </title>

<author initials='P.' surname="Hoffman" fullname='Paul Hoffman'>
<organization>VPN Consortium</organization> <address>
<email>paul.hoffman@vpnc.org</email> </address> </author>

<date month="June" year="2011"/>

<abstract>

<t>The IETF intends to provide a new tool to Area Directors for the
creation, re-chartering, and closing of Working Groups. The tool will
also allow the IETF community to view the status of the chartering
process. This document describes the requirements for the proposed
new tool, and it is intended as input to a later activity for the
design and development of such a tool.</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC2418"/> describes the guidelines and procedures
for formation and operation of IETF Working Groups (WGs). Since the
publication of RFC 2418 in 1998, the IETF has started many dozen new
WGs, and has shut down many dozen. In that time, many WGs have had
some (often dozens) changes to their charters.</t>

<t>Today, virtually all of the tasks associated with creating,
rechartering, and closing a WG are performed manually. An Area
Director (AD) requests one of these actions by manually sending a
message to the Secretariat's ticket system. A member of the
Secretariat staff manually updates the internal Secretariat database
and the IETF Datatracker, manually places the WG on the IESG
teleconference agenda (when appropriate), and manually sends out all
of the required messages and announcements.</t>

<t>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) would like to create a better tool for those tasks, and
this document lists the requirements for such a tool. When complete,
this document may be used to issue an RFP for the design and
development of the tool. This document was prepared at the request of
the IAOC.</t>

<section title="WG Charter Process Overview">

<t>As described in <xref target="RFC2418"/>, a key responsibility of
the IESG is the creation, re-chartering, and closing of WGs. Creation
and rechartering of WGs is a multi-step process that involves
internal review of a draft charter by the IESG and IAB, an external
review of the draft charter by the IETF community and by other
standards bodies, and (likely) approval of a final charter by the
IESG. The internal review by the IESG and IAB, and the external
review by the IETF community, often result in revisions to the draft
charter.</t>

<t>Closing of a WG does not require review or approval by the IESG.
Rather, a WG may be closed at the request of an AD, normally the Area
Advisor for the WG.</t>

<t>Note that the charter and recharter processes do not involve changing
of WG milestones. A tool that handles milestone updates will likely
be created in the future.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="General Requirements">

<t>The tool described here holds records for new WGs that are being
considered as well as for all WGs whose charter are under review.</t>

<section title="WG Records">

<t>A WG record contains the following fields:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
<t>name of the WG</t> <t>the WG's
acronym</t> <t>names of the WG chairs (if known)</t> <t>names of the
WG secretary (if any)</t> <t>names of the WG technical advisors (if
any)</t> <t>shepherding AD</t> <t>IETF area</t> <t>charter text</t>
<t>mailing list address and archive location</t> <t>previous mailing
list (if any)</t> <t>other web sites (such as wikis, trackers, and/or
project sites, if any) including web sites existing prior to the WG
formation</t> <t>earlier acronyms for the WG</t> <t>explanation for
why the WG is being chartered or rechartered (if any)</t> </list></t>

<t>In addition, a WG record contains the state of the WG in the
review process. That state has one annotation: whether or not the
state is for a proposed WG or for an existing WG undergoing
rechartering. Some changes in state cause messages to be sent to the
Secretariat so that the Secretariat can perform additional steps,
such as sending out mail to various parties about the latest version
of the charter text, deadlines for an upcoming decision, and so
on.</t>

<t>When a WG record is displayed, that display should also reflect
whether the WG currently exists or has been closed; that data
comes from a different part of the Datatracker database.</t>

<t>Any AD can modify fields in an existing WG record. Any AD can use
the tool to change the review state of a WG record. The normal order
for steps is shown in this document, but an AD can set the state to
any valid value at any time.</t>

</section>

<section title="Comments">

<t>During the reviews for WG creation and rechartering, ADs can
comment on the reviews. Any AD can add a comment to the record of a
WG that is under review. Each comment can be flagged as either
"blocking" (meaning blocking forward movement until it is resolved)
and "non-blocking" (meaning that it is only informative or
editorial).</t>

</section>

<section title="Naming of Charter Text Proposals">

<t>Charter text proposals are to be kept for historical purposes.
They are kept in files with a specific naming pattern. The pattern
for charters before a WG is formed is:
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
charter-ietf-wgacronym-nn[-mm]
]]></artwork></figure>

<list style='symbols'>

<t>"wgacronym" is the acronym of the proposed WG.</t>

<t>"nn" is a two-digit charter number assigned in sequence. It starts
at "00" for before the WG is first chartered; the first finished
charter has a value of "01".</t>

<t>"mm" is a two-digit proposal number assigned in sequence. It
starts at "00" for the first proposal for a particular version of
charter. It is omitted in the actual charter file.</t>

</list></t>

<t>For instance, if the "example" WG is chartered and then
rechartered twice, you might have the following sequence of files:

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
charter-ietf-example-00-00.txt (first proposal)
charter-ietf-example-00-01.txt (second proposal)
charter-ietf-example-00-02.txt (third proposal)
charter-ietf-example-01.txt (first charter)
charter-ietf-example-01-00.txt (first recharter proposal)
charter-ietf-example-01-01.txt (second recharter proposal)
charter-ietf-example-01-02.txt (third recharter proposal)
charter-ietf-example-02.txt (second charter)
charter-ietf-example-02-00.txt (next recharter proposal)
. . .
charter-ietf-example-03.txt (third charter)
]]></artwork></figure></t>

</section>

<section title="Wording of Announcements">

<t>An AD can view and edit the standard "WG Review" and "WG Action"
announcements before they are sent out during the WG creation,
rechartering, and closing processes. If the AD edits the message, the
Secretariat is alerted to that fact when they receive the
request.</t>

</section>

<section title="Access to the Tool">

<t>Area Directors and the IETF Secretariat currently have access to
perform some actions in the Datatracker that other community
members do not; this access control continues to be used in many of
the extensions listed in this document. Further, the IETF Secretariat
can perform all actions that can be performed by any AD in this
tool.</t>

</section>

<section title="Initializing the Tool">

<t>Records for all WGs that are being created, or are in the process
of charter updates, will be added before the tool is first publicly
deployed.</t>

<t>The database should also be initialized with current and
historical data, namely as much information as is currently known
about existing and closed WGs that can be done in a mostly-automated
fashion.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Creating and Rechartering WGs">

<section title="Chartering a New WG">

<t>Any AD can create a new WG record using a simple web form.
Creating a record should succeed as long as there is no other WG with
the same name. Names must be unique, so the tool will warn the AD if
the acronym that is being proposed has been used in earlier WG
charter proposals and suggest against its use for a new charter. 
By default, the field in the form listing the shepherding AD will be
prepopulated with the name of the AD who is filling in the form.
The AD can fill in all the fields for the proposed WG. The names of the WG
chairs can be left off during the initial chartering process.</t>

<t>(Some Secretariat tools have trouble with acronyms of more than
eight characters: they truncate the name.  This will probably be
fixed in the future. The new tool should have a configuration setting
that is set to 8 initially, and it should be adjusted when the Secretariat
tools are updated. There may also be problems with names that have
hyphens in them. However, WGs that have more than eight characters in
their names, and WGs with hyphens in their names, have existed for
over a year.)</t>

<t>Creating a new WG record causes the Datatracker state for this
potential new WG to be "Informal IESG review". When the record is
created, the AD proposes a length of time (in weeks) for the internal
review time; the default is one week.</t>

<t>The review states in which a WG can exist during its initial
chartering are:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>

<t>Informal IESG review -- This is the initial state, moved into by
the tool when an AD creates a WG record. When the WG record is moved
to this state, a message is sent to the Secretariat. The normal next
state is "Internal review" if the idea is accepted, or "Not currently
under review" if the idea is abandoned. The tool should prompt the AD
if they try to move to the next state in less than the minimum
elapsed time set by the AD when creating the WG, but allow the
move if the AD responds to the prompt.</t>

<t>Internal review -- The IESG and IAB are reviewing the early draft
of the charter; this is the initial IESG and IAB review. When moved
to this state, a note is sent to the Secretariat to place this on the
next IESG telechat and to inform the IAB. The usual next state is
"External review" if the idea is adopted, or "Informal IESG review"
if the IESG decides the idea needs more work, or "Not currently under
review" if the idea is abandoned.</t>

<t>External review -- The IETF community and possibly other standards
development organizations (SDOs) are reviewing the proposed charter.
When moved to this state, a note is sent to the Secretariat to send
out the external review announcement to the appropriate lists. The
external review announcement will be sent out to the normal
IETF-related mailing lists. The AD can specify whether or not to send
the announcement to other SDOs (with the default being that it should
be), and the AD can also specify additional recipients who should
receive the announcement. When moved to this state, a separate note
is sent to the Secretariat to schedule discussion for the next IESG
telechat. The usual next state is "IESG review", although it might
move to "Not currently under review" if the idea is abandoned during
the external review.</t>

<t>IESG review -- The IESG is reviewing the discussion from the
external review of the proposed charter. The usual next state is "WG
exists", or "Not currently under review" if the idea is
abandoned.</t>

<t>WG exists -- The WG was approved by the IESG. When moved to this
state, a note is sent to the Secretariat to publish the charter and
send the appropriate announcements. The WG remains in this state
until there is a request to update the charter.</t>

<t>Not currently under review -- The proposed WG is not being
considered at this time. A proposed WG charter will remain in this
state until an AD moves it to "Informa1 IESG review".</t>

</list></t>

<t>All states above, except for "WG exists", are given the annotation
"Initial chartering".</t>

<t>The chartering process involves the proposed charter appearing on
two IESG telechats.  The tool should allow an AD and/or the
Secretariat to select the telechat date for the approval events. When
the telechat is selected, the state determines where it appears on
that telechat's agenda.</t>

</section>

<section title="Rechartering an Existing WG">

<t>Any AD can request that a WG be rechartered using a simple web
form. This form prompts with the current charter and allows all
fields to be edited. Asking for a recharter causes the Datatracker
state for this WG to be "Informal IESG review".  When the recharter
record is created, the AD proposes a length of time (in weeks) for
the internal review time; the default is one week.</t>

<t>The review states in which a WG can exist during rechartering
are:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>

<t>WG exists; Informal IESG recharter review -- This is the initial
state, moved into by the tool when an AD asks for a WG to be
rechartered. When the WG record is moved to this state, a message is
sent to the Secretariat. The normal next state is "WG exists;
Internal review" if the idea is accepted, or "WG exists" if this
attempt to recharter is abandoned. The tool should prompt the AD if
they try to move to the next state in less than the minimum elapsed
time set by the AD when asking to recharter the WG.</t>

<t>WG exists; Internal recharter review -- The IESG and IAB are
reviewing the proposed new charter; this is the initial IESG and IAB
review of the new charter. When moved to this state, a note is sent
to the Secretariat to place this on the next IESG telechat and to
inform the IAB. The usual next state is "WG exists; External review"
if the idea is adopted, or "WG exists; Informal IESG review" if the
IESG decides the idea needs more work, or "WG exists" if the current
rechartering is abandoned or if the new charter is approved during
internal review.</t>

<t>WG exists; External recharter review -- The IETF community and
possibly other SDOs are reviewing the proposed new charter. When
moved to this state, a note is sent to the Secretariat to send out
the external review announcement to the appropriate lists. The
external review announcement will be sent to the normal
IETF-related mailing lists. The AD can specify whether or not to send
the announcement to other SDOs (with the default being that it should
be), and the AD can also specify additional recipients who should
receive the announcement. The usual next state is "WG exists; IESG
review", although it might move to "WG exists" if the current
rechartering is abandoned during the external review.</t>

<t>WG exists; IESG recharter review -- The IESG is reviewing the
discussion from the external review of the recharter. When moved to
this state, a note is sent to the Secretariat to schedule discussion
for the next IESG telechat. The usual next state is "WG exists".</t>

</list></t>

<t>All states above are given the annotation "Rechartering".</t>

<t>When rechartering existing WGs, the IESG decides whether or not
the recharter needs an external review; many do not.</t>

<t>The rechartering process involves the proposed charter appearing
on one or two IESG telechats.  The tool should allow an AD and/or the
Secretariat to select the telechat date for the approval events. When
the telechat is selected, the state determines where it appears on
that telechat's agenda.</t>

</section>

<section title="Ballots for Charter Approval">

<t>The current Datatracker has facilities for ballots on adoption of
Internet-Drafts to become RFCs. A separate facility needs to be
created to allow balloting for initial chartering or rechartering
during IESG review. The balloting for charter and rechartering will allow ADs
to express "yes", "no", and "abstain" positions, and will allow ADs to change
their positions over time.
</t>

<t>As described in Section 2.2, comments can be added to the record
for a WG. It is expected that such comments will be added during the
balloting process.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Requesting the Closing of a WG">

<t>An AD can use the tool to request that the Secretariat close an
existing WG. The request action will prompt the AD to provide
instructions regarding the disposition of each active Internet-Draft
(such as to withdraw the draft, move it to another WG, convert it to
an individual submission, and so on), wording for the closure
announcement, and the status of the WG mailing list (will it remain
open or should it be closed).</t>

</section>

<section title="Searching, Comparing, and Tracking Charters">

<section title="Viewing and Searching the Charter Database">

<t>All members of the IETF community can view the public portions of
the charter database. This public view should have an explanation of
the states given in this document. They can also search for a WG
record in the tool based on one or more of the following
criteria:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>

<t>WG name (full or partial)</t>
<t>WG acronym</t>
<t>WG charter state</t>
<t>Shepherding AD</t>
<t>Area</t>
<t>Text in any of the fields</t>
<t>Earlier acronyms for the WG</t>

</list></t>

<t>Further, all users can view all snapshots of earlier versions of a
WG's charter. Snapshots include the Area, AD, WG name, WG acronym,
chairs, and charter text.</t>

</section>

<section title="Seeing Differences between Versions of Pre-approval
Wordings">

<t>It needs to be easy to compare differences between different
versions of proposed charter language, up to and including the
approved version. Using the naming formats given in Section 2, this
means that it must be easy to compare wgacronym-charter-ss (for the
highest value of "ss") with wgacronym-recharter-ss-nn. It must also
be possible to compare any two versions of approved charters (that
is, of two values for "ss" in wgacronym-charter-ss). It also must be
easy to compare two versions that have different acronyms in the case
that the acronym changes during the chartering process.</t>

</section>

<section title="Tracking Charters with an Atom Feed">

<t>The tool needs to provide an Atom feed <xref target="RFC4287"/>
for the changes in a charter. The contents of the feed are the full
WG record, plus an indication of what changed since the last entry in
the feed.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title='Security Considerations'> <t>Creating a new tool for
tracking the charter of WGs does not affect the security of the
Internet in any significant fashion.</t> </section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">

<t>This document draws heavily on earlier work done on this topic by
other writers, such as previous IESG and IAB members. Various members
of the IESG contributed many suggestions to this document. In
particular David Harrington, Robert Sparks, and Russ Housley
contributed a great deal of wording and many ideas.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

&rfc2418;

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

&rfc4287;

</references>

</back>

</rfc>
