<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2205 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3209 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml'>        
    <!ENTITY rfc2330 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2330.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2679 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2679.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2681 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2681.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4208 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4208.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6383 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6383.xml'>        
    <!ENTITY RFC5814 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5814.xml'>
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6777" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"> 
       
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

    <front>
      <title abbrev='LSP Data Path Delay Metrics'>
            Label Switched Path (LSP) Data Path Delay Metrics in
	    Generalized MPLS and MPLS Traffic Engineering (MPLS-TE) Networks
            </title>

        <author initials='W.' surname="Sun" fullname='Weiqiang Sun' role="editor">
            <organization abbrev='SJTU'>
                Shanghai Jiao Tong University
            </organization>
                    <address>
                      <postal>
                        <street>800 Dongchuan Road</street>
                        <city>Shanghai</city> 
                        <code>200240</code>
                        <country>China</country>
                      </postal>
                        <phone>+86 21 3420 5359</phone>
                        <email>sun.weiqiang@gmail.com</email> 
                    </address>
            </author>
        
        <author initials='G.' surname="Zhang" fullname='Guoying Zhang' role="editor">
          <organization abbrev='CATR'>
               China Academy of Telecommunication Research, MIIT, China
          </organization>
                <address>
                   <postal>
                      <street>No. 52 Hua Yuan Bei Lu, Haidian District</street>
                      <city>Beijing</city> 
                      <code>100191</code>
                      <country>China</country>
                      </postal>
                      <phone>+86 1062300103</phone>
                      <email>zhangguoying@catr.cn</email> 
                </address>
        </author>

        <author initials="J" surname="Gao" fullname="Jianhua Gao">
            <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.
            </organization>
                   <address>
                      <postal>
                        <street></street>
                        <country>China</country>
                      </postal>
                        <phone>+86 755 28973237</phone>
                        <email>gjhhit@huawei.com</email>
                    </address>
        </author>

        <author initials="G" surname="Xie" fullname="Guowu Xie">
            <organization abbrev="UC Riverside">
              University of California, Riverside
            </organization>
                   <address>
                      <postal>
                        <street>900 University Ave.</street>
                        <city>Riverside</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>92521</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                      </postal>
                        <phone>+1 951 237 8825</phone>
                        <email>xieg@cs.ucr.edu</email>
                    </address>
        </author>

        <author initials="R" surname="Papneja" fullname="Rajiv Papneja">
            <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>
                   <address>
                      <postal>
                        <street>Santa Clara, CA  95050</street>
                        <city>Reston</city>
                        <region>VA</region>
                        <code>20190</code>
                        <country>USA</country>
                      </postal>
                        <email>rajiv.papneja@huawei.com</email>
                    </address>
        </author>


        <date month="November" year="2012"/>
      
<keyword>Provisioning performance</keyword>
<keyword>Performance measurement</keyword>
<keyword>UNI</keyword>
<keyword>Bandwidth on Demand</keyword>
<keyword>performance evaluation</keyword>
<keyword>Measurement methodologies</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
                When setting up a Label Switched Path (LSP) in Generalized MPLS (GMPLS)
		and MPLS Traffic Engineering (MPLS-TE) networks, the completion 
                  of the signaling process does not necessarily mean that the cross-connection along the LSP has been 
                  programmed accordingly and in a timely manner.    Meanwhile, the
                  completion of the signaling process may be used by LSP users or
                  applications that control their use as an indication that the data path
                  has become usable. The existence of the inconsistency 
                 between the signaling messages and
                 cross-connection programming, and the possible failure of cross-connection
                 programming, if not properly treated, will result in data loss or even
                 application failure. Characterization of this performance can thus help
                 designers to improve the way in which LSPs are used and to make
                 applications or tools that depend on and use LSPs more robust. This document defines a series of performance 
                  metrics to evaluate the connectivity of the data path in the signaling process. 
                   </t>
            </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    <t>
        Label Switched Paths (LSPs) are established, controlled, and allocated for use by management
        tools or directly by the components that use them.  In this document,
        we call such management tools and the components that use LSPs
        "applications".  Such applications may be Network Management Systems
        (NMSs); hardware or software components that forward data onto
        virtual links; programs or tools that use dedicated links; or any
        other user of an LSP.
        </t>
        
    <t>
                Ideally, the completion of the signaling process means that
                the signaled LSP is 
                ready to carry traffic. However, in actual implementations, vendors may choose to 
                program the cross-connection in a pipelined manner, so that the overall LSP provisioning delay can be 
                reduced. In such situations, the data path may not be ready for use instantly after the signaling process 
                completes. Implementation deficiency may also cause inconsistency between the signaling process 
                and data path provisioning. For example, if the data plane fails to program the cross-connection 
                accordingly but does not manage to report this to the control plane, the signaling process may complete 
                successfully while the corresponding data path will never become functional at all.
    </t>
    <t>
                On the other hand, the completion of the signaling process may
		be used in many cases as an indication of 
                data path connectivity. For example, when invoking through the
                User-Network Interface (UNI) <xref target= "RFC4208"/>, a client device 
                or an application may use the reception of the correct Resv
		message as an indication that the data path is 
                fully functional and start to transmit traffic. This will result in data loss or even application failure.
    </t>
    <t>
                Although RSVP(-TE) specifications have suggested that the cross-connections are programmed before signaling 
                messages are propagated upstream, it is still worthwhile to verify the conformance of an implementation 
                and measure the delay, when necessary.    
    </t>
    <t>
                This document defines a series of performance metrics to
		evaluate the connectivity of the data path during the 
                signaling process. The metrics defined in this document complement the control plane metrics 
                defined in <xref target = "RFC5814"/>. These metrics can be used to verify the conformance of 
                implementations against related specifications, as elaborated in 
                <xref target = "RFC6383"/>. They also can be used to build more 
                robust applications. 
    </t>
    </section>

     <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
     </section>

     <section title="Overview of Performance Metrics">
      <t>
                In this memo, we define five performance metrics to characterize the performance of data path 
                provisioning with GMPLS/MPLS-TE signaling. These metrics complement the metrics defined in 
                <xref target = "RFC5814"/>, in the sense that the completion of the signaling 
                process for an LSP and the programming of cross-connections along the LSP 
                may not be consistent. The performance metrics in <xref target = "RFC5814"/> 
                characterize the performance of LSP provisioning from the pure signaling point of view, while 
                the metric in this document takes into account the validity of the data path. 
        </t>
        <t>
                The five metrics are:
        </t>
        <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                <t>
                        Resv Received, Forward Data (RRFD) - the delay between
			the point when the Resv message is received by the ingress node 
			and the forward data path becomes ready for use.
                </t>
                
                <t>
                        Resv Sent, Reverse Data (RSRD) - the delay between the
			point when the Resv message is sent by the egress node and 
			the reverse data path becomes ready for use.
                </t>

                <t>
                        PATH Received, Forward Data (PRFD) - the delay between
			the point when the PATH message is received by the egress node and 
			the forward data path becomes ready for use.
                </t>
                
                <t>
                        PATH Sent, Forward Data (PSFD) - the delay between the
			point when the PATH message is sent by the ingress node 
			and the forward data path becomes ready for use.
                </t>
                
                <t>
                        PATH Sent, Reverse Data (PSRD) - the delay between the
			point when the PATH message is sent by the ingress node 
			and the reverse data path becomes ready for use.
</t>
                </list>
        </t>
        <t>
                As in <xref target = "RFC5814"/>, we continue to use the structures and notions introduced 
                and discussed in the IP Performance Metrics (IPPM) Framework documents <xref target="RFC2330"/> <xref target="RFC2679"/> 
                <xref target="RFC2681"/>.  The reader is assumed to be familiar with the notions in those documents. 
                The reader is also assumed to be familiar with the definitions in <xref target = "RFC5814"/>.
        </t>
     </section>
     
     <section title="Terms Used in This Document">
    <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                        <t>
                                        Forward data path - the data path from
					the ingress node to the egress node.  Instances of a forward data 
                                        path include the data path of a
					unidirectional LSP and a data path from the ingress node to the 
                                        egress node in a bidirectional LSP.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                        Reverse data path - the data path from the egress node to the ingress node in a bidirectional LSP. 
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                        Data path delay - the time needed to complete the data path configuration, 
                                        in relation to the signaling process. Five types of data path delay are defined in this document,
                                        namely RRFD, RSRD, PRFD, PSFD, and
					PSRD. Data path delay as used in this document must be distinguished 
                                        from the transmission delay along the data path, i.e., the time needed to transmit traffic from one 
                                        side of the data path to the other.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                        Error-free signal - data-plane-specific indication of connectivity of the data path. 
                                        For example, for interfaces capable of
					packet switching, the reception of the first error-free packet 
                                        from one side of the LSP to the other
					may be used as the error-free signal. For Synchronous Digital
					Hierarchy/Synchronous Optical Network (SDH/SONET)
                                        cross-connects, the disappearance of alarm can be used as the error-free signal. Throughout
                                        this document, we will use "error-free signal" as a general term. An implementation
                                        must choose a proper data path signal that is specific to the data path technology being tested.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                        Ingress/egress node - in this memo, an ingress/egress node means a measurement endpoint with both control plane 
                                        and data plane features. Typically, the control plane part on an ingress/egress node interacts with the control plane 
                                        of the network under test. The data plane part of an ingress/egress node will generate data path signals and 
                                        send the signal to the data plane of the network under test, or receive data path signals from the 
                                        network under test.
                        </t>
                </list>
          </t>
     </section>

    <section anchor="singleton_RRFD" title="A Singleton Definition for RRFD"> 
        <t>
                This part defines a metric for forward data path delay when an LSP is set up.  
        </t>
        <t>
                As described in <xref target="RFC6383"/>, the completion of the RSVP-TE 
                signaling process does not necessarily mean that the cross-connections along the LSP being set up are in 
                place and ready to carry traffic. This metric defines the time
		difference between the reception of a Resv 
                message by the ingress node and the completion of the cross-connection programming along the forward 
                data path.
        </t>

        <section title="Motivation">
          <t> 
                  RRFD is useful for the following reasons:
          </t>
          <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>
                                For the reasons described in <xref target="RFC6383"/>, 
                                the data path may not be ready for use instantly after the completion of the RSVP-TE 
                                signaling process. The delay itself is part of the implementation performance.
                  </t> 

                  <t>
                                The completion of the signaling process may be used by application designers as an
                                indication of data path connectivity. The existence of this delay and the potential 
                                failure of cross-connection programming, if not properly treated, will result in data 
                                loss or application failure. The typical value of this delay can thus help designers 
                                to improve the application model.
                  </t>
                </list>
  </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Metric Name">
                  <t> RRFD = Resv Received, Forward Data path
                  </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Metric Parameters">
    <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>ID0, the ingress Label Switching Router (LSR) ID</t>
                  <t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
                  <t>T, a time when the setup is attempted</t>
                </list>
          </t>
          </section>
                
          <section title="Metric Units">
                <t>
                        The value of RRFD is either a real number of
			milliseconds or undefined.
                </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Definition">
                <t>
                    For a real number dT,
		</t>
		<t>
		<list>
		<t>
			RRFD from ingress node ID0 to egress node ID1 at T is dT 
		</t>
		</list>
		</t>
		<t>
		    means that
		</t>
		<t>
		<list style="symbols">
			
                        <t>
			    ingress node ID0 sends a PATH message to 
			    egress node ID1,
			</t>
			
			<t> 
			    the last bit of the corresponding Resv message 
			    is received by ingress node ID0 at T, and
			</t>
			
			<t>
			    an error-free signal is received by egress node ID1 by 
			    using a data-plane-specific test pattern at T+dT.
			</t>
		</list>
		</t>

          </section>

          <section title="Discussion">
        <t>The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
                <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>
                                The accuracy of RRFD depends on the clock resolution of both the ingress node 
                                and egress node. Clock synchronization between the ingress node and egress node 
                                is required.
                  </t>

                  <t>
                                The accuracy of RRFD is also dependent on how the error-free signal is received 
                                and may differ significantly when the underlying data plane technology is different. 
                                For instance, for an LSP between a pair of Ethernet interfaces, the ingress node 
                                may use a rate-based method to verify the connectivity of the 
                                data path and use the reception of the first error-free frame as the error-free signal. 
                                In this case, the interval between two successive frames has a significant impact on accuracy. 
                                It is RECOMMENDED that the ingress node use small intervals, under the condition that the 
                                injected traffic does not exceed the capacity
				of the forward data path.
The value of such 
                                intervals MUST be reported.
                  </t>

              <t>
                                The accuracy of RRFD is also dependent on the time needed to propagate the error-free signal 
                                from the ingress node to the egress node. A typical value for propagating the error-free signal 
                                from the ingress node to the egress node under the same measurement setup MAY be reported. 
                                The methodology to obtain such values is outside the scope of this document.
              </t>
         <t>
             The accuracy of this metric is also dependent on the physical-layer serialization/deserialization of
             the test signal for certain data path technologies. For instance,
	     for an LSP between a pair of low-speed Ethernet interfaces, the time needed to
	     serialize/deserialize a large frame may not be
             negligible. In this case, it is RECOMMENDED that the ingress node use small frames.
             The average length of the frame MAY be reported.
         </t>

                <t>
                                It is possible that under some implementations, a node may program the cross-connection before 
                                it sends a PATH message further downstream, and the data path may be ready for use before a Resv 
                                message reaches the ingress node. In such cases, RRFD can be a negative value. It is RECOMMENDED 
                                that a PRFD measurement be carried out to further characterize the forward data path delay 
                                when a negative RRFD value is observed.
                </t>
                        
                        <t>
                                If an error-free signal is received by the
				egress node before a PATH message is sent on the ingress node, 
                                an error MUST be reported and the measurement SHOULD terminate.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                If the corresponding Resv message is received but no error-free signal is received by the 
                                egress node within a reasonable period of time, i.e., a threshold, RRFD MUST be treated as 
                                undefined. The value of the threshold MUST be reported.                        
                        </t>
                        
                        <t>
                                If the LSP setup fails, this metric value MUST NOT be counted.                 
                        </t>
                </list>
                </t>
          </section>


          <section title="Methodologies">
        <t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
                <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                        <t>
                                Make sure that the network has enough resources to set up the requested LSP.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                Start the data path measurement and/or monitoring procedures on the ingress node and 
                                egress node. If an error-free signal is received by the egress node before a PATH message is sent, 
                                report an error and terminate the measurement.
                        </t>
                        
                        <t>
                                At the ingress node, form the PATH message according to the LSP requirements and 
                                send the message towards the egress node.
                        </t>
                        
                        <t>
                                Upon receiving the last bit of the corresponding Resv message, take the timestamp 
                                (T1) on the ingress node as soon as possible.                        
                        </t>
      
                      <t>
                                When an error-free signal is observed on the egress node, take the timestamp (T2) 
                                as soon as possible. An estimate of RRFD
				(T2&nbsp;-&nbsp;T1) can be computed.
                        </t>
      
                      <t>
                                If the corresponding Resv message arrives but no error-free signal is received within 
                                a reasonable period of time by the ingress node, RRFD is deemed to be undefined.
                        </t>
                        
                     <t>
                                If the LSP setup fails, RRFD is not counted.
                        </t>
                </list>
                </t>
          </section>
          </section>

          <section anchor="singleton_RSRD" title="A Singleton Definition for RSRD"> 
          <t>
                  This part defines a metric for reverse data path delay when an LSP is set up. 
    </t>
    
    <t>
                  As described in <xref target="RFC6383"/>, the completion of the 
                RSVP-TE signaling process does not necessarily mean that the cross-connections along the LSP
                being set up are in place and ready to carry traffic. This metric defines the time difference 
                between the completion of the signaling process and the completion of the cross-connection 
                programming along the reverse data path. This metric MAY be used together with RRFD to 
                characterize the data path delay of a bidirectional LSP.
          </t>
  
          <section title="Motivation">
            <t> 
                  RSRD is useful for the following reasons:
            </t>
            <t>
                  <list style='symbols'>
                    <t>
                                  For the reasons described in <xref target="RFC6383"/>, 
                                the data path may not be ready for use instantly after the completion of the RSVP-TE signaling 
                                process. The delay itself is part of the implementation performance.
                    </t> 
                  
                    <t>
                                  The completion of the signaling process may be used by application designers as an indication 
                                of data path connectivity. The existence of
				this delay and the possible failure of cross-connection programming, if not
				properly treated, will result in data loss or application 
				failure. The typical value of this delay can thus help designers to improve the 
                                application model.
                    </t>
                  </list>
          </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Metric Name">
                    <t> RSRD = Resv Sent, Reverse Data path</t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Metric Parameters">
      <t>
                    <list style='symbols'>
                      <t>ID0, the ingress LSR ID</t>
                      <t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
                      <t>T, a time when the setup is attempted</t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
            </section>
                  
            <section title="Metric Units">
                  <t>
                          The value of RSRD is either a real number of milliseconds or undefined.
                  </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Definition">
                  <t>
		      For a real number dT, 
		  </t>
		  <t>
		      <list>
			 <t>				 
			  RSRD from ingress node ID0 to egress node ID1 at T is dT 
			 </t>
		      </list>
		  </t>
		  <t>
			  means that 
		  </t>
		  <t>
		      <list style="symbols">
			  <t>
			      ingress node ID0 sends a PATH message to egress node ID1,
			  </t>
			  <t>
			      the last bit of the corresponding Resv message is sent by egress node ID1 at T, and 
			  </t>
			  <t>
			      an error-free signal is received by the ingress node ID0 using 
			      a data-plane-specific test pattern at T+dT.                
			  </t>
		      </list>
		     </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Discussion">
      <t>The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
                  <t>
                    <list style='symbols'>
                      <t>
                                The accuracy of RSRD depends on the clock resolution of both the ingress node and egress node. 
                                Clock synchronization between the ingress node and egress node is required.
                      </t>
      
                      <t>
                              The accuracy of RSRD is also dependent on how the error-free signal is received and may differ 
                                significantly when the underlying data plane technology is different. For instance, for an LSP 
                                between a pair of Ethernet interfaces, the
				egress node (sometimes the tester) may use a rate-based method to verify the
				connectivity of the data path and use the reception of the first 
                                error-free frame as the error-free signal. In this case, the interval between two successive 
                                frames has a significant impact on accuracy. It
				is RECOMMENDED in this case that the egress 
                                node use small intervals, under the condition that the injected traffic does not exceed the 
                                capacity of the reverse data path. The value of the interval MUST be reported.
                      </t>
      
          <t>
                                The accuracy of RSRD is also dependent on the time needed to propagate the error-free signal 
                                from the egress node to the ingress node. A typical value for propagating the error-free signal 
                                from the egress node to the ingress node under the same measurement setup MAY be reported. 
                                The methodology to obtain such values is outside the scope of this document.
          </t>
          
         <t>
             The accuracy of this metric is also dependent on the physical-layer serialization/deserialization of
             the test signal for certain data path technologies. For instance,
	     for an LSP between a pair of low-speed Ethernet interfaces, the time needed to
	     serialize/deserialize a large frame may not be
             negligible. In this case, it is RECOMMENDED that the egress node use small frames.
             The average length of the frame MAY be reported.
         </t>

                      <t>
                                If the corresponding Resv message is sent but no error-free signal is received by the ingress 
                                node within a reasonable period of time, i.e., a threshold, RSRD MUST be treated as undefined. 
                                The value of the threshold MUST be reported.
                      </t>
                        <t>
                                If an error-free signal is received before a PATH message is sent on the ingress node, 
                                an error MUST be reported and the measurement SHOULD terminate.                        
                        </t>                                
          <t>
                              If the LSP setup fails, this metric value MUST NOT be counted. 
          </t>
                    </list>
      </t>
            </section>
  
                  <section title="Methodologies">
                  <t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
                          <t>
                          <list style='symbols'>
                                  <t> 
                                          Make sure that the network has enough resources to set up the requested LSP.
                                  </t>

                                  <t>
                                        Start the data path measurement and/or monitoring procedures on the ingress node and egress node. 
                                        If an error-free signal is received by the ingress node before a PATH message is sent, 
                                        report an error and terminate the measurement.
                                  </t>                                
                                  <t>
                                        At the ingress node, form the PATH message according to the LSP requirements and send 
                                        the message towards the egress node.
                                  </t>
                                  
                                  <t>
                                          Upon sending the last bit of the
					  corresponding Resv message, take the timestamp (T1) on the egress node as soon
					  as possible.
                                  </t>
                                  
                                  <t>
                                          When an error-free signal is observed on the ingress node, take the timestamp (T2) 
                                        as soon as possible. An estimate of
					RSRD (T2&nbsp;-&nbsp;T1) can be computed.
                                  </t>
         
                         <t>
                                          If the LSP setup fails, RSRD is not counted.
                                  </t>
          
                          <t>
                                        If no error-free signal is received within a reasonable period of time by 
                                        the ingress node, RSRD is deemed to be undefined.
                          </t>
                          </list>
                          </t>
                    </section>
          </section>

          <section anchor="singleton_PRFD" title="A Singleton Definition for PRFD"> 
    <t>
                  This part defines a metric for forward data path delay when an LSP is set up. 
          </t>
        
        <t>
                In an RSVP-TE implementation, when setting up an LSP, each node may choose to program the 
                cross-connection before it sends a PATH message further downstream. In this case, the forward 
                data path may become ready for use before the signaling process completes, i.e., before the Resv message
                reaches the ingress node. This metric can be used to identify
		such an implementation practice 
                and give useful information to application designers.
        </t>
        
          <section title="Motivation">
            <t> 
           PRFD is useful for the following reasons:
            </t>
            <t>
                  <list style='symbols'>
                    <t>
                        PRFD can be used to identify an RSVP-TE implementation practice in which cross-connections 
                        are programmed before a PATH message is sent
			downstream. 
                  </t>
                    <t>
                        The value of PRFD may also help application designers to fine-tune their application model.
                    </t>
                  </list>
          </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Metric Name">
                    <t> PRFD = PATH Received, Forward Data path</t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Metric Parameters">
      <t>
                    <list style='symbols'>
                      <t>ID0, the ingress LSR ID</t>
                      <t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
                      <t>T, a time when the setup is attempted</t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
            </section>
                  
            <section title="Metric Units">
                  <t>
                        The value of PRFD is either a real number of milliseconds or undefined.
                  </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Definition">
                 <t>
		      For a real number dT, 
		  </t>
		  <t>
		      <list>
			 <t>				 
			  PRFD from ingress node ID0 to egress node ID1 at T is dT 
			 </t>
		      </list>
		  </t>
		  <t>
			  means that 
		  </t>
		  <t>
		      <list style="symbols">
			  <t>
			      ingress node ID0 sends a PATH message to egress node ID1,
			  </t>
			  <t>
			      the last bit of the PATH message is received by egress node ID1 at T, and
			  </t>
			  <t>
			      an error-free signal is received by the egress node ID1 using a 
			      data-plane-specific test pattern at T+dT.
			  </t>
		      </list>
		     </t>
            </section>
  
            <section title="Discussion">
      <t>The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
                  <t>
                    <list style='symbols'>
                      <t>
                                The accuracy of PRFD depends on the clock resolution of the egress node. Clock synchronization 
                                between the ingress node and egress node is not required.
                      </t>
      
                      <t>
                                The accuracy of PRFD is also dependent on how the error-free signal is received and may differ 
                                significantly when the underlying data plane technology is different. For instance, for an LSP 
                                between a pair of Ethernet interfaces, the
				egress node (sometimes the tester) may use a rate-based method to verify the
				connectivity of the
				data path and use the reception of the first 
                                error-free frame as the error-free signal. In this case, the interval between two successive 
                                frames has a significant impact on accuracy. It
				is RECOMMENDED in this case that the ingress 
                                node use small intervals, under the condition that the injected traffic does not exceed the 
                                capacity of the forward data path. The value of the interval MUST be reported.
                      </t>
      
          <t>
                                The accuracy of PRFD is also dependent on the time needed to propagate the error-free signal 
                                from the ingress node to the egress node. A typical value for propagating the error-free signal 
                                from the ingress node to the egress node under the same measurement setup MAY be reported. 
                                The methodology to obtain such values is outside the scope of this document.
          </t>

         <t>
             The accuracy of this metric is also dependent on the physical-layer serialization/deserialization of
             the test signal for certain data path technologies. For instance,
	     for an LSP between a pair of low-speed Ethernet interfaces, the time needed to
	     serialize/deserialize a large frame may not be
             negligible. In this case, it is RECOMMENDED that the ingress node use small frames.
             The average length of the frame MAY be reported.
         </t>
                  
                  <t>
                                If an error-free signal is received before a PATH message is sent, an error MUST be reported 
                                and the measurement SHOULD terminate.                        
                  </t>
          <t>
                                If the LSP setup fails, this metric value MUST NOT be counted. 
          </t>
         
                  <t>
                                This metric SHOULD be used together with
				RRFD. It is RECOMMENDED that a PRFD measurement be
                                carried out after a negative RRFD value has already been observed.
              </t>        
        </list>
        
      </t>
            </section>
  
                  <section title="Methodologies">
                  <t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
                          <t>
                          <list style='symbols'>
                                  <t> 
                                          Make sure that the network has enough resources to set up the requested LSP.
                                  </t>

                                  <t>
                                        Start the data path measurement and/or monitoring procedures on the ingress node and egress node. 
                                        If an error-free signal is received by the egress node before a PATH message is sent, report 
                                        an error and terminate the measurement.
                                  </t>                                
                          <t>
                                        At the ingress node, form the PATH message according to the LSP requirements and 
                                        send the message towards the egress node.
                          </t>
                                  
                                  <t>
                                        Upon receiving the last bit of the PATH message, take the timestamp (T1) on 
                                        the egress node as soon as possible.
                                  </t>
                                  
                                  <t>
                                        When an error-free signal is observed on the egress node, take the timestamp (T2) 
                                        as soon as possible. An estimate of
					PRFD (T2&nbsp;-&nbsp;T1) can be computed.
                                  </t>
         
                                <t>
                                        If the LSP setup fails, PRFD is not counted.
                                </t>
          
                          <t>
                                        If no error-free signal is received within a reasonable period of 
                                        time by the egress node, PRFD is deemed to be undefined.
                          </t>
                          </list>
                          </t>
                    </section>
          </section>

                  <section anchor="singleton_PSFD" title="A Singleton Definition for PSFD"> 
            <t>
                          This part defines a metric for forward data path delay when an LSP is set up. 
                  </t>

                <t>
                        As described in <xref target = "RFC6383"/>, the
                        completion of the RSVP-TE signaling process does not necessarily mean
                        that the cross-connections along the LSP being set up are in place and
                        ready to carry traffic.  This metric defines the time
			difference between the point when the PATH message is
                        sent by the ingress node and the completion of the cross-connection 
                        programming along the LSP forward data path.

                </t>

                  <section title="Motivation">
                    <t> 
                   PSFD is useful for the following reasons:
                    </t>
                    <t>
                          <list style='symbols'>
                            <t>
                                For the reasons described in <xref target = "RFC6383"/>, 
                                the data path setup delay may not be consistent with the control plane 
                                LSP setup delay. The data path setup delay metric is more precise for LSP 
                                setup performance measurement. 
                          </t>
                            <t>
                                The completion of the signaling process may be used by application
                                designers as an indication of data path connectivity.  The difference between the control 
                                plane setup delay and data path delay, and the potential failure of cross-connection
                                programming, if not properly treated, will result in data loss or
                                application failure. This metric can thus help designers to improve the application model.
                            </t>
                          </list>
                  </t>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Metric Name">
                            <t>PSFD = PATH Sent, Forward Data path</t>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Metric Parameters">
              <t>
                            <list style='symbols'>
                              <t>ID0, the ingress LSR ID</t>
                              <t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
                              <t>T, a time when the setup is attempted</t>
                            </list>
                          </t>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Metric Units">
                          <t>
                                The value of PSFD is either a real number of milliseconds or undefined.
                          </t>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Definition">			  
			<t>
			    For a real number dT, 
			</t>
			<t>
			    <list>
				<t>				 
				    PSFD from ingress node ID0 to egress node ID1 at T is dT
				</t>
			    </list>
			</t>
			<t>
			    means that 
			</t>
			<t>
			    <list style="symbols">
				<t>
				    ingress node ID0 sends the first bit of a PATH message to egress node ID1 at T, and
				</t>
				<t>
				    an error-free signal is received by the egress node ID1 using a
				    data-plane-specific test pattern at T+dT.
				</t>
			    </list>
			</t>
                   </section>

                    <section title="Discussion">
              <t>The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
                          <t>
                            <list style='symbols'>
                              <t>
                                        The accuracy of PSFD depends on the clock resolution of both the ingress node and egress node. 
                                        Clock synchronization between the ingress node and egress node is required.
                              </t>

                              <t>
                                        The accuracy of PSFD is also dependent on how the error-free
                                        signal is received and may differ significantly when the underlying
                                        data plane technology is different.  For instance, for an LSP
                                        between a pair of Ethernet interfaces, the ingress node may use a
                                        rate-based method to verify the connectivity of the data path and
                                        use the reception of the first error-free frame as the error-free
                                        signal.  In this case, the interval between two successive frames
                                        has a significant impact on accuracy.  It is RECOMMENDED that the
                                        ingress node use small intervals, under the condition that the
                                        injected traffic does not exceed the capacity of the forward data
                                        path.  The value of the interval MUST be reported.
                              </t>

                  <t>
                                The accuracy of PSFD is also dependent on the time needed to
                                      propagate the error-free signal from the ingress node to the
                                      egress node.  A typical value for propagating the error-free signal
                                      from the ingress node to the egress node under the same
                                      measurement setup MAY be reported.  The methodology to obtain such
                                      values is outside the scope of this document.
                  </t>        

         <t>
             The accuracy of this metric is also dependent on the physical-layer serialization/deserialization of
             the test signal for certain data path technologies. For instance,
	     for an LSP between a pair of low-speed Ethernet interfaces, the time needed to
	     serialize/deserialize a large frame may not be
             negligible. In this case, it is RECOMMENDED that the ingress node use small frames.
             The average length of the frame MAY be reported.
         </t>

                          <t>
                                        If an error-free signal is received before a PATH message is sent, an error MUST be reported 
                                        and the measurement SHOULD terminate.                        
                          </t>
                  <t>
                                        If the LSP setup fails, this metric value MUST NOT be counted. 
                  </t>
                          <t>
                                        If the PATH message is sent by the ingress node but no error-free
                                      signal is received by the egress node within a reasonable period
                                      of time, i.e., a threshold, PSFD MUST be treated as undefined.
                                      The value of the threshold MUST be reported.
                         </t>
                </list>

              </t>
                    </section>

                          <section title="Methodologies">
                          <t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
                                  <t>
                                  <list style='symbols'>
                                          <t> 
                                                  Make sure that the network has enough resources to set up the requested LSP.
                                          </t>

                                          <t>
                                                Start the data path measurement and/or monitoring procedures on the ingress node and egress node. 
                                                If an error-free signal is received by the egress node before a PATH message is sent, report 
                                                an error and terminate the measurement.
                                          </t>                                
                                  <t>
                                                At the ingress node, form the PATH message according to the LSP requirements and 
                                                send the message towards the egress node. A timestamp (T1) may be stored locally in the 
                                                ingress node when the PATH message packet is sent towards the egress node.
                                                
                                  </t>
                                          <t>
                                                When an error-free signal is observed on the egress node, take the timestamp (T2) 
                                                as soon as possible. An
						estimate of PSFD (T2&nbsp;-&nbsp;T1) can be computed.
                                          </t>

                                        <t>
                                                If the LSP setup fails, PSFD is not counted.
                                        </t>

                                  <t>
                                                If no error-free signal is received within a reasonable period of 
                                                time by the egress node, PSFD is deemed to be undefined.
                                  </t>
                                  </list>
                                  </t>
                            </section>
                  </section>

                          <section anchor="singleton_PSRD" title="A Singleton Definition for PSRD"> 
                    <t>
                                  This part defines a metric for reverse data path delay when an LSP is set up. 
                          </t>

                        <t>
                                This metric defines the time difference between
				the point when the ingress node sends the PATH message and
                                the completion of the cross-connection programming along the LSP reverse 
                                data path. This metric MAY be used together with PSFD to characterize the 
                                data path delay of a bidirectional LSP.
                        </t>

                          <section title="Motivation">
                            <t> 
                           PSRD is useful for the following reasons:
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                  <list style='symbols'>
                                    <t>
                                        For the reasons described in <xref target = "RFC6383"/>, 
                                        the data path setup delay may not be consistent with the control plane 
                                        LSP setup delay. The data path setup delay metric is more precise for LSP 
                                        setup performance measurement. 
                                  </t>
                                    <t>
                                        The completion of the signaling process may be used by application
                                        designers as an indication of data path connectivity.  The difference between the control 
                                        plane setup delay and data path delay, and the potential failure of cross-connection
                                        programming, if not properly treated, will result in data loss or
                                        application failure. This metric can thus help designers to improve the application model.
                                    </t>
                                  </list>
                          </t>
                            </section>

                            <section title="Metric Name">
                                    <t>PSRD = PATH Sent, Reverse Data path</t>
                            </section>

			    <section title="Metric Parameters">
				<t>
				    <list style='symbols'>
					<t>ID0, the ingress LSR ID</t>
					<t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
					<t>T, a time when the setup is attempted</t>
				    </list>
				</t>
			    </section>

                            <section title="Metric Units">
                                  <t>
                                        The value of PSRD is either a real number of milliseconds or undefined.
                                  </t>
                            </section>

                            <section title="Definition">
				<t>
				    For a real number dT, 
				</t>
				<t>
				    <list>
					<t>				 
					    PSRD from ingress node ID0 to egress node ID1 at T is dT
					</t>
				    </list>
				</t>
				<t>
				    means that 
				</t>
				<t>
				    <list style="symbols">
					<t>
					    ingress node ID0 sends the first bit of a PATH message 
					    to egress node ID1 at T, and
					</t>
					<t>
					    an error-free signal is received through the reverse data 
					    path by the ingress node ID0 using a data-plane-specific test pattern at T+dT.
					</t>
				    </list>
				</t>
			    </section>

                            <section title="Discussion">
				<t>The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
				<t>
				    <list style='symbols'>
					<t>
					    The accuracy of PSRD depends on the clock resolution of the ingress node. 
					    Clock synchronization between the ingress node and egress node is not required.
					</t>
					
					<t>
					    The accuracy of PSRD is also dependent on how the error-free
					    signal is received and may differ significantly when the underlying
					    data plane technology is different.  For instance, for an LSP
					    between a pair of Ethernet interfaces, the egress node may use a
					    rate-based method to verify the connectivity of the data path and
					    use the reception of the first error-free frame as the error-free
					    signal.  In this case, the interval between two successive frames
					    has a significant impact on accuracy.  It is RECOMMENDED that the
					    egress node use small intervals, under the condition that the
					    injected traffic does not exceed the capacity of the forward data
					    path.  The value of the interval MUST be reported.
					</t>
					
					<t>
					    The accuracy of PSRD is also dependent on the time needed to
					    propagate the error-free signal from the egress node to the
					    ingress node.  A typical value for propagating the error-free signal
					    from the egress node to the ingress node under the same
					    measurement setup MAY be reported.  The methodology to obtain such
					    values is outside the scope of this document.
					</t>        
					
					
					<t>
					    The accuracy of this metric is also dependent on the physical-layer serialization/deserialization of
					    the test signal for certain data path technologies. For instance,
					    for an LSP between a pair of low-speed Ethernet interfaces, the time needed to
					    serialize/deserialize a large frame may not be
					    negligible. In this case, it is RECOMMENDED that the egress node use small frames.
					    The average length of the frame MAY be reported.
					</t>
					
					<t>
					    If an error-free signal is received before a PATH message is sent, an error MUST be reported 
					    and the measurement SHOULD terminate.                        
					</t>
					<t>
					    If the LSP setup fails, this metric value MUST NOT be counted. 
					</t>
					<t>
					    If the PATH message is sent by the ingress node but no error-free
					    signal is received by the ingress node within a reasonable period
					    of time, i.e., a threshold, PSRD
					    MUST be treated as undefined.
					    The value of the threshold MUST be reported.
					</t>
				    </list>
				    
				</t>
                            </section>

                                  <section title="Methodologies">
                                  <t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
                                          <t>
                                          <list style='symbols'>
                                                  <t> 
                                                          Make sure that the network has enough resources to set up the requested LSP.
                                                  </t>

                                                  <t>
                                                        Start the data path measurement and/or monitoring procedures on the ingress node and egress node. 
                                                        If an error-free signal is received by the egress node before a PATH message is sent, report 
                                                        an error and terminate the measurement.
                                                  </t>                                
                                          <t>
                                                        At the ingress node, form the PATH message according to the LSP requirements and 
                                                        send the message towards the egress node. A timestamp (T1) may be stored locally in the 
                                                        ingress node when the PATH message packet is sent towards the egress node.

                                          </t>
                                                  <t>
                                                        When an error-free signal is observed on the ingress node, take the timestamp (T2) 
                                                        as soon as possible. An
							estimate of PSRD (T2&nbsp;-&nbsp;T1) can be computed.

                                                </t>

                                                <t>
                                                        If the LSP setup fails, PSRD is not counted.
                                                </t>

                                          <t>
                                                        If no error-free signal is received within a reasonable period of 
                                                        time by the ingress node, PSRD is deemed to be undefined.
                                          </t>
                                          </list>
                                          </t>
                                    </section>
                          </section>

    <section anchor="sample_dpd" title="A Definition for Samples of Data Path Delay"> 
	<t>
	    In Sections <xref target="singleton_RRFD" format="counter"/>, <xref target="singleton_RSRD" format="counter"/>, <xref target="singleton_PRFD" format="counter"/>, 
	    <xref target="singleton_PSFD" format="counter"/>, and <xref target="singleton_PSRD" format="counter"/>,
	    we defined the singleton metrics of data path
	    delay.  Now, we define how to get one particular sample of such a delay.  
	    Sampling is done to select a particular portion of singleton values of the given parameters.
	    As in <xref target="RFC2330"/>, we use Poisson sampling as an example.
	</t>
    
	<section title="Metric Name">
	    <t>Type &lt;X&gt; data path delay sample, where X is either RRFD, RSRD, PRFD, PSFD, or PSRD.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Metric Parameters">
	    <t>
		<list style='symbols'>
		    <t>ID0, the ingress LSR ID</t>
		    <t>ID1, the egress LSR ID</t>
		    <t>T0, a time</t>
		    <t>Tf, a time</t>
		    <t>Lambda, a rate in reciprocal milliseconds</t>
		    <t>Th, the LSP holding time</t>
		    <t>Td, the maximum waiting time for successful LSP setup</t>
		    <t>Ts, the maximum waiting time for an error-free signal</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
	</section>
                    
	<section title="Metric Units">
	    <t>
		A sequence of pairs; the elements of each pair are:
	    </t>
	    <t>
		<list style='symbols'>
		    <t>T, a time when setup is attempted</t>
		    <t>dT, either a real number of milliseconds or undefined</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Definition">
	    <t>
		Given T0, Tf, and Lambda, compute a pseudo-random Poisson process beginning 
		at or before T0, with average arrival rate Lambda, and ending at or after Tf. 
		Those time values greater than or equal to T0 and less than or equal to Tf are 
		then selected. At each of the 
		times in this process, we obtain the value of a data 
		path delay sample of type &lt;X&gt; at this time. The value of the sample is 
		the sequence made up of the resulting &lt;time, type &lt;X&gt; data path delay&gt; 
		pairs. If there are no such pairs, the sequence is of length zero and the sample 
		is said to be empty.
	    </t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Discussion">
	    <t>
		The following issues are likely to come up in practice:</t>
		<t>
		    <list style='symbols'>
			<t>
			    The parameters Lambda, Th, and Td should be carefully chosen, as explained in the 
			    discussions for LSP setup delay (see <xref target="RFC5814"/>).
			</t>
			
			<t>
			    The parameter Ts should be carefully chosen and MUST be reported along with the 
			    LSP forward/reverse data path delay sample.
			</t>
			
		    </list>
		</t>
	    </section>
	    
	    <section anchor="sample_dpd_meth" title="Methodologies">
		<t>Generally, the methodology would proceed as follows:</t>
		<t>
		    <list style='symbols'>
			<t>
			    Select specific times, using the specified Poisson arrival process.
			</t>
			
			<t>
			    Set up the LSP and obtain the value of type &lt;X&gt; data path delay.
			</t>
			
			<t>
			    Release the LSP after Th, and wait for the next Poisson arrival process.
			</t>
		    </list>
		</t>
	    </section>
        
        <section title="Typical Testing Cases">                  
                    <section title="With No LSP in the Network">
                            <section title="Motivation">
                            <t>
                                                Data path delay with no LSP in the network is important because this reflects the inherent 
                                                delay of a device implementation. The minimum value provides an indication of the delay 
                                                that will likely be experienced when an LSP data path is configured under light traffic load.
                            </t>
                            </section>
                            <section title="Methodologies">
                            <t>
                                                Make sure that there is no LSP in the network, and proceed with the methodologies described in <xref target="sample_dpd_meth" />.                                    
                                        </t>
                            </section>        
                    </section>
                    <section title="With a Number of LSPs in the Network">
                            <section title="Motivation">
                            <t>
                                                Data path delay with a number of LSPs in the network is important because it reflects the performance of an 
                                                operational network with considerable load. This delay may vary significantly as the number of existing LSPs 
                                                varies. It can be used as a scalability metric of a device implementation.
                            </t>
                            </section>
                           
                            <section title="Methodologies">
                            <t>
                            <list style="symbols">
                              <t>Set up the required number of LSPs.</t>
                              <t>Wait until the network reaches a stable state.</t> 
                              <t>Then proceed with the methodologies described in <xref target="sample_dpd_meth" />.</t>
                            </list></t>
                                </section>
                                </section>
                    </section>
    </section>   

<section anchor="Statistics" title="Some Statistics Definitions for Metrics to Report">
          <t>
                  Given the samples of the performance metric, we now offer several statistics of
                  these samples to report.  From these statistics, we can draw
		  some useful conclusions regarding
                  a GMPLS network. The value of these metrics is either a real
		  number of milliseconds or undefined. In the following discussion, we
                  only consider the finite values.
          </t>
          
          <section title="The Minimum of the Metric">
                <t>
                        The minimum of the metric is the minimum of all the dT values in the sample. In computing this, 
                        undefined values SHOULD be treated as infinitely large. Note that this means that the minimum 
                        could thus be undefined if all the dT values are undefined. In addition, the metric minimum 
                        SHOULD be set to undefined if the sample is empty.
                </t>
          </section>
          
          <section title="The Median of the Metric">
                <t>
                        The median of the metric is the median of the dT values in the given sample.  In computing 
                        the median, the undefined values MUST NOT be included. The median SHOULD be set to 
                        undefined if all the dT values are undefined, or if the
			sample is empty. When the number of 
                       defined values in the given sample is small, the metric median may not be typical and 
                       SHOULD be used carefully.
                </t>
          </section>
          
          <section title="The Percentile of the Metric">
                        <t>
                                The "empirical distribution function" (EDF) of a set of scalar
                                measurements is a function F(x), which, for any x, gives the fractional
                                proportion of the total measurements that were &lt;= x.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                                Given a percentage X, the Xth percentile of the
				metric means the 
                                smallest value of x for which F(x) &gt;= X. &nbsp;In computing the percentile, 
                                undefined values MUST NOT be included.
                        </t>        
                        <t>
                                See <xref target="RFC2330"/> for further details.
                   </t>                
          </section>

          <section title="Failure Probability">
                   <t>
                        Given the samples of the performance metric, we now offer two statistics
                        of failure events of these samples to report: Failure
			Count and Failure Ratio. The two statistics can be applied
                        to both the forward data path and reverse data path. For example, when a sample of 
                        RRFD has been obtained, the forward data path failure statistics can be obtained, while
                        a sample of RSRD can be used to calculate the reverse data path failure statistics.
                        Detailed definitions of Failure Count and Failure Ratio are given below. 
                   </t>
           
                   <section title="Failure Count">
                           <t>
                                  Failure Count is defined as the number of the undefined value of the
                                  corresponding performance metric in a sample.  The value of Failure Count is an integer.
                           </t>
                   </section>
           
                   <section title="Failure Ratio">
                                <t>
                                  Failure Ratio is the percentage of the number of failure events to
                                  the total number of requests in a sample. Here, a failure event means
                                  that the signaling completes with no error, while no error-free signal is observed.
                                  The calculation for Failure Ratio is defined as follows:
                                </t>
                                <t>
                                  Failure Ratio = Number of undefined value/(Number of valid metric values 
                                  + Number of undefined value) * 100%.
                                </t>
                   </section>
          </section>
</section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
           In the control plane, since the measurement endpoints must be conformant to
           signaling specifications and behave as normal signaling endpoints, it
           will not incur security issues other than normal LSP provisioning.
           However, the measurement parameters must be carefully selected so
           that the measurements inject trivial amounts of additional traffic
           into the networks they measure.  If they inject "too much" traffic,
           they can skew the results of the measurement and in extreme cases
           cause congestion and denial of service.
        </t>

        <t>
                In the data plane, the measurement endpoint MUST use a signal that is 
                consistent with what is specified in the control plane. For example, in 
                a packet switched case, the traffic injected into the data plane MUST NOT 
                exceed the specified rate in the corresponding LSP setup request. In a 
                wavelength switched case, the measurement endpoint MUST use the specified 
                or negotiated lambda with appropriate power.    
        </t>
        
    <t>
                The security considerations pertaining to the original RSVP protocol <xref target="RFC2205"/> 
                and its TE extensions <xref target="RFC3209"/> also remain relevant.
    </t>
        </section>

   

    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title='Normative References'>
        &rfc2119;
        &rfc2205;
        &rfc2679;
        &rfc2681;
        &rfc3209;
        </references>

        <references title='Informative References'>
          &rfc2330;
          &RFC6383;
          &RFC4208;
          &RFC5814;
        </references>

        <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>
                We wish to thank Adrian Farrel, Lou Berger, and Al Morton 
                for their comments and help. We also wish to thank
                Klaas Wierenga and Alexey Melnikov for their reviews.
    </t>

    <t>
                This document contains ideas as well as text that have appeared in existing IETF documents. 
                The authors wish to thank G. Almes, S. Kalidindi, and M. Zekauskas.
    </t>
    
    <t>
                We also wish to thank Weisheng Hu, Yaohui Jin, and Wei Guo in the state key laboratory of advanced optical 
                communication systems and networks for their valuable comments.
		We also wish to thank the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)
		and the 863&nbsp;program of China for their support.
    </t>
        </section>

   <section title="Contributors">
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Bin Gu
   IXIA
   Oriental Kenzo Plaza 8M, 48 Dongzhimen Wai Street
   Dongcheng District
   Beijing  200240
   China

   Phone: +86 13611590766
   EMail: BGu@ixiacom.com


   Xueqin Wei
   Fiberhome Telecommunication Technology Co., Ltd.
   Wuhan
   China

   Phone: +86 13871127882
   EMail: xqwei@fiberhome.com.cn


   Tomohiro Otani
   KDDI R&D Laboratories, Inc.
   2-1-15 Ohara Kamifukuoka Saitama
   356-8502
   Japan

   Phone: +81-49-278-7357
   EMail: tm-otani@kddi.com


   Ruiquan Jing
   China Telecom Beijing Research Institute
   118 Xizhimenwai Avenue
   Beijing  100035
   China

   Phone: +86-10-58552000
   EMail: jingrq@ctbri.com.cn ]]></artwork></figure>

   </section>
   

    </back>

</rfc>
