<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="6642"
     submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Third-Party Loss Report">RTP Control Protocol (RTCP)
    Extension for a Third-Party Loss Report</title>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." role="editor" surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Frank Xia" initials="F." surname="Xia">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Dr., Suite 500</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX 75075</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>

        <email>xiayangsong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R." surname="Even">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>14 David Hamelech</street>

          <region>Tel Aviv 64953</region>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>even.roni@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2012"/>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Feedback Suppression, NACK, Retransmission</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In a large RTP session using the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) feedback
      mechanism defined in RFC 4585, a feedback target may experience
      transient overload if some event causes a large number of receivers to
      send feedback at once. This overload is usually avoided by ensuring that
      feedback reports are forwarded to all receivers, allowing them to avoid
      sending duplicate feedback reports. However, there are cases where it is
      not recommended to forward feedback reports, and this may allow feedback
      implosion. This memo discusses these cases and defines a new RTCP
      Third-Party Loss Report that can be used to inform receivers that the
      feedback target is aware of some loss event, allowing them to suppress
      feedback. Associated Session Description Protocol (SDP) signaling is
      also defined.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) feedback messages <xref
      target="RFC4585"/> allow the receivers in an RTP session to report
      events and ask for action from the media source (or a delegated feedback
      target when using unicast RTCP feedback with Source-Specific Multicast
      (SSM) <xref target="RFC5760"/>). There are cases where multiple
      receivers may initiate the same, or an equivalent, message towards the
      same media source or the same feedback target. When the receiver count
      is large, this behavior may cause transient overload of the media
      source, the network, or both. This is known as a "feedback storm" or a
      "NACK storm".</t>

      <t>One scenario that can cause such feedback storms involves video Fast
      Update requests. A storm of these feedback messages can occur in
      conversational multimedia scenarios like multipoint video switching
      conference <xref target="RFC4587"/>, where many receivers may
      simultaneously lose synchronization with the video stream when the
      speaker is changed in the middle of a session. Receivers that issue Fast
      Update requests (i.e., Full Intra Request (FIR) described in <xref
      target="RFC5104">RFC 5104</xref>), can cause an implosion of FIR
      requests from receivers to the same media source since these requests
      must currently be made blind, without knowledge of requests made by
      other receivers.</t>

      <t>RTCP feedback storms may cause short-term overload and, in extreme
      cases, pose a possible risk of increasing network congestion on the
      control channel (e.g., RTCP feedback), the data channel, or both. It is
      therefore desirable to provide a way of suppressing unneeded feedback.
      This document specifies a new Third-Party Loss Report for this function.
      It supplements the existing use of RTCP NACK packets and is also more
      precise in the uses where the network is active to suppress feedback. It
      tells receivers explicitly that feedback for a particular packet or
      frame loss is not needed and can provide an early indication before the
      receiver reacts to the loss and invokes its packet loss repair
      machinery. <xref target="Use"/> provides some example use cases of when
      to send the Third-Party Loss Report message.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <section title="Requirements Notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Glossary">
        <t>
          <list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="TPLR">- Third-Party Loss Report</t>

            <t hangText="TLLEI">- Transport-Layer Third-Party Loss Early
            Indication</t>

            <t hangText="PSLEI">- Payload-Specific Third-Party Loss Early
            Indication</t>



            <t hangText="PT">- Payload Type</t>

            <t hangText="FMT">- Feedback Message Type</t>

            <t hangText="FCI">- Feedback Control Information <xref
            target="RFC4585"/></t>

            <t hangText="AVPF">- Audio-Visual Profile with RTCP-based feedback
            <xref target="RFC4585"/></t>

            <t hangText="SSRC">- Synchronization Source</t>

            <t hangText="BRS">- Burst/Retransmission Source <xref
            target="RFC6285"/></t>

            <t hangText="FIR">- Full Intra Request <xref
            target="RFC5104"/></t>

            <t hangText="PLI">- Picture Loss Indication <xref
            target="RFC4585"/></t>

            <t hangText="SSM">- Source-Specific Multicast <xref
            target="RFC5760"/></t>

            <t hangText="RAMS">- Unicast-based Rapid Acquisition of Multicast
            Stream <xref target="RFC6285"/></t>

            <t hangText="MCU">- Multipoint Control Unit <xref
            target="RFC5117"/></t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Use" title="Example Use Cases">
      <t>The operation of feedback suppression is similar for all types of RTP
      sessions and topologies <xref target="RFC5117"/>; however, the exact
      messages used and the scenarios in which suppression is employed differ
      for various use cases. The following sections outline some of the
      intended use cases for using the Third-Party Loss Report for feedback
      suppression and give an overview of each. 

</t>

      <section title="Source-Specific Multicast (SSM) Use Case">
        <t>In SSM RTP sessions as described in "RTP Control Protocol (RTCP)
        Extensions for Single-Source Multicast Sessions with Unicast Feedback"
        <xref target="RFC5760"/>, one or more media sources send RTP packets
        to a distribution source. The distribution source relays the RTP
        packets to the receivers using a source-specific multicast group.</t>

        <t>As outlined in <xref target="RFC5760">RFC 5760</xref>, there are
        two Unicast Feedback models that may be used for reporting: the Simple
        Feedback Model and the Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model. In
        the Simple Feedback Model, there's no need for the distribution source
        to create the RTCP TPLRs; instead, RTCP NACKs are reflected by the
        distribution source to the other receivers. However, in the
        Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model, the distribution source
        will not redistribute the NACK for some reason (e.g., to prevent
        revealing the identity or existence of a system sending NACK) and may
        send an RTCP TPLR message to the systems that were unable to receive
        the NACK and won't receive the NACK via other means. The RTCP TPLR can
        be generated at the distribution source when downstream loss is
        reported (e.g., downstream loss report is received), which indicates
        to the receivers that they should not transmit feedback messages for
        the same loss event for a certain time. Therefore, the distribution
        source in the Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model can be
        reasonably certain that it will help the situation (i.e., the
        distribution source is unable receive the NACK) by sending this RTCP
        TPLR message to all the relevant receivers impacted by the packet
        loss.</t>


      </section>

      <section title="Unicast-Based Rapid Acquisition of Multicast Stream (RAMS) Use Case">

        <t>The typical RAMS architecture <xref target="RFC6285"/> may have
        several Burst/Retransmission Sources (BRSs) behind the multicast
        source placed at the same level. These BRSs will receive the primary
        multicast RTP stream from the media source and cache the most recent
        packets after joining the multicast session. If packet loss happens at
        the upstream of all the BRSs or the downstream of BRSs, one or all of
        the BRSs may send an RTCP NACK or RTCP TPLR message to the
        distribution source, where the SSRC in this RTCP NACK or RTCP TPLR
        message is the BRS that is sending the message. The distribution
        source forwards/reflects this message down on the primary SSM. The
        details on how the distribution source deals with this message are
        specified in <xref target="RETRANS-FOR-SSM"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RTP Transport Translator Use Case">
        <t>A Transport Translator (Topo-Trn-Translator), as defined in <xref
        target="RFC5117">RFC 5117</xref>, is typically forwarding the RTP and
        RTCP traffic between RTP clients, for example, converting from
        multicast to unicast for domains that do not support multicast. The
        translator may suffer a loss of important video packets. In this case,
        the translator may forward an RTCP TPLR message received from upstream
        in the same way it forwards other RTCP traffic. If the translator
        acting as the monitor <xref target="MONARCH"/> is aware of packet
        loss, it may use the SSRC of the monitor as the SSRC of the packet
        sender to create a NACK message and send it to the receivers that are
        not aware of packet loss.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multipoint Control Unit (MCU) Use Case">
        <t>When the speaker is changed in a voice-activated multipoint video
        switching conference <xref target="RFC4587"/>, an RTP mixer can be
        used to select the available input streams and forward them to each
        participant. If the MCU is doing a blind switch without waiting for a
        synchronization point on the new stream, it can send a FIR to the new
        video source. In this case, the MCU should send a FIR suppression
        message to the new receivers. For example, when the RTP mixer starts
        to receive FIR from some participants, it can suppress the remaining
        session participants from sending FIR by sending out an RTCP TPLR
        message.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mixer Use Case">
        <t>A mixer, in accordance with <xref target="RFC5117">RFC 5117</xref>,
        aggregates multiple RTP streams from other session participants and
        generates a new RTP stream sent to the session participants. In some
        cases, the delivery of video frames delivery may get damaged, for
        example, due to packet loss or delayed delivery, between the media
        source and the mixer. In such cases, the mixer needs to check if the
        packet loss will result in PLI or FIR transmissions from most of the
        group by analyzing the received video. If so, the mixer may initiate
        FIR or PLI towards the media source on behalf of all the session
        participants and send out an RTCP TPLR message to the session
        participants that may or are expected to send a PLI or FIR.
        Alternatively, when the mixer starts to receive FIR or PLI from some
        participants and would like to suppress the remaining session participants
        from sending FIR or PLI, it can just forward the FIR/PLI from one
        session participant to others.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Overview">
      <t>This document extends the RTCP feedback messages defined in the
      RTP/AVPF <xref target="RFC4585"/> by defining an RTCP Third-Party Loss
      Report (TPLR) message. The RTCP TPLR message can be used by the
      intermediaries to inform the receiver that the sender of the RTCP TPLR
      has received reports that the indicated packets were lost and ask the
      receiver not to send feedback to it regarding these packets. 

      Intermediaries are variously referred to as distribution sources,
      Burst/Retransmission Sources, MCUs, RTP translators, or RTP mixers,
      depending on the precise use case described <xref target="Use"/>.</t>

      <t>RTCP TPLR follows a similar message type format as RTCP NACK or Full
      Intra Request Command. However, RTCP TPLR is defined as an indication
      that the sender of the feedback has received reports that the indicated
      packets were lost, while NACK <xref target="RFC4585"/> just indicates
      that the sender of the NACK observed that these packets were lost. The
      RTCP TPLR message is generated by an intermediary that may not have seen
      the actual packet loss. It is sent following the same timing rule as
      sending NACK, defined in <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>. The
      RTCP TPLR message may be sent in a regular full compound RTCP packet or
      in an early RTCP packet, as per the RTP/AVPF rules. Intermediaries in
      the network that receive an RTCP TPLR MUST NOT send their own additional
      Third-Party Loss Report messages for the same packet sequence numbers.
      They SHOULD simply forward the RTCP TPLR message received from upstream
      to the receiver(s). Additionally, they may generate their own RTCP TPLR
      that reports a set of the losses they see, which are different from ones
      reported in the RTCP TPLR they received. The RTCP TPLR does not have
      retransmission request <xref target="RFC4588"/> semantics.</t>

      <t>When a receiver gets an RTCP TPLR message, it MUST follow the rules
      for NACK suppression in <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref> and
      refrain from sending a feedback request (e.g., NACK or FIR) for the
      missing packets reported in the message, which is dealt with in the same
      way as receiving a NACK.</t>

      <t>To increase the robustness to the loss of a TPLR, the RTCP TPLR may
      be retransmitted. If the additional TPLR arrives at the receiver, the
      receiver SHOULD deal with the additional TPLR in the same way as
      receiving the first TPLR for the same packet, and no additional behavior
      for receiver is required.</t>

      <t>A receiver may have sent a feedback message according to the RTP/AVPF
      scheduling algorithm of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref> before
      receiving an RTCP TPLR message, but further feedback messages for those
      sequence numbers SHOULD be suppressed after receiving the RTCP TPLR.
      Nodes that do not understand the RTCP TPLR message will ignore it and
      might therefore still send feedback according to the AVPF scheduling
      algorithm of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>. The media source or
      intermediate nodes cannot be certain that the use of an RTCP TPLR
      message actually reduces the amount of feedback they receive.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec4" title="Format of RTCP Feedback Messages">
      <t>This document introduces two new RTCP feedback messages for
      Third-Party Loss Report. Applications that are employing one or more
      loss- repair methods MAY use the RTCP TPLR together with their existing
      loss-repair methods either for every packet they expect to receive or
      for an application-specific subset of the RTP packets in a session.</t>

      <t>The following two sections each define an RTCP TPLR message. Both
      messages are feedback messages as defined in Section 6.1 of <xref
      target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref> and use the header format defined
      there. Each section defines how to populate the PT, FMT, length, SSRC of
      packet sender, SSRC of media source, and FCI fields in that header.</t>

      <section title="Transport-Layer Feedback: Third-Party Loss Report (TPLR)">
        <t>This TPLR message is identified by RTCP packet type values PT=RTPFB
        and FMT=7.</t>

        <t>Within the common packet header for feedback messages (as defined
        in Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>), the "SSRC
        of packet sender" field indicates the source of the request, and the
        "SSRC of media source" field denotes the media sender of the flow for
        which the indicated losses are being suppressed.</t>

        <t>The FCI field MUST contain one or more entries of Transport-Layer
        Third-Party Loss Early Indication (TLLEI). Each entry applies to the
        same media source identified by the SSRC contained in the "SSRC of
        media source" field of the Feedback header. The length field in the
        TLLEI feedback message MUST be set to N+2, where N is the number of
        FCI entries.</t>

        <t>The FCI field for TLLEI uses a similar message type format to that
        defined in the Section 6.2.1 of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC
        4585</xref>. The format is shown in <xref target="fig2"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig2"
                title="Syntax of an FCI Entry in the TLLEI Feedback Message">
          <artwork> 
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |            PID                |             BLP               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Packet ID (PID): 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The PID field is used to specify a lost packet. The PID field
            refers to the RTP sequence number of the lost packet.</t>

            <t hangText="bitmask of lost packets (BLP): 16 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1"/> The BLP allows for reporting losses of any of the
            16 RTP packets immediately following the RTP packet indicated by
            the PID. The BLP's definition is identical to that given in
            Section 6.2.1 of <xref target="RFC4585"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Payload-Specific Feedback:  Third-Party Loss Report (TPLR)">
        <t>This TPLR message is identified by RTCP packet type values PT=PSFB
        and FMT=8, which are used to suppress FIR <xref target="RFC5104"/> and
        PLI <xref target="RFC4585"/>.</t>

        <t>Within the common packet header for feedback messages (as defined
        in Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>), the "SSRC
        of packet sender" field indicates the source of the request, and the
        "SSRC of media source" is not used and SHALL be set to 0. The SSRCs of
        the media senders to which this message apply are in the corresponding
        FCI entries.</t>

        <t>The FCI field for a Payload-Specific Third-Party Loss Early
        Indication (PSLEI) consists one or more FCI entries. Each entry
        applies to a different media source, identified by its SSRC, the
        content of which is depicted in Figure 2. The length field in the
        PSLEI feedback message MUST be set to N+2, where N is the number of
        FCI entries.</t>

        <t>The format is shown in <xref target="fig3"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig3"
                title="Syntax of an FCI Entry in the PSLEI Feedback Message">
          <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                              SSRC                             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Synchronization source (SSRC): 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1"/>The SSRC value of the media source that is already
            aware, or in the process of being made aware, that some receiver
            lost synchronization with the media stream and for which the PSLEI
            receiver's own response to any such error is suppressed.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SDP Signaling">
      <t>The Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref target="RFC4566"/>
      attribute, rtcp-fb, is defined in Section 4 of <xref
      target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref> and may be used to negotiate the
      capability to handle specific AVPF commands and indications. The ABNF
      for rtcp-fb is described in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC
      4585</xref>. In this section, we extend the rtcp-fb attribute to include
      the commands and indications that are described for Third-Party Loss
      Reports in the present document.</t>

      <t>In the ABNF <xref target="RFC5234"/> for rtcp-fb-val defined in <xref
      target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>, the feedback type "nack", without
      parameters, indicates use of the Generic NACK feedback format as defined
      in Section 6.2.1 of <xref target="RFC4585">RFC 4585</xref>. In this
      document, we define two parameters that indicate the third-party loss
      supported for use with "nack", namely: <list style="symbols">
          <t>"tllei" denotes support of Transport-Layer Third-Party Loss Early
          Indication.</t>

          <t>"pslei" denotes support of Payload-Specific Third-Party Loss
          Early Indication.</t>
        </list> The ABNF for these two parameters for use with "nack" is
      defined here (please refer to Section 4.2 of <xref
      target="RFC4585">RFC4585</xref> for complete ABNF syntax).</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
   rtcp-fb-val        =/ "nack" rtcp-fb-nack-param
   rtcp-fb-nack-param = SP "tllei"
                           ;Transport-Layer Third-Party
                           ; Loss Early Indication
                       / SP "pslei"
                           ;Payload-Specific Third-Party
                           ; Loss Early Indication
                       / SP token [SP byte-string]
                           ; for future commands/indications
   token =     &lt;as defined in Section 9 of [RFC4566]&gt;
   byte-string = &lt;as defined in Section 9 of [RFC4566]&gt;
</artwork>
      </figure>


    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations documented in <xref target="RFC4585"/>
      are also applicable for the TPLR messages defined in this document.</t>

      <t>More specifically, spoofed or maliciously created TPLR feedback
      messages cause missing RTP packets to not be repaired in a timely
      fashion and add risk of (undesired) feedback suppression at RTCP
      receivers that accept such TPLR messages. Any packet loss detected by a
      receiver that also receives a TPLR message for the same missing
      packet(s) will negatively impact the application that relies on the
      (timely) RTP retransmission capabilities.</t>

      <t>A solution to prevent such attack with maliciously sent TPLR messages
      is to apply an authentication and integrity protection framework for the
      feedback messages. This can be accomplished using the RTP profile that
      combines Secure RTP <xref target="RFC3711"/> and AVPF into SAVPF <xref
      target="RFC5124"/>.</t>

      <t>Note that intermediaries that are not visible at the RTP layer that
      wish to send the Third-Party Loss Reports on behalf of the media source
      can only do so if they spoof the SSRC of the media source. This is
      difficult if SRTP is in use. If the intermediary is visible at the RTP
      layer, this is not an issue, provided the intermediary is part of the
      security context for the session.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Per this document, IANA has added two values to the '"ack" and "nack"
      Attribute Values' sub-registry <xref target="RFC4585"/> of the 'Session
      Description Protocol (SDP) Parameters' registry.</t>

<t>  The value registration for the attribute value "nack":

     <figure>
          <artwork>
   Value name:     tllei
   Long name:      Transport-Layer Third-Party Loss Early Indication
   Usable with:    nack
   Reference:      RFC 6642

   Value name:     pslei
   Long name:      Payload-Specific Third-Party Loss Early Indication
   Usable with:    nack
   Reference:      RFC 6642
     </artwork>
        </figure></t>

 <t>The following value has been registered as one FMT value in the "FMT
   Values for RTPFB Payload Types" registry (http://www.iana.org/assignments/rtp-parameters).

<figure
          align="center">
          <artwork>   
RTPFB range
Name           Long Name                         Value  Reference
-------------- --------------------------------- -----  ---------
TLLEI          Transport-Layer Third-Party         7    [RFC6642]
               Loss Early Indication
</artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The following value has been registered as one FMT value in the "FMT
Values for PSFB Payload Types" registry
(http://www.iana.org/assignments/rtp-parameters).

<figure
          align="center">
          <artwork>
PSFB range
Name            Long Name                        Value  Reference
-------------- --------------------------------- -----  ---------
PSLEI          Payload-Specific Third-Party        8    [RFC6642]
               Loss Early Indication 
</artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank David R. Oran, Magnus Westerlund,
      Colin Perkins, Ali C. Begen, Tom Van Caenegem, Francis Dupont, Ingemar
      Johansson, Bill Ver Steeg, Jonathan Lennox, and WeeSan Lee for their
      valuable comments and suggestions on this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>


    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4585"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4588"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5104"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3711"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5124"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6285"?>


      <reference anchor="MONARCH">
        <front>
          <title>Monitoring Architectures for RTP</title>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization>Huawei</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Philip Arden" initials="P." surname="Arden">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2012"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="RETRANS-FOR-SSM">
        <front>
          <title>Retransmission for Source-Specific Multicast (SSM)
          Sessions</title>

          <author fullname="Tom Caenegem" initials="T." surname="Van Caenegem">
            <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bill Ver Steeg" initials="B." surname="Ver Steeg">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Ali Begen" initials="A." surname="Begen">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5117"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4587"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5760"?>
    </references>

    <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
  </back>
</rfc>
