<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>

<rfc number="6776" category="std" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Measurement Identity and Duration">Measurement Identity and
    Information Reporting Using a Source Description (SDES) Item and an RTCP
Extended Report (XR) Block</title>

    <author fullname="Alan Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
      <organization abbrev="Telchemy">Telchemy Incorporated</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2905 Premiere Parkway, Suite 280</street>

          <city>Duluth</city>

          <region>GA</region>

          <code>30097</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>alan.d.clark@telchemy.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2012" />

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure Area</area>

    <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>Real Time Control Protocol</keyword>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that we have lowercased "block" except when it is part
of part of a Block Type Name, section title, or registry name.  Please let us
know any objections.  

Additionally, the text referred to "XR Report Blocks", which would expand as 
"Extended Report (XR) Report Block".  We have removed the seemingly redundant 
use of "Report".  Please let us know any objections. 
-->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines an RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Source
      Description (SDES) item and an RTCP Extended Report (XR) block carrying
      parameters that identify and describe a measurement period to which one
      or more other RTCP XR blocks may refer.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines one new RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Source
      Description (SDES) <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> item and one new
      Extended Report (XR) block carrying parameters that identify and
      describe a measurement period to which one or more other RTCP XR 
      blocks may refer.</t>

      <t>The SDES item provides a field for an application-specific auxiliary
      identifier. This identifier may be used to correlate data in XR blocks
      within an RTP session with data from a non-RTP session.</t>

      <t>An RTCP Measurement Identity SDES packet may be associated with a set
      of RTCP XR metrics blocks that share the same application-specific
      measurement identifier.</t>

      <t>The XR block does not contain any measurement results
      (metrics). Instead, it provides information relevant to a measurement
      reported in one or more other block types, including: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>the sequence number of the first packet of the RTP session,</t>

          <t>the extended sequence numbers of the first packet of the current
          measurement interval, and the last packet included in the
          measurement,</t>

          <t>the duration of the most recent measurement interval, and</t>

          <t>the duration of the interval applicable to cumulative
          measurements (which may be the duration of the RTP session to
          date).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The calculation method of the extended RTP sequence number is
      provided in the Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP) <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The RTCP XR block containing the measurement information is
      intended to provide a single copy of the information necessary to relate
      measurement data in the RTCP XR blocks to the stream and measurement
      period to which they refer. Commonly, multiple other small metric
      blocks contain measurement data for the same stream and period, and overhead
      would be large if all of these metric blocks carried
      duplicated data for measurement identification.</t>

      <t>The RTCP XR block may be associated with a set of RTCP XR
      metrics blocks that share the same information relevant to a reported
      measurement. There may be several such sets in an RTCP packet, in which
      each set shares the same information relevant to a reported measurement.
      There may also be RTCP XR blocks in the packet that are not associated
      with a Measurement Information block, for example, blocks that were
      defined before the Measurement Identity and information mechanism were
      introduced by this document.</t>

      <section title="RTCP and RTCP XRs">
        <t>The use of RTCP for reporting is defined in <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref>. <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> defines an
        extensible structure for reporting by using an RTCP XR.  
<xref target="RFC3611"></xref> also 
defines the use of XR blocks.  This document defines a new Extended Report
block. 
</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Performance Metrics Framework">
        <t>The Performance Metrics Framework <xref target="RFC6390"></xref>
        provides guidance on the definition and specification of performance
        metrics. The RTP Monitoring Architectures <xref
        target="MONARCH"></xref> provides guidelines for reporting block format
        using RTCP XR. The SDES item and XR block described in this document
        are in accordance with <xref target="RFC6390"></xref> and <xref
        target="MONARCH"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
        <t>The RTCP SDES item and the RTCP XR block defined in this document
        provide information relevant to the measurements for members of a
        family of RTCP XR metrics blocks that are designed to use it. To use
        the mechanism defined here, the RTCP XR block containing measurement
        information is not required to be in the same RTCP packet as the SDES
        item containing measurement identity.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <section title="Standards Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Identity SDES Item">
      <t>This section defines the format of the Measurement Identity SDES
      item. The SDES item is carried in the RTCP SDES packet. The packet
      format for the RTCP SDES is defined in Section 6.5 of <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref>. Each SDES packet is composed of a header with
      fixed-length fields for version, source count, packet type (PT), and
      length, followed by zero or more SDES items. In the SDES packet, the PT
      field is set to SDES (202).</t>

      <section title="APSI: Application-Specific Identifier SDES Item">
        <figure>
          <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    APSI=10    |     length    |application-specific identifier 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   ....
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The application-specific identifier is an additional identifier that
        is useful in the context of a specific application, e.g., an MPEG-2
        transport identifier <xref target="MPEG2"></xref>. This item MUST be
        ignored by applications that are not configured to make use of it. The
        identifier is variable length. Its length is described by the length
        field. The value of the length field does not include the two-octet
        SDES item header.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Information XR Block">
      <section title="Report Block Structure">
        <figure title="Report Block Structure">
          <artwork>
 0               1               2               3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     BT=14     |    Reserved   |      block length = 7         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    SSRC of stream source                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Reserved           |    first sequence number      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|           extended first sequence number of interval          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                 extended last sequence number                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              Measurement Duration (Interval)                  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Measurement Duration (Cumulative) - Seconds (bit 0-31)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Measurement Duration (Cumulative) - Fraction (bit 0-31)   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Definition of Fields in Measurement Information Report Block">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Block type (BT): 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />A
            Measurement Information Block is identified by the constant
            14.
</t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />These
            bits are reserved. They MUST be set to zero by senders and ignored
            by receivers. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Block Length: 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            length of this report block in 32-bit words minus one. For the
            Measurement Information Block, the block length is equal to 7.
            <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="SSRC of source: 32 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" /> As
            defined in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />These
            bits are reserved. They MUST be set to zero by senders and ignored
            by receivers. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="First sequence number: 16 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The RTP sequence number of the first received RTP
            packet of the session, used to determine the number of packets
            contributing to cumulative measurements. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t
            hangText="Extended first sequence number of interval: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The extended RTP sequence number of the first
            received RTP packet of the current measurement interval. The
            extended sequence number is expressed as the low 16-bit value
            containing the sequence number received in an RTP data packet and
            the most significant 16-bit value containing the corresponding
            count of sequence number cycles. For additional information on
            extended sequence numbers, see the "extended highest sequence number
            received" definition in Section 6.4.1 of RFC 3550 and Appendix A.1
of RFC 3550.</t>

            <t hangText="Extended last sequence number: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The extended RTP sequence number of the last
            received RTP packet that contributed to this measurement. The
            extended sequence number is expressed as the low 16-bit value
            containing the sequence number received in an RTP data packet and
            the most significant 16-bit value containing the corresponding
            count of sequence number cycles. For additional information on
            extended sequence numbers, see the "extended highest sequence number
            received" definition in Section 6.4.1 of RFC 3550 and Appendix A.1
of RFC 3550.</t>

            <t hangText="Measurement Duration (Interval): 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The duration, expressed in units of 1/65536
            seconds, of the reporting interval applicable to Interval reports
            that use this Measurement Information Block. The value of this
            field can be calculated by the receiver of the RTP media stream,
            for example, based on received RTP media packets or using the RTCP
            method described in <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>.</t>

            <t hangText="Measurement Duration (Cumulative): 64 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The duration of the reporting interval applicable
            to Cumulative reports that use this Measurement Information
            Block. The value of this field is represented using a 64-bit
            NTP-format timestamp as defined in <xref target="RFC5905"></xref>,
            which is a 64-bit unsigned fixed-point number with the integer part
            in the first 32 bits and the fractional part in the last 32 bits.
            It can be calculated by the receiver of the RTP media stream, for
            example, based on received RTP media packets or using the RTCP method
            described in <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>A new SDES item type for RTCP SDES and a new XR block type for RTCP
XR have been registered with IANA. For
      general guidelines on IANA considerations, refer to <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref> for RTCP SDES and <xref target="RFC3611" /> for
RTCP XR.</t>

      <section title="New RTCP SDES Item Type Value">
        <t>This document adds the Measurement Identity SDES item to the IANA "RTP
SDES item types" registry as follows:
        <figure>
            <artwork>
abbrev.      name                               value
APSI         Application-Specific Identifier    10
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="New RTCP XR Block Type Value">
        <t>This document assigns the block type value 14 in the IANA "RTCP XR
        Block Type Registry" to the "Measurement Information Block".</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Contact Information for Registrations">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
The contact information for the registrations is:

Qin Wu (sunseawq@huawei.com)
101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District
Nanjing, Jiangsu  210012
China
</artwork>
          </figure><vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>RTCP reports can contain sensitive information, including information
      about the nature and duration of a session established between two or
      more endpoints. Therefore, the use of security mechanisms with RTP, as
      documented in Section 9 of <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>, applies.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
 <reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17491' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5905'>

<front>
<title>Network Time Protocol Version 4: Protocol and Algorithms Specification</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Mills' fullname='D. Mills'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Martin' fullname='J. Martin' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Burbank' fullname='J. Burbank'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Kasch' fullname='W. Kasch'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is widely used to synchronize computer clocks in the Internet.  This document describes NTP version 4 (NTPv4), which is backwards compatible with NTP version 3 (NTPv3), described in RFC 1305, as well as previous versions of the protocol.  NTPv4 includes a modified protocol header to accommodate the Internet Protocol version 6 address family.  NTPv4 includes fundamental improvements in the mitigation and discipline algorithms that extend the potential accuracy to the tens of microseconds with modern workstations and fast LANs.  It includes a dynamic server discovery scheme, so that in many cases, specific server configuration is not required.  It corrects certain errors in the NTPv3 design and implementation and includes an optional extension mechanism. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5905' />
<format type='TXT' octets='241096' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5905.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC3550'>

<front>
<title>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Casner' fullname='S. Casner'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Frederick' fullname='R. Frederick'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='V. Jacobson'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This memorandum describes RTP, the real-time transport protocol.  RTP provides end-to-end network transport functions suitable for applications transmitting real-time data, such as audio, video or simulation data, over multicast or unicast network services.  RTP does not address resource reservation and does not guarantee quality-of- service for real-time services.  The data transport is augmented by a control protocol (RTCP) to allow monitoring of the data delivery in a manner scalable to large multicast networks, and to provide minimal control and identification functionality.  RTP and RTCP are designed to be independent of the underlying transport and network layers.  The protocol supports the use of RTP-level translators and mixers.  Most of the text in this memorandum is identical to RFC 1889 which it obsoletes.  There are no changes in the packet formats on the wire, only changes to the rules and algorithms governing how the protocol is used.  The biggest change is an enhancement to the scalable timer algorithm for calculating when to send RTCP packets in order to minimize transmission in excess of the intended rate when many participants join a session simultaneously. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='64' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3550' />
<format type='TXT' octets='259985' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.txt' />
<format type='PS' octets='630740' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.ps' />
<format type='PDF' octets='504117' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3550.pdf' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC3611'>

<front>
<title>RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Friedman' fullname='T. Friedman' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Caceres' fullname='R. Caceres' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='A. Clark' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines the Extended Report (XR) packet type for the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP), and defines how the use of XR packets can be signaled by an application if it employs the Session Description Protocol (SDP).  XR packets are composed of report blocks, and seven block types are defined here.  The purpose of the extended reporting format is to convey information that supplements the six statistics that are contained in the report blocks used by RTCP's Sender Report (SR) and Receiver Report (RR) packets.  Some applications, such as multicast inference of network characteristics (MINC) or voice over IP (VoIP) monitoring, require other and more detailed statistics.  In addition to the block types defined here, additional block types may be defined in the future by adhering to the framework that this document provides.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3611' />
<format type='TXT' octets='126736' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3611.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="MONARCH">
        <front>
          <title>Monitoring Architectures for RTP</title>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Philip Arden" initials="P." surname="Arden">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPEG2">
<!-- [rfced] It appears as though a third edition of this standard was 
published in October 2007.  May we refer to the updated version of the 
Standard? -->

        <front>
          <title>Standard 13818-1, Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures
and associated audio information: Systems</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6390'>

<front>
<title>Guidelines for Considering New Performance Metric Development</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Clark' fullname='A. Clark'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Claise' fullname='B. Claise'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes a framework and a process for developing Performance Metrics of protocols and applications transported over IETF-specified protocols.  These metrics can be used to characterize traffic on live networks and services.  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='170' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6390' />
<format type='TXT' octets='49930' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6390.txt' />
</reference>


    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
