<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2387 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2387.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3335 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3335.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4130 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4130.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4823 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4823.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5402 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5402.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6017 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6017.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" number="6362" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Multiple Attachments for EDIINT">Multiple Attachments for
Electronic Data Interchange - Internet&nbsp;Integration (EDIINT)</title>

    <author fullname="Kyle Meadors" initials="K.M." role="editor"
            surname="Meadors">
      <organization>Drummond Group, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Nashville</city>

          <region>Tennessee</region>

          <code>37221</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 (817) 709-1627</phone>

        <email>kyle@drummondgroup.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="August" year="2011" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>

    <keyword>EDIINT, AS2, Multiple, Attachments</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Electronic Data Interchange - Internet Integration (EDIINT)
   AS1, AS2, and AS3 messages were designed specifically for 
   the transport of EDI documents. Since multiple interchanges could be 
   placed within a single EDI document, there was not a need for sending
   multiple EDI documents in a single message. As adoption of EDIINT 
   grew, other uses developed aside from single EDI document transport. 
   Some transactions required multiple attachments to be interpreted 
   together and stored in a single message. This Informational RFC 
   describes how multiple documents, including non-EDI payloads, can be 
   attached and transmitted in a single EDIINT transport message. The 
   attachments are stored within the MIME multipart/related structure. A 
   minimal list of content-types to be supported as attachments is 
   provided.</t>
    </abstract>
    
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The primary work of the EDIINT working group (WG) was to develop a secure means of 
   transporting EDI documents over the Internet. This was described in 
   the three WG-developed standards for secure transport over 
   SMTP <xref target="RFC3335">AS1</xref>, HTTP <xref target="RFC4130">AS2</xref>, 
   and FTP <xref target="RFC4823">AS3</xref>.  For most uses of EDI, all 
   relevant information to complete a single business transaction could 
   be stored in a single document. As adoption of EDIINT grew, new 
   industries and businesses began using AS2 and also needed to include 
   multiple documents in a single message to complete a trading-partner 
   transaction. These documents were a variety of MIME media types. 
    
   This Informational RFC describes how to use the MIME 
   multipart/related body structure within EDIINT messages to store 
   multiple document attachments. Details of computing the
   message integrity check (MIC) value 
   over this body are covered. A minimum listing of MIME media types 
   to support within the multipart/related body is given along with 
   information on extracting these documents.</t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
   </section>

   <section title="Using Multiple Attachments in EDIINT">

   <section title="Multipart/Related Structure">
   <t>Multiple payload attachments for EDIINT messages are stored within a 
   multipart/related MIME body <xref target="RFC2387"/>. The multipart/related 
   structure allows multiple MIME attachments or message payloads
   to be communicated in a single structure and message.</t>

   <t>The attached payloads can be of any MIME content-type depending on 
   the trading-partner agreement, but <xref target="sup-cont-types"/>
   lists the content-types that MUST be supported. The use and format of the 
   multipart/related body follows the rules in <xref target="RFC2387">RFC 2387</xref>, including 
   the required type parameter to determine the root body part. The use 
   of the optional start parameter is RECOMMENDED.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="EDIINT-Features Header">  
   <t>To indicate support for multiple attachments (MAs), an EDIINT application
MUST use the EDIINT-Features header <xref target="RFC6017"></xref>. The EDIINT-Features
 header indicates that the
   instance application can support various features, such as 
   certification exchange. The header is present in all messages from 
   the instance application, not just those that feature certification 
   exchange.</t>

   <t>For applications implementing multiple attachments, the MA-Feature-
   Name MUST be used within the EDIINT-Features header as listed
   in this <xref target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref> syntax:</t>
    
   <t>&nbsp;&nbsp; MA-Feature-Name = "multiple-attachments"</t>

   <t>An example of the EDIINT-Features header in a message from an 
   application supporting MA:</t>
    
   <t>&nbsp;&nbsp; EDIINT-Features: multiple-attachments</t>

   </section>

   <section title="MIC Calculation">
   <t>MIC calculation in an EDIINT message with multiple attachments is 
   performed in the same manner as for a single EDI payload. The only difference 
   is calculating the message integrity check (MIC) over the whole multipart/related 
   body rather than a single EDI payload. Section 5.2.1 
   of <xref target="RFC3335">AS1</xref> and Section 4 of
   <xref target="RFC5402">EDIINT COMPRESSION</xref> describe the MIC 
   calculations used for a single payload document within an EDIINT message.
   The approach is summarized below for the multipart/related body. Refer to stated sections 
   above for more details.</t>
    
   <t>For a compressed but unsigned message, regardless of encryption, the
   MIC is calculated over the uncompressed multipart/related body
   including any applied Content-Transfer-Encoding.  The body MUST
   be canonicalized according to the procedure described in the underlying
   transport protocol (e.g., HTTP AS2 <xref target="RFC4130"/>)
   before the MIC is calculated.</t>
    
   <t>For an encrypted but unsigned and uncompressed message, the MIC is 
   calculated on the decrypted multipart/related body, including the
   header and all attached documents. The body MUST be canonicalized 
   according to the procedure described in the underlying
   transport protocol (e.g., HTTP AS2 <xref target="RFC4130"/>)
   before the MIC is calculated.</t>
    
   <t>For an unsigned and unencrypted message, the MIC is calculated over 
   the data inside the multipart/related boundaries prior to Content-
   Transfer-Encoding. However, unsigned and unencrypted messages SHOULD 
   NOT be sent due to lack of security.</t>
    
   <t>If the expected MIC value differs from the calculated MIC value, all 
   attachments MUST be considered invalid and retransmitted.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Document Processing">
   <t>Upon receipt of an EDIINT message with multiple attachments, the 
   receiving user agent MUST be able to extract the attached payloads 
   from the message rather than only removing the multipart/related 
   body from the message. The storing or processing of the documents 
   as they relate to the pending transaction is implementation 
   dependent.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Content-Types to Support" anchor="sup-cont-types">
   <t>Documents of the following MIME media types MAY be found in a 
   multipart/related body and MUST be accepted by the user agent. 
   However, any media type can be used depending upon industry need, and 
   other media types MAY be accepted depending upon the trading-partner 
   agreement. Please see <xref target="MIMEREG"/> for the definitions
   of the media types listed below.</t>

   <t><list>
   <t>application/xml</t>
   <t>application/pdf</t> 
   <t>application/msword </t>
   <t>application/rtf </t>
   <t>application/octet-stream  </t>
   <t>application/zip </t>
   <t>image/gif </t>
   <t>image/tiff </t>
   <t>image/jpeg </t>
   <t>text/plain </t>
   <t>text/html </t>
   <t>text/rtf </t>
   <t>text/xml </t>
   </list> </t>
   </section>

   </section>

   <section title="Example Message">
   <t>Below is an example AS2 message that uses two attachments. The first 
   attachment is an XML document, which is the root attachment, and the 
   second attachment is a PDF document. The content of both the XML and PDF 
   documents, as well as the applied digital signature, has 
   been omitted for size consideration. This example is provided as an 
   illustration only and is not considered part of the specification. If 
   the example conflicts with the definitions specified above or in the 
   other referenced RFCs, the example is considered invalid.</t>

   <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   POST /as2 HTTP/1.1 
   Host: www.example.com:8080 
   Connection: Close, TE 
   Message-ID: <1109712943488@10.65.122.242> 
   Subject: Multiple Attachment Example 
   Date: Tue, 01 Mar 2005 21:37:03 GMT 
   AS2-To: TradingPartner 
   AS2-From: User 
   AS2-Version: 1.2 
   EDIINT-Features: multiple-attachments 
   Disposition-Notification-To: http://www.example.com/as2 
   Disposition-Notification-Options: 
      signed-receipt-protocol=optional,pkcs7-signature; 
      signed-receipt-micalg=optional,sha-1 
   Content-type: multipart/signed; 
      protocol="application/pkcs7-signature"; micalg=sha-1; 
      boundary="OUTER-BOUNDARY" 
   Content-length: 207440 
    
   --OUTER-BOUNDARY  
   Content-type: multipart/related; boundary="INNER-BOUNDARY"; 
      start="<root.attachment>"; type="application/xml" 
    
   --INNER-BOUNDARY 
   Content-type: application/xml 
   Content-ID: <root.attachment> 
    
   [XML DOCUMENT] 
    
   --INNER-BOUNDARY 
   Content-type: application/pdf 
   Content-ID: <2nd.attachment> 
    
   [PDF DOCUMENT] 
    
   --INNER-BOUNDARY-- 
    
   --OUTER-BOUNDARY 
   Content-type: application/pkcs7-signature 
    
   [DIGITAL SIGNATURE] 
    
   --OUTER-BOUNDARY-- 
]]></artwork></figure>

   </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Multiple attachments have security concerns that are very similar to those 
   described in the three EDIINT transport standards. These include the importance
   of using strong cryptography and the necessity of using valid certificates and 
   chaining to a trusted certification authority (CA).  Please refer to these
standards -- SMTP <xref target="RFC3335">AS1</xref>, 
   HTTP <xref target="RFC4130">AS2</xref>,
   and FTP <xref target="RFC4823">AS3</xref> --
   for details of their security considerations.</t>

   <t>The only additional security consideration is that if the MIC calculation by the
   user agent differs from the expected MIC calculation, all the attached 
   documents MUST be considered invalid. Because the MIC calculation is
   over the multipart/related body, the MIC validates the content integrity of all the documents.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="MIMEREG" target="http://www.iana.org/">
<front>
<title>MIME Media Types</title>
<author initials="" surname="" fullname=""/>
<author initials="" surname="" fullname=""/>
<date month="" year=""/>
</front>
</reference>

     &RFC2119;

     &RFC2387;

     &RFC3335;

     &RFC4130;

     &RFC4823;

<reference anchor='RFC5234'>
<front>
<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Overell' fullname='P. Overell'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='68' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5234' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5402'>
<front>
<title>Compressed Data within an Internet Electronic Data Interchange (EDI) Message</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Harding' fullname='T. Harding' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='February' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5402' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6017'>
<front>
<title>Electronic Data Interchange - Internet Integration (EDIINT) Features Header Field</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Meadors' fullname='K. Meadors' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6017' />
</reference>

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
