<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2860 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2860.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC1918 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5736 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5736.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4380 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4380.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5180 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5180.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5735 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5735.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3068 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3068.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3779 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3779.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5771 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5771.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3849 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3849.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC0791 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2460 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC1122 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3927 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3927.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5737 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5737.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3879 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3879.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC919 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0919.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC922 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0922.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC1112 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1112.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4843 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4843.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2544 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2544.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4193 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>


<rfc number="6491" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr='trust200902'>

<front>
        
    <title abbrev='IANA RPKI Objects'>Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)
Objects Issued by IANA</title>

    <author initials="T" surname="Manderson" fullname="Terry Manderson">
                <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned
Names and Numbers</organization>
                <address>
                        <postal>
                                <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
                                <city>Marina del Rey</city> <region>CA</region>
                                <code>90292</code>
                                <country>United States of America</country>
                        </postal>
<phone>+1-310-823-9358</phone>
<email>terry.manderson@icann.org</email>
<uri>http://www.iana.org/</uri>
</address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="L" surname="Vegoda" fullname="Leo Vegoda">
                <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names
and Numbers</organization>
                <address>
                        <postal>
                                <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
                                <city>Marina del Rey</city> <region>CA</region>
                                <code>90292</code>
                                <country>United States of America</country>
                        </postal>
<phone>+1-310-823-9358</phone>
<email>leo.vegoda@icann.org</email>
<uri>http://www.iana.org/</uri>
</address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="S" surname="Kent" fullname="Steve Kent">
                <organization abbrev="">BBN</organization>
                <address><email>kent@bbn.com</email></address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2012" month="January" />
    <area>Routing</area>
<keyword>sidr</keyword>
<keyword>rpki</keyword>
<keyword>iana</keyword>
<keyword>as0</keyword>
<keyword>roa</keyword>

    <abstract>
    <t>This document provides specific direction to IANA as to the Resource
Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) objects it should issue.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="Intro" title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC6480">"An Infrastructure to Support Secure Internet Routing"</xref> directs 
IANA <xref target="RFC2860"></xref> to issue Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) objects for which it is authoritative. 
This document describes the objects IANA will issue. 
If IANA is directed to issue additional RPKI objects in future,
this document will be revised and a new version issued.</t>


<t>The signed objects described here that IANA will issue 
are the unallocated, reserved, special use IPv4 
and IPv6 address blocks, and the unallocated and reserved Autonomous System numbers. These number resources are managed by IANA 
for the IETF; thus, IANA bears the responsibility of issuing the 
corresponding RPKI objects. The reader is encouraged to consider the technical effects on the public 
routing system of the signed object issuance proposed for IANA in this
document.
</t>

<t>This document does not deal with <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref> routing 
systems, as those are under the policy controls of the 
organizations that operate them. Readers are directed to <xref target="TA-MGMT">"Local Trust Anchor Management for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure"</xref>
for a description of how to locally override IANA issued objects, e.g., to enable use of 
unallocated, reserved, and special use IPv4 
and IPv6 address blocks in a local context.
</t>

<t>The direction to IANA contained herein follows the ideal that it should represent the ideal technical
behavior for registry and related registry actions.</t>

</section>

<section title="Requirements Notation">
  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
  "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
  and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
  described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="reading" title="Required Reading">

<t>
Readers should be familiar with the RPKI, the RPKI repository
   structure, and the various RPKI objects, uses, and interpretations described in the following:
  <xref target="RFC6480"></xref>,
  <xref target="RFC6487"></xref>,
  <xref target="RFC6482"></xref>,
  <xref target="RFC6493"></xref>,
  <xref target="TA-MGMT"></xref>,
  <xref target="RFC6483"></xref>,
  <xref target="RPKI-USE"></xref>,
  <xref target="RFC6484"></xref>, and
  <xref target="RFC6486"></xref>.
</t>

<t>Note: The addresses used in this document are not example addresses;
therefore, they are not compliant with <xref target="RFC3849"></xref>, <xref target="RFC5735"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC5771"></xref>.  This is
intentional, as the practices described in this document are directed to specific instances of real
world addresses.</t>

</section>

<section title="Definitions">

<t>Internet Number Resources (INR): The number identifiers for IPv4 <xref
target="RFC0791"></xref> and IPv6 <xref target="RFC2460"></xref> addresses, and
for Autonomous Systems (ASes).</t>
<t>IANA: Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (a traditional name, used
   here to refer to the technical team making and publishing the
   assignments of Internet protocol technical parameters). The technical team of IANA
   is currently a part of ICANN <xref target="RFC2860"/>.</t>

<t>RPKI: Resource Public Key Infrastructure. A Public Key Infrastructure designed to provide a secure 
        basis for assertions about holdings of Internet number resources. Certificates issued under the 
        RPKI contain additional attributes that identify IPv4, IPv6, and Autonomous System number resources <xref target="RFC6480"></xref>.
</t>
        
<t>ROA: Route Origination Authorization. A ROA is an RPKI object that enables the holder of the address prefix to specify an AS that 
        is permitted to originate (in BGP) routes for that prefix <xref target="RFC6482"></xref>.</t>

<t>AS 0 ROA: A ROA containing a value of 0 in the ASID field. <xref
target="RFC6483">"Validation of Route Origination Using the Resource
Certificate Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) and Route Origination
Authorizations (ROAs)"</xref> states "A ROA with a subject of AS 0 (AS 0 ROA)
is an attestation by the holder
        of a prefix that the prefix described in the ROA, and any more specific prefix, 
        should not be used in a routing context."

</t>
        
<t>&quot;Not intended to be (publicly) routed&quot;: This phrase refers to prefixes that are not meant 
        to be represented in the global Internet routing table (for example 192.168/16 <xref target="RFC1918"></xref>).</t>

</section>

<section title="Reserved Resources">
<t>Reserved IPv4 and IPv6 resources are held back for various reasons by IETF action. 
        Generally, such resources are not intended to be globally routed. An example of such a 
        reservation is 127.0.0.0/8 <xref target="RFC5735"></xref>. See
Appendixes A and B for IANA reserved resources.</t>

<t>IANA SHOULD issue an AS 0 ROA for all reserved IPv4 and 
        IPv6 resources not intended to be routed. The selection of the <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> terminology is 
   intentional as there may be situations where the AS 0 ROA is removed or not
issued prior to an IANA registry action. It is not 
   appropriate to place IANA into a situation where, through normal internal operations, its bahavior contradicts IETF standards.</t>

        
<t>There are a small number of reserved resources that are intended to be
routed, for example 192.88.99.0/24 <xref target="RFC3068"></xref>. See 
Appendixes A and B for IANA reserved resources.</t>

<t>IANA MUST NOT issue any ROAs (AS 0 or otherwise) for reserved resources that
are expected to be globally routed.

</t>

</section>

<section title="Unallocated Resources">
<t>Internet Number Resources that have not yet been allocated for 
        special purposes <xref target="RFC5736"></xref>, to Regional
        Internet Registries (RIRs), or to others are considered as not intended to 
        be globally routed.</t>
   
   <t>IANA SHOULD issue an AS 0 ROA for all Unallocated Resources. The selection of the <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> terminology is 
   intentional as there may be situations where the AS 0 ROA is removed or not
issued prior to an IANA registry action. 

It is not 
   appropriate to place IANA into a situation where, through normal internal operations, its bahavior contradicts IETF standards.
</t>    
</section>

<section title="Special Purpose Registry Resources">
        <t>Special Registry Resources <xref target="RFC5736"></xref> fall into one of two categories in terms of routing. Either 
                the resource is intended to be seen in the global Internet 
                routing table in some fashion, or it isn't. An example of a
Special Registry Resources INR 
                that is intended for global routing is 2001::/32 <xref
target="RFC4380"></xref>.  

                An example of an INR not intended to be seen would be
2001:002::/48 <xref target="RFC5180"></xref>.
</t> 
        <t>IANA MUST NOT issue any ROAs (AS 0 or otherwise) for Special Purpose
Registry Resources that are intended to be globally routed.
</t>
        <t>IANA SHOULD issue an AS 0 ROA for Special Purpose Registry Resources
that are not intended to be globally routed.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Multicast">
        <t>Within the IPv4 multicast <xref target="RFC5771"></xref> and IPv6 multicast <xref target="RFC4291"></xref> registries 
        there are a number of Multicast registrations that are not intended to be globally routed.</t>
        <t>IANA MUST issue an AS 0 ROA covering the following IPv4 and IPv6 multicast INRs:</t>
        
                <figure><artwork>
<![CDATA[
IPv4:
        - Local Network Control Block 
           224.0.0.0 - 224.0.0.255 (224.0.0/24)
        - IANA Reserved portions of RESERVED 
           224.1.0.0-224.1.255.255 (224.1/16)
        - RESERVED 
           224.5.0.0-224.251.255.255 (251 /16s)
           225.0.0.0-231.255.255.255 (7 /8s)
                                
IPv6:
        - Node-Local Scope Multicast Addresses
        - Link-Local Scope Multicast Addresses
]]></artwork></figure>
                                
        <t>IANA MUST NOT issue any ROAs (AS 0 or otherwise) for any other
multicast addresses unless directed by an IESG-approved Standards Track 
                document with an appropriate IANA Considerations section.</t>
        
</section>


<section title="Informational Objects">
<t>One informational object that can exist at a publication point of an RPKI repository is 
        the <xref target="RFC6493">Ghostbusters Record</xref>.</t>
<t>IANA MUST issue a ghostbusters object appropriate in content for the
resources IANA maintains.

</t>

        
</section>

<section title="Certificates and Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs)">
<t>Before IANA can issue a ROA, it MUST first establish an RPKI Certification Authority (CA) that covers unallocated, 
        reserved, and special use INRs. A CA that covers these INRs MUST contain <xref target="RFC3779">RFC 3379 extensions</xref> for those corresponding number resources in its certificate.
        This CA MUST issue single-use end-entity (EE) certificates for each ROA that it generates. The EE certificate will conform to the
         <xref target="RFC6487">Resource Certificate Profile</xref> and the additional constraints specified in 
         <xref target="RFC6482"></xref>. IANA MUST maintain a publication point for this CA's use and MUST publish <xref target="RFC6486">manifests</xref> (with its corresponding EE 
        certificate) for this publication point. IANA MUST issue a CRL under this CA certificate for the EE certificates noted above. All objects issued by this CA will 
        conform to the RPKI <xref target="RFC6484">Certificate Policy</xref>.
        </t>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document directs IANA to issue, or refrain from issuing, the specific RPKI objects described 
        here for the current set of reserved, unallocated, and special registry Internet Number Resources. 
        Further, IANA MUST notify all other INR registries that RPKI objects have been issued for the Internet Number Resources
        described in this document to avoid the potential for issuance of
duplicate objects that might confuse relying parties.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>This document does not alter the security profile of the RPKI from that already discussed in SIDR-WG documents.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The authors acknowledge Dave Meyer 
        for helpful direction with regard to multicast assignments.</t>
</section>


</middle>



<back>
  
  <references title="Normative References">
        

        &RFC2119;

<!-- &I-D.ietf-sidr-arch; -->

<reference anchor='RFC6480'>
<front>
<title>An Infrastructure to Support Secure Internet Routing</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Lepinski' fullname='Matt Lepinski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Kent' fullname='Stephen Kent'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document describes an architecture for an infrastructure to
support improved security of Internet routing. The foundation of this
architecture is a resource public key infrastructure (RPKI) that represents the
allocation hierarchy of IP address space and Autonomous System (AS) Numbers;
and a distributed repository system for storing and disseminating the data
objects that comprise the RPKI, as well as other signed objects necessary for
improved routing security. As an initial application of this architecture, the
document describes how a legitimate holder of IP address space can explicitly
and verifiably authorize one or more ASes to originate routes to that address
space. Such verifiable authorizations could be used, for example, to more
securely construct BGP route filters.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6480' />

</reference>


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-roa-format; -->

<reference anchor='RFC6482'>
<front>
<title>A Profile for Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs)</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Lepinski' fullname='Matt Lepinski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Kent' fullname='Stephen Kent'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Kong' fullname='Derrick Kong'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a standard profile for Route Origin
Authorizations (ROAs).  A ROA is a digitally signed object that provides a
means of verifying that an IP address block holder has authorized an Autonomous
System (AS) to originate routes to one or more prefixes within the address
block.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6482' />

</reference>


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-ghostbusters; -->
<reference anchor='RFC6493'>
<front>
<title>The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) Ghostbusters Record</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Bush' fullname='Randy Bush'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>In the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI), resource
certificates completely obscure names or any other information which might be
useful for contacting responsible parties to deal with issues of certificate
expiration, maintenance, roll-overs, compromises, etc.  This draft describes
the RPKI Ghostbusters Record containing human contact information which may be
verified (indirectly) by a CA certificate.  The data in the record are those of
a severely profiled vCard.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6493' />

</reference>

        
<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-roa-validation; -->
<reference anchor='RFC6483'>
<front>
<title>Validation of Route Origination Using the Resource Certificate Public Key
Infrastructure (PKI) and Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs)</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Huston' fullname='Geoff Huston'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Michaelson' fullname='George Michaelson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document defines the semantics of a Route Origin
Authorization (ROA) in terms of the context of an application of the Resource
Public Key Infrastructure to validate the origination of routes advertised in
the Border Gateway Protocol.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6483' />

</reference>


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-cp; -->
<reference anchor='RFC6484'>
<front>
<title>Certificate Policy (CP) for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Kent' fullname='Stephen Kent'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Kong' fullname='Derrick Kong'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='K' surname='Seo' fullname='Karen Seo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Watro' fullname='Ronald Watro'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document describes the certificate policy for a Public Key
Infrastructure (PKI) used to support attestations about Internet Number
Resource (INR) holdings. Each organization that distributes IP addresses or
Autonomous System (AS) numbers to an organization will, in parallel, issue a
(public key) certificate reflecting this distribution. These certificates will
enable verification that the resources indicated in the certificate have been
distributed to the holder of the associated private key and that this
organization is the current, unique holder of these resources.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='173' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6484' />

</reference>


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-rpki-manifests; -->
<reference anchor='RFC6486'>
<front>
<title>Manifests for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Austein' fullname='Rob Austein'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Huston' fullname='Geoff Huston'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Kent' fullname='Stephen Kent'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Lepinski' fullname='Matt Lepinski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a "manifest" for use in the Resource Public
Key Infrastructure (RPKI).  A manifest is a signed object (file) that contains
a listing of all the signed objects (files) in the repository publication point
(directory) associated with an authority responsible for publishing in the
repository.  For each certificate, Certificate Revocation List (CRL), or other
type of signed objects issued by the authority, that are published at this
repository publication point, the manifest contains both the name of the file
containing the object, and a hash of the file content.  Manifests are intended
to enable a relying party (RP) to detect certain forms of attacks against a
repository.  Specifically, if an RP checks a manifest's contents against the
signed objects retrieved from a repository publication point, then the RP can
detect "stale" (valid) data and deletion of signed objects.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6486' />
</reference>


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs; -->
<reference anchor='RFC6487'>
<front>
<title>A Profile for X.509 PKIX Resource Certificates</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Huston' fullname='Geoff Huston'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Michaelson' fullname='George Michaelson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Loomans' fullname='Robert Loomans'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a standard profile for X.509 certificates
for the purposes of supporting validation of assertions of "right-of-use" of
Internet Number Resources (INRs).  The certificates issued under this profile
are used to convey the Issuer's authorisation of the Subject to be regarded as
the current holder of a "right-of-use" of the INRs that are described in the
certificate.  This document contains the normative specification of Certificate
and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) syntax in the Resource Public Key
Infrastructure (RPKI).  The document also specifies profiles for the format of
certificate requests.  The document also specifies the Relying Party RPKI
certificate path validation procedure.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6487' />

</reference>

        
  </references>
  
  <references title="Informative References">
        &RFC0791;
        &RFC2460;
        &RFC4193;


<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-usecases -->

<reference anchor='RPKI-USE'>
<front>
<title>Use Cases and Interpretation of RPKI Objects for Issuers and Relying Parties</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Manderson' fullname='Terry Manderson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='K' surname='Sriram' fullname='Kotikalapudi Sriram'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='White' fullname='Russ White'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document provides use cases, directions, and interpretations
for organizations and relying parties when creating or encountering RPKI object
scenarios in the public RPKI.  All of the above are discussed here in relation
to the Internet routing system.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>

<!--    &I-D.ietf-sidr-ltamgmt -->
<reference anchor='TA-MGMT'>
<front>
<title>Local Trust Anchor Management for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Reynolds' fullname='Mark Reynolds'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Kent' fullname='Stephen Kent'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document describes a facility to enable a relying party (RP)
to manage trust anchors (TAs) in the context of the Resource Public Key
Infrastructure (RPKI). It is common to allow an RP to import TA material in the
form of self-signed certificates. The facility described in this document
allows an RP to impose constraints on such TAs. Because this mechanism is
designed to operate in the RPKI context, the relevant constraints are the RFC
3779 extensions that bind address spaces and/or autonomous system (AS) numbers
to entities. The primary motivation for this facility is to enable an RP to
ensure that resource allocation information that it has acquired via some
trusted channel is not overridden by the information acquired from the RPKI
repository system or by the putative TAs that the RP imports. Specifically, the
mechanism allows an RP to specify a set of bindings between public key
identifiers and RFC 3779 extension data and will override any conflicting
bindings expressed via the putative TAs and the certificates downloaded from
the RPKI repository system. Although this mechanism is designed for local use
by an RP, an entity that is accorded administrative control over a set of RPs
may use this mechanism to convey its view of the RPKI to a set of RPs within
its jurisdiction. The means by which this latter use case is effected is
outside the scope of this document.</t></abstract> 

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>


        &RFC2860;
        &RFC1918;
        &RFC5736;
        &RFC4380;
        &RFC5180;
        &RFC5735;
        &RFC3068;
        &RFC4271;
        &RFC3779;
        &RFC4291;
        &RFC5771;
        &RFC3849;
        &RFC1122;
        &RFC3927;
        &RFC5737;
        &RFC2544;
        &RFC1112;
        &RFC919;
        &RFC922;
        &RFC3879;
        &RFC4843;
        
  </references>

<section anchor="appenA" title="IANA Reserved IPv4 Address Blocks">
<t>This list of Address Space and RFCs was correct at the time of writing this document.</t>
        
  <texttable anchor='v4_reserved' title="IPv4 Address Blocks and the RFCs that
    Direct IANA to Reserve Them">
        <ttcol align='center'>Prefix</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>RFC</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>TBR</ttcol>
        <c>0.0.0.0/8</c>  <c><xref target="RFC1122" />, Section 3.2.1.3</c><c>No</c>
        <c>10.0.0.0/8</c> <c><xref target="RFC1918" /></c><c>No</c>
        <c>127.0.0.0/8</c> <c><xref target="RFC1122" />, Section 3.2.1.3</c><c>No</c>
        <c>169.254.0.0/16</c> <c><xref target="RFC3927" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>172.16.0.0/12</c> <c><xref target="RFC1918" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>192.0.0.0/24</c> <c><xref target="RFC5736" /></c><c>Various</c>
                <c>192.0.2.0/24</c> <c><xref target="RFC5737" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>192.88.99.0/24</c> <c><xref target="RFC3068" /></c><c>Yes</c>
                <c>192.168.0.0/16</c> <c><xref target="RFC1918" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>198.18.0.0/15</c> <c><xref target="RFC2544" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>198.51.100.0/24</c> <c><xref target="RFC5737" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>203.0.113.0/24</c> <c><xref target="RFC5737" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>224.0.0.0/4</c> <c><xref target="RFC5771" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>240.0.0.0/4</c> <c><xref target="RFC1112" />, Section 4</c><c>No</c>
                <c>255.255.255.255/32</c> <c><xref target="RFC0919" />, Section
7 and <xref target="RFC0922" />, Section 7</c><c>No</c>
                <postamble>TBR: To Be Routed, the intention of the RFC pertaining to the address block.</postamble>        
    </texttable>
</section> 


<section anchor="appenB" title="IANA Reserved IPv6 Address Blocks">
        <t>This list of Address Space and RFCs was correct at the time of
writing this document.</t>
<texttable anchor='v6_reserved' title="IPv6 Address Blocks and the RFCs that
Direct IANA to Reserve Them">
        <ttcol align='center'>Prefix</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>RFC</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>TBR</ttcol>    
        <c>0000::/8</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>0100::/8</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>0200::/7</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>0400::/6</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>0800::/5</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>1000::/4</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>4000::/3</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c> 
                <c>6000::/3</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>8000::/3</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>     
                <c>A000::/3</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>     
                <c>C000::/3</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>     
                <c>E000::/4</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>F000::/5</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>     
                <c>F800::/6</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>   
                <c>FC00::/7</c> <c><xref target="RFC4193" /></c><c>No</c>     
                <c>FE00::/9</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>  
                <c>FE80::/10</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>FEC0::/10</c> <c><xref target="RFC3879" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>FF00::/8</c> <c><xref target="RFC4291" /></c><c>No</c> 
                <c>2001:0002::/48</c> <c><xref target="RFC5180" /></c><c>No</c>
                <c>2001:10::/28</c> <c><xref target="RFC4843" /></c><c>No</c>
                <postamble>TBR: To Be Routed, the intention of the RFC pertaining to the address block.</postamble>
</texttable>

</section>

</back>
</rfc>
