<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" number="6431" submissionType="independent">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Port Range IPCP Options">Huawei Port Range Configuration
    Options for PPP IP&nbsp;Control&nbsp;Protocol&nbsp;(IPCP)</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pierre Levis" initials="P." surname="Levis">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Caen</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pierre.levis@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gabor Bajko" initials="G." surname="Bajko">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
        </postal>
        <email>gabor.bajko@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Teemu Savolainen" initials="T." surname="Savolainen">
      <organization abbrev="Nokia">Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <email>teemu.savolainen@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tina Tsou" initials="T." surname="Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>
        <email>tina.tsou.zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2011" />

    <keyword>Port Range, IPv4 Address Exhaustion, IPv4 service continuity,
    IPv6, A+P</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines two Huawei IPCP (IP Control Protocol)
      options used to convey a set of ports. These options can be used in the
      context of port range-based solutions or NAT-based solutions for port
      delegation and forwarding purposes.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Within the context of IPv4 address depletion, several solutions have
      been investigated to share IPv4 addresses. Two flavors can be
      distinguished: NAT-based solutions (e.g., Carrier-Grade NAT (CGN)
      <xref target="CGN-REQS"></xref>) and port
      range-based solutions (e.g., <xref target="RFC6346"></xref> <xref
      target="PORT-RANGE-ARCH"></xref> <xref
      target="SAM"></xref>). Port range-based solutions do not
      require an additional NAT level in the service provider's domain.
      Several means may be used to convey port range information.</t>

      <t>This document defines the notion of "Port Mask", which is generic and
      flexible. Several allocation schemes may be implemented when using a
      Port Mask. It proposes a basic mechanism that allows the allocation of a
      unique port range to a requesting client. This document defines Huawei
      IPCP options to be used to carry port range information.</t>

      <t>IPv4 address exhaustion is only provided as an example of the usage
      of the PPP IPCP options defined in this document. In particular, Port
      Range options may be used independently of the presence of the
      IP-Address IPCP Option.</t>

      <t>This document adheres to the considerations defined in <xref
      target="RFC2153"></xref>.</t>

<t>
   This document is not a product of PPPEXT working group.
</t>

<t>
   Note that IPR disclosures apply to this document (see
   https://datatracker.ietf.org/ipr/).
</t>

      <section title="Use Cases">
        <t>Port Range options can be used in port range-based solutions (e.g.,
        <xref target="RFC6346"></xref>) or in a CGN-based solution. These
        options can be used in a CGN context to bypass the NAT (i.e., for
        transparent NAT traversal, and to avoid involving several NAT levels
        in the path) or to delegate one or a set of ports to the requesting
        client (e.g., to avoid the ALG (Application Level Gateway), or for
        port forwarding).</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC6346">Section 3.3.1 of</xref> specifies an example
        of usage of the options defined in this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>To differentiate between a port range containing a contiguous span
        of port numbers and a port range with non-contiguous and possibly
        random port numbers, the following denominations are used:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Contiguous Port Range: A set of port values that form a
            contiguous sequence.</t>

            <t>Non-Contiguous Port Range: A set of port values that do not
            form a contiguous sequence.</t>

            <t>Random Port Range: A cryptographically random set of port
            values.</t>
          </list>Unless explicitly mentioned, "Port Mask" refers to the tuple
        (Port Range Value, Port Range Mask).</t>

        <t>In addition, this document makes use of the following terms:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Delegated port or delegated port range: A port or a range of
            ports that belong to an IP address managed by an upstream device
            (such as NAT) and that are delegated to a client for use as the
            source address and port when sending packets.</t>

            <t>Forwarded port or forwarder port range: A port or a range of
            ports that belong to an IP address managed by an upstream device
            such as (NAT) and that are statically mapped to the internal IP
            address of the client and same port number of the client.</t>
          </list>

        This memo uses the same terminology as <xref target="RFC1661"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="values" title="Port Range Options">
      <t>This section defines the IPCP Option for port range delegation. The
      format of vendor-specific options is defined in <xref
      target="RFC2153"></xref>. Below are the values to be conveyed when the
      Port Range Option is used:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI): This field is set to
          781DBA (hex).</t>

          <t>Kind: This field is set to F0 (hex).</t>

          <t>Value(s): The content of this field is specified in Sections <xref
          target="value_1" format="counter"></xref>
          and <xref target="value_2" format="counter"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section anchor="value_1"
               title="Description of Port Range Value and Port Range Mask">
        <t>The Port Range Value and Port Range Mask are used to specify one
        range of ports (contiguous or non-contiguous) pertaining to a given IP
        address. Concretely, the Port Range Mask and Port Range Value are used to
        notify a remote peer about the Port Mask to be applied when selecting
        a port value as a source port. The Port Range Value is used to infer a
        set of allowed port values. A Port Range Mask defines a set of ports
        that all have in common a subset of pre-positioned bits. This set of
        ports is also referred to as the port range.</t>

        <t>Two port numbers are said to belong to the same port range if and
        only if they have the same Port Range Mask.</t>

        <t>A Port Mask is composed of a Port Range Value and a Port Range
        Mask:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The Port Range Value indicates the value of the significant
            bits of the Port Mask. The Port Range Value is coded as follows:
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>The significant bits may take a value of 0 or 1.</t>

                <t>All of the other bits (i.e., non-significant ones) are set
                to&nbsp;0.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The Port Range Mask indicates, by the bit(s) set to 1, the
            position of the significant bits of the Port Range Value.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This IPCP Configuration Option provides a way to negotiate the Port
        Range to be used on the local end of the link. It allows the sender of
        the Configure-Request message to state which port range associated
        with a given IP address is desired, or to request that the peer provide
        the configuration. The peer can provide this information by NAKing the
        option, and returning a valid port range (i.e., (Port Range Value,
        Port Range Mask)).</t>

        <t>If a peer issues a request enclosing the IPCP Port Range Option
        and the server does not support this option, the Port Range Option
        is rejected by the server.</t>

        <t>The set of ports conveyed in an IPCP Port Range Option applies to
        all transport protocols.</t>

        <t>The set of ports conveyed in an IPCP Port Range Option is revoked
        when the link is no longer up (e.g., when Terminate-Request and
        Terminate-Ack are exchanged).</t>

        <t>The Port Range IPCP option adheres to the format defined in
        Section&nbsp;2.1 of <xref target="RFC2153"></xref>.
        The "Value(s)" field of the option
        defined in <xref target="RFC2153"></xref> when conveying the Port Range
        IPCP Option is provided in <xref target="Figure_1"></xref>.</t>

        <figure anchor="Figure_1"
            title="Format of the Port Range IPCP Option">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |M|          Reserved           |      Port Range Value         |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |      Port Range Mask          |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Most significant bit (MSB) network order is used
          for encoding the Port Range Value and Port Range Mask fields.</postamble>
          </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>M: mode bit. The mode bit indicates the mode for which
            the port range is allocated. A value of zero indicates that
            the port ranges are delegated, while a value of 1 indicates
            that the port ranges are port-forwarded.</t>

            <t>Port Range Value (PRV): The PRV indicates the value of the
            significant bits of the Port Mask. By default, no PRV is
            assigned.</t>

            <t>Port Range Mask (PRM): The Port Range Mask indicates the
            position of the bits that are used to build the
            Port Range Value. By default, no PRM value is assigned.
            The 1 values in the Port Range Mask indicate by their
            position the significant bits of the Port Range Value.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><xref target="Figure_3"></xref> provides an example of the
        resulting port range:</t>

        <t>- The Port Range Mask is set to 0001010000000000 (5120).</t>

        <t>- The Port Range Value is set to 0000010000000000 (1024).</t>

            <figure anchor="Figure_3"
            title="Example of Port Range Mask and Port Range Value">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0| Port Range Mask
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          |   |
          |   | (two significant bits)
          v   v
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0| Port Range Value
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |x x x 0 x 1 x x x x x x x x x x| Usable ports
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+      (x may be set to 0 or 1)
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

        <t>Port values belonging to this port range must have the fourth
        bit from the left set to 0, and the sixth bit from the left set to 1.
        Only these port values will be used by the peer when enforcing the
        configuration conveyed by PPP IPCP.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Cryptographically Random Port Range Option">
        <t>A cryptographically random Port Range Option may be used as a
        mitigation tool against blind attacks such as those described
        in <xref target="RFC6056"></xref>.</t>

        <section anchor="function" title="Random Port Delegation Function">
          <t>Delegating random ports can be achieved by defining a function
          that takes as input a key 'K' and an integer 'x' within the
          1024-65535 port range and produces an output 'y' also within the
          1024-65535 port range.</t>

          <t>The cryptographic mechanism uses the 1024-65535 port range
          rather than the ephemeral range, 49152-65535, for generating
          a set of ports to optimize IPv4 address utilization efficiency
          (see "Appendix B. Address Space Multiplicative Factor" of <xref
          target="RFC6269"></xref>). This behavior is compliant with the
          recommendation to use the whole 1024-65535 port range for
          the ephemeral port selection algorithms
          (see <xref target="RFC6056">Section 3.2 of</xref>).</t>

          <t>The cryptographic mechanism ensures that the entire 64k port
          range can be efficiently distributed to multiple nodes such that
          when nodes calculate the ports, the results will never overlap with
          ports that other nodes have calculated (property of permutation), and
          ports in the reserved range (smaller than 1024) are not used. As the
          randomization is done cryptographically, an attacker seeing a node
          using some port X cannot determine which other ports the node may be
          using (as the attacker does not know the key). Calculation of the
          random port list is done as follows:</t>

          <t>The cryptographic mechanism uses an encryption function y =
          E(K,x) that takes as input a key K (for example, 128 bits) and an
          integer x (the plaintext) in the 1024-65535 port range, and
          produces an output y (the ciphertext), also an integer in the
          1024-65535 port range. This section describes one such encryption
          function, but others are also possible.</t>

          <t>The server will select the key K. &nbsp;When the server wants to
          allocate, for example, 2048 random ports, it selects a starting
          point 'a' (1024&nbsp;&lt;= a &lt;= 65536-2048) such that the port
          range (a, a+2048) does not overlap with any other active client, and
          calculates the values E(K,a), E(K,a+1), E(K,a+2), ..., E(K,a+2046),
          E(K,a+2047). These are the port numbers allocated for this node.
          Instead of sending the port numbers individually, the server just
          sends the values 'K', 'a', and '2048'. The client will then repeat
          the same calculation.</t>

          <t>The server SHOULD use a different key K for each IPv4 address it
          allocates, to make attacks as difficult as possible. This way,
          learning the key K used in IPv4 address IP1 would not help in
          attacking IPv4 address IP2 where IP2 is allocated by the same
          server to different nodes.</t>

          <t>With typical encryption functions (such as AES and DES), the
          input (plaintext) and output (ciphertext) are blocks of some fixed
          size -- for example, 128 bits for AES, and 64 bits for DES. For port
          randomization, we need an encryption function whose input and output
          is an integer in the 1024-65535 port range.</t>

          <t>One possible way to do this is to use the 'Generalized Feistel
          Cipher' <xref target="CIPHERS"></xref> construction by Black and
          Rogaway, with AES as the underlying round function.</t>

          <t>This would look as follows (using pseudo-code):</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
        def E(k, x):
            y = Feistel16(k, x)
            if y >= 1024:
                  return y
            else:
                  return E(k, y)]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Note that although E(k,x) is recursive, it is guaranteed to
          terminate. The average number of iterations is just slightly over
          1.</t>

          <t>Feistel16 is a 16-bit block cipher:</t>

          <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
        def Feistel16(k, x):
            left = x & 0xff
            right = x >> 8
            for round = 1 to 3:
                temp = left ^ FeistelRound(k, round, right))
                left = right
                right = temp
            return (right << 8) | left]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The Feistel round function uses:</t>

          <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
        def FeistelRound(k, round, x):
            msg[0] = round
            msg[1] = x
            msg[2...15] = 0
            return AES(k, msg)[0]]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Performance: To generate a list of 2048 port numbers, about
          6000 calls to AES are required (i.e., encrypting 96 kilobytes).
          Thus, it will not be a problem for any device that can do, for
          example, HTTPS (web browsing over Secure Sockets Layer/Transport
          Layer Security (SSL/TLS)).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="value_2"
             title="Description of Cryptographically Random Port Range Option">
          <figure anchor="Figure_8"
             title="Format of the Cryptographically Random Port Range Option">

              <preamble>The cryptographically random Port Range IPCP Option
              adheres to the format defined in Section 2.1 of <xref
              target="RFC2153"></xref>. The "Value(s)" field of the option
              defined in <xref target="RFC2153"></xref> when conveying the
              cryptographically random Port Range IPCP Option is illustrated
              in <xref target="Figure_8"></xref>.</preamble>

              <artwork><![CDATA[
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |M|          Reserved           |          function             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |        starting point         |   number of delegated ports   |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                             key K               ...
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ...                                                           ...
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ...                                                           ...
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ...                                                             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>M: mode bit. The mode bit indicates the mode for which
              the port range is allocated. A value of zero indicates
              that the port ranges are delegated, while a value of 1
              indicates that the port ranges are port-forwarded.</t>

              <t>Function: A 16-bit field whose value is associated with
              predefined encryption functions. This specification associates
              value 1 with the predefined function described in <xref
              target="function"></xref>.</t>

              <t>Starting Point: A 16-bit value used as an input to the
              specified function.</t>

              <t>Number of delegated ports: A 16-bit value specifying the
              number of ports delegated to the client for use as source port
              values.</t>

              <t>Key K: A 128-bit key used as input to the predefined function
              for delegated port calculation.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>
   When the option is included in the IPCP Configure-Request, the "Key
   K" and "Starting Point" fields SHALL be set to all zeros.  The
   requester MAY indicate in the "Function" field which encryption
   function the requester prefers, and in the "Number of Delegated
   Ports" field the number of ports the requester would like to obtain.
   If the requester has no preference, it SHALL also set the "Function"
   field and/or "Number of Delegated Ports" field to zero.
</t>

          <t>The usage of the option in IPCP message negotiation
          (Request/Reject/Nak/Ack) follows the logic described for Port Mask
          and Port Range options in <xref target="value_1"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Illustration Examples">
        <t></t>

        <section title="Overview">
          <t>The following flows provide examples of the usage of IPCP to
          convey the Port Range Option. As illustrated in Figures
          <xref target="Figure_4" format="counter"></xref>,
          <xref target="Figure_5" format="counter"></xref>, and
          <xref target="Figure_6" format="counter"></xref>,
          IPCP messages are exchanged between a
          Host and a BRAS (Broadband Remote Access Server).</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Successful Flow: Port Range Options Supported by Both the Client and the Server">
          <t>The following message exchange (<xref target="Figure_4"></xref>)
          depicts a successful IPCP
          configuration operation where the Port Range IPCP Option is used.</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure_4" title="Successful Flow">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
  +-----+                                          +-----+
  | Host|                                          | BRAS|
  +-----+                                          +-----+
     |                                                |
     |              (1) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=0.0.0.0            |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=0            |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=0             |
     |===============================================>|
     |                                                |
     |              (2) IPCP Configure-Nak            |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=80           |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=496           |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
     |              (3) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=80           |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=496           |
     |===============================================>|
     |                                                |
     |              (4) IPCP Configure-Ack            |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=80           |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=496           |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

          <t>The main steps of this flow are listed below:

         <list style="empty">
           <list style="format (%d)">
              <t>The Host sends a first Configure-Request,
              which includes
              the set of options it desires to negotiate. All of these
              configuration options are negotiated simultaneously. In this
              step, the Configure-Request carries information about the
              IP address, the Port Range Value, and the Port Range Mask.
              The IP-Address Option is set to 0.0.0.0, the 
              Port Range Value is set to 0, and the Port Range Mask is set
              to 0.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends back a Configure-Nak and sets
              the enclosed
              options to its preferred values. In this step, the 
              IP&nbhy;Address Option is set to a.b.c.d, the Port Range Value
              is set to 80, and the Port Range Mask is set to 496.</t>

              <t>The Host re-sends a Configure-Request
              requesting that the IP&nbhy;Address Option be set to
              a.b.c.d, the Port Range Value 
              be set to 80, and the Port Range Mask be set to 496.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends a Configure-Ack message.</t>
            </list>
          </list>

          As a result of this exchange, the Host is configured to use
          a.b.c.d as its local IP address, and the following 128 contiguous
          port ranges resulting from the Port Mask (Port Range Value == 0,
          Port Range Mask == 496):</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>- from 80 to 95</t>

              <t>- from 592 to 607</t>

              <t>- ...</t>

              <t>- from 65104 to 65119</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Port Range Option Not Supported by the Server">
          <t><xref target="Figure_5"></xref> depicts an
          exchange of messages where the BRAS does not support the
          IPCP Port Range Option.</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure_5"
            title="Failed Flow: Port Range Option Not Supported by the Server">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
  +-----+                                          +-----+
  | Host|                                          | BRAS|
  +-----+                                          +-----+
     |                                                |
     |              (1) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=0.0.0.0            |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=0            |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=0             |
     |===============================================>|
     |                                                |
     |              (2) IPCP Configure-Reject         |
     |                  PORT RANGE VALUE=0            |
     |                  PORT RANGE MASK=0             |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
     |              (3) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=0.0.0.0            |
     |===============================================>| 
     |                                                |
     |              (4) IPCP Configure-Nak            |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
     |              (5) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |===============================================>|
     |                                                |
     |              (6) IPCP Configure-Ack            |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=a.b.c.d            |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

          <t>The main steps of this flow are listed below:

          <list style="empty">
              <list style="format (%d)">
              <t>The Host sends a first Configure-Request,
              which includes
              the set of options it desires to negotiate. All of these
              configuration options are negotiated simultaneously. In this
              step, the Configure-Request carries the codes of the
              IP&nbhy;Address, Port Range Value, and Port Range Mask options.
              The IP-Address Option is set to 0.0.0.0, the Port Range Value
              is set to 0, and the Port Range Mask is set to 0.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends back a Configure-Reject to
              decline the Port Range Option.</t>

              <t>The Host sends a Configure-Request, which
              includes only
              the codes of the IP-Address Option. In this step, the
              IP&nbhy;Address Option is set to 0.0.0.0.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends back a Configure-Nak and sets
              the enclosed
              option to its preferred value. In this step, the
              IP&nbhy;Address Option is set to a.b.c.d.</t>

              <t>The Host re-sends a Configure-Request
              requesting that the IP&nbhy;Address Option be set to a.b.c.d.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends a Configure-Ack message.</t>
            </list>
          </list>

          As a result of this exchange, the Host is configured to use
          a.b.c.d as its local IP address. This IP address is not a shared IP
          address.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Port Range Option Not Supported by the Client">
          <t><xref target="Figure_6"></xref> depicts exchanges
          where only shared IP addresses are assigned to end-users' devices.
          The server is configured to assign only shared IP addresses. If Port
          Range options are not enclosed in the configuration request, the
          request is rejected, and the requesting peer will be unable to access
          the service.</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure_6"
              title="Port Range Option Not Supported by the Client">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
  +-----+                                          +-----+
  | Host|                                          | BRAS|
  +-----+                                          +-----+
     |                                                |
     |              (1) IPCP Configure-Request        |
     |                  IP ADDRESS=0.0.0.0            |
     |===============================================>|
     |                                                |
     |              (2) IPCP Protocol-Reject          |
     |<===============================================|
     |                                                |
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>The main steps of this flow are listed below:

            <list style="empty">
              <list style="format (%d)">
              <t>The Host sends a Configure-Request
              requesting that the IP&nbhy;Address
              Option be set to 0.0.0.0, and without enclosing the Port Range
              Option.</t>

              <t>The BRAS sends a Protocol-Reject message.</t>
              </list>
            </list>

          As a result of this exchange, the Host is not able to access
          the service.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce any security issues in addition to
      those related to PPP. Service providers should use authentication
      mechanisms such as the Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol
      (CHAP) <xref target="RFC1994"></xref> or PPP link
      encryption <xref target="RFC1968"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The use of small and non-random port ranges may increase host
      exposure to attacks, as described in <xref target="RFC6056"></xref>.
      This risk can be reduced by using larger port ranges, by using the
      random Port Range Option, or by activating means to improve the
      robustness of TCP against blind in-window attacks
      <xref target="RFC5961"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>Jean-Luc Grimault and Alain Villefranque contributed to this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank C. Jacquenet, J. Carlson, B.
      Carpenter, M. Townsley, and J. Arkko for their review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

<reference anchor='RFC1661'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Point-to-Point Protocol'>The Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP)</title>
<author initials='W.' surname='Simpson' fullname='William Allen Simpson' role="editor">
<organization>Daydreamer, Computer Systems Consulting Services</organization>
</author>
<date year='1994' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='51' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1661' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1968'>
<front>
<title>The PPP Encryption Control Protocol (ECP)</title>
<author initials='G.' surname='Meyer' fullname='Gerry Meyer'>
<organization>Spider Systems</organization>
</author>
<date year='1996' month='June' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1968' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1994'?>

<reference anchor='RFC2153'>
<front>
<title>PPP Vendor Extensions</title>
<author fullname='William Allen Simpson' initials='W.' surname='Simpson'>
<organization>DayDreamer, Computer Systems Consulting Services</organization>
</author>
<date year='1997' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2153' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5961'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
<!-- draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements ("I-D Exists") -->
<reference anchor='CGN-REQS'>
<front>
<title>Common requirements for Carrier Grade NAT (CGN)</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Perreault' fullname='Simon Perreault' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='Yamagata' fullname='Ikuhei Yamagata'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Miyakawa' fullname='Shin Miyakawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Nakagawa' fullname='Akira Nakagawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Ashida' fullname='Hiroyuki Ashida'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2011' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6346'>
<front>
<title>The Address plus Port (A+P) Approach to the IPv4 Address Shortage</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Bush' fullname='R. Bush' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='August' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6346' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6269'>
<front>
<title>Issues with IP Address Sharing</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Ford' fullname='M. Ford' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Boucadair' fullname='M. Boucadair'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Durand' fullname='A. Durand'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Levis' fullname='P. Levis'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Roberts' fullname='P. Roberts'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='June' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6269' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-boucadair-port-range (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='PORT-RANGE-ARCH'>
<front>
<title>IPv4 Connectivity Access in the Context of IPv4 Address Exhaustion: Port Range based IP Architecture</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohammed Boucadair' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='P' surname='Levis' fullname='Pierre Levis'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='G' surname='Bajko' fullname='Gabor Bajko'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='T' surname='Savolainen' fullname='Teemu Savolainen'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2009' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-despres-sam (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='SAM'>
<front>
<title>Scalable Multihoming across IPv6 Local-Address Routing Zones Global-Prefix/Local-Address Stateless Address Mapping (SAM)</title>
<author initials='R' surname='Despres' fullname='Remi Despres'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2009' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6056'?>

      <reference anchor="CIPHERS">
        <front>
          <title>Ciphers with Arbitrary Finite Domains.  Topics in
          Cryptology</title>
          <author fullname="John Black" initials="J." surname="Black">
            <organization>Geoff Huston</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Phillip Rogaway" initials="P." surname="Rogaway">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="CT-RSA 2002," value="Lecture Notes in Computer
Science, vol. 2271" />
      </reference>

    </references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
  </back>
</rfc>
