<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3697 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3697.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" submissionType="IETF" number="6908" consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Deployment Considerations for DS-Lite">Deployment
    Considerations for Dual-Stack Lite</title>

  

    <author fullname="Yiu L. Lee" initials="Y." surname="Lee">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

  

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>

        <email>yiu_lee@cable.comcast.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>

  
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roberta Maglione" initials="R." surname="Maglione">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>181 Bay Street</street>

  

          <city>Toronto, ON</city>

          <code>M5J 2T3</code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <email>robmgl@cisco.com</email>

  
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carl Williams" initials="C." surname="Williams">
      <organization>MCSR Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>

        <email>carlw@mcsr-labs.org</email>

  
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Jacquenet" initials="C." surname="Jacquenet">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>christian.jacquenet@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2013" />

  

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Softwire</workgroup>


    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses the deployment issues of and the
      requirements for the deployment and operation of Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite). This
      document describes the various deployment considerations and applicability 
      of the DS-Lite architecture.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="over" title="Overview">
      <t>DS-Lite <xref target="RFC6333"></xref> is a transition
      technique that enables operators to multiplex public IPv4 addresses while
      provisioning only IPv6 to users. DS-Lite is designed to continue offering
      IPv4 services while operators upgrade their networks
      incrementally to IPv6. DS-Lite combines IPv4-in-IPv6
      softwire <xref target="RFC2473"/> and Network Address Translator IPv4/IPv4 (NAT44) <xref target="RFC3022"/> to
      enable more than one user to share a public IPv4 address. </t>
      <t>
      While Appendix A of <xref
      target="RFC6333"></xref> explains how to deploy DS-Lite within specific scenarios, 
      the purpose of this document is to describe problems that arise when deploying DS-Lite 
      and what guidance should be taken to mitigate those issues.  
      The information is based on real deployment experience and is compiled in one 
      comprehensive document so that operators aren't required to search through various 
      RFCs deciding which sections are applicable and impact their DS-Lite deployment.
    </t>
    </section>

    <!-- overview  -->


    <section title="AFTR Deployment Considerations">
      <section title="Interface Consideration">
        <t>Address Family Transition Router (AFTR) is a network element
	that is deployed inside the operator's network. 
	An AFTR can be a stand-alone device or
        be embedded into a router. The AFTR is the IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel termination
        point and the NAT44 device. It is deployed at the IPv4-IPv6 network
        border where the tunnel interface is IPv6 and the external NAT44 
	interface is IPv4.  The Basic Bridging BroadBand (B4) element <xref target="RFC6333"/> 
	is a function implemented on a dual-stack-capable
        node (either a host device or a home gateway) that
        creates a tunnel to an AFTR.  Although an operator can configure both
        softwire tunnel termination and interface for NAT44 functions on a single
	physical interface (yet, keep them logically separated), there are scenarios we recommend 
	to configure two individual interfaces
        (i.e., one dedicated for IPv4 and one dedicated for IPv6) to segregate
        the functions. 
	<list style="symbols">


	<t> The access network between the B4 and AFTR is an IPv6-only network, and the network between the AFTR and IPv4 network is an IPv4-only network.
        In this deployment scenario, the AFTR interface to the IPv6-only network and 
	the interface to the 
	IPv4 network should use two physical interfaces on the AFTR.</t>

	<t> Operators may use Operations Support System (OSS) tools 
	(e.g., Multi Router Traffic Grapher) to 
	collect interface data packet count information. If
	an operator wants to separate the softwire function and NAT44 function on different 
	physical interfaces for collecting a data packet count, and the AFTR does not support
	packet count for logical interfaces, 
	they should use two physical interfaces on the AFTR.</t>
	</list>

      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="MTU and Fragmentation Considerations">
        <t>DS-Lite is part tunneling protocol. Tunneling introduces overhead
        to the packet and decreases the effective MTU size after encapsulation.
	DS-Lite users may experience problems with applications such as not being able to
        download Internet pages or transfer large files. 
        </t>
        <t>  Since fragmentation and reassembly is not optimal, the operator should do everything possible to 
             eliminate the need for it. If the operator uses simple IPv4-in-IPv6
	softwire <xref target="RFC2473"/>, it is recommended that the MTU size of the IPv6 network between the B4 and the
        AFTR accounts for the additional overhead (40 bytes). If the access network MTU size is fixed and
	cannot be changed, the operator should be aware that the B4 and the AFTR must support fragmentation as defined in
	<xref target="RFC6333"/>.   The operator should also be aware that reassembly at the Tunnel Exit-Point is resource
	intensive as a large number of B4 may terminate on the same AFTR. Scalability of the AFTR is advised in this scenario. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Logging at the AFTR">
        <t>A source-specific log is essential for backtracking specific
        hosts when a problem is identified with one of the AFTR's NAT-ed
	addresses.
	The source-specific log contains the B4 IPv6 source address, 
	transport protocol, source port, and source IPv4
	address after it has been NAT-ed. Using the source-specific log, operators can 
        uniquely identify a specific host when a DS-Lite host 
	experiences problems accessing the IPv4 network.
	To maximize IPv4 shared ratio, an operator may configure
	a short timeout value for NAT44 entries. This will result in a large number 
	of logs created by the AFTR. For operators who desire to aggregate the logs, 
	they can configure the AFTR to preallocate a range of ports to each B4. 
	This range of ports will be used in the NAT44 function, and the AFTR will
	create one log entry for the whole port range.
	This aggregation can significantly reduce the log size for 
	source-specific logging.
	</t>



	<t>Some operators may require logging both source and destination information 
	for a host's connections. This is called
	a destination-specific log. A destination-specific log contains
        the B4's IPv6 address, transport protocol, source port, source IPv4
        address after it has been NAT-ed, destination port, and destination IPv4 address.
	A destination-specific log is session-based; the operators should be 
	aware that they will 
        not be able to aggregate log entries. When using a destination-specific log, the
        operator must be careful of the large number of log entries created by
        the AFTR. Some AFTR implementations may keep the logs in their main memory. 
	This may be CPU and memory resource intensive.  The operators should configure the AFTR to periodically send logs to storage facility and then purge them from the AFTR. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Blacklisting a Shared IPv4 Address">
        <t>The AFTR is a NAT device.  It enables multiple B4s to
   share a single public IPv4 address.  <xref target="RFC6269"/> discusses some
   considerations when sharing an IPv4 address.  When a public IPv4
   address is blacklisted by a remote peer, this may affect multiple
   users or hosts.  Operators deploying DS-Lite should be aware that
   Internet hosts may not be aware that a given single IPv4 address is
   actually shared by multiple B4s.  A content provider
   might block services for a shared IPv4 address and this would then
   impact all B4s sharing this particular IPv4 address.
The operator would be likely to receive calls related to 
service outage
and would then need to take appropriate corrective actions.  <xref target="RFC6302" /> describes necessary information required to identify a user
   or host in shared address environment.  It is also worth mention that
   <xref target="NAT-REVEAL" /> analyses different approaches to identify a user or host
   in a shared address environment.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="AFTR's Policies">
        <t>There are two types of AFTR policies: 
	
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t> Outgoing Policies apply to packets originating from B4 to the AFTR. 
	  These policies should be provisioned on the AFTR's IPv6 interface that
	  is connected to the B4s.</t>


	  <t> Incoming Policies apply to packets originating from IPv4 networks to B4s.
	  These policies should be provisioned on the IPv4 interface connected to the
	  IPv4 network.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	
	<section title="Outgoing Policy">
	  <t>Outgoing Policies may include
	  Access Control List (ACL) and Quality of Service (QoS)
	  settings. These policies control the packets from B4s to the AFTR.
	  For example, the operator may configure the AFTR only to
	  accept B4 connections that originated from specific IPv6 prefixes configured
	  in the AFTR. More discussion of this use case can be found in 
	  <xref target="security"/>. An operator may configure the AFTR 
	  to give priority to the packets marked
	  by certain Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) values <xref target="RFC2475"/>. Furthermore, 
	  an AFTR may also apply an Outgoing Policy to limit the rate of port allocation
	  for a single B4's IPv6 address.</t>
	  
	  <t>Some operators offer different service level agreements (SLAs) to users
	  to meet their requirements. Some users 
	  may require more ports and some may require different service priority. In this 
	  deployment scenario, the operator can implement Outgoing Policies specified to a 
	  user's B4 or a group of B4s sharing the same policies.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Incoming Policy">
        <t> Similar to the Outgoing Policy, an Incoming Policy may also include ACL and QoS settings. 
	The Outgoing Policy controls packets coming from the IPv4 network to the B4s.
	Incoming packets are normally treated equally, so these policies are globally applied.
	For example, an operator wants to use a predefined DSCP value to signal the IPv6 access
	network to apply certain traffic policies. In this deployment scenario, the operator 
	can configure the AFTR to mark the incoming packets with the predefined DSCP value. 
	This policy will apply to all incoming packets from the IPv4 network.</t>
	</section>

      </section>
      
      <section title="AFTR Impacts on Accounting Process">
	<t>This section discusses IPv4 and IPv6 traffic accounting in the DS-Lite environment.
	In a typical broadband access scenario (e.g., DSL or Cable), the B4 is
embedded in a Residential Gateway.  The edge router for the B4s in the
provider's network is an IPv6 edge router. The edge router is usually responsible for
	IPv6 accounting and the user management functions such as
	authentication, authorization, and accounting (AAA). However, given the
	fact that IPv4 traffic is encapsulated in an IPv6 packet at the B4
	and only decapsulated at the AFTR, the edge router will require
	additional functionality to associate IPv4 accounting information to the B4
	IPv6 address. If
	DS-Lite is the only application using the IPv4-in-IPv6 protocol in the IPv6
	access network, the operator can configure the edge router
	to check the IPv6 Next Header field in the IPv6
	header, identify the protocol type (i.e., 0x04), and 
	collect IPv4 accounting information.</t>
	
	<t>Alternatively, the AFTR may perform accounting for IPv4 traffic.
	However, operators must be aware that this will introduce some
	challenges, especially in DSL deployment.  In DSL deployment, the
	AAA transaction normally happens between the edge router, i.e.,
	(BNG), and AAA server.  <xref target="RFC6333"/> does not
	require the AFTR to interact with the AAA server or edge router.
	Thus, the AFTR may not have the AAA parameters (e.g., Account Session
	ID) associated with B4s to generate an IPv4 accounting record.  IPv4
	traffic accounting at the AFTR is not recommended when the AAA
	parameters necessary to generate complete IPv4 accounting records
	are not available. 

	The accounting process at the AFTR is only
	necessary if the operator requires separating per-B4 accounting
	records for IPv4 and IPv6 traffic.  If the per-B4 IPv6 accounting
	records, collected by the edge router, are sufficient, then the
	additional complexity of enabling IPv4 accounting at the AFTR is
	not required.  It is important to notice that, since the IPv4
	traffic is encapsulated in IPv6 packets, the data collected by the
	edge router for IPv6 traffic already contains the total amount of
	traffic (i.e.,  IPv4 and IPv6).</t>
	
	<t>Even if detailed accounting records collection for IPv4 traffic
	may not be required, it would be useful for an operator, in some scenarios,
        to have information that the edge router generates 
	for the IPv6 traffic.  This information can be used to 
        identify the AFTR who is handling the IPv4 traffic for that B4.
        This can be achieved by adding additional information to the IPv6 accounting 
	records. For example, operators can use RADIUS attribute information specified in
	<xref target="RFC6519"/> or a new attribute to be specified in Internet Protocol
	Detailed Record (IPDR).</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Reliability Considerations of AFTR">
        <t>For robustness, reliability, and load distribution purposes, operators
	may deploy multiple AFTRs. In such cases, the IPv6 prefixes and algorithm to build the tunneling
mechanisms configured on each of these AFTRs will be the same.
	In <xref target="RFC6333"/>, Appendix A.3 mentions that 
	High Availability (HA) is the operator's responsibility. 
	Since DS-Lite
	is a stateful mechanism, all requirements for load-balancing and failover 
	mechanisms apply. There are many ways to implement HA in
	a stateful mechanism; the most common are
	Cold Standby mode and Hot Standby mode. More discussion on deploying  
	these two modes for NAT can be found in 
	<xref target="NAT-STANDBY"/>.
        In Cold Standby mode, the AFTR states are not replicated from the
        Primary AFTR to the Backup AFTR. When the Primary AFTR fails, all the
        existing established sessions will be flushed out. The internal hosts
        are required to reestablish sessions with the external hosts. In Hot Standby
	mode, the session's states
        are replicated on-the-fly from the Primary AFTR to the Backup AFTR. When the
        Primary AFTR fails, the Backup AFTR will take over all the existing
        established sessions. In this mode, the internal hosts are not required
        to reestablish sessions with the external hosts.</t>

	<t>For operators, the decision to use Cold Standby mode or Hot Standby mode
	depends on the trade-off between capital cost and operational cost. Cold Standby
	mode does not require a Backup Standby AFTR to synchronize session states. This
	simplifies the operational model. When the Primary AFTR goes down, any AFTR with extra
	capacity can take over. Hot Standby mode provides a smoother failover experience 
	to users; the cost for the operators is more careful failover planning.
	For most deployment scenarios, we
	believe that Cold Standby mode should be sufficient enough and is thus recommended.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Strategic Placement of AFTR">
	<t>In the DS-Lite environment, the AFTR is the logical next-hop router of the B4s
	to access the IPv4 network, so the placement of the AFTR
	will affect the traffic flows in the access network and overall network design.

	In general, there are two placement models to deploy an AFTR. Model One
	deploys the AFTR at the edge of the network to cover a small
	region. Model Two deploys the AFTR at the core of the 
	network to cover a large region. </t>

	<t>When an operator considers where to deploy the AFTR, the operator must
	make trade-offs.  The AFTR in Model One serves fewer B4s; thus, 
	it requires a less powerful AFTR. Moreover, the traffic flows are more
	evenly distributed to the AFTRs. However, it requires deploying more
	AFTRs to cover the entire network. Often, the operation cost increases
	proportionally with the amount of network equipment.</t>

	<t>The AFTR in Model Two covers a larger 
	area; thus, it serves more B4s. The operator could deploy only
	a few AFTRs to support the entire user
	base. However, this model requires a more powerful
	AFTR to sustain the load at peak hours. Since the AFTR would support
	B4s from different regions, the AFTR would be deployed closer
	to the core network.
	</t>

	<t>DS-Lite framework can be incrementally deployed. An operator may 
	consider starting with Model Two. When the demand increases, the operator can push
	the AFTR closer to the edge, which would effectively become Model One.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="AFTR Considerations for Geographically Aware Services">
        <t>By centralizing public IPv4 addresses in the AFTR, remote services can no
	longer rely on an IPv4 address and IPv4 routing information to derive 
	a host's geographical information. For example, the IPv6
	access network and the AFTR may be in two different cities. If the remote 
	services rely on the IPv4 address to locate a host, they may have
	thought the host was in a different city. <xref target="RFC6269"/> Section 7
	describes the problem in more detail. Applications could explicitly
	ask users to enter location information, such as postal code 
	or telephone number, before offering geographical service. In contrast,
	applications could use HTTP-Enabled Location Delivery (HELD) <xref target="RFC5985"/> to get the location
	information from the Location Information Server and give this information
	to the remote peer.
	<xref target="RFC6280"/>
	describes an architecture to enable location-based services.
	However, to
	mitigate the impact, we recommend that operators deploy the AFTR as close to 
	B4s as possible.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impacts on QoS Policy">
        <t>This section describes the application of <xref target="RFC2983"/> to the DS-Lite
        deployment model. Operators must
        ensure that the QoS policy that is in place operates properly within the DS-Lite
        deployment. In this regard, operators
        commonly use DSCP <xref target="RFC2475"/> to classify and prioritize 
	different types of traffic in their networks.
        DS-Lite tunnel can be seen as a particular case of uniform
        conceptual tunnel model, as described in Section 3.1 of <xref
        target="RFC2983"/>. The uniform model views an IP tunnel only as 
        a necessary mechanism to forward traffic to its destination: the
        tunnel has no significant impact on traffic conditioning. In this
        model, any packet has exactly one DSCP field that is used for traffic
        conditioning at any point, and it is the field in the outermost IP
        header. In the DS-Lite model, this is the Traffic Class field in the IPv6
        header. According to <xref target="RFC2983"/>, implementations of
        this model copy the DSCP value to the outer IP header at encapsulation
        and copy the outer header's DSCP value to the inner IP header at
        decapsulation. </t>

	<t> Operators should use this model by provisioning the network such that 
	the AFTR copies the DSCP value in the IPv4 header to the Traffic Class 
        field in the IPv6 header, after the encapsulation for the downstream traffic.
        Similarly, the B4 copies the DSCP value in the IPv4 header to the Traffic Class
        field to the IPv6 header, after the encapsulation for the upstream
        traffic. Traffic identification and classification can be done by examining
	the outer IPv6 header in the IPv6 access network.</t>

      </section>



      <section title="Port Forwarding Considerations">
        <t>Some applications behind the B4 require 
	the B4 to accept incoming requests. If the remote
	application wants to communicate to 
	the application behind the B4, 
	the remote application must know both the 
	NAT-ed IPv4 address used by the B4 and the IPv4 destination
	port.
	Some applications use Universal Plug and Play (UPnP) 
	(e.g., popular gaming consoles)
        or Interactive Community Establishment (ICE) <xref target="RFC5245"/> to request incoming ports.
	Some applications rely on Application Level Gateway (ALG) or
        manual port configuration to reserve a port in the NAT. 
	For the DS-Lite deployment scenario whereby the B4 does not own a full
IPv4 address, the operator will manage port-forwarding in the serving AFTR.
	Operators may use Port Control Protocol (PCP) <xref
        target="PCP-BASE"/>  as guidance to provide port forwarding
	service.
        Operators will deploy PCP client in the B4s. 
	PCP permits the PCP server to be deployed in a stand-alone
	server. However, we recommend that operators consider deploying the PCP
	server in the AFTR. This will ease the overhead to design a global configuration
	for the PCP server for many AFTRs because each PCP server will be dedicated to
	the collocated AFTR.</t>

	<t>When sharing an IPv4 address, not all of the ports are available to a B4.
	Some restricted ports (i.e., 0-1023) are 
	well known such as TCP port 25 and 80. Many users
	may want to be provisioned with the restricted ports.
	For fairness, we recommend that operators configure the AFTR and not
	allocate the restricted ports to regular DS-Lite B4s.
	This operation model ensures that
	DS-Lite B4s will have uniform configuration, which can simplify 
	provisioning and operation.
	For users who want to use the restricted ports, 
	operators can consider provisioning a full IPv4 address
	to those users' B4s. If an operator still wants to provision restricted ports to 
	specific B4s, it may require implementing a static B4's configuration in 
	the AFTR
	to match the B4's IPv6 address to the NAT rules. Alternatively, the B4
	may dynamically allocate the ports, and the AFTR authenticates the session's request
	using PCP <xref target="PCP-BASE"/>.
	</t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="security" title="DS-Lite Tunnel Security ">
        <t><xref target="RFC6333"/>, Section 11 describes security
	issues associated with the DS-Lite mechanism. To restrict the service offered by the AFTR
        only to registered B4s, an operator can implement the Outgoing Policy on
        the AFTR's tunnel interface to accept only the IPv6 prefixes
        defined in the policy. For static provisioning, the operator will 
	need to know in advance the
        IPv6 prefixes provisioned to the B4s for the softwire in order to 
	configure the policy. To simplify operation, operators should configure 
	the AFTRs in the same region with the same IPv6 prefixes' Outgoing Policy. 
	The AFTRs
	will accept both regular connections and failover connections from the B4s 
	in the same service region.</t>
      </section>

     <section title="IPv6-Only Network Considerations ">
        <t>In environments where the operator wants to deploy the AFTR 
        in an IPv6-only network, the AFTR nodes may not have direct IPv4 
        connectivity.  In this scenario, the operator extends the 
        IPv6-only boundary to the border of the network and only the border 
	routers have IPv4 connectivity.
        For both scalability and performance purposes, the AFTR is located in the 
	IPv6-only network closer to B4s.
	In this scenario, the AFTR has only IPv6 connectivity
        and must be able to send and receive IPv4 packets.  Enhancements to the DS-Lite
        AFTR are required to achieve this.  <xref
        target="DS-LITE"/> describes such issues and 
        enhancements to DS-Lite in IPv6-only deployments. </t>
     </section>

    </section>

    <section title="B4 Deployment Considerations">
      <t>In order to configure the IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel, the B4 needs
      the IPv6 address of the AFTR. This IPv6 address can be
      configured using a variety of methods ranging from an out-of-band
      mechanism, manual configuration, and DHCPv6 option to RADIUS. If an
      operator uses DHCPv6 to provision the B4, the B4 must implement
      the DHCPv6
      option defined in <xref target="RFC6334"/>. If an operator uses 
      RADIUS to provision the B4, the B4 must implement 
      <xref target="RFC6519"/>.</t>

      <section title="DNS Deployment Considerations">
        <t><xref target="RFC6333"/> recommends that the B4 send DNS
        queries to an external recursive resolver over IPv6. The B4 should
	implement a proxy resolver that will proxy a DNS query from IPv4 transport to 
	the DNS server in the IPv6 network. <xref target="RFC6333"/> does not describe
	the DNS proxy behavior. In deployment, the operator must ensure that the 
	DNS proxy implementation must follow <xref target="RFC5625"/>. This is
	important especially for operators who have deployed, or will consider deploying,
	DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4035"/>.</t>

	<t>Some operators may want to give hosts
behind the B4 an IPv4 address of an external DNS recursive resolver. The B4 will treat the DNS packets as normal
	IP packets and forward them over the softwire.
	Note that
        there is no effective way to provision an IPv4 DNS address to the B4 over
	IPv6; operators who use this DNS deployment model must be aware that 
	how to provision an IPv4 DNS address over an IPv6 network is undefined, so it will introduce
	additional complexity in B4 provisioning.
	Moreover, this will increase the load to the AFTR by creating entries in the NAT 
	table for DNS sessions. Operators may deploy a local DNS caching resolver in the AFTR
	to reduce the load in the NAT table. Nonetheless, this DNS model is not covered in 
	<xref target="RFC6333"/> and is not recommended. </t>
      </section>


      <section title="IPv4 Service Monitoring">
	<section title="B4 Remote Management">
	  <t>B4 is connected to the IPv6 access network to offer IPv4 services. When
	  users experience IPv4 connectivity issues, operators must be able to
	  remotely access (e.g., TR-069) the B4 to verify its configuration
	  and status. Operators should access B4s using native IPv6.
	  Operators should not access B4 over the softwire.
	  </t>
	</section>


	<section title="IPv4 Connectivity Check">
	  <t>The DS-Lite framework provides IPv4 services over the IPv6 access network. 
	  Operators and users must be able to check the IPv4 connectivity from the B4
	  to its AFTR using ping and IPv4 traceroute. The AFTR should 
	  be configured with an IPv4 address 
	  to enable a PING test and a Traceroute test.  Operators should assign the same IPv4 address
	  (e.g., 192.0.0.2/32 <xref target="RFC6333"/>) to all AFTRs.  IANA has allocated
	  the 192.0.0.0/29 network prefix to provide IPv4 addresses for this
	  purpose [RFC6333].</t>
	</section>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not present any new security issues. <xref
      target="RFC6333"/> discusses DS-Lite
      related security issues.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Mr. Nejc Skoberne and Dr. Maoke Chen for their thorough 
      review and 
      helpful comments. We also want to thank Mr. Hu Jie for sharing his DS-Lite
      deployment experience with us. He gave us recommendations of what his company
      learned while testing DS-Lite in the production network.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6333'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6519'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6334'?> 
    </references>


    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2473'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2475'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2983'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3022'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4035'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5245'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5625'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5985'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6269'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6280'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6302'?>

<!--draft-ietf-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis-04; Active -->

<reference anchor='NAT-REVEAL'>
<front>
<title>Analysis of Solution Candidates to Reveal a Host Identifier (HOST_ID) in Shared Address Deployments</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohamed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Touch' fullname='Joseph Touch'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Levis' fullname='Pierre Levis'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Penno' fullname='Reinaldo Penno'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='13' year='2013' />

<abstract><t>This document is a collection of solutions to reveal a host identifier (denoted as HOST_ID) when a Carrier Grade NAT (CGN) or application proxies are involved in the path.  This host identifier is used by a remote server to sort out the packets by sending host. The host identifier must be unique to each host under the same shared IP address.  This document analyzes a set of solution candidates to reveal a host identifier; no recommendation is sketched in the document.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>


<!--draft-ietf-pcp-base-29; AUTH48 as RFC 6887, but authors do not wish to hold-->


<reference anchor='PCP-BASE'>
<front>
<title>Port Control Protocol (PCP)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Wing' fullname='Dan Wing'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Cheshire' fullname='Stuart Cheshire'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohamed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Penno' fullname='Reinaldo Penno'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Selkirk' fullname='Paul Selkirk'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' day='7' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>The Port Control Protocol allows an IPv6 or IPv4 host to control how incoming IPv6 or IPv4 packets are translated and forwarded by a network address translator (NAT) or simple firewall, and also allows a host to optimize its outgoing NAT keepalive messages.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>







<!--boucadair-softwire-dslite-v6only; expired -->

<reference anchor='DS-LITE'>
<front>
<title>Deploying Dual-Stack Lite in IPv6 Network</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohammed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Jacquenet' fullname='Christian Jacquenet'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Grimault' fullname='Jean-Luc Grimault'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Kassi-Lahlou' fullname='Mohamed Kassi-Lahlou'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Levis' fullname='Pierre Levis'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Cheng' fullname='Dean Cheng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='5' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>Dual-Stack lite requires that the AFTR must have IPv4 connectivity. This forbids a service provider who wants to deploy AFTR in an IPv6- only network.  This memo proposes an extension to implement a stateless IPv4-in-IPv6 encapsulation in the AFTR so that AFTR can be deployed in an IPv6-only network.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-boucadair-softwire-dslite-v6only-01.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-xu-behave-stateful-nat-standby-06; Expired -->

<reference anchor='NAT-STANDBY'>
<front>
<title>Redundancy Requirements and Framework for Stateful Network Address Translators (NAT)</title>

<author initials='X' surname='Xu' fullname='Xiaohu Xu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohammed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Chen' fullname='Gang Chen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='20' year='2010' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a set of requirements and a framework for ensuring redundancy for stateful Network Address Translators (NAT), including NAT44, NAT64 and NAT46.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-xu-behave-stateful-nat-standby-06.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <?rfc ?>
  </back>
</rfc>

