<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5996 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5996.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4302 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4302.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4303 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3748 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5295 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5295.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5778 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5778.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4285 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4285.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3748 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
     
]>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6738">


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
    <front>



      <title abbrev='Diameter IKEv2 SK'>
Diameter IKEv2 SK: Using Shared Keys to Support 
  Interaction between IKEv2 Servers and Diameter Servers
      </title>
      <author initials='V.' surname='Cakulev' fullname='Violeta Cakulev'>
	<organization>Alcatel Lucent</organization>

	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street>600 Mountain Ave.</street>
	    <street>3D-517</street>
	    <city>Murray Hill</city> <region>NJ</region> <code>07974</code>
	    <country>US</country>
	  </postal>

	  <phone>+1 908 582 3207</phone>
	  <email>violeta.cakulev@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
	</address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="Avi Lior" initials="A." surname="Lior">
	<organization>Bridgewater Systems</organization>
	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street>303 Terry Fox Drive</street>
	    <city>Ottawa</city>
	    <region>Ontario</region>
	    <code>K2K 3J1</code>
	    <country>Canada</country>
	  </postal>
	  <phone>+1 613-591-6655</phone>
	  <email>avi.ietf@lior.org</email>
	</address>
      </author>

<author initials='S.' surname='Mizikovsky' fullname='Semyon Mizikovsky'>
	<organization>Alcatel Lucent</organization>

	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street>600 Mountain Ave.</street>
	    <street>3C-506</street>
	    <city>Murray Hill</city> <region>NJ</region> <code>07974</code>
	    <country>US</country>
	  </postal>

	  <phone>+1 908 582 0729</phone>
	  <email>Simon.Mizikovsky@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
	</address>
      </author>


        <date month="October" year="2012"/>



        <abstract><t>

The Internet Key Exchange Protocol version 2 (IKEv2) is a component of 
   the IPsec architecture and is used to perform mutual authentication as well 
   as to establish and to maintain IPsec Security Associations (SAs) between 
   the respective parties. IKEv2 supports several different authentication 
   mechanisms, such as the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP), 
   certificates, and Shared Key (SK).</t>

   <t>Diameter interworking for Mobile IPv6 between the Home 
   Agent (HA), as a Diameter client, and the Diameter server has been specified. 
   However, that specification focused on the usage of EAP and did not 
   include support for SK-based authentication available 
   with IKEv2. This document specifies the IKEv2-server-to-Diameter-server
  communication when the IKEv2 peer authenticates using IKEv2 with SK.

</t></abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">
            <t>

The Internet Key Exchange Protocol version 2 (IKEv2) <xref target="RFC5996"/> 
is used to mutually 
authenticate two parities and to establish a Security Association
(SA) that can be used to efficiently secure the communication between the
IKEv2 peer and server, for example, using Encapsulating Security Payload
(ESP) <xref target="RFC4303"/> and/or Authentication Header (AH) <xref target="RFC4302"/>.

 The IKEv2 protocol 
allows several different mechanisms for authenticating an IKEv2 peer to be used,
 such as the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP), certificates, and SK.</t>

<t>From a service provider perspective, it is important to ensure that a user 
is 
authorized to use the services. Therefore, the IKEv2 server must verify that 
the IKEv2 peer is authorized for the requested services, possibly with the 
assistance of the operator's Diameter servers. <xref target="RFC5778"/> defines the home 
  agent as a Diameter-client-to-Diameter-server
   communication when the mobile node authenticates using the IKEv2 protocol 
  with the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) <xref target="RFC3748"/>
   or using the Mobile IPv6 Authentication Protocol <xref target="RFC4285"/>. 
 This document specifies the IKEv2-server-to-Diameter-server
  communication when the IKEv2 peer authenticates using IKEv2 with SK.</t> 

<t> <xref target="arch"/> depicts the reference architecture for this document.</t>
<t>
            <figure title="Architecture Overview" anchor="arch">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                                    +--------+
                                    |Diameter|
                                    |Server  |
                                    +--------+
                                        ^
                               Back-End | IKEv2 Server<->HAAA Server
                               Support  | Interaction
                               Protocol | (this document)
                                        v
+---------+                      +---------------+
| IKEv2   |  Front-End Protocol  |IKEv2 Server/  |
| Peer    |<-------------------->|Diameter Client|
+---------+       IKEv2          +---------------+
 ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>
 
 <t>An example use case for this architecture is Mobile IPv6 deployment 
 in which the Mobile IPv6 signaling between the Mobile Node and the 
 Home Agent is protected using IPsec. The Mobile node acts as the 
 IKEv2 peer and the Home Agent acts as an IKEv2 server. In this use 
 case, IKEv2 with SK-based 
 initiator authentication is used for the setup of the IPsec SAs.  The 
 HA obtains the SK using the Diameter application specified in this document.
  </t>
  <t>This document assumes that the SK provided to the IKEv2 peer as well as the SK delivered to the IKEv2 server by the Diameter server are established or derived using the same rules. Furthermore, it assumes that these rules are agreed to by the external protocol on a peer side providing the key to the IKEv2 peer, and on the Diameter server side providing the key to the IKEv2 server. This document allows for the SK to be obtained for a specific IKEv2 session and exchanged between IKEv2 server and the Home Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (HAAA) server.  The protocol provides IKEv2 attributes to allow the HAAA to compute the SK specific to the session if desired (see <xref target="scsection"/>).
 This is accomplished 
through the use of a new Diameter application specifically designed for 
performing IKEv2 authorization decisions. This document focuses on the IKEv2 server, as a Diameter
   client, communicating to the Diameter server, and it specifies the Diameter application needed for this communication.
Other
   protocols leveraging this Diameter application MAY specify
   their own SK derivation scheme.
For example see <xref target="X.S0047"/> and <xref target="X.S0058"/>.
This document specifies the default procedure for derivation of the SK used in IKEv2 authentication when protocols leveraging this Diameter application do not specify their own derivation procedure. Selection of either default or other SK derivation procedure is done by the
external protocol between the Peer
and the Diameter Server, and is outside the scope of this
document.</t>

	    </section>

        <section title="Requirements Notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

 <section title="Abbreviations">
	      <t><list hangIndent="10" style="hanging">
		
		 <t hangText="AH"> Authentication Header </t>
		 <t hangText="AVP"> Attribute-Value Pair </t>
		  <t hangText="EAP"> Extensible Authentication Protocol </t>
		   <t hangText="ESP"> Encapsulating Security Payload </t>
		   <t hangText="HAAA"> Home Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting</t>
		  <t hangText="IKEv2"> Internet Key Exchange Protocol version 2</t>
		  <t hangText="NAI"> Network Access Identifier</t>
		   <t hangText="PSK"> Pre-Shared Key</t>
		  <t hangText="SA"> Security Association</t>
		  <t hangText="SK"> Shared Key</t>
		  <t hangText="SPI">  Security Parameter Index </t>
	      </list></t>	
	    </section>

        </section>

 <section title="Application Identifier">

   <t>This specification defines a new Diameter application and its
   respective Application Identifier:</t>

     <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Diameter IKE SK  (IKESK)  11
]]>
 </artwork></figure>


   <t>The IKESK Application Identifier is used when the IKEv2 peer is to be authenticated
   and authorized using IKEv2 with SK-based authentication. </t>



  </section>

	<section title="Protocol Description">
	  <section title="Support for IKEv2 and Shared Keys">
	    <t>When IKEv2 is used with SK-based initiator authentication, 
the Diameter commands IKEv2-SK-Request/Answer defined in this 
document are used between the IKEv2 server and a Home AAA  (HAAA) server to 
authorize the IKEv2 peer for the services.  Upon 
receiving the IKE_AUTH message from the IKEv2 peer, the IKEv2 server uses the 
information received in IDi <xref target="RFC5996"/> to identify the IKEv2 peer and the SPI, if available, to determine the correct SK for this IKEv2 peer. 
If no SK associated with this IKEv2 peer is found, the IKEv2 server 
MUST send an Authorize-Only (Auth-Request-Type set to "Authorize-Only") 
Diameter IKEv2-SK-Request message to the HAAA to obtain the SK. If the IDi payload extracted from the IKE_AUTH message 
contains an identity that is meaningful for the Diameter infrastructure, such 
as a Network Access Identifier (NAI), it SHALL be used by the IKEv2 server to 
populate the User-Name AVP in the Diameter message. Otherwise, it is out of scope of this document how the IKEv2 server maps the value received in the IDi payload to the User-Name AVP and whether or not the User-Name AVP is included in the IKEv2-SK-Request message. In the same Diameter message, the IKEv2 server SHALL also 
include the IKEv2-Nonces AVP with the
initiator and responder nonces (Ni and Nr) exchanged during initial IKEv2 
exchange. Finally, the IKEv2 server SHALL 
include the IKEv2-Identity AVP in the IKEv2-SK-Request message. The Initiator-Identity AVP SHALL be populated with the IDi field extracted from the IKE_AUTH message. If the IDr payload was included in the IKE_AUTH message received 
from the IKEv2 peer, the IKEv2 server SHALL also include a Responder-Identity AVP  populated with the received 
IDr.</t>

 <t>The IKEv2 server sends the IKEv2-SK-Request message to the IKEv2 peer's HAAA. The Diameter message is routed to the correct HAAA per <xref target="RFC6733"/>. </t>

<t>Upon receiving a Diameter 
IKEv2-SK-Request message from the IKEv2 server, the HAAA SHALL use the 
   User-Name 
AVP (if present) and/or Initiator-Identity AVP to retrieve the associated keying material. When the default SK-generation procedure specified in this document is used, the peer side that provides the SK to the IKEv2 peer, as well as the Diameter server, SHALL use the same SK derivation that follows the methodology similar to that specified in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC5295"/>, specifically:

            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
SK = KDF(PSK, key label | "\0" | Ni | Nr | IDi | length)
]]></artwork></figure>
</t>

<t>Where:</t>

<t>
	    <list style='symbols'>
<t>KDF is the default key derivation function based on HMAC-SHA-256 as specified in Section 3.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5295"/>. </t>

<t>Pre-Shared Key (PSK) is the key available to the protocol leveraging this Diameter application, e.g., the long-term shared secret, or the Extended Master Session Key (EMSK) as the result of prior EAP authentication, etc. Selection of this value is left up to the protocol leveraging this Diameter application. </t>

<t>Key label is set to 'sk4ikev2@ietf.org'. </t>

<t>| denotes concatenation</t>

<t>"\0" is a NULL octet (0x00 in hex)</t>
        
<t>Length is a 2-octet unsigned integer in network byte order of the
   output key length, in octets.
</t>
</list>
</t>


<t> 

When applications using this protocol define their own SK-generation 
algorithm, it is strongly RECOMMENDED that the nonces Ni and Nr be used 
in the computation.  It is also RECOMMENDED that IDi be used. IDr SHOULD 
NOT be used in the SK generation algorithm.  Applications that want to 
use IDr in the computation should take into consideration that the IDr 
asserted by the IKEv2 peer may not be the same as the IDr returned by the
IKEv2 responder.  This mismatch will result in different SKs being generated.
   The HAAA returns the SK 
to the IKEv2 server using the Key AVP as specified in 
<xref target="RFC6734"/>.  

</t> 

 <t>Once the IKEv2 server receives the SK from the HAAA, the IKEv2 server 
verifies the IKE_AUTH message received from the IKEv2 peer. If the 
verification of AUTH is successful, the IKEv2 server sends the IKE message 
back to the IKEv2 peer. </t>
	  </section>
	

	  <section title="Session Management">
<t>The HAAA may maintain Diameter session state or may be stateless.  This is indicated by 
the presence or absence of the Auth-Session-State AVP included in the answer message.  The IKEv2 server MUST 
support the Authorization Session State Machine defined in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.</t>

	
<section title="Session-Termination-Request/Answer">
<t>In the case where the HAAA is maintaining session state, when the IKEv2 server 
terminates the SA, it SHALL send a Session-Termination-Request (STR) message 
<xref target="RFC6733"/> to inform the HAAA that the authorized session has been 
terminated.</t> 

<t>The Session-Termination-Answer (STA) message <xref target="RFC6733" /> is sent by the 
HAAA to acknowledge the notification that the session has been terminated.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Abort-Session-Request/Answer">
<t>The Abort-Session-Request (ASR) message <xref target="RFC6733"/> is sent by the HAAA to 
the IKEv2 server to terminate the authorized session.  When the IKEv2 server 
receives the ASR message, it MUST delete the corresponding IKE_SA and all 
CHILD_SAs set up through it.  </t>
<t>The Abort-Session-Answer (ASA) message <xref target="RFC6733"/> is sent by the IKEv2 server 
in response to an ASR message.</t>
	</section>
	</section>
</section>

<section title="Command Codes for Diameter IKEv2 with SK" anchor='ccsection'>
<t>This section defines new Command Code values that MUST be supported by all 
Diameter implementations conforming to this specification.</t>
    
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<texttable title='Command Codes' anchor='CCtable'>
<ttcol align='center'>Command Name</ttcol>
<ttcol align='center'>Abbrev.</ttcol>
<ttcol align='center'>Code</ttcol>
<ttcol align='center'> Section Reference</ttcol>
<ttcol align='center'>Application</ttcol>
<c>IKEv2-SK-Request</c>
<c>IKESKR</c>
<c>329</c>
<c><xref target="request"/></c>
<c>IKESK</c>
<c>IKEv2-SK-Answer</c>
<c>IKESKA</c>
<c>329</c>
<c><xref target="answer"/></c>
<c>IKESK</c>
</texttable>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>

<section anchor="ipr" title="IKEv2-SK-Request (IKESKR) Command" anchor="request">
<t>The IKEv2-SK-Request message, indicated with the Command Code set to 329 and 
the 'R' bit set in the Command Flags field, is sent from the IKEv2 server to the 
HAAA to initiate IKEv2 with SK authorization. In this case, the
   Application-Id field of the Diameter header MUST be set to the
   Diameter IKE SK Application-Id (11). </t>



<t>Message format</t>

<t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
      <IKEv2-SK-Request> ::= < Diameter Header: 329, REQ, PXY >         
                              < Session-Id >
                              { Auth-Application-Id }
                              { Origin-Host }
                              { Origin-Realm }  
                              { Destination-Realm }
                              { Auth-Request-Type }     
                              [ Destination-Host ]      
                              [ NAS-Identifier ]
                              [ NAS-IP-Address ]        
                              [ NAS-IPv6-Address ]      
                              [ NAS-Port ]      
                              [ Origin-State-Id ]
                              [ User-Name ]
                              [ Key-SPI ]
                              { IKEv2-Identity }
                              [ Auth-Session-State ]    
                              { IKEv2-Nonces }
                            * [ Proxy-Info ]
                            * [ Route-Record ] 
                              ...
                            * [ AVP ]
                              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>

<t>The IKEv2-SK-Request message MUST 
include an IKEv2-Nonces AVP containing the Ni and Nr nonces swapped during 
initial IKEv2 exchange. The IKEv2-SK-Request message MAY contain a Key-SPI AVP (Key-SPI AVP is specified in 
  <xref target="RFC6734"/>). If included, it contains the SPI that HAAA SHALL  use, in addition to the other parameters (e.g., Initiator-Identity), to identify the appropriate SK. The IKEv2-SK-Request message MUST include IKEv2-Identity AVP. The Initiator-Identity AVP SHALL contain IDi as received in IKE_AUTH message. The Responder-Identity AVP SHALL be included in the IKEv2-SK-Request message, if IDr payload was included in the IKE_AUTH message received from the IKEv2 peer. If included, the Responder-Identity AVP contains the received IDr.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="ipa" title="IKEv2-SK-Answer (IKESKA) Command"  anchor="answer">
<t>The IKEv2-SK-Answer (IKESKA) message, indicated by the Command Code field 
set to 329 and the 'R' bit cleared in the Command Flags field, is sent 
by the HAAA to the IKEv2 server in response to the IKESKR command. In this case, the
   Application-Id field of the Diameter header MUST be set to the
   Diameter IKE SK Application-Id (11). </t>

<t>Message format</t>

<t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
        <IKEv2-SK-Answer> ::= < Diameter Header: 329, PXY >
                               < Session-Id >   
                               { Auth-Application-Id }
                               { Auth-Request-Type }    
                               { Result-Code }
                               { Origin-Host }
                               { Origin-Realm }
                               [ User-Name ]    
                               [ Key ]
                               [ Responder-Identity ]
                               [ Auth-Session-State ]
                               [ Error-Message ]
                               [ Error-Reporting-Host ]
                             * [ Failed-AVP ]
                               [ Origin-State-Id ]
                             * [ Redirect-Host ]                
                               [ Redirect-Host-Usage ]
                               [ Redirect-Max-Cache-Time ]      
                             * [ Proxy-Info ]
                             * [ Route-Record ]
                               ...
                             * [ AVP ] 
        		  ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>

<t>If the authorization procedure is successful, then the IKEv2-SK-Answer 
  message SHALL include the Key AVP as specified in 
  <xref target="RFC6734"/>. The value of the Key-Type AVP 
  SHALL be set to IKEv2 SK (3). The Keying-Material AVP SHALL contain the SK. If the Key-SPI AVP is received in IKEv2-SK-Request, the Key-SPI AVP SHALL be included in the Key AVP. The Key-Lifetime AVP may be included; if so, then the associated key SHALL NOT be used by the receiver of the answer if the lifetime has expired. Finally, the Responder-Identity AVP may be included. </t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="avps" title="Attribute-Value Pair Definitions">

<t>This section defines new AVPs for IKEv2 with SK.</t>


<section title="IKEv2-Nonces" anchor="nonces">
<t>The IKEv2-Nonces AVP (Code 587) is of type Grouped and contains the 
nonces exchanged between the IKEv2 peer and the IKEv2 server during IKEv2 
initial exchange. The nonces are used for SK generation.</t>

<t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
            IKEv2-Nonces ::= < AVP Header: 587 > 
                             {Ni}
                             {Nr}       
                            *[AVP]
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>

<section title="Ni" anchor="Nr">
<t>The Ni AVP (AVP Code 588) is of type OctetString and contains the IKEv2 
initiator nonce as contained in Nonce Data field.</t>
</section>

<section title="Nr" anchor="Ni">
<t>The Nr AVP (AVP Code 589) is of type OctetString and contains the IKEv2 
responder nonce as contained in Nonce Data field.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="IKEv2-Identity" anchor="ids">
<t>The IKEv2-Identity AVP (Code 590) is of type Grouped and contains the 
Initiator and possibly Responder identities as included in IKE_AUTH message sent from the IKEv2 peer to the IKEv2 server.</t>

<t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
            IKEv2-Identity ::= < AVP Header: 590 >       
                             {Initiator-Identity}
                             [Responder-Identity]       
                            *[AVP]
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>
<section title="Initiator-Identity" anchor="idi">
<t>The Initiator-Identity AVP (AVP Code 591) is of type Grouped and
   contains the identity type and identification data of the IDi payload of the IKE_AUTH message. </t>

<t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
            Initiator-Identity ::= < AVP Header: 591 >   
                             {ID-Type}
                             {Identification-Data}      
                            *[AVP]
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>
<section title="ID-Type" anchor="idtype">
<t>The ID-Type AVP (AVP Code 592) is of type Enumerated and contains the ID type value of IDi payload of the IKE_AUTH message.</t>
</section>

<section title="Identification-Data" anchor="iddata">
<t>The Identification-Data AVP (AVP Code 593) is of type OctetString and contains the Identification Data field of IDi payload of the IKE_AUTH message.</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="Responder-Identity" anchor="idr">
<t>The Responder-Identity AVP (AVP Code 594) is of type Grouped and
   contains the identity type and identification data of the IDr payload of the IKE_AUTH message.</t>
<t>


            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
            Responder-Identity ::= < AVP Header: 594 >   
                             {ID-Type}
                             {Identification-Data}      
                            *[AVP]
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
</t>
<section title="ID-Type" anchor="idtyper">
<t>The ID-Type AVP (AVP Code 592) is of type Enumerated and contains the ID type value of IDr payload of the IKE_AUTH message.</t>
</section>

<section title="Identification-Data" anchor="iddatar">
<t>The Identification-Data AVP (AVP Code 593) is of type OctetString and contains the Identification Data field of IDr payload of the IKE_AUTH message.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</section>


 <section title="AVP Occurrence Tables">

      <t>The following tables present the AVPs defined or used in this document 
	and their occurrences in
        Diameter messages. Note that AVPs that can only be present within a 
	Grouped AVP are not
        represented in this table.</t>

      <t>The table uses the following symbols:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging" hangIndent="9">
          <t hangText="0:">The AVP MUST NOT be present in the
              message.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="0+:">Zero or more instances of the AVP MAY be present
            in the message.</t>
          <t hangText="0-1:">Zero or one instance of the AVP MAY be present
            in the message.</t>
          <t hangText="1:">One instance of the AVP MUST be present in the
            message. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
        <t>
          <figure title="IKESKR and IKESKA Commands AVP Table">
            <artwork><![CDATA[

                                  +-------------------+
                                  |   Command Code    |       
                                  |---------+---------+
   AVP Name                       | IKESKR  | IKESKA  |
   -------------------------------|---------+---------+
   Key                            |    0    |   0-1   |
   Key-SPI                        |   0-1   |    0    |  
   IKEv2-Nonces                   |    1    |    0    | 
   IKEv2-Identity                 |    1    |    0    | 
   Responder-Identity             |    0    |   0-1   |
                                  +---------+---------+
                  ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
       
      </section>

 <section title="AVP Flag Rules">
<t>The following table describes the Diameter AVPs, their AVP Code  
values, types, and possible flag values. 
The Diameter base protocol <xref target="RFC6733"/> specifies the AVP Flag rules for AVPs in Section 4.5. </t>


      <t>
        <figure title="AVP Flag Rules Table">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                              +---------+
                                              |AVP Flag |
                                              |  Rules  |
                                              +----+----+
                    AVP  Section              |    |MUST|
 Attribute Name     Code Defined   Value Type |MUST| NOT|
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Key                 581  Note 1   Grouped    |  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Keying-Material     583  Note 1   OctetString|  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Key-Lifetime        584  Note 1   Integer64  |  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Key-SPI             585  Note 1   Unsigned32 |  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Key-Type            582  Note 1   Enumerated |  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|IKEv2-Nonces        587  6.1      Grouped    |  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Ni                  588  6.1.1    OctetString|  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Nr                  589  6.1.2    OctetString|  M | V  | 
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|IKEv2-Identity      590  6.2      Grouped    |  M | V  |
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Initiator-Identity  591  6.2.1    Grouped    |  M | V  |
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|ID-Type             592  6.2.1.1  Enumerated |  M | V  |
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Identification-Data 593  6.2.1.2  OctetString|  M | V  |
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+
|Responder-Identity  594  6.2.2    Grouped    |  M | V  |
+---------------------------------------------+----+----+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t> 

      <t> Note 1: The Key, Keying-Material, Key-Lifetime, Key-SPI, and Key-Type AVPs
	are defined in <xref target="RFC6734"/>. </t>
 </section> 

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<section title="Command Codes">
<t>IANA has allocated a Command Code value for the following new command
   from the Command Code namespace defined in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.</t>

 
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   Command Code                     | Value
   ---------------------------------+------
   IKEv2-SK-Request/Answer          | 329

]]>
      </artwork></figure>

 </section>

<section title="AVP Codes">
<t> This specification requires IANA to register the following new AVPs from the AVP Code
          namespace defined in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>IKEv2-Nonces - 587</t>
            <t>Ni - 588</t>
            <t>Nr - 589</t>
	    <t>IKEv2-Identity - 590</t>
	    <t>Initiator-Identity - 591</t>
	    <t>ID-Type - 592</t>
	    <t>Identification-Data - 593</t>
	    <t>Responder-Identity - 594</t>
          </list></t><t>The AVPs are defined in <xref target="avps"/>.
        </t>

 </section>

<section title="AVP Values">
  <t> IANA is requested to create a new value for the
   Key-Type AVP. The new value 3 signifies that IKEv2 SK is being sent. </t>
</section>

<section title="Application Identifier">
        <t> This specification requires IANA to allocate one new
          value "Diameter IKE SK" 
	  from the Application Identifier namespace defined
          in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.
        </t>


      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[ 
Application Identifier         | Value
-------------------------------+------
Diameter IKE SK (IKESK)        | 11
]]>
      </artwork></figure>

      </section>
 </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations" anchor='scsection'>
        
<t> The security considerations of the Diameter base 
protocol <xref target="RFC6733"/> are applicable to this document (e.g., it 
is expected that Diameter protocol is used with security mechanism and 
that Diameter messages are secured). </t>

<t>
In addition, the assumption is that the IKEv2 server and the Diameter 
server, where the SK is generated, are in a trusted relationship. Hence, 
the assumption is that there is an appropriate security mechanism to 
protect the communication between these servers.  For example, the IKEv2 
server and the Diameter server would be deployed in the same secure 
network or would utilize transport-layer security as specified in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.</t>


<t> The Diameter messages between the IKEv2 server and the HAAA may be
   transported via one or more AAA brokers or Diameter agents.  In this
   case, the IKEv2 server to the Diameter server AAA communication
   is hop-by-hop protected; hence, it relies on the security properties of 
 the intermediating AAA inter-connection networks, AAA brokers, and Diameter agents.  Furthermore,
   any agents that process IKEv2-SK-Answer messages can see the
   contents of the Key AVP.</t>

<t>To mitigate the threat of exposing a long-lived PSK, this specification expects that the HAAA derive and return 
  the associated SK to the IKEv2 server. Given that SK derivation is security-critical, for the SK
  derivation, this specification recommends the use of short-lived 
   secrets, possibly based on a previous network access authentication, 
   if such secrets are available. To ensure key freshness and to limit the 
  key scope, this specification strongly recommends the use of nonces included in the IKEv2-SK-Request.  The specifics of
   key derivation depend on the security characteristics of the system that is leveraging
 this specification (for example, see <xref target="X.S0047"/> and <xref target="X.S0058"/>); therefore, this specification
   does not define how the
   Diameter server derives required keys for these systems. For systems and protocols that leverage this Diameter application but do not specify the key derivation procedure, this document specifies the default key derivation procedure that preserves expected security characteristics.</t>

        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>
	    &rfc4302; &rfc4303; &rfc5295; &rfc5996; 


<reference anchor='RFC6734'>
<front>
<title>Diameter Attribute-Value Pairs for Cryptographic Key Transport</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Zorn' fullname='Glen Zorn'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Wu' fullname='Wenson Wu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='V' surname='Cakulev' fullname='Violeta Cakulev'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October'  year='2012' />

<abstract><t>Some Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) applications require the transport of cryptographic keying material.  This document specifies a set of Attribute-Value Pairs (AVPs) providing native Diameter support of cryptographic key delivery.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6734' />

</reference>


<reference anchor='RFC6733'>
<front>
<title>Diameter Base Protocol</title>

<author initials='V' surname='Fajardo' fullname='Victor Fajardo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Arkko' fullname='Jari Arkko'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Loughney' fullname='John Loughney'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Zorn' fullname='Glen Zorn'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2012' />

<abstract><t>The Diameter base protocol is intended to provide an Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA) framework for applications such as network access or IP mobility in both local and roaming situations. This document specifies the message format, transport, error reporting, accounting and security services used by all Diameter applications.  The Diameter base protocol as defined in this document obsoletes RFC 3588 and RFC 5719 and must be supported by all new Diameter implementations.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6733' />

</reference>

	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
            &rfc2119; &rfc3748; &rfc5778; &rfc4285; 
<reference anchor="X.S0047">
<front>
		<title>Mobile IPv6 Enhancements</title>
		<author>
			<organization>3GPP2: X.S0047</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="February" year="2009"></date>
	</front>

   </reference>

<reference anchor="X.S0058">
<front>
		<title>WiMAX-HRPD Interworking: Core Network Aspects</title>
		<author>
			<organization>3GPP2: X.S0058</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="June" year="2010"></date>
	</front>

   </reference>
        </references>
    </back>

</rfc>
