<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!--used v2 -->

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" number="7073"
     ipr="trust200902">

<front>

 <title abbrev="Email Identifiers Response Set">
	A Reputation Response Set for Email Identifiers
 </title>

 <author fullname="Nathaniel Borenstein" initials="N." surname="Borenstein">
  <organization>Mimecast</organization>
  <address>
   <postal>
    <street>203 Crescent St., Suite 303</street>
    <city>Waltham</city>
    <region>MA</region>
    <code>02453</code>
    <country>USA</country>
   </postal>
   <phone>+1 781 996 5340</phone>
   <email>nsb@guppylake.com</email>
  </address>
 </author>
    
 <author fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy" initials="M. S." surname="Kucherawy">
  <address>
   <postal>
    <street>270 Upland Drive</street>
    <city>San Francisco</city>
    <region>CA</region>
    <code>94127</code>
    <country>USA</country>
   </postal>
   <email>superuser@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
 </author>
    
 <date month="November" year="2013" />

 <area>Applications</area>
 <workgroup>REPUTE Working Group</workgroup>

 <keyword>reputation</keyword>
 <keyword>domain</keyword>
 <keyword>security</keyword>
 <keyword>messaging</keyword>
 <keyword>dkim</keyword>
 <keyword>spf</keyword>
 <keyword>authentication</keyword>

 <abstract>
  <t> This document defines a response set for describing assertions
      a reputation service provider can make about email identifiers,
      for use in generating reputons. </t>
 </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
 <section title="Introduction">
  <t> This document specifies a response set for describing the reputation of an
      email identifier.  A "response set" in this context is defined in
      <xref target="RFC7070"/> and is used to describe assertions
      a reputation service provider can make about email identifiers as well
      as metadata that can be included in such a reply beyond the base set
      specified there. </t>

  <t> An atomic reputation response is called a "reputon", defined in
      <xref target="RFC7071"/>.  That document also defines a
      media type to contain a reputon for transport, and creates a
      registry for reputation applications and the interesting parameters of
      each. </t>
 </section> <!-- Introduction -->

 <section title="Terminology and Definitions" anchor="terms_and_defs">
  <t>This section defines terms used in the rest of the document.</t>

  <section title="Key Words" anchor="defs_keywords">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in
      <xref target="KEYWORDS"/>.</t>
  </section> <!-- Keywords -->

  <section title="Email Definitions" anchor="defs_email">
   <t> Commonly used definitions describing entities in the email architecture
       are defined and discussed in <xref target="EMAIL-ARCH"/>. </t>
  </section> <!-- Email Definitions -->

  <section title="Other Definitions" anchor="defs_other">
   <t> Other terms of importance in this document are defined in
       <xref target="RFC7070"/>, the base document for the reputation
       services work. </t>
  </section> <!-- Other Definitions -->
 </section> <!-- Terminology and Definitions -->

 <section title="Discussion" anchor="discussion">
  <t> The expression of reputation about an email identifier requires
      extensions of the base set defined in <xref target="RFC7070"/>.
      This document defines and registers some common assertions about
      an entity found in a piece of <xref target="MAIL"/>. </t>

  <section title="Assertions" anchor="assertions">
   <t> The "email-id" reputation application recognizes the following
       assertions:

	<list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="abusive:"> The subject identifier is associated
			with sending or handling email of a personally
			abusive, threatening, or otherwise harassing
			nature </t>

		<t hangText="fraud:"> The subject identifier is
			associated with the sending or handling of fraudulent
			email, such as "phishing" (some good discussion
		        on this topic can be found in
			<xref target="IODEF-PHISHING"/>) </t>

		<t hangText="invalid-recipients:"> The subject
			identifier is associated with delivery attempts to
			nonexistent recipients </t>

		<t hangText="malware:"> The subject identifier is
			associated with the sending or handling of
			malware via email </t>

		<t hangText="spam:"> The subject identifier is associated
			with the sending or handling of unwanted bulk email </t>
	</list> </t>

    <t> For all assertions, the "rating" scale is linear: a value of 0.0 means
        there is no data to support the assertion, a value of 1.0 means all
        accumulated data support the assertion, and the intervening values
        have a linear relationship (i.e., a score of "x" is twice as strong
        of an assertion as a value of "x/2"). </t>
  </section> <!-- Assertions -->

  <section title="Response Set Extensions" anchor="response_set">
   <t> The "email-id" reputation application recognizes the following
       OPTIONAL extensions to the basic response set defined in
       <xref target="RFC7071"/>:

	<list style="hanging">
		<t hangText="email-id-identity:"> A token indicating the
			source of the identifier; that is, where the subject
			identifier was found in the message.  This MUST be
			one of:

			<list style="hanging">
				<t hangText="dkim:"> The signing domain, i.e.,
					the value of the "d=" tag, found
					on a valid DomainKeys Identified Mail <xref target="DKIM"/>
					signature in the message </t>

				<t hangText="ipv4:"> The IPv4 address of
					the client </t>

				<t hangText="ipv6:"> The IPv6 address of
					the client </t>

				<t hangText="rfc5321.helo:"> The
					RFC5321.HELO value used by the client
					(see <xref target="SMTP"/>) </t>

				<t hangText="rfc5321.mailfrom:"> The
					RFC5321.MailFrom value of the envelope
					of the message
					(see <xref target="SMTP"/>) </t>

				<t hangText="rfc5322.from:"> The RFC5322.From
					field of the message (see
					<xref target="MAIL"/>) </t>

				<t hangText="spf:"> The domain name portion of
					the identifier (RFC5321.MailFrom or
					RFC5321.HELO) verified by
					<xref target="SPF"/> </t>
			</list> </t>

		<t hangText="sources:"> A token relating a count of the
			number of sources of data that contributed to
			the reported reputation.  This is in contrast to
			the "sample-size" parameter, which indicates the
			total number of reports across all reporting
			sources. </t>
	</list> </t>

   <t> A reply that does not contain the "identity" or "sources" extensions is
       making a non-specific statement about how the reputation returned
       was developed.  A client can use or ignore such a reply at its
       discretion. </t>
  </section> <!-- Response Set Extensions -->

  <section title="Identifiers" anchor="ident">
   <t> In evaluating an email message on the basis of reputation, there can
       be more than one identifier in the message needing to be validated.
       For example, a message may have different email addresses in the
       RFC5321.MailFrom parameter and the RFC5322.From header field.
       The RFC5321.Helo identifier will obviously be different.  Consequently,
       the software evaluating the email message may need to query for the
       reputation of more than one identifier. </t>

   <t> The purpose of including the identity in the reply is to expose to
       the client the context in which the identifier was extracted from the
       message under evaluation.  In particular, several of the items listed
       are extracted verbatim from the message and have not been subjected to
       any kind of validation, while a domain name present in a valid DKIM
       signature has some more reliable semantics associated with it.
       Computing or using reputation information about unauthenticated
       identifiers has substantially reduced value, but can sometimes be useful
       when combined.  For example, a reply that indicates a message contained
       one of these low-value identifiers with a high "spam" rating might not
       be worthy of notice, but a reply that indicates a message contained
       several of them could be grounds for suspicion. </t>

   <t> A client interested in checking these weaker identifiers would issue
       a query about each of them using the same
       assertion (e.g., "spam"), and then collate the results to determine
       which ones and how many of them came back with ratings indicating
       content of concern, and take action accordingly.  For stronger
       identifiers, decisions can typically be made based on a few or even
       just one of them. </t>
  </section> <!-- Identifiers -->

  <section title="Query Extensions" anchor="query_ext">
   <t> A query within this application can include the OPTIONAL query
       parameter "identity" to indicate which specific identity is of
       interest to the query.  Legal values are the same as those listed
       in <xref target="response_set"/>. </t>
  </section> <!-- Query Extensions -->
 </section> <!-- Discussion -->

 <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana_considerations">
  <t> This memo presents one action for IANA, namely the registration of
      the reputation application "email-id". </t>

  <section title="Registration of 'email-id' Reputation Application"
           anchor="iana_reg">
   <t> This section registers the "email-id" reputation application, as
       per the IANA Considerations section of
       <xref target="RFC7071"/>.  The registration parameters
       are as follows: 

	<list style="symbols">
	 <t> Application symbolic name: email-id </t>

	 <t> Short description: Evaluates DNS domain names or IP addresses
	     found in email identifiers </t>

	 <t> Defining document: [RFC7073] </t>

	 <t> Status: current </t>

	 <t> Subject: A string appropriate to the identifier of interest (see
	     <xref target="response_set"/> of this document) </t>

	 <t> Application-specific query parameters:
		<list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="identity:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="query_ext"/>
				of this document </t>
		</list> </t>

	 <t> Application-specific assertions:
		<list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="abusive:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="assertions"/>
				of this document </t>

			<t hangText="fraud:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="assertions"/>
				of this document </t>

			<t hangText="invalid-recipients:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="assertions"/>
				of this document </t>

			<t hangText="malware:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="assertions"/>
				of this document </t>

			<t hangText="spam:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="assertions"/>
				of this document </t>
		</list> </t>

	 <t> Application-specific response set extensions:
		<list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="identity:"> (current)
				as defined in <xref target="response_set"/>
				of this document </t>
		</list> </t>
	</list> </t>
  </section> <!-- Registration of 'email-id' Reputation Application -->
 </section> <!-- IANA Considerations -->

 <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec_considerations">
  <t> This document is primarily an IANA action and doesn't describe
      any protocols or protocol elements that might introduce new security
      concerns.  </t>

  <t> Security considerations relevant to email and email authentication can
      be found in most of the documents listed in the References sections
      below.  Information specific to use of reputation services can be found
      in <xref target="CONSIDERATIONS"/>. </t>
 </section> <!-- Security Considerations -->
</middle>

<back>
 <references title="Normative References">


<reference anchor='DKIM'>

<front>
<title>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) Signatures</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker' role='editor'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Hansen' fullname='T. Hansen' role='editor'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Kucherawy' fullname='M. Kucherawy' role='editor'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='September' />
<abstract>
<t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) permits a person, role, or organization that owns the signing domain to claim some responsibility for a message by associating the domain with the message. This can be an author's organization, an operational relay, or one of their agents. DKIM separates the question of the identity of the Signer of the message from the purported author of the message. Assertion of responsibility is validated through a cryptographic signature and by querying the Signer's domain directly to retrieve the appropriate public key. Message transit from author to recipient is through relays that typically make no substantive change to the message content and thus preserve the DKIM signature.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This memo obsoletes RFC 4871 and RFC 5672. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='76' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6376' />
<format type='TXT' octets='176999' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6376.txt' />
</reference>




<reference anchor='EMAIL-ARCH'>

<front>
<title>Internet Mail Architecture</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>Over its thirty-five-year history, Internet Mail has changed significantly in scale and complexity, as it has become a global infrastructure service.  These changes have been evolutionary, rather than revolutionary, reflecting a strong desire to preserve both its installed base and its usefulness.  To collaborate productively on this large and complex system, all participants need to work from a common view of it and use a common language to describe its components and the interactions among them.  But the many differences in perspective currently make it difficult to know exactly what another participant means.  To serve as the necessary common frame of reference, this document describes the enhanced Internet Mail architecture, reflecting the current service.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5598' />
<format type='TXT' octets='115741' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5598.txt' />
<format type='PDF' octets='342738' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5598.pdf' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='KEYWORDS'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17970' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-repute-media-type; Companion Doc; RFC7071 -->
<reference anchor='RFC7071'>
<front>
<title>A Media Type for Reputation Interchange</title>

<author initials='N' surname='Borenstein' fullname='Nathaniel Borenstein'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Kucherawy' fullname='Murray Kucherawy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2013' />

<abstract><t>This document defines the format of reputation response data ("reputons"), the media-type for packaging it, and definition of a registry for the names of reputation applications and response sets.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7071' />

</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-repute-model; companion Doc RFC 7070-->
<reference anchor='RFC7070'>
<front>
<title>An Architecture for Reputation Reporting</title>

<author initials='N' surname='Borenstein' fullname='Nathaniel Borenstein'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Kucherawy' fullname='Murray Kucherawy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Sullivan' fullname='Andrew Sullivan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2013' />

<abstract><t>This document describes a general architecture for a reputation-based service, allowing one to request reputation-related data over the Internet, where "reputation" refers to predictions or expectations about an entity or an identifier such as a domain name.  The document roughly follows the recommendations of RFC4101 for describing a protocol model.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7070' />

</reference>




<reference anchor='SMTP'>

<front>
<title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Klensin' fullname='J. Klensin'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This document is a specification of the basic protocol for Internet electronic mail transport.  It consolidates, updates, and clarifies several previous documents, making all or parts of most of them obsolete.  It covers the SMTP extension mechanisms and best practices for the contemporary Internet, but does not provide details about particular extensions.  Although SMTP was designed as a mail transport and delivery protocol, this specification also contains information that is important to its use as a "mail submission" protocol for "split-UA" (User Agent) mail reading systems and mobile environments. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5321' />
<format type='TXT' octets='225929' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5321.txt' />
</reference>




<reference anchor='SPF'>

<front>
<title>Sender Policy Framework (SPF) for Authorizing Use of Domains in E-Mail, Version 1</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Wong' fullname='M. Wong'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Schlitt' fullname='W. Schlitt'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='April' />
<abstract>
<t>E-mail on the Internet can be forged in a number of ways.  In particular, existing protocols place no restriction on what a sending host can use as the reverse-path of a message or the domain given on the SMTP HELO/EHLO commands.  This document describes version 1 of the ender Policy Framework (SPF) protocol, whereby a domain may explicitly authorize the hosts that are allowed to use its domain name, and a receiving host may check such authorization.  This memo defines an Experimental Protocol for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4408' />
<format type='TXT' octets='105009' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4408.txt' />
</reference>



 </references>

 <references title="Informative References">


<!--draft-ietf-repute-considerations: I-D Exists -->
<reference anchor='CONSIDERATIONS'>
<front>
<title>Operational Considerations Regarding Reputation Services</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Kucherawy' fullname='Murray Kucherawy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May'  year='2013' />

<abstract><t>The use of reputation systems is has become a common tool in many applications that seek to apply collected intelligence about traffic sources.  Often this is done because it is common or even expected operator practice.  It is therefore important to be aware of a number of considerations for both operators and consumers of the data.  This document includes a collection of the best advice available regarding providers and consumers of reputation data, based on experience to date.  Much of this is based on experience with email reputation systems, but the concepts are generally applicable.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>



<reference anchor='IODEF-PHISHING'>

<front>
<title>Extensions to the IODEF-Document Class for Reporting Phishing</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Cain' fullname='P. Cain'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Jevans' fullname='D. Jevans'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This document extends the Incident Object Description Exchange Format (IODEF) defined in RFC 5070 to support the reporting of phishing events, which is a particular type of fraud.  These extensions are flexible enough to support information gleaned from activities throughout the entire electronic fraud cycle -- from receipt of the phishing lure to the disablement of the collection site.  Both simple reporting and complete forensic reporting are possible, as is consolidating multiple incidents. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5901' />
<format type='TXT' octets='97325' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5901.txt' />
</reference>




<reference anchor='MAIL'>

<front>
<title>Internet Message Format</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Resnick' fullname='Peter W. 
Resnick' role='editor'>
<organization>Qualcomm Incorporated</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>5775 Morehouse Drive</street>
<city>San Diego</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92121-1714</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 858 651 4478</phone>
<email>presnick@qualcomm.com</email>
<uri>http://www.qualcomm.com/~presnick/</uri></address></author>
<date year='2008' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies the Internet 
Message Format (IMF), a syntax for text messages
			that are sent between computer users, within 
the framework of "electronic mail"
			messages. This specification is a revision of 
Request For Comments (RFC) 2822, which
			itself superseded Request For Comments (RFC) 
822, "Standard for the Format of ARPA
			Internet Text Messages", updating it to 
reflect current practice and incorporating
			incremental changes that were specified in 
other RFCs.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5322' />
<format type='TXT' octets='122322' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5322.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='213393' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc5322.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='174234' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc5322.xml' />
</reference>



 </references>

 <section title="Positive vs. Negative Assertions" anchor="plus_minus">
   <t> <xref target="CONSIDERATIONS"/> some current theories
       about reputation, namely that it will possibly have more impact to develop
       positive reputations and focus on giving preferential treatment to
       content or sources that earn those.  However, the assertions defined
       in this document are all clearly negative in nature. </t>

   <t> In effect, this document is recording current use of reputation and
       of this framework in particular.  It is expected that, in the future,
       the application being registered here will be augmented, and other
       applications registered, that focus more on positive assertions rather
       than negative ones. </t>
 </section>

 <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="acks">
  <t> The authors wish to acknowledge the contributions of the following to
      this specification:
      Scott Hollenbeck,
      Scott Kitterman,
      Peter Koch,
      John Levine,
      Danny McPherson,
      S. Moonesamy,
      Doug Otis,
      and
      David F. Skoll. </t>
 </section>


</back>
</rfc>
