<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="exp" number="7215" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
consensus="yes">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="LISP Deployment">Locator/Identifier Separation Protocol
(LISP) Network&nbsp;Element&nbsp;Deployment&nbsp;Considerations</title>


    <author fullname="Lorand Jakab" initials="L." surname="Jakab">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 Tasman Drive</street>
          <code>95134</code>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>lojakab@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Albert Cabellos-Aparicio" initials="A."
surname="Cabellos-Aparicio">
      <organization>Technical University of Catalonia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>C/Jordi Girona, s/n</street>
          <code>08034</code>
          <city>BARCELONA</city>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>acabello@ac.upc.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Florin Coras" initials="F." surname="Coras">
      <organization>Technical University of Catalonia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>C/Jordi Girona, s/n</street>
          <code>08034</code>
          <city>BARCELONA</city>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>fcoras@ac.upc.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jordi Domingo-Pascual" initials="J."
surname="Domingo-Pascual">
      <organization>Technical University of Catalonia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>C/Jordi Girona, s/n</street>
          <code>08034</code>
          <city>BARCELONA</city>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jordi.domingo@ac.upc.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Darrel Lewis" initials="D." surname="Lewis">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 Tasman Drive</street>
          <code>95134</code>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>darlewis@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2014" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <keyword>LISP, deployment</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document is a snapshot of different Locator/Identifier Separation
Protocol (LISP) deployment scenarios.  It discusses the placement of new
network elements introduced by the protocol, representing the thinking of the
LISP working group as of Summer 2013.  LISP deployment scenarios may have
evolved since then. This memo represents one stable point in that evolution of
understanding.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Locator/Identifier Separation Protocol (LISP) is designed to
address the scaling issues of the global Internet routing system identified in
<xref target="RFC4984" /> by separating the current addressing scheme into
Endpoint IDentifiers (EIDs) and Routing LOCators (RLOCs). The main protocol
specification <xref target="RFC6830" /> describes how the separation is
achieved and which new network elements are introduced, and it details the
packet formats for the data and control planes.</t>

      <t>LISP assumes that such separation is between the edge and core and
uses mapping and encapsulation for forwarding. While the boundary between both
is not strictly defined, one widely accepted definition places it at the border
routers of stub autonomous systems, which may carry a partial or complete
default-free zone (DFZ) routing table. The initial design of LISP took this
location as a baseline for protocol development. However, the applications of
LISP go beyond just decreasing the size of the DFZ routing table and include
improved multihoming and ingress traffic engineering (TE) support for edge
networks, and even individual hosts. Throughout this document, we will use the
term "LISP site" to refer to these networks/hosts behind a LISP Tunnel
Router. We formally define the following two terms:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Network element:">Facility or equipment used in the
provision of a communications service over the Internet <xref
target="TELCO96"/>.</t>

          <t hangText="LISP site:">A single host or a set of network elements
in an edge network under the administrative control of a single organization,
delimited from other networks by LISP Tunnel Router(s).</t>

        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Since LISP is a protocol that can be used for different purposes, it
is important to identify possible deployment scenarios and the additional
requirements they may impose on the protocol specification and other protocols.
Additionally, this document is intended as a guide for the operational
community for LISP deployments in their networks.  It is expected to evolve as
LISP deployment progresses, and the described scenarios are better understood
or new scenarios are discovered.</t>

      <t>Each subsection considers an element type and discusses the impact of
deployment scenarios on the protocol specification. For definitions of terms,
please refer to the appropriate documents (as cited in the respective
sections).</t>

      <t>This experimental document describes deployment considerations.
These considerations and the LISP specifications have areas that require
additional experience and measurement.  LISP is not recommended for deployment
beyond experimental situations.  Results of experimentation may lead to
modifications and enhancements of LISP mechanisms.  Additionally, at the time
of this writing there is no standardized security to implement.  Beware that
there are no countermeasures for any of the threats identified in <xref
target="LISP-THREATS" />.  See Section 15 of <xref target="RFC6830"/>
for specific known issues that are in need of further work during development,
implementation, and experimentation, and see <xref target="LISP-THREATS"/> for
recommendations to ameliorate the above-mentioned security threats.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Tunnel Routers">
      <t>The device that is the gateway between the edge and the core is called
a Tunnel Router (xTR); it performs one or both of two separate functions:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Encapsulating packets originating from an end host to be
transported over intermediary (transit) networks towards the other endpoint of
the communication.</t>

          <t>Decapsulating packets entering from intermediary (transit)
networks, originated at a remote end host.</t>

        </list>
        The first function is performed by an Ingress Tunnel Router (ITR) and
the second by an Egress Tunnel Router (ETR).
      </t>

      <t>Section 8 of the main LISP specification <xref target="RFC6830" /> has
a short discussion of where Tunnel Routers can be deployed and some of the
associated advantages and disadvantages. This section adds more detail to the
scenarios presented there and provides additional scenarios as well.
Furthermore, this section discusses functional models, that is, network
functions that can be achieved by deploying Tunnel Routers in specific
ways.</t>

      <section title="Deployment Scenarios" anchor="sec_deployment">
      <section title="Customer Edge (CE)" anchor="sec_ce">
        <t>The first scenario we discuss is the customer edge, when xTR
functionality is placed on the router(s) that connects the LISP site to its
upstream(s) but is under its control.  As such, this is the most common
expected scenario for xTRs, and this document considers it the reference
location, comparing the other scenarios to this one.</t>

     <figure align="center" title="xTRs at the Customer Edge" anchor="fig_ce">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
    ISP1    ISP2
     |        | 
     |        | 
   +----+  +----+
+--|xTR1|--|xTR2|--+
|  +----+  +----+  |
|                  |
|     LISP site    |
+------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>  
        <t>From the LISP site's perspective, the main advantage of this type of
deployment (compared to the one described in the next section) is having direct
control over its ingress traffic engineering. This makes it easy to set up and
maintain active/active, active/backup, or more complex TE policies, adding ISPs
and additional xTRs at will, without involving third parties.</t>

        <t>Being under the same administrative control, reachability
information of all ETRs is easier to synchronize, because the necessary control
traffic can be allowed between the locators of the ETRs. A correct synchronous
global view of the reachability status is thus available, and the
Locator-Status-Bits can be set correctly in the LISP data header
of outgoing packets.</t>

        <t>By placing the Tunnel Router at the edge of the site, existing
internal network configuration does not need to be modified. Firewall rules,
router configurations, and address assignments inside the LISP site remain
unchanged. This helps with incremental deployment and allows a quick upgrade
path to LISP. For larger sites distributed in geographically diverse points of
presence (PoPs) and having many external connections and complex internal
topology, it may, however, make more sense to both encapsulate and decapsulate
as soon as possible, to benefit from the information in the IGP to choose the
best path.  See <xref target="split" /> for a discussion of this scenario.</t>

        <t>Another thing to consider when placing Tunnel Routers is MTU issues.
Encapsulation increases the amount of overhead associated with each packet.
This added overhead decreases the effective end-to-end path MTU (unless
fragmentation and reassembly are used).  Some transit networks are known to
provide larger MTU values than the typical value of 1500 bytes for popular
access technologies used at end hosts (e.g., IEEE 802.3 and 802.11).  However,
placing the LISP router connecting to such a network at the customer edge could
possibly bring up MTU issues, depending on the link type to the provider as
opposed to the following scenario. See <xref target="RFC4459" /> for MTU
considerations of tunneling protocols and how to mitigate potential issues.
Still, even with these mitigations, path MTU issues are still possible.</t>

        </section>
      <section title="Provider Edge (PE)">
        <t>The other location at the core-edge boundary for deploying LISP
routers is at the Internet service provider edge. The main incentive for this
case is that the customer does not have to upgrade the CE router(s) or change
the configuration of any equipment. Encapsulation/decapsulation happens in the
provider's network, which may be able to serve several customers with a single
device. For large ISPs with many residential/business customers asking for
LISP, this can lead to important savings, since there is no need to upgrade the
software (or hardware, if that's the case) at each client's location. Instead,
they can upgrade the software (or hardware) on a few PE routers serving the
customers. This scenario is depicted in <xref target="fig_pe" />.</t>

      <figure align="center" title="xTRs at the Provider Edge" anchor="fig_pe">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+----------+        +------------------+
|   ISP1   |        |       ISP2       |
|          |        |                  |
|  +----+  |        |  +----+  +----+  |
+--|xTR1|--+        +--|xTR2|--|xTR3|--+
   +----+              +----+  +----+
      |                  |       |
      |                  |       |
      +--<[LISP site]>---+-------+
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>While this approach can make transition easy for customers and may
be cheaper for providers, the LISP site loses one of the main benefits of LISP:
ingress traffic engineering. Since the provider controls the ETRs, additional
complexity would be needed to allow customers to modify their mapping
entries.</t>

        <t>The problem is aggravated when the LISP site is multihomed. Consider
the scenario in <xref target="fig_pe" />: whenever a change to TE policies is
required, the customer contacts both ISP1 and ISP2 to make the necessary
changes on the routers (if they provide this possibility). It is, however,
unlikely that both ISPs will apply changes simultaneously, which may lead to
inconsistent state for the mappings of the LISP site. Since the different
upstream ISPs are usually competing business entities, the ETRs may even be
configured to compete, to either attract all the traffic or get no traffic.
The former will happen if the customer pays per volume, the latter if
the connectivity has a fixed price. A solution could be to configure the
Map-Server(s) to do proxy-replying and have the Mapping Service Provider (MSP)
apply policies.</t>

        <t>Additionally, since xTR1, xTR2, and xTR3 are in different
administrative domains, locator reachability information is unlikely to be
exchanged among them, making it difficult to set the Locator-Status-Bits (LSBs)
correctly on encapsulated packets. Because of this, and due to the security
concerns about LSBs as described in <xref target="LISP-THREATS"/>,
their use is discouraged (set the L-bit to 0).  Map-Versioning is another
alternative <xref target="RFC6834" />.</t>

        <t>Compared to the customer edge scenario, deploying LISP at the
provider edge might have the advantage of diminishing potential MTU issues,
because the Tunnel Router is closer to the core, where links typically have
higher MTUs than edge network links.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Tunnel Routers behind NAT">
        <t>"NAT" in this section refers to IPv4 network address and port
translation.</t>

          <section title="ITR">
            <figure align="center" title="ITR behind NAT" anchor="fig_nat_itr">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
       _.--.                                           _.--.
   ,-''     `--.              +-------+            ,-''     `--. 
  '     EID     `   (Private) |  NAT  | (Public) ,'     RLOC    `. 
 (                )---[ITR]---|       |---------(                 )  
  .    space    ,'  (Address) |  Box  |(Address)  .    space    ,' 
   `--.     _.-'              +-------+            `--.     _.-'    
       `--''                                           `--''     
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
          <t>Packets encapsulated by an ITR are just UDP packets from a NAT
device's point of view, and they are handled like any UDP packet; there are no
additional requirements for LISP data packets.</t>

          <t>Map-Requests sent by an ITR, which create the state in the NAT
table, have a different 5-tuple in the IP header than the Map-Reply generated
by the authoritative ETR. Since the source address of this packet is different
from the destination address of the request packet, no state will be matched in
the NAT table and the packet will be dropped. To avoid this, the NAT device has
to do the following:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Send all UDP packets with source port 4342, regardless of the
destination port, to the RLOC of the ITR. The simplest way to achieve this
is configuring 1:1 NAT mode from the external RLOC of the NAT device to the
ITR's RLOC (called "DMZ" mode in consumer broadband routers).</t>

              <t>Rewrite the ITR-AFI and "Originating ITR RLOC Address" fields
in the payload.</t>

            </list>
          </t>
        <t>This setup supports only a single ITR behind the NAT device.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="ETR">
          <t>An ETR placed behind NAT is reachable from the outside by the
Internet-facing locator of the NAT device. It needs to know this locator (and
configure a loopback interface with it), so that it can use it in Map-Reply and
Map-Register messages. Thus, support for dynamic locators for the mapping
database is needed in LISP equipment.</t>

        <t>Again, only one ETR behind the NAT device is supported.</t>
        <figure align="center" title="ETR behind NAT" anchor="fig_nat_etr">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
       _.--.                                           _.--.
   ,-''     `--.              +-------+            ,-''     `--. 
  '     EID     `   (Private) |  NAT  | (Public) ,'     RLOC    `. 
 (                )---[ETR]---|       |---------(                 )  
  .    space    ,'  (Address) |  Box  |(Address)  .    space    ,' 
   `--.     _.-'              +-------+            `--.     _.-'    
       `--''                                           `--''     
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
        </section>
        <section title="Additional Notes">
          <t>An implication of the issues described above is that LISP sites
with xTRs cannot be behind carrier-based NATs, since two different sites would
collide on the same forwarded UDP port.  An alternative to static
hole-punching to explore is the use of the Port Control Protocol (PCP) <xref
target="RFC6887"/>.
</t>

          <t>We only include this scenario due to completeness, to show that a
LISP site can be deployed behind NAT should it become necessary. However, LISP
deployments behind NAT should be avoided, if possible.</t>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section title="Functional Models with Tunnel Routers">
        <t>This section describes how certain LISP deployments can provide
network functions.</t>

              <section title="Split ITR/ETR" anchor="split">
          <t>In a simple LISP deployment, xTRs are located at the border of the
LISP site (see <xref target="sec_ce" />). In this scenario, packets are routed
inside the domain according to the EID. However, more complex networks may want
to route packets according to the destination RLOC. This would enable them to
choose the best egress point.</t>

        <t>The LISP specification separates the ITR and ETR functionality and
allows both entities to be deployed in separated network equipment.  ITRs can
be deployed closer to the host (i.e., access routers).  This way, packets are
encapsulated as soon as possible, and egress point selection is driven by
operational policy.  In turn, ETRs can be deployed at the border routers of the
network, and packets are decapsulated as soon as possible.  Once decapsulated,
packets are routed based on the destination EID according to internal routing
policy.</t>

        <t>We can see an example in <xref target="fig_split"/>. The Source (S)
transmits packets using its EID, and in this particular case packets are
encapsulated at ITR_1. The encapsulated packets are routed inside the domain
according to the destination RLOC and can egress the network through the best
point (i.e., closer to the RLOC's Autonomous System (AS)). On the other hand,
inbound packets are received by ETR_1, which decapsulates them. Then, packets
are routed towards S according to the EID, again following the best path.</t>

      <figure align="center" title="Split ITR/ETR Scenario" anchor="fig_split">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+---------------------------------------+
|                                       |
|       +-------+                   +-------+         +-------+
|       | ITR_1 |---------+         | ETR_1 |-RLOC_A--| ISP_A |
|       +-------+         |         +-------+         +-------+
|  +-+        |           |             |
|  |S|        |    IGP    |             |
|  +-+        |           |             |
|       +-------+         |         +-------+         +-------+
|       | ITR_2 |---------+         | ETR_2 |-RLOC_B--| ISP_B |
|       +-------+                   +-------+         +-------+
|                                       |
+---------------------------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>This scenario has a set of implications:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The site must carry more-specific routes in order to choose the
best egress point, and typically BGP is used for this, increasing the
complexity of the network. However, this is usually already the case for LISP
sites that would benefit from this scenario.</t>

            <t>If the site is multihomed to different ISPs and any of the
upstream ISPs are doing unicast reverse path forwarding (uRPF) filtering,
this scenario may become impractical. To set the correct source RLOC in the
encapsulation header, ITRs need to first determine which ETR will be used by
the outgoing packet.

 This adds
complexity and reliability concerns.</t>

            <t>In LISP, ITRs set the reachability bits when encapsulating data
packets. Hence, ITRs need a mechanism to be aware of the liveness of all ETRs
serving their site.</t>

            <t>The MTU within the site network must be large enough to
accommodate encapsulated packets.</t>

            <t>In this scenario, each ITR is serving fewer hosts than in the
case when it is deployed at the border of the network. It has been shown that
the cache hit rate grows logarithmically with the amount of users <xref
target="CACHE" />. Taking this into account, when ITRs are deployed closer to
the host the effectiveness of the mapping cache may be lower (i.e., the miss
rate is higher). Another consequence of this is that the site may transmit a
higher amount of Map-Requests, increasing the load on the distributed mapping
database.</t>

            <t>By placing the ITRs inside the site, they will still need global
RLOCs.  This may add complexity to intra-site routing configurations and
more intra-site issues when there is a change of providers.</t>

          </list>
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Inter-Service-Provider Traffic Engineering">
        <t>At the time of this writing, if two ISPs want to control their
ingress TE policies for transit traffic between them, they need to rely on
existing BGP mechanisms.  This typically means deaggregating prefixes to choose
on which upstream link packets should enter.  This either is not feasible (if
fine-grained per-customer control is required, the very-specific prefixes may
not be propagated) or increases DFZ table size.</t>

        <t>Typically, LISP is seen as applicable only to stub networks;
however, LISP can also be applied in a recursive manner, providing
service provider ingress/egress TE capabilities without impacting the DFZ table
size.</t>

        <t>In order to implement this functionality with LISP, consider the
scenario depicted in <xref target="fig_inter" />.  The two ISPs willing to
achieve ingress/egress TE are labeled as ISP_A and ISP_B.  They are servicing
Stub1 and Stub2, respectively.  Both are required to be LISP sites with
their own xTRs.  In this scenario, we assume that Stub1 and Stub2 are
communicating with each other; thus, ISP_A and ISP_B offer transit for such
communications.  ISP_A has RLOC_A1 and RLOC_A2 as upstream IP addresses, while
ISP_B has RLOC_B1 and RLOC_B2.  The shared goal among ISP_A and ISP_B is to
control the transit traffic flow between RLOC_A1/A2 and RLOC_B1/B2.</t>

        <figure align="center" title="Inter-Service-Provider TE Scenario"
anchor="fig_inter">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                               _.--.                              
Stub1 ...   +-------+      ,-''     `--.      +-------+   ... Stub2
         \  |   R_A1|----,'             `. ---|R_B1   |  /
          --|       |   (     Transit     )   |       |--
 ...  .../  |   R_A2|-----.             ,' ---|R_B2   |  \... ...
            +-------+      `--.     _.-'      +-------+
 ...  ...     ISP_A            `--''            ISP_B     ... ...
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>Both ISPs deploy xTRs on RLOC_A1/A2 and RLOC_B1/B2, respectively
and reach a bilateral agreement to deploy their own private mapping system.
This mapping system contains bindings between the RLOCs of Stub1 and Stub2
(owned by ISP_A and ISP_B, respectively) and RLOC_A1/A2 and RLOC_B1/B2.  Such
bindings are in fact the TE policies between both ISPs, and the convergence
time is expected to be fast, since ISPs only have to update/query a mapping
to/from the database.</t>

        <t>The packet flow is as follows.  First, a packet originated at Stub1
towards Stub2 is LISP encapsulated by Stub1's xTR.  The xTR of ISP_A
recursively encapsulates it, and according to the TE policies stored in the
private mapping system the ISP_A xTR chooses RLOC_B1 or RLOC_B2 as the outer
encapsulation destination.  Note that the packet transits between ISP_A and
ISP_B double-encapsulated.  Upon reception at the xTR of ISP_B, the packet is
decapsulated and sent towards Stub2, which performs the last decapsulation.</t>

        <t>This deployment scenario, which uses recursive LISP, includes three
important caveats.  First, it is intended to be deployed between only two ISPs.
If more than two ISPs use this approach, then either the xTRs deployed at the
participating ISPs must query multiple mapping systems, or the ISPs must
agree on a common shared mapping system. Furthermore, keeping this deployment
scenario restricted to only two ISPs maintains a scalable solution, given
that only two entities need to agree on using recursive LISP and only one
private mapping system is involved. </t>

        <t>Second, the scenario is only recommended for ISPs providing
connectivity to LISP sites, such that source RLOCs of packets to be recursively
encapsulated belong to said ISP. Otherwise, the participating ISPs must
register prefixes they do not own in the above-mentioned private mapping
system. This results in either requiring complex authentication mechanisms or
enabling simple traffic redirection attacks. Failure to follow these
recommendations may lead to operational security issues when deploying this
scenario.</t> 
        <t>And third, recursive encapsulation models are typically complex to
troubleshoot and debug.</t>

        <t>Besides these recommendations, the main disadvantages of this
deployment case are:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>An extra LISP header is needed. This increases the packet size
and requires that the MTU between both ISPs accommodate double-encapsulated
packets.</t>

            <t>The ISP ITR must encapsulate packets and therefore must know the
RLOC-to-RLOC bindings. These bindings are stored in a mapping database and may
be cached in the ITR's mapping cache. Cache misses lead to an additional lookup
latency, unless a push-based mapping system is used for the private mapping
system.</t>

            <t>Maintaining the shared mapping database involves operational
overhead.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section title="Summary and Feature Matrix">
        <t>When looking at the deployment scenarios and functional models
above, there are several things to consider when choosing an appropriate
model, depending on the type of the organization doing the deployment.</t>

        <t>For home users and small sites that wish to multihome and have
control over their ISP options, the "CE" scenario offers the most advantages:
it's simple to deploy, and in some cases it only requires a software upgrade of
the Customer Premises Equipment (CPE), getting mapping service, and configuring
the router.  It retains control of TE and choosing upstreams by the user.  It
doesn't provide too many advantages to ISPs, due to the lessened dependence on
their services in cases of multihomed clients.  It is also unlikely that ISPs
wishing to offer LISP to their customers will choose the "CE" model, as they
would need to send a technician to each customer and, potentially, a new CPE
device.  Even if they have remote control over the router and a software
upgrade could add LISP support, the operation is too risky.</t>

        <t>For a network operator, a good option to deploy is the "PE"
scenario, unless a hardware upgrade is required for its edge routers to support
LISP (in which case upgrading CPEs may be simpler).  It retains control of TE
as well as the choice of Proxy Egress Tunnel Router (PETR) and
Map-Server/Map-Resolver. It also lowers potential MTU issues, as discussed
above. Network operators should also explore the "inter-service-provider TE"
(recursive) functional model for their TE needs.</t>

        <t>To optimize their traffic flow, large organizations can benefit the
most from the "split ITR/ETR" functional model.</t>

        <t>The following table gives a quick overview of the features supported
by each of the deployment scenarios discussed above (marked with an "x" in the
appropriate column): "CE" for customer edge, "PE" for provider edge, "Split"
for split ITR/ETR, and "Recursive" for inter-service-provider traffic
engineering. The discussed features include:

          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Control of ingress TE:">This scenario allows the LISP
site to easily control LISP ingress traffic engineering policies.</t>

            <t hangText="No modifications to existing int. network
infrastructure:">This scenario doesn't require the LISP site to modify internal
network configurations.</t>

            <t hangText="Locator-Status-Bits sync:">This scenario allows easy
synchronization of the Locator Status Bits.</t>

            <t hangText="MTU/PMTUD issues minimized:">The scenario minimizes
potential MTU and Path MTU Discovery (PMTUD) issues.</t>

          </list>
        </t>

        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
Feature                         CE    PE    Split   Recursive   NAT
--------------------------------------------------------------------
Control of ingress TE            x     -      x         x        x
No modifications to existing
   int. network infrastructure   x     x      -         -        x
Locator-Status-Bits sync         x     -      x         x        -
MTU/PMTUD issues minimized       -     x      -         -        -
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>      
    </section>

    <section title="Map-Servers and Map-Resolvers">
      <t>Map-Servers and Map-Resolvers make up the LISP mapping system and
provide a means to find authoritative EID-to-RLOC mapping information,
conforming to <xref target="RFC6833" />.  They are meant to be deployed in RLOC
space, and their operation behind NAT is not supported.</t>

      <section title="Map-Servers">
        <t>The Map-Server learns EID-to-RLOC mapping entries from an
authoritative source and publishes them in the distributed mapping
database. These entries are learned through authenticated Map-Register messages
sent by authoritative ETRs. Also, upon reception of a Map-Request, the
Map-Server verifies that the destination EID matches an EID-Prefix for which
it is authoritative and then re-encapsulates and forwards it to a matching
ETR. Map-Server functionality is described in detail in <xref target="RFC6833"
/>.</t>

        <t>The Map-Server is provided by a Mapping Service Provider (MSP).  The
MSP participates in the global distributed mapping database infrastructure by
setting up connections to other participants according to the specific mapping
system that is employed (e.g., Alternative Logical Topology (ALT) <xref
target="RFC6836" />, Delegated Database Tree (DDT) <xref target="LISP-DDT"/>).
Participation in the mapping database and the storing of EID-to-RLOC mapping
data are subject to the policies of the "root" operators, who should check
ownership rights for the EID-Prefixes stored in the database by participants.
These policies are out of scope for this document.</t>

        <t>The LISP DDT protocol is used by LISP MSPs to provide
reachability between those providers' Map-Resolvers and Map-Servers.
The DDT root is currently operated by a collection of organizations on an open
basis.  See <xref target="DDT-ROOT" /> for more details.  Similarly to the DNS
root, it has several different server instances using names of the letters of
the Greek alphabet (alpha, delta, etc.), operated by independent organizations.
When this document was published, there were 6 such instances, with one of them
being anycasted.  <xref target="DDT-ROOT" /> provides the list of server
instances on its web site and configuration files for several Map-Server
implementations.  The DDT root and LISP Mapping Providers both rely on and
abide by existing allocation policies as defined by Regional Internet
Registries (RIRs) to determine prefix ownership for use as EIDs.</t>

        <t>It is expected that the DDT root organizations will continue to
evolve in response to experimentation with LISP deployments for Internet edge
multihoming and VPN use cases.</t>

        <t>In all cases, the MSP configures its Map-Server(s) to publish the
prefixes of its clients in the distributed mapping database and start
encapsulating and forwarding Map-Requests to the ETRs of the AS. These ETRs
register their prefix(es) with the Map-Server(s) through periodic authenticated
Map-Register messages. In this context, for some LISP sites, there is a need
for mechanisms to:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Automatically distribute EID-Prefix(es) shared keys between the
ETRs and the EID-registrar Map-Server.</t>

            <t>Dynamically obtain the address of the Map-Server in the ETR of
the AS.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>The Map-Server plays a key role in the reachability of the
EID-Prefixes it is serving. On one hand, it is publishing these prefixes
into the distributed mapping database, and on the other hand, it is
encapsulating and forwarding Map-Requests to the authoritative ETRs of these
prefixes.  ITRs encapsulating towards EIDs for which a failed Map-Server 
is responsible will be unable to look up any of their covering prefixes.  The
only exceptions are the ITRs that already contain the mappings in their local
caches. In this case, ITRs can reach ETRs until the entry expires (typically
24 hours). For this reason, redundant Map-Server deployments are desirable.  A
set of Map-Servers providing high-availability service to the same set of
prefixes is called a redundancy group.  ETRs are configured to send
Map-Register messages to all Map-Servers in the redundancy group.  The
configuration for fail-over (or load-balancing, if desired) among the members
of the group depends on the technology behind the mapping system being
deployed.  Since ALT is based on BGP and DDT takes its inspiration from the
Domain Name System (DNS), deployments can leverage current industry best
practices for redundancy in BGP and DNS.  These best practices are out of
scope for this document.</t> 
        <t>Additionally, if a Map-Server has no reachability for any ETR
serving a given EID block, it should not originate that block into the mapping
system.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Map-Resolvers">
        <t>A Map-Resolver is a network infrastructure component that accepts
LISP-encapsulated Map-Requests, typically from an ITR, and finds the
appropriate EID-to-RLOC mapping by consulting the distributed mapping
database. Map-Resolver functionality is described in detail in <xref
target="RFC6833" />.</t>

        <t>Anyone with access to the distributed mapping database can set up a
Map-Resolver and provide EID-to-RLOC mapping lookup service. Database access
setup is mapping system specific.</t>

        <t>For performance reasons, it is recommended that LISP sites use
Map-Resolvers that are topologically close to their ITRs. ISPs supporting LISP
will provide this service to their customers, possibly restricting access to
their user base. LISP sites not in this position can use open access
Map-Resolvers, if available. However, regardless of the availability of open
access resolvers, the MSP providing the Map-Server(s) for a LISP site should
also make available Map-Resolver(s) for the use of that site.</t>

        <t>In medium- to large-size ASes, ITRs must be configured with the RLOC
of a Map-Resolver; this type of operation can be done manually. However, in
Small Office/Home Office (SOHO) scenarios, a mechanism for autoconfiguration
should be provided.</t>

        <t>One solution to avoid manual configuration in LISP sites of any size
is the use of anycast <xref target="RFC4786" /> RLOCs for Map-Resolvers,
similar to the DNS root server infrastructure. Since LISP uses UDP
encapsulation, the use of anycast would not affect reliability. LISP routers
are then shipped with a preconfigured list of well-known Map-Resolver RLOCs,
which can be edited by the network administrator, if needed.</t>

        <t>The use of anycast also helps improve mapping lookup
performance. Large MSPs can increase the number and geographical diversity of
their Map-Resolver infrastructure, using a single anycasted RLOC. Once LISP
deployment is advanced enough, very large content providers may also be
interested in running this kind of setup, to ensure minimal connection setup
latency for those connecting to their network from LISP sites.</t>

        <t>While Map-Servers and Map-Resolvers implement different
functionalities within the LISP mapping system, they can coexist on the same
device. For example, MSPs offering both services can deploy a single
Map-Resolver/Map-Server in each PoP where they have a presence.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Proxy Tunnel Routers">
      <section title="PITRs" anchor="pitr">
        <t>Proxy Ingress Tunnel Routers (PITRs) are part of the non-LISP/LISP
transition mechanism, allowing non-LISP sites to reach LISP sites. They
announce via BGP certain  EID-Prefixes (aggregated, whenever possible) to
attract traffic from non-LISP sites towards EIDs in the covered range. They do
the mapping system lookup and encapsulate received packets towards the
appropriate ETR. Note that for the reverse path, LISP sites can reach non-LISP
sites by simply not encapsulating traffic. See <xref target="RFC6832" /> for a
detailed description of PITR functionality.</t>

        <t>The success of new protocols depends greatly on their ability to
maintain backwards compatibility and interoperate with the protocol(s) they
intend to enhance or replace, and on the incentives to deploy the necessary new
software or equipment. A LISP site needs an interworking mechanism to be
reachable from non-LISP sites. A PITR can fulfill this role, enabling early
adopters to see the benefits of LISP, similar to tunnel brokers helping the
transition from IPv4 to IPv6. A site benefits from new LISP functionality
(proportionally with existing global LISP deployment) when migrating to LISP,
so it has the incentives to deploy the necessary Tunnel Routers. In order to be
reachable from non-LISP sites, it has two options: keep announcing its
prefix(es) with BGP, or have a PITR announce prefix(es) covering them.</t>

        <t>If the goal of reducing the DFZ routing table size is to be reached,
the second option is preferred. Moreover, the second option allows LISP-based
ingress traffic engineering from all sites. However, the placement of PITRs
significantly influences performance and deployment incentives. <xref
target="migration" /> is dedicated to the migration to a LISP-enabled Internet
and includes deployment scenarios for PITRs.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="PETRs">
        <t>In contrast to PITRs, PETRs are not required for the correct
functioning of all LISP sites. There are two cases where they can be of great
help:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>LISP sites with unicast reverse path forwarding (uRPF)
restrictions, and</t>

            <t>Communication between sites using different address family
RLOCs.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>In the first case, uRPF filtering is applied at the LISP site's
upstream provider's PE router. When forwarding traffic to non-LISP sites, an
ITR does not encapsulate packets, leaving the original IP headers intact. As a
result, packets will have EIDs in their source address. Since we are
discussing the transition period, we can assume that a prefix covering the
EIDs belonging to the LISP site is advertised to the global routing tables by
a PITR, and the PE router has a route towards it. However, the next hop will
not be on the interface towards the CE router, so non-encapsulated packets
will fail uRPF checks.</t>

        <t>To avoid this filtering, the affected ITR encapsulates packets
towards the locator of the PETR for non-LISP destinations. Now the source
address of the packets, as seen by the PE router, is the ITR's locator, which
will not fail the uRPF check. The PETR then decapsulates and forwards the
packets.</t>

        <t>The second use case is IPv4-to-IPv6 transition. Service providers
using older access network hardware that only supports IPv4 can still offer
IPv6 to their clients by providing a CPE device running LISP, and PETR(s) for
accessing IPv6-only non-LISP sites and LISP sites, with IPv6-only
locators. Packets originating from the client LISP site for these destinations
would be encapsulated towards the PETR's IPv4 locator. The PETR is in a
native IPv6 network, decapsulating and forwarding packets. For non-LISP
destinations, the packet travels natively from the PETR. For LISP destinations
with IPv6-only locators, the packet will go through a PITR in order to reach
its destination.</t>

        <t>For more details on PETRs, see <xref target="RFC6832" />.</t>

        <t>PETRs can be deployed by ISPs wishing to offer value-added services
to their customers. As is the case with PITRs, PETRs too may introduce path
stretch (the ratio between the cost of the selected path and that of the
optimal path). Because of this, the ISP needs to consider the tradeoff of using
several devices close to the customers to minimize it, or fewer devices
farther away from the customers to minimize cost instead.</t>

        <t>Since the deployment incentives for PITRs and PETRs are different,
it is likely that they will be deployed in separate devices, except for the
Content Delivery Network (CDN) case, which may deploy both in a single device.
</t>

        <t>In all cases, the existence of a PETR involves another step in the
configuration of a LISP router. CPE routers, which are typically configured by
DHCP, stand to benefit most from PETRs. Autoconfiguration of the PETR locator
could be achieved by a DHCP option or by adding a PETR field to either
Map-Notify or Map-Reply messages.</t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="migration" title="Migration to LISP">
      <t>This section discusses a deployment architecture to support the
migration to a LISP-enabled Internet. The loosely defined terms "early
transition phase", "late transition phase", and "LISP Internet phase" refer to
time periods when LISP sites are a minority, a majority, or represent all edge
networks, respectively.</t>

      <section title="LISP+BGP">
        <t>For sites wishing to migrate to LISP with their
Provider-Independent (PI) prefix, the least disruptive way is to upgrade their
border routers to support LISP and register the prefix into the LISP mapping
system, but to keep announcing it with BGP as well. This way, LISP sites will
reach them over LISP, while legacy sites will be unaffected by the change. The
main disadvantage of this approach is that no decrease in the DFZ routing
table size is achieved. Still, just increasing the number of LISP sites is an
important gain, as an increasing LISP/non-LISP site ratio may decrease the
need for BGP-based traffic engineering that leads to prefix
deaggregation. That, in turn, may lead to a decrease in the DFZ size and churn
in the late transition phase.</t>


        <t>This scenario is not limited to sites that already have their
prefixes announced with BGP. Newly allocated EID blocks could follow this
strategy as well during the early LISP deployment phase, depending on the
cost/benefit analysis of the individual networks. Since this leads to an
increase in the DFZ size, the following architecture should be preferred for
new allocations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mapping Service Provider (MSP) PITR Service">
        <t>In addition to publishing their clients' registered prefixes in the
mapping system, MSPs with enough transit capacity can offer PITR service to
them as a separate service. This service is especially useful for new PI
allocations to sites without existing BGP infrastructure wishing to avoid
BGP altogether. The MSP announces the prefix into the DFZ, and the client
benefits from ingress traffic engineering without prefix deaggregation. The
downside of this scenario is added path stretch.</t>

        <t>Routing all non-LISP ingress traffic through a third party that is
not one of its ISPs is only feasible for sites with modest amounts of traffic
(like those using the IPv6 tunnel broker services today), especially in the
first stage of the transition to LISP, with a significant number of legacy
sites. This is because the handling of said traffic is likely to result in
additional costs, which would be passed down to the client. When the
LISP/non-LISP site ratio becomes high enough, this approach can prove
increasingly attractive.</t>

        <t>Compared to LISP+BGP, this approach avoids DFZ bloat caused by
prefix deaggregation for traffic engineering purposes, resulting in slower
routing table increase in the case of new allocations and potential decrease
for existing ones. Moreover, MSPs serving different clients with adjacent
aggregatable prefixes may lead to additional decrease, but quantifying this
decrease is subject to future research study.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Proxy-ITR Route Distribution (PITR-RD)">
        <t>Instead of a LISP site or the MSP announcing its EIDs with BGP
to the DFZ, this function can be outsourced to a third party, a PITR Service
Provider (PSP). This will result in a decrease in operational complexity at
both the site and the MSP.</t>

        <t>The PSP manages a set of distributed PITR(s) that will advertise
the corresponding EID-Prefixes through BGP to the DFZ. These PITRs will then
encapsulate the traffic they receive for those EIDs towards the RLOCs of the
LISP site, ensuring their reachability from non-LISP sites.</t>

        <t>While it is possible for a PSP to manually configure each client's
EID-Routes to be announced, this approach offers little flexibility and is not
scalable. This section presents a scalable architecture that offers automatic
distribution of EID-Routes to LISP sites and service providers.</t>

        <t>The architecture requires no modification to existing LISP network
elements, but it introduces a new (conceptual) network element, the EID-Route
Server, which is defined as a router that either propagates routes learned
from other EID-Route Servers or originates EID-Routes. The EID-Routes that it
originates are those for which it is authoritative. It propagates these routes
to Proxy-ITRs within the AS of the EID-Route Server. It is worth noting that a
BGP-capable router can also be considered an EID-Route Server.</t>

        <t>Further, an EID-Route is defined as a prefix originated via the
Route Server of the MSP, which should be aggregated if the MSP has
multiple customers inside a single large continuous prefix. This prefix
is propagated to other PITRs both within the MSP and to other PITR operators
with which it peers. EID-Route Servers are operated by either the LISP site,
MSPs, or PSPs and may be collocated with a Map-Server or PITR, but they are
functionally discrete entities. They distribute EID-Routes, using BGP, to other
domains according to policies set by participants. </t>

        <figure align="center" title="PITR-RD Architecture" anchor="pitrrd">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     MSP (AS64500)
                     RS ---> PITR
                      |        /
                      |  _.--./           
                     ,-''    /`--.      
    LISP site   ---,' |     v     `. 
                  (   |   DFZ       )----- Mapping system
non-LISP site   ----. |    ^      ,'
                     `--. /   _.-'      
                      |  `--''          
                      v /
                    PITR
                    PSP (AS64501)
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The architecture described above decouples EID origination from
route propagation, with the following benefits:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Can accurately represent business relationships between PITR
operators</t>

            <t>Is more mapping system agnostic</t>
            <t>Makes minor changes to PITR implementation; no changes to other
components</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>In the example in <xref target="pitrrd"/>, we have a MSP providing
services to the LISP site. The LISP site does not run BGP and gets an EID
allocation directly from a RIR, or from the MSP, which may be a Local Internet
Registry (LIR). Existing PI allocations can be migrated as well. The MSP
ensures the presence of the prefix in the mapping system and runs an
EID-Route Server to distribute it to PSPs. Since the LISP site does not run
BGP, the prefix will be originated with the AS number of the MSP.</t>

        <t>In the simple case depicted in <xref target="pitrrd"/>, the
EID-Route of a LISP site will be originated by the Route Server and announced
to the DFZ by the PSP's PITRs with AS path 64501 64500. From that point on,
the usual BGP dynamics apply. This way, routes announced by the PITR are still
originated by the authoritative Route Server. Note that the peering
relationships between MSPs/PSPs and those in the underlying forwarding plane may
not be congruent, making the AS path to a PITR shorter than it is in
reality.</t>

        <t>The non-LISP site will select the best path towards the EID-Prefix
according to its local BGP policies. Since AS-path length is usually an
important metric for selecting paths, careful placement of PITRs could
significantly reduce path stretch between LISP and non-LISP sites.</t>

        <t>The architecture allows for flexible policies between
MSPs/PSPs. Consider the EID-Route Server networks as control plane overlays,
facilitating the implementation of policies necessary to reflect the business
relationships between participants. The results are then injected into the
common underlying forwarding plane. For example, some MSPs/PSPs may agree to
exchange EID-Prefixes and only announce them to each of their forwarding plane
customers. Global reachability of an EID-Prefix depends on the MSP from
which the LISP site buys service and is also subject to agreement between the
above-mentioned parties.</t>

        <t>In terms of impact on the DFZ, this architecture results in a slower
routing table increase for new allocations, since traffic engineering will be
done at the LISP level. For existing allocations migrating to LISP, the DFZ may
decrease, since MSPs may be able to aggregate the prefixes announced.</t>

        <t>Compared to LISP+BGP, this approach avoids DFZ bloat caused by
prefix deaggregation for traffic engineering purposes, resulting in slower
routing table increase in the case of new allocations and potential decrease
for existing ones. Moreover, MSPs serving different clients with adjacent
aggregatable prefixes may lead to additional decrease, but quantifying this
decrease is subject to future research study. </t>

        <t>The flexibility and scalability of this architecture do not come
without a cost, however: A PSP operator has to establish either transit or
peering relationships to improve its connectivity.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Migration Summary">
        <t>Registering a domain name typically entails an annual fee that
should cover the operating expenses for publishing the domain in the global
DNS.  This situation is similar for several other registration services.  A
LISP MSP client publishing an EID-Prefix in the LISP mapping system has
the option of signing up for PITR services as well, for an extra fee.
These services may be offered by the MSP itself, but it is expected that
specialized PSPs will do it.  Clients that do not sign up will be responsible
for getting non-LISP traffic to their EIDs (using the LISP+BGP scenario).</t>

        <t>Additionally, Tier 1 ISPs have incentives to offer PITR services to
non-subscribers in strategic places just to attract more traffic from
competitors and thus more revenue.</t>

        <t>The following table presents the expected effects that the
transition scenarios at various phases will have on the DFZ routing table size:

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
Phase            | LISP+BGP     | MSP PITR        | PITR-RD
-----------------+--------------+-----------------+----------------
Early transition | no change    | slower increase | slower increase
Late transition  | may decrease | slower increase | slower increase
LISP Internet    |             considerable decrease       
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>It is expected that PITR-RD will coexist with LISP+BGP during the
migration, with the latter being more popular in the early transition phase. As
the transition progresses and the MSP PITR and PITR-RD ecosystem gets more
ubiquitous, LISP+BGP should become less attractive, slowing down the increase
of the number of routes in the DFZ.</t>

        <t>Note that throughout <xref target="migration" /> we focused on the
effects of LISP deployment on the DFZ routing table size.  Other metrics may be
impacted as well but to the best of our knowledge have not been measured as
yet.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>All security implications of LISP deployments are to be discussed in
separate documents. <xref target="LISP-THREATS" /> gives an overview of LISP
threat models, including ETR operators attracting traffic by overclaiming an
EID-Prefix (Section 4.4.3 of <xref target="LISP-THREATS" />). Securing
mapping lookups is discussed in <xref target="LISP-SEC"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ACKs" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to Margaret Wasserman for her contribution to the IETF 76
presentation that kickstarted this work. The authors would also like to thank
Damien Saucez, Luigi Iannone, Joel Halpern, Vince Fuller, Dino Farinacci, Terry
Manderson, Noel Chiappa, Hannu Flinck, Paul Vinciguerra, Fred Templin, Brian
Haberman, and everyone else who provided input.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6830.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6832.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6833.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4984.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6834.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6835.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6836.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6887.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4459.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4786.xml"?>

<!-- draft-ietf-lisp-ddt (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='LISP-DDT'>
<front>
<title>LISP Delegated Database Tree</title>
<author initials='V' surname='Fuller' fullname='Vince Fuller'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Lewis' fullname='Darrel Lewis'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='V' surname='Ermagan' fullname='Vina Ermagan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Jain' fullname='Amit Jain'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-lisp-sec (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='LISP-SEC'>
<front>
<title>LISP-Security (LISP-SEC)</title>
<author initials='F' surname='Maino' fullname='Fabio Maino'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='V' surname='Ermagan' fullname='Vina Ermagan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Cabellos-Aparicio' fullname='Albert Cabellos-Aparicio'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Saucez' fullname='Damien Saucez'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='O' surname='Bonaventure' fullname='Olivier Bonaventure'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-lisp-threats (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='LISP-THREATS'>
<front>
<title>LISP Threats Analysis</title>
<author initials='D' surname='Saucez' fullname='Damien Saucez'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='L' surname='Iannone' fullname='Luigi Iannone'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='O' surname='Bonaventure' fullname='Olivier Bonaventure'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' year='2014' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

      <reference anchor="CACHE">
        <front>
          <title>DNS performance and the effectiveness of caching</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Jung" />
          <author initials="E." surname="Sit" />
          <author initials="H." surname="Balakrishnan" />
          <author initials="R." surname="Morris" />
          <date month="October" year="2002" />
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name="IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (TON),"
        value="Volume 10, Issue 5, pages 589-603"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DDT-ROOT" target="http://ddt-root.org/">
        <front>
          <title>Introduction to LISP DDT: DDT Root</title>
          <author/>
          <date month="March" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TELCO96" target="http://transition.fcc.gov/telecom.html">
        <front>
          <title>Telecommunications Act of 1996</title>
          <author><organization>Federal Communications Commission</organization></author>
          <date year="1996"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section title="Step-by-Step Example BGP-to-LISP Migration Procedure">
      <t>To help the operational community deploy LISP, this informative
section offers a step-by-step guide for migrating a BGP-based Internet presence
to a LISP site.  It includes a pre-install/pre&nbhy;turn&nbhy;up checklist, and customer
and provider activation procedures.</t>

      <section title="Customer Pre-Install and Pre-Turn-Up Checklist">
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Determine how many current physical service provider connections
the customer has, and their existing bandwidth and traffic engineering
requirements.

              <vspace blankLines="1" />
              This information will determine the number of routing locators,
and the priorities and weights that should be configured on the xTRs.</t>

            <t>Make sure the customer router has LISP capabilities.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Check the OS version of the CE router. If LISP is an add-on,
check to see if it is installed.

                  <vspace blankLines="1" />
                  This information can be used to determine if the platform is
appropriate to support LISP, in order to determine if a software and/or
hardware upgrade is required.</t>

                <t>Have the customer upgrade (if necessary, software and/or
hardware) to be LISP capable.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Obtain the current running configuration of the CE router. A
suggested LISP router configuration example can be customized to the customer's
existing environment.</t>

            <t>Verify MTU handling.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Request an increase in MTU to 1556 or more on service
provider connections. Prior to the MTU change, verify the transmission of a
1500-byte packet from the PxTR to the RLOC with the Don't Fragment (DF) bit
set.</t>

                <t>Ensure that the customer is not filtering
ICMP Unreachable or Time Exceeded messages on their firewall or router.</t>

              </list>
              LISP, like any tunneling protocol, will increase the size of
packets when the LISP header is appended.  If increasing the MTU of the access
links is not possible, care must be taken that ICMP is not being filtered in
order to allow Path MTU Discovery to take place.</t>

            <t>Validate member prefix allocation.
              <vspace blankLines="1" />
              This step checks to see whether the prefix used by the customer
              is a direct (Provider-Independent) prefix or a prefix assigned
              by a physical service provider (Provider Aggregatable). If the
              prefixes are assigned by other service providers, then a
              Letter of Agreement is required to announce prefixes through
              the Proxy Service Provider.</t>

            <t>Verify the member RLOCs and their reachability.
              <vspace blankLines="1" />
              This step ensures that the RLOCs configured on the CE router are
in fact reachable and working.</t>

            <t>Prepare for cut-over.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>If possible, have a host outside of all security and
filtering policies connected to the console port of the edge router or
switch.</t>

                <t>Make sure the customer has access to the router in order to
configure it.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Customer Activating LISP Service">
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>The customer configures LISP on CE router(s) according to
            the configuration recommended by the service provider.

              <vspace blankLines="1" />
              The LISP configuration consists of the EID-Prefix, the locators,
and the weights and priorities of the mapping between the two values.  In
addition, the xTR must be configured with Map-Resolver(s), Map-Server(s), and
the shared key for registering to Map-Server(s).  If required, Proxy-ETR(s) may
be configured as well.

              <vspace blankLines="1" />
              In addition to the LISP configuration:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Ensure that the default routes(s) to next-hop
                external neighbors is included and RLOCs are present in the
                configuration.</t>

                <t>If two or more routers are used, ensure that all RLOCs are
included in the LISP configuration on all routers.</t>

                <t>It will be necessary to redistribute the default route via
                IGP between the external routers.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
            <t>When transition is ready, perform a soft shutdown on existing
eBGP peer session(s).

              <list style="symbols">
                <t>From the CE router, use the LISP Internet Groper (LIG)
                <xref target="RFC6835"/> to ensure that registration is
                successful.</t>

                <t>To verify LISP connectivity, find and ping LISP connected
sites.  If possible, find ping destinations that are not covered by a prefix in
the global BGP routing system, because PITRs may deliver the packets even if
LISP connectivity is not working.  Traceroutes may help determine if this
is the case.</t>

                <t>To verify connectivity to non-LISP sites, try accessing a
landmark (e.g., a major Internet site) via a web browser.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Cut-Over Provider Preparation and Changes">
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Verify site configuration, and then verify active registration
            on Map-Server(s).

              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Authentication key.</t>
                <t>EID-Prefix.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Add EID space to map-cache on proxies.</t>
            <t>Add networks to BGP advertisement on proxies.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Modify route-maps/policies on PxTRs.</t>
                <t>Modify route policies on core routers (if non-connected
                member).</t>
                <t>Modify ingress policies on core routers.</t>
                <t>Ensure route announcement in looking glass servers,
                RouteViews.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Perform traffic verification test.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Ensure that MTU handling is as expected (PMTUD working).</t>
                <t>Ensure Proxy-ITR map-cache population.</t>
                <t>Ensure access from traceroute/ping servers around
                Internet.</t>

                <t>Use a looking glass to check for external visibility of
                registration via several Map-Resolvers.</t>

              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
