<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY RFC1396 PUBLIC '' 
		'reference.RFC.1396.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC2026 PUBLIC '' 
		'reference.RFC.2026.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC2418 PUBLIC '' 
		'reference.RFC.2418.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC3710 PUBLIC '' 
		'reference.RFC.3710.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC7437 PUBLIC '' 
		'reference.RFC.7437.xml'>
]>

<rfc number="7475" seriesNo="9" category="bcp" ipr="trust200902" 
	submissionType="IETF" updates="2026, 2418">


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

	<front>

	        <title abbrev='More Area Directors in an Area'>
			Increasing the Number of Area Directors in an IETF Area</title>

		<author initials="S." surname="Dawkins" fullname="Spencer Dawkins">
			<organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>
			<address>
	      			<email>spencerdawkins.ietf@gmail.com</email>
	 		</address>
	  	</author>

        	<date month="March" year="2015" />
		<workgroup>IESG</workgroup>

<keyword>IESG</keyword>
<keyword>AD</keyword>

        	<abstract>
			<t>This document removes a limit on the number of Area Directors who manage an 
				Area in the definition of "IETF Area".
				This document updates RFC 2026 (BCP 9) and RFC 2418 (BCP 25).
			</t>
		</abstract>

	</front>

	<middle>

        <section title="Introduction and Scope">

		<t>This document updates RFC 2026 (<xref target="RFC2026"/>, BCP 9) to remove a
			limit on the number of Area Directors who manage an Area in the definition of 
            "IETF Area".
			This document also updates RFC 2418 (<xref target="RFC2418"/>, BCP 25) to reflect this 
			updated definition.
		</t>

		<t>The change described in this document is intended to allow the
			IESG additional flexibility in organizing the IETF's work.  It does
   			not make any changes to the role of an Area and does
   			not argue that assigning more than two Area Directors to an
   			Area is an optimal solution in the long run. In particular, this
   			change is not intended to increase the size of the IESG
   			significantly. If several Areas will require more than two Area
   			Directors, the IESG should consider investigating alternative
   			ways of organizing the IETF's work.
		</t>

	</section>

        <section title="Discussion">

        	<t>In recent discussions, the IESG has explored splitting and combining Areas. 
			One proposal resulted in a single Area that would be managed by three Area Directors.
		</t>

        	<t>An Area managed by three Area Directors conflicts with this definition 
			in Section 14, &quot;DEFINITIONS OF TERMS&quot; of RFC 2026 (<xref target="RFC2026"/>):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>IETF Area - A management division within the IETF.  An Area consists
      				of Working Groups related to a general topic such as routing.  An
      				Area is managed by one or two Area Directors.
			</t>
		</list></t>

		<t>A similar statement appears in Section 1, &quot;Introduction&quot; of RFC 2418 (<xref target="RFC2418"/>):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>Each IETF area is managed by one or two Area Directors (ADs). 
			</t>
		</list></t>

        <t>While it's true that recent IESGs have had two Area Directors in each Area 
            except for the General Area, the number of Area Directors in each Area has 
            varied since the publication of RFC 1396 (<xref target="RFC1396"/>). (For reference, see
            &lt;http://www.ietf.org/iesg/past-members.html&gt;.)
        </t>
            
        <t>This variation was due to a number of factors, including workload and personal
            preferences, and happened as a natural part of the IESG organizing itself to 
            do the work the IESG is chartered to do.
        </t>
            
        <t>At one point, the IESG placed three Area Directors in a single Area (Scott Bradner,
            Deirdre Kostick, and Michael O'Dell, in the Operational &amp; Management 
            Requirements Area, between IETF 36 and IETF 37 in 1996).
		</t>

		<t>The last time the IESG increased the number of Area
			Directors in an Area was when they requested that the Nominating Committee
			provide a second Area Director in the Routing Area in 1999. Although the number of 
            Area Directors in an 
			Area hasn't changed since then, the IESG continues to be responsible for specifying the 
			positions that the Nominating Committee fills each year. 
		</t>


		<t>It is consistent with the IESG's role in creating and dismantling entire Areas to allow the IESG
			flexibility in assigning enough Area Directors who have been selected by the Nominating Committee to
			effectively manage the working groups within an Area.
		</t>

		<t>Note the requirement in RFC 7437  (<xref target="RFC7437"/>, BCP 10) 
			that the Nominating Committee review (approximately) 
			half the positions for the IESG each
			year is unchanged. The Nominating Committee may assign an appropriate term duration for each position to 
			ensure the ideal application of this rule in the future,
			and this is also unchanged.
		</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Normative Text Change">

        	<t>For this text (OLD) in Section 14, &quot;DEFINITIONS OF TERMS&quot; 
			of RFC 2026 (<xref target="RFC2026"/>):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>IETF Area - A management division within the IETF.  An Area consists
      				of Working Groups related to a general topic such as routing.  An
      				Area is managed by one or two Area Directors.
			</t>
		</list></t>

        	<t>Replace with this text (NEW):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>IETF Area - A management division within the IETF.  An Area consists
      				of Working Groups related to a general topic such as routing.  An
      				Area is managed by one or more Area Directors.
			</t>
		</list></t>

        	<t>For this text (OLD) in Section 1, &quot;Introduction&quot; of RFC 2418 (<xref target="RFC2418"/>):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>Each IETF area is managed by one or two Area Directors (ADs).  
			</t>
		</list></t>

        	<t>Replace with this text (NEW):
		</t>

		<t><list style="empty">
			<t>Each IETF area is managed by one or more Area Directors (ADs).  
			</t>
		</list></t>

		<t>Informational RFCs such as RFC 3710 (<xref target="RFC3710"/>) and informal descriptions
			of IETF organizational structure that also describe 
			IETF Areas as being managed by one or two Area Directors should be considered updated
			by this normative specification.
		</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">

        	<t>This document updates an IETF process BCP 
			and has no direct Internet security implications.
		</t>

        </section>


    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title='Normative References'>

		  &RFC2026;
		  &RFC2418;
		  &RFC7437;

	    </references>

        <references title='Informative References'>

          &RFC1396;
          &RFC3710;

	    </references>


        <section title="Acknowledgements">

        	<t>Thanks to Barry Leiba and Jari Arkko for applying the giggle test to version -00
                 of this document,
			     and to Adrian Farrel, Alexey Melnikov, Brian Carpenter, Christer Holmberg, 
                 David Crocker, 
                 David Harrington, Donald Eastlake, Kathleen Moriarty, Murray Kucherawy, 
                 Susan Hares, Stephan Farrell, and Stewart Bryant for providing review comments.
		    </t>
            
            <t>Thanks to Fred Baker, Michael St. Johns, 
                and Scott Bradner for providing a better understanding of
                the history of how the IESG ended up with two Area Directors 
                in most Areas
                and even, at one point, three Area Directors in one Area.
            </t>

        </section>

    </back>

</rfc>
