<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>  
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="7444" ipr="trust200902" category="info" submissionType="independent">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Security Labels in Internet Email">Security Labels in Internet Email</title>
    <author initials="K." surname="Zeilenga" fullname="Kurt Zeilenga">
      <organization>Isode Limited</organization>
      <address>
	<email>Kurt.Zeilenga@isode.com</email>
     </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
      <organization>Isode Limited</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>14 Castle Mews</street>
	  <city>Hampton</city>
	  <region>Middlesex</region>
	  <code>TW12 2NP</code>
	  <country>United Kingdom</country>
	</postal>
	<email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
     </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2015"/>

    <keyword>email</keyword>
    <keyword>header fields</keyword>
    <keyword>ESS</keyword>
    <keyword>Security Label</keyword>
    <keyword>Confidential Label</keyword>
    <keyword>Message Sensitivity</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a header field, SIO-Label, for use in
      Internet email to convey the sensitivity of the message. This header
      field may carry a textual
        representation (a display marking) and/or a structural representation
	(a security label) of the sensitivity of the message. This document
	also describes a header field,
        SIO-Label-History, for recording changes in the message's label.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>A security label, sometimes referred to as a confidentiality label,
      is a structured representation of the sensitivity of a piece of
      information. A security label can be
        used in conjunction with a clearance, a structured representation of
	what sensitive information a person (or other entity) is
	authorized to access, and a security
        policy to control access to each piece of information. For instance,
	an email message could have an "EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL" label that
	requires the sender and the
        receiver to have a clearance granting access to information labeled
	"EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL". <xref target="X.841">X.841</xref> provides a
	discussion of security labels,
        clearances, and security policy.</t>

      <t>A display marking is a textual representation of the sensitivity of a piece of information. For instance, "EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL" is a textual representation of the
        sensitivity. A security policy can be used to generate display markings from security labels. Display markings are generally expected to be prominently displayed whenever
        the content is displayed.</t>

      <t>Sensitivity-based authorization is used in networks that operate
      under a set of information classification rules, such as in government and
      military agency networks. 


The
        standardized formats for security labels, clearances, security policy, and associated authorization models are generalized and can be used in non-government deployments
        where appropriate.</t>

      <t>Security labels may also be used for purposes other than authorization. In particular, they may be used simply to convey the sensitivity of a piece information. The
        security label could be used, for instance, to organize content in a content store.</t>

      <t>This document describes a protocol for conveying the sensitivity of a electronic mail message <xref target="RFC5322"/> as a whole. In particular, this document describes
        a header field, SIO-Label, that carries a security label, a display
	marking, and display colors. This document also describes a header
	field, SIO-Label-History, that records
        changes in the message's security label.</t>

      <t>This protocol is based in part upon "XEP-0258: Security Labels in XMPP" <xref target="XEP258"/>.</t>

      <section title="Relationship to Inline Sensitivity Markings">
        <t>In environments requiring messages to be marked with an indication of their sensitivity, it is common to place a textual representation of the sensitivity, a display
          marking, within the body to the message and/or in the Subject header field. For instance, the authors often receives messages of the form:</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
To: author <author@example.com>;
From: Some One <someone@example.net>;
Subject: the subject (UNCLASSIFIED)

UNCLASSIFIED

Text of the message.

UNCLASSIFIED
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Typically, when placed in the body of the message, the marking is
	inserted into the content such that it appears as the first line(s) of
	text in the body of the message.
          This is known as a FLOT (First Line(s) of Text) marking. The marking
	  may or may not be surrounded by other text indicating that the marking denotes the sensitivity of the
          message. A FLOT may also be accompanied by a LLOT (Last Line(s) of
	  Text) marking. The message above contains a two-line FLOT and a
	  two-line LLOT (in both cases, a line
          providing the marking and an empty line between the marking and the
       	original content appear).</t>


        <t>Typically, when placed in the Subject of the message, the marking
	is inserted before or after the contents of the original Subject
	field; it is surrounded by parentheses or the
          like and/or separated from the content by white space.</t>


        <t>The particular syntax and semantics of inline sensitivity markings
	are generally a local matter. This hinders interoperability within an
	organization wanting to take
          actions based upon these markings and hinders interoperability
	between cooperating organizations wanting to usefully share
	sensitivity information</t>


        <t>The authors expect that such markings will continue to be widely used,
	especially in the absence of ubiquitous support for a standardized
	header field indicating the sensitivity
          of the message.</t>

        <t>The authors hope that through the use of a formally specified header
	field, interoperability within organizations and between organizations
	can be improved.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Relationship to Preexisting Security Label Header Fields">
        <t> A number of non-standard header fields, such as the X-X411 field,
	are used to carry a representation of the sensitivity of the message,
	whether a structured
          representation or textual representation. </t>

        <t> The authors hope that the use of preexisting (non-standard) header
	fields will be replaced, over time, with the use of the header field
	described in this document. </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Relationship to Enhanced Security Services for S/MIME">
        <t>Enhanced Security Services for S/MIME (ESS) <xref
	target="RFC2634"/> provides, amongst other services, signature
	services "for content integrity, non-repudiation with
          the proof of origin, and [securely] binding attributes (such as a
	security label) to the original content".</t>

        <t>While it may be possible to utilize the protocol described in this
	document concurrently with ESS, this protocol should generally be
	viewed as an alternative to ESS.</t>

        <t>It is noted that in ESS, the security label applies to MIME <xref
	target="RFC2045"/> content, where in this protocol, the label applies
	to the message as a whole.</t>

        <t>It is also noted that in ESS, security labels are securely bound to
	the MIME content through the use of digital signatures. This protocol
	does not provide message-signing services and hence does not provide secure binding the
	label to the message, content integrity, or non-repudiation
	of the proof of origin.</t>

        <t>This protocol is designed for situations/environments where message
	signing is not necessary to provide sufficient security.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

      <t>The formal syntax specifications in this document use the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) as described in <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

      <t>The term "base64 encoding" is used to refer to the "Base 64 encoding"
      defined in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC4648"/>. The term "BER
      encoding" is used to refer to encoding
        per the Basic Encoding Rules (BER) as defined in <xref target="X.690"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">

      <t>A Mail User Agent (MUA) originating a message can, if so configured,
      offer the user a menu of sensitivities to choose from and, upon
      selection, insert the display
        marking, foreground and background colors, and security label
      parameters associated with that selection into the SIO-Label header
      field of the message. </t>


      <t>Mail Submission Agents (MSAs), Mail Transfer Agents (MTAs), and Mail
      Delivery Agents (MDAs) can then, if so configured, use the provided 
 sensitivity
        information (or lack thereof) in determining whether to accept, forward, or otherwise
	act on the message as submitted. These agents, hereafter referred to
	as Service Agents (SAs), can, if
        so configured, modify the sensitivity information of the message, such
	as replacing the security label and/or display marking with 
	equivalent representations of the
        sensitivity of the message. SAs that add, modify, or delete the
      SIO-Label header field SHOULD add an SIO-Label-History header.</t>


      <t>Receiving MUAs that implement this extension SHALL, when displaying
      the message, also prominently display the marking, if any, conveyed in
      the SIO-Label header field or,
        if policy-aware and configured to display locally generated markings,
	a marking generated by the conveyed label and the governing policy. It
	is also desirable to display
        this marking in listings of messages. In the case the conveyed marking
	is displayed, the marking SHOULD be displayed using the foreground and
	background colors conveyed in the
        header field. In the case the marking was generated from a conveyed
	label and the governing policy, the marking SHOULD be displayed using
	the foreground and background colors
        conveyed by the governing policy.</t>

      <t>While MUAs are not expected to make authorization decisions based
      upon values of the SIO-Label header field, MUAs can otherwise use the
      provided 
        sensitivity information (or lack thereof) in determining how to act on
	the message. For instance, the MUA may organize messages in its store
	of messages based upon the content of this header
        field.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="The SIO-Label Header Field">
      <t>The header field name is "SIO-Label", and its content is a set of
      key/value pairs, each referred to as a parameter.</t>

      <t>Formal header field syntax:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork type="ABNF"><![CDATA[
sio-label = "SIO-Label:" [FWS] sio-label-parm-seq [FWS] CRLF

sio-label-parm-seq = sio-label-parm
    [ [FWS] ";" [FWS] sio-label-parm-seq ]

sio-label-parm = parameter
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>where the parameter production is defined in 
<xref target="RFC2231"/>, the FWS production is
 defined in <xref target="RFC5322"/>, and the CRLF production is defined in
 <xref target="RFC5234"/>. It is noted that the productions defined in <xref target="RFC2231"/>
	  rely on the ABNF in <xref target="RFC0822"/>, which implicitly allows for
	  white space in certain cases. In                             
        particular, white space is implicitly allowed in the parameter
	production immediately before and after the "=". It is also noted that
	<xref target="RFC2231"/> allows for quoted-string                              
        values (for parameter production) of substantial length, for
	string characters outside of US-ASCII, or for other such
	cases. Implementors should consult the referenced                            
        specifications for details.</t>


      <t>The "marking" parameter is a display string for use by
      implementations that are unable or unwilling to utilize the governing
      security policy to generate display markings.
      The "marking" parameter SHOULD generally be provided in SIO-Label
      header fields. It ought only be absent where an SA relies on other SAs
      to generate the marking.</t>

      <t>The "fgcolor" and "bgcolor" parameters are tokens restricted to color
      production representing the foreground and background colors,
      respectively, for use in colorizing the
        display marking string. Their values are RGB colors in hexadecimal
	format (e.g., "#ff0000"), or one of the Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) color names (e.g., "red")
	given in named-color type below
        (the 16 HTML4 colors + "orange") <xref target="CSS3-Color"/>. The
	default foreground color is black. The default background is
	white. The "fgcolor" and "bgcolor" parameters
        SHALL be absent if the "marking" parameter is absent. The HEXDIG
      production below is defined in <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

      <t>Formal color syntax:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork type="ABNF"><![CDATA[
color = hex-color / named-color

hex-color = "#" 6HEXDIG    ; Hex-encoded RGB

named-color =
           "aqua" /
           "black" /
           "blue" /
           "fuschia" /
           "gray" /
           "green" /
           "lime" /
           "maroon" /
           "navy" /
           "olive" /
           "purple" /
           "red" /
           "silver" /
           "teal" /
           "white" /
           "yellow" /
           "orange" ; named colors        
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>The "type" parameter is a quoted string containing the string ":ess",
      the string ":x411", the string ":xml", or a URI <xref
      target="RFC3986"/> denoting the type and
        encoding of the "label" parameter. The "label" parameter value is a quoted
	string. The "type" parameter SHALL be present if the "label" parameter
	is present. The "label"
        parameter SHALL be present if the "type" parameter is present. 
        When sensitivity-based
        authorization is performed, the
	absence of the "type" and "label" parameters indicates that the message is
	handled under default handling rules (e.g., as if
      no SIO-Label was present).</t>

      <t>The string ":ess" indicates that the "label" parameter value is the base64 encoding of the BER encoding of an ESS security label <xref target="RFC2634"/>. </t>
      <t>ESS Label Example:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
SIO-Label: marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    fgcolor=black; bgcolor=red;
    type=":ess"; label="MQYGASkCAQM="
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>The string ":x411" indicates that the "label" parameter value is the base64 encoding of the BER encoding of an X.411 security label <xref target="X.411"/>.</t>
      <t>X.411 Label Example:</t>
      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
SIO-Label: marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    fgcolor=black; bgcolor=red;
    type=":x411"; label="MQYGASkCAQM="
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>The string ":xml" indicates that the "label" parameter value is the base64
      encoding of a security label represented using <xref target="XML"/>. The XML prolog SHOULD be absent
        unless specifically required (such as when the character encoding is not UTF-8). The particular flavor of security label representation is indicated by the root element
        name and its name space.</t>


      <t>XML Label Example:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
SIO-Label: marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    fgcolor=black; bgcolor=red;
    type=":xml";
    label*0="PFNlY0xhYmVsIHhtbG5zPSJodHRwOi8vZXhhbX";
    label*1="BsZS5jb20vc2VjLWxhYmVsLzAiPjxQb2xpY3lJ";
    label*2="ZGVudGlmaWVyIFVSST0idXJuOm9pZDoxLjEiLz";
    label*3="48Q2xhc3NpZmljYXRpb24+MzwvQ2xhc3NpZmlj";
    label*4="YXRpb24+PC9TZWNMYWJlbD4=";
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>where the XML label, with new lines and white space added for readability, is:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<SecLabel xmlns="http://example.com/sec-label/0">
    <PolicyIdentifier URI="urn:oid:1.1"/>
    <Classification>3</Classification>
</SecLabel>
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The ":ess" and ":x411" formats SHOULD be used to represent ESS or
      X.411 security labels, respectively, instead of any direct XML
      representation of these formats.</t>

      <t>The header field SHALL minimally contain a "marking" parameter or contain both the "type" and "label" parameters.</t>
      <t>This header field may be extended to include additional parameters by
      future document formally updating (or replacing) this
      document. Implementations SHOULD ignore
        additional parameters they do not recognize. 
This recommendation is not a mandate so as to allow agents to process a
message with an SIO-Label header field with unrecognized parameters
differently than a message with an SIO-Label header field without the
unrecognized parameters.
</t>

      <t>Each message SHALL contain zero or one SIO-Label header field.</t>

      <t>Extended Example:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
SIO-Label: marking*=us-ascii'en'EXAMPLE%20CONFIDENTIAL;
    fgcolor = black ; bgcolor = red ;
    type=":ess"; label*0="MQYG";
    label*1="ASkCAQM="
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
      <t>The Extended Example is equivalent to the ESS Label Example above.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The SIO-Label-History Header Field">
      <t>Any service agent MAY record label changes in an SIO-Label-History
      header. This header field is intended to provide trace information (and
      only trace information). For
        instance, it can be used to record the label change when an SIO-Label
	header is added, modified, or deleted by a service agent. This field
	can be used in other situations
        as well. For instance, a gateway that
translates X.400 messages to RFC 5322 mail can use
this header field to record labeling changes made while translating a
message.</t>

<t>The SIO-Label-History header field is considered to be a trace field as
defined in Section 3.6.7 of [RFC5322].
</t>


      <t>The formal syntax of the SIO-Label-History header is the same as the
      SIO-Label, but with the following parameters:


<list style="symbols">
      <t>change - one of "add", "replace", "delete".</t>

      <t>changed-by - contains a string identifying the agent, commonly the
      agent's fully qualified domain name.</t>

      <t>changed-at - contains a date-time production, as specified in <xref
      target="RFC5322"/>, representing the date and time the header was
      rewritten.</t>

      <t>changed-comment - contains a string containing a comment.</t>

      <t>marking, fgcolor, bgcolor, type, label - records the message's label
      information prior to adding, modifying, or deleting SIO-Label, using
      the same
      parameter syntax used for SIO-Label.
        These parameters are absent when the change action is "add".</t>

      <t>
new-marking, new-fgcolor, new-bgcolor, new-type, new-label -
records the message's label information after adding, modifying,
or deleting SIO-Label, using the same parameter syntax used for
corresponding SIO-Label parameters.  These parameters are absent
when the change type is "delete".
</t>
</list>
</t>

      <t>The header field SHALL minimally contain the "change", "changed-by", and "changed-at" parameters.</t>

      <t>This header field can be extended to include additional parameters by
      future documents formally updating (or replacing) this document.</t>

      <t>Each message can contain zero or more SIO-Label-History header fields. All SIO-Label-History header fields should immediately follow the SIO-Label header field, if
        any, and be grouped together. Additional SIO-Label-History header fields should be added immediately preceding any existing SIO-Label-History header fields.</t>

      <t>SIO Label History Add, Modify, Delete Example:</t>
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
SIO-Label-History: marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    fgcolor=black; bgcolor=red;
    type=":xml";
    label*0="PFNlY0xhYmVsIHhtbG5zPSJodHRwOi8vZXhhbX";
    label*1="BsZS5jb20vc2VjLWxhYmVsLzAiPjxQb2xpY3lJ";
    label*2="ZGVudGlmaWVyIFVSST0idXJuOm9pZDoxLjEiLz";
    label*3="48Q2xhc3NpZmljYXRpb24+MzwvQ2xhc3NpZmlj";
    label*4="YXRpb24+PC9TZWNMYWJlbD4=";
    change=delete;
    changed-by="delete.example.com";
    changed-at="18 Feb 2013 9:24 PDT";
    changed-comment="delete" 
SIO-Label-History: marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    fgcolor=black; bgcolor=red;
    type=":ess"; label="MQYGASkCAQM=";
    new-marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    new-fgcolor=black; new-bgcolor=red;
    new-type=":xml";
    new-label*0="PFNlY0xhYmVsIHhtbG5zPSJodHRwOi8vZXhhbX";
    new-label*1="BsZS5jb20vc2VjLWxhYmVsLzAiPjxQb2xpY3lJ";
    new-label*2="ZGVudGlmaWVyIFVSST0idXJuOm9pZDoxLjEiLz";
    new-label*3="48Q2xhc3NpZmljYXRpb24+MzwvQ2xhc3NpZmlj";
    new-label*4="YXRpb24+PC9TZWNMYWJlbD4=";
    change=replace;
    changed-by="modify.example.net";
    changed-at="18 Feb 2013 8:24 PDT";
    changed-comment="replaced with XML variant"
SIO-Label-History: new-marking="EXAMPLE CONFIDENTIAL";
    new-fgcolor=black; new-bgcolor=red;
    new-type=":ess"; new-label="MQYGASkCAQM=";
    change=add;
    changed-by="add.example.net";
    changed-at="18 Feb 2013 7:24 PDT";
    changed-comment="added label"
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The SIO-Label and SIO-Label-History header fields
      have been registered in the "Provisional Message Header Field Registry" in accordance with <xref
          target="RFC3864"/>.</t>

      <t>Header field name: SIO-Label<vspace/> 
Applicable protocol: mail <xref target="RFC5322"/><vspace/> 
Status: provisional<vspace/> 
Author/change controller: Kurt Zeilenga
        (kurt.zeilenga@isode.com)<vspace/> 
Specification document(s): RFC 7444<vspace/>
      </t>

      <t> Header field name: SIO-Label-History<vspace/> 
Applicable protocol: mail <xref target="RFC5322"/><vspace/>
Status: provisional<vspace/> 
Author/change controller: Kurt Zeilenga (kurt.zeilenga@isode.com)<vspace/> 
Specification document(s): RFC 7444<vspace/>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="seccons">

      <t>Sensitive information should be appropriately protected (whether
      labeled or not). For email messages, it is generally appropriate for the
      sending entity to authenticate
        the receiving entity and to establish transport-level security,
	including protective services for both data integrity and data
	confidentiality. When a receiving entity makes
        authorization decisions based upon assertions of the sending entity,
	including assertions of identity, it is generally appropriate for the
	receiving entity to authenticate
        the sending entity.</t>

      <t>This document provides a facility for expressing the sensitivity of
      an email message. The mere expression of actual sensitivity generally
      does not elevate the
        sensitivity of the message; however, expressions of sensitivities can
	themselves be regarded as sensitive information. For instance, a
	marking of "BLACK PROJECT RESTRICTED"
        could disclose the existence of a sensitivity project.</t>

      <t>The SIO-Label header field expresses the sensitivity of the whole
      message, including the header and body. This document does not provide a
      means to express the sensitivity
        of portions of an email message, such as the possibly different
	sensitivities of various MIME parts that the message may be composed
	of. 
The approach used in
this document favors simplicity and ease of use (i.e., a single expression
of sensitivity) over the complexity and difficulty of
marking and labeling portions of a message.
</t>



      <t>The expressed sensitivity can be used in determining how to handle a
      message. For instance, the value of the SIO-Label header 
 field (or lack thereof) can be used to
        determine if it is appropriate to be forwarded to a particular entity
	and, if so, what minimum security services ought to
	be used in the forwarding
        exchange. The mechanism for determining how to handle a message-based
      expressed sensitivity is beyond the scope of this document.</t>


      <t>The actual content may have more or less sensitivity than indicated
      by the security label. Agents should avoid lowering security
      requirements for message exchange with a
        particular entity based upon conveyed sensitivity.</t>

      <t>
This protocol does not itself provide message-signing services, such
as used in providing message integrity protection, non-repudiation,
and binding of attributes (such as the security label to the message).
While it possible that this protocol could be used with a general message-signing service, this document does not detail such use.</t>

      <t>While security label and display marking parameters are expected to express the same sensitivity, nothing in this specification ensures that the security label and display
        marking values express the same sensitivity. For instance, an MUA
	could submit a message that contains a security label that expresses
	one sensitivity and a display marking with
        a different sensitivity, and by doing so, possibly cause an SA to
	inappropriately handle the message. It is generally appropriate for
	each SA using the SIO-Label
        values to determine if the security label and display marking values
      express the same sensitivity and, if not, take appropriate action (such
      as rejecting the message). </t>

      <t>This document also provides a facility for expressing changes to the
      label of a message. This is intended to be used for trace purposes
      only. It is noted that the
        SIO-Label-History header field can include sensitive information and,
	as such, can be removed from the message when its inclusion would
	result in disclosure of inappropriate
        information.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <!-- Keywords -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2231"?>
      <!-- 2231 -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2634"?>
      <!-- ESS -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3864"?>
      <!-- message headers -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986"?>
      <!-- URI -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4648"?>
      <!-- Base64 -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322"?>
      <!-- Email -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>
      <!-- ABNF -->

      <reference anchor="XML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126">
        <front>
          <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Bray" fullname="Tim Bray">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="J." surname="Paoli" fullname="Jean Paoli">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="C." surname="Sperberg-McQueen" fullname="C. M. Sperberg-McQueen">
            <organization/>
          </author>


          <author initials="E." surname="Maler" fullname="Eve Maler">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="F." surname="Yergeau" fullname="Francois Yergeau">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" day="26" year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="W3C  Recommendation" value="REC-xml-20081126"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="X.411">
        <front>
          <title>Message Handling Systems (MHS) - Message Transfer System: Abstract Service Definition and Procedures</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.411"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="X.690">
        <front>
          <title>ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.690"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CSS3-Color" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/CR-css3-color-20030514">
        <front>
          <title>CSS3 Color Module</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Celik" fullname="Tantek Celik">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="C." surname="Lilley" fullname="Chris Lilley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="May" day="14" year="2003"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="W3C Candidate Recommendation" value="CR-css3-color-20030514"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/CR-css3-color-20030514"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0822"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2045"?>


      <reference anchor="X.841">
        <front>
          <title>Security information objects for access control</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            <address>
      </address>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2000"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.841"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="XEP258">
        <front>
          <title>XEP-0258: Security Labels in XMPP</title>
          <author initials="K." surname="Zeilenga" fullname="Kurt Zeilenga">
            <organization>XMPP Standards Foundation</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="XEP" value="XMPP Extension Protocols"/>
      </reference>

    </references>


    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors appreciate the review, comment, and text provided by community members, including Dave Cridland, Brad Hards, Russ Housley, Steve Kille, Graeme Lunt, Alan Ross,
        Jim Schaad, and David Wilson.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
