<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" number="7534"
  obsoletes="6304" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title>AS112 Nameserver Operations</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>Dyn, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>103-186 Albert Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N6A 1M1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>jabley@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='W.' surname="Sotomayor" fullname='William F. Maton Sotomayor'>
      <organization abbrev="OttIX">Ottawa Internet Exchange</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Constitution Square</street>
          <street>1400-340 Albert Street</street>
          <city>Ottawa</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>K1R 0A5</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>wfms@ottix.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4 addresses
        that are not globally unique.  Examples are the addresses
        designated in RFC 1918 for private use within individual
        sites.</t>

      <t>Devices in such environments may occasionally originate
        Domain Name System (DNS) queries (so-called "reverse lookups")
        corresponding to those private-use addresses. Since the
        addresses concerned have only local significance, it is good
        practice for site administrators to ensure that such queries are
        answered locally. However, it is not uncommon for such queries
        to follow the normal delegation path in the public DNS instead
        of being answered within the site.</t>

      <t>It is not possible for public DNS servers to give
        useful answers to such queries. In addition, due to the
        wide deployment of private-use addresses and the continuing
        growth of the Internet, the volume of such queries is large
        and growing.  The AS112 project aims to provide a distributed
        sink for such queries in order to reduce the load on the
        corresponding authoritative servers.  The AS112 project is
        named after the Autonomous System Number (ASN) that was
        assigned to it.</t>

      <t>This document describes the steps required to install a new AS112
        node and offers advice relating to such a node's operation.</t>

      <t>This document obsoletes RFC 6304.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4
        addresses that are not globally unique.  Examples are the
        addresses designated in <xref target="RFC1918"/> for private
        use within individual sites.</t>
        
      <t>Devices in such environments may occasionally originate
        Domain Name System (DNS) <xref target="RFC1034"/> queries
        (so-called "reverse lookups") corresponding to those
        private-use addresses. Since the addresses concerned have
        only local significance, it is good practice for site
        administrators to ensure that such queries are answered
        locally <xref target="RFC6303"/>.  However, it is not
        uncommon for such queries to follow the normal delegation
        path in the public DNS instead of being answered within the
        site.</t>

      <t>It is not possible for public DNS servers to give
        useful answers to such queries. In addition, due to the
        wide deployment of private-use addresses and the continuing
        growth of the Internet, the volume of such queries is large
        and growing. The AS112 project aims to provide a distributed
        sink for such queries in order to reduce the load on the
        <xref target="RFC5855">IN-ADDR.ARPA authoritative
        servers</xref>.</t>

      <t>The AS112 project encompasses a loosely coordinated
        collection of independently operated nameservers. Each
        nameserver functions as a single node in an AS112 <xref
        target="RFC4786">anycast cloud</xref> and is configured to
        answer authoritatively for a particular set of nominated zones.</t>

      <t>The AS112 project is named after the Autonomous System Number
         (ASN) that was assigned to it (see <xref target="history"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="AS112 DNS Service">
      <section title="Approach">
        <section title="Direct Delegation">
          <t>The AS112 project currently uses an approach whereby
            zones whose traffic should be directed towards an AS112
            sink should be directly delegated to AS112 nameservers.
            Correspondingly, each AS112 node is manually configured
            to answer appropriately for those zones.</t>

          <t>The guidance in this document describes this capability
            for the zones that were originally delegated in this
            fashion. AS112 nodes that were implemented in accordance
            with the guidance found here will
            continue to provide service for those zones.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DNAME Redirection">
          <t><xref target="RFC7535"/> describes
            a different approach whereby queries towards specific
            zones are redirected to an empty zone also
            hosted on AS112 servers, using <xref
            target="RFC6672">DNAME</xref>.</t>

          <t>The guidance in this document introduces this capability,
            allowing any zone administrator to sink query traffic in
            AS112 infrastructure without requiring changes to any
            AS112 node.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Zones" anchor="zones">
        <t>To support Direct Delegation AS112 service, AS112
          nameservers answer authoritatively for the following zones,
          corresponding to <xref target="RFC1918"/> private-use
          netblocks:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>10.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
            <t>16.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA, 17.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA, ...,
              31.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
            <t>168.192.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
          </list>

          and the following zone, corresponding to the "link
          local" netblock 169.254.0.0/16 listed in <xref
          target="RFC6890"/>:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>254.169.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>To support DNAME redirection AS112 service, AS112
          nameservers answer authoritatively for the following zone,
          as specified in <xref target="RFC7535"/>:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>EMPTY.AS112.ARPA</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>To aid identification of AS112 anycast nodes, each
          node also answers authoritatively for the following zones:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>HOSTNAME.AS112.NET</t>
            <t>HOSTNAME.AS112.ARPA</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>See <xref target="dns"/> for the recommended contents
          of all these zones.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Nameservers" anchor="nameServers">
        <t>To support Direct Delegation AS112 service, the relevant
          zones listed in <xref target="zones"/> are delegated to
          the two nameservers BLACKHOLE&nbhy;1.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.6,
          2620:4f:8000::6) and BLACKHOLE&nbhy;2.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.42,
          2620:4f:8000::42).</t>

        <t>Additionally, the server PRISONER.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.1,
          2620:4f:8000::1) is listed in the MNAME field of the SOA
          records of the IN-ADDR.ARPA zones served by AS112
          nameservers. PRISONER.IANA.ORG receives mainly dynamic
          update queries.</t>

        <t>The addresses of all these nameservers are covered by
          the single IPv4 prefix 192.175.48.0/24 and the IPv6 prefix
          2620:4f:8000::/48. To date, IPv6 transport for these
          nameservers has only been available for pre-production
          testing.  IANA has added AAAA RRSets for the
          owner names of these nameservers; see <xref
          target="ianaConsiderations"/>.</t>

        <t>To support DNAME redirection AS112 service, the single zone
          EMPTY.AS112.ARPA is delegated to the single nameserver
          BLACKHOLE.AS112.ARPA (192.31.196.1, 2001:4:112::1).
          The addresses of that nameserver are covered by the
          single IPv4 prefix 192.31.196.0/24 and the single IPv6
          prefix 2001:4:112::/48.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Installation of a New Node">
      <section title="Useful Background Knowledge">
        <t>Installation of an AS112 node is relatively straightforward.
          However, experience in the following general areas may
          prove useful:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>inter-domain routing with <xref
              target="RFC4271">BGP</xref>;</t>

            <t>DNS authoritative server operations; and</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC4786">anycast</xref> distribution
              of DNS services.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Topological Location">
        <t>AS112 nodes may be located anywhere on the Internet. For
          nodes that are intended to provide a public service to
          the Internet community (as opposed to private use), it
          may well be advantageous to choose a location that is
          easily (and cheaply) reachable by multiple providers,
          such as an Internet Exchange Point.</t>

        <t>AS112 nodes may advertise their service prefix to BGP
          peers for local use (analogous to a conventional peering
          relationship between two providers) or for global use
          (analogous to a customer relationship with one or more
          providers).</t>

        <t>It is good operational practice to notify the community
          of users that may fall within the reach of a new AS112 node
          before it is installed. At an Internet Exchange, local
          mailing lists usually exist to facilitate such announcements.
          For nodes that are intended to be globally reachable,
          coordination with other AS112 operators is highly recommended.
          See also <xref target="communications"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operating System and Host Considerations">
        <t>Examples in this document are based on UNIX and UNIX-like
          operating systems, but other operating systems exist that
          are suitable for use in construction of an AS112 node.</t>

        <t>The chosen platform should include either support for
          cloned loopback interfaces or the capability to bind
          multiple addresses to a single loopback interface. The
          addresses of the nameservers listed in <xref
          target="nameServers"/> will be configured on these
          interfaces in order that the DNS software can respond to
          queries properly.</t>

        <t>A host that is configured to act as an AS112 anycast
          node should be dedicated to that purpose and should not be
          used to simultaneously provide other services. This guidance
          is provided due to the unpredictable (and occasionally high)
          traffic levels that AS112 nodes have been seen to attract.</t>

        <t>System startup scripts should be arranged such that the
          various AS112-related components start automatically following
          a system reboot. The order in which interfaces are configured
          and software components started should be arranged such that
          routing software startup follows DNS software startup, and
          DNS software startup follows loopback interface configuration.</t>

        <t>Wrapper scripts or other arrangements should be employed to
          ensure that the anycast service prefix for AS112 is not advertised
          while either the anycast addresses are not configured or
          the DNS software is not running.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing Software">
        <t>AS112 nodes signal the availability of AS112 nameservers
          to the Internet using <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref>:
          each AS112 node is a BGP speaker and announces the
          prefixes 192.175.48.0/24 and 2620:4f:8000::/48 to the
          Internet with origin AS 112 (see also <xref
          target="nameServers"/>).</t>

        <t>The examples in this document are based on the
          Quagga Routing Suite &lt;http://www.quagga.net&gt;
          running on Linux, but other software packages exist that
          also provide suitable BGP support for AS112 nodes.</t>

        <t>The "bgpd.conf" file is used by Quagga's bgpd daemon, which
          provides BGP support. The router ID in this example
          is 203.0.113.1; the AS112 node peers with external peers
          192.0.2.1, 192.0.2.2, 2001:db8::1, and 2001:db8::2.  Note that
          the local AS number is 112, and the service prefixes originated
          from the AS112 node to support Direct Delegation service are 
          192.175.48.0/24 and 2620:4f:8000::/48; the IPv4 prefix
          192.31.196.0/24 and the IPv6 prefix 2001:4:112::/48 support
          DNAME redirection.</t> 

        <t>For clarity, an IPv4-only AS112 node need not configure
          any of the IPv6 elements that follow; similarly, an IPv6-only
          AS112 node need not configure any of the IPv4 elements.
          Such single-stack hosts can still contribute usefully to
          IPv4 and IPv6 AS112 services, however, and single-stack
          operation is not discouraged.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
! bgpd.conf
!
hostname as112-bgpd
password &lt;something&gt;
enable password &lt;supersomething&gt;
!
! Note that all AS112 nodes use the local Autonomous System Number
! 112, and originate the IPv4 prefixes 192.175.48.0/24 and
! 192.31.196.0/24 and the IPv6 prefixes 2620:4f:8000::/48 and
! 2001:4:112::/48.
!
! All other addresses shown below are illustrative, and
! actual numbers will depend on local circumstances.
!
! IPv4-only or IPv6-only AS112 nodes should omit advertisements
! for address families they do not support.
!
router bgp 112
 bgp router-id 203.0.113.1
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 remote-as 64496
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 next-hop-self
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 prefix-list AS112-v4 out
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 filter-list 1 out
!
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 remote-as 64497
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 next-hop-self
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 prefix-list AS112-v4 out
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 filter-list 1 out
!
 neighbor 2001:db8::1 remote-as 64498
 neighbor 2001:db8::1 next-hop-self
 neighbor 2001:db8::1 prefix-list AS112-v6 out
 neighbor 2001:db8::1 filter-list 1 out
!
 neighbor 2001:db8::2 remote-as 64499
 neighbor 2001:db8::2 next-hop-self
 neighbor 2001:db8::2 prefix-list AS112-v6 out
 neighbor 2001:db8::2 filter-list 1 out
!
 network 192.175.48.0/24
 network 192.31.196.0/24 
!
 address-family ipv6 unicast
  network 2620:4f:8000::/48
  network 2001:4:112::/48
 exit-address-family
!
ip prefix-list AS112-v4 permit 192.175.48.0/24
ip prefix-list AS112-v4 permit 192.31.196.0/24 
!
ipv6 prefix-list AS112-v6 permit 2620:4f:8000::/48
ipv6 prefix-list AS112-v6 permit 2001:4:112::/48
!
ip as-path access-list 1 permit ^$
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The configuration above includes two restrictions on
          what the AS112 should advertise to its BGP neighbours:
          a prefix filter that permits only the service prefixes,
          and an AS_PATH filter that matches only locally originated
          routes.  Together, these measures prevent the node from
          becoming a transit point for its adjacent ASes.</t>

        <t>The "zebra.conf" file is required to provide integration
          between protocol daemons (bgpd, in this case) and the
          kernel.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
! zebra.conf
!
hostname as112
password &lt;something&gt;
enable password &lt;supersomething&gt;
!
interface lo
!
interface eth0
!
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Software" anchor="dns">
        <t>Although the queries received by AS112 nodes are
          definitively misdirected, it is important that they be
          answered in a manner that is accurate and consistent.
          For this reason, AS112 nodes operate as <xref
          target="RFC1034">fully functional
          and standards-compliant DNS authoritative servers</xref>,
          and hence require appropriate DNS software.</t>

        <t>Examples in this document are based on ISC BIND9
          &lt;http://www.isc.org/software/BIND/&gt;, but other
          DNS software exists that is suitable for use in
          construction of an AS112 node.</t>

        <t>The following is a sample BIND9 "named.conf" file for a
          dedicated AS112 server. Note that the nameserver is
          configured to act as an authoritative-only server (i.e.,
          recursion is disabled).  The nameserver is also configured
          to listen on the various AS112 anycast nameserver addresses,
          as well as its local addresses.</t>

        <t>A basic logging example is included in the sample as well.
          AS112 operators may exercise discretion at the amount of logging
          detail they desire or the type of logging they may use in
          the maintenance of their node.  The detail of information can
          then be used to single out bad implementors or badly
          managed nameservers, or it can be used for simple measurement
          analysis.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
// named.conf

// Global options

options {
  listen-on {
    127.0.0.1;         // localhost

  // The following address is node-dependent and should be set to
  // something appropriate for the new AS112 node.

    203.0.113.1;       // local address (globally unique, unicast)

  // The following addresses are used to support Direct Delegation
  // AS112 service and are the same for all AS112 nodes.

    192.175.48.1;      // prisoner.iana.org (anycast)
    192.175.48.6;      // blackhole-1.iana.org (anycast)
    192.175.48.42;     // blackhole-2.iana.org (anycast)

  // The following address is used to support DNAME redirection
  // AS112 service and is the same for all AS112 nodes.

    192.31.196.1;      // blackhole.as112.arpa (anycast)
  };

  listen-on-v6 {
    ::1;               // localhost

  // The following addresses are used to support Direct Delegation
  // AS112 service and are the same for all AS112 nodes.

    2620:4f:8000::1;   // prisoner.iana.org (anycast)
    2620:4f:8000::6;   // blackhole-1.iana.org (anycast)
    2620:4f:8000::42;  // blackhole-2.iana.org (anycast)

  // The following address is used to support DNAME redirection
  // AS112 service and is the same for all AS112 nodes.

    2001:4:112::1;    // blackhole.as112.arpa (anycast)
  };

  directory "/var/named";
  recursion no;        // authoritative-only server
};

// Log queries, so that when people call us about unexpected
// answers to queries they didn't realise they had sent, we
// have something to talk about.  Note that activating this
// naively has the potential to create high CPU load and consume
// enormous amounts of disk space.  This example retains 2 old 
// versions at a maximum of 500 MB each before rotating out the
// oldest one.

logging {
  channel "querylog" { 
    file "/var/log/query.log" versions 2 size 500m;
    print-time yes;
  };
  category queries { querylog; };
};

// Direct Delegation AS112 Service

// RFC 1918

zone "10.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "16.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "17.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "18.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "19.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "20.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "21.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "22.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "23.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "24.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "25.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "26.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "27.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "28.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "29.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "30.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "31.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };
zone "168.192.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };

// RFC 6890

zone "254.169.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.dd-empty"; };

// DNAME redirection AS112 Service

zone "empty.as112.arpa" { type master; file "db.dr-empty"; };

// Also answer authoritatively for the HOSTNAME.AS112.NET and
// HOSTNAME.AS112.ARPA zones, which contain data of operational
// relevance.

zone "hostname.as112.net" {
  type master;
  file "db.hostname.as112.net";
};

zone "hostname.as112.arpa" {
  type master;
  file "db.hostname.as112.arpa";
};
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The "db.dd-empty" file follows, below.  This is the source
          data used to populate all the IN-ADDR.ARPA zones listed
          in <xref target="zones"/> that support Direct Delegation
          AS112 service. Note that the RNAME specified in the SOA
          record corresponds to hostmaster@root-servers.org, a
          suitable email address for receiving technical queries 
          about these zones.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.dd-empty
;
; Empty zone for Direct Delegation AS112 service.
;
$TTL    1W
@  IN  SOA  prisoner.iana.org. hostmaster.root-servers.org. (
                               1       ; serial number
                               1W      ; refresh
                               1M      ; retry
                               1W      ; expire
                               1W )    ; negative caching TTL
;
       NS     blackhole-1.iana.org.
       NS     blackhole-2.iana.org.
;
; There should be no other resource records included in this zone.
;
; Records that relate to RFC 1918-numbered resources within the
; site hosting this AS112 node should not be hosted on this
; nameserver.
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The "db.dr-empty" file follows, below. This is the source
          data used to populate the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone that
          supports DNAME redirection AS112 service. Note that the
          RNAME specified in the SOA record corresponds to
          noc@dns.icann.org, a suitable email address for technical
          queries about this zone.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.dr-empty
;
; Empty zone for DNAME redirection AS112 service.
;
$TTL    1W
@  IN  SOA  blackhole.as112.arpa. noc.dns.icann.org. (
                               1       ; serial number
                               1W      ; refresh
                               1M      ; retry
                               1W      ; expire
                               1W )    ; negative caching TTL
;
       NS     blackhole.as112.arpa.
;
; There should be no other resource records included in this zone.
;
; Records that relate to RFC 1918-numbered resources within the
; site hosting this AS112 node should not be hosted on this
; nameserver.
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The "db.hostname.as112.net" and "db.hostname.as112.arpa"
          files follow, below.  These zones contain various resource
          records that provide operational data to users for
          troubleshooting or measurement purposes; the data should be
          edited to suit local circumstances.  Note that the responses
          to the queries "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET IN TXT" and
          "HOSTNAME.AS112.ARPA IN TXT" should fit within a 512-octet
          DNS/UDP datagram: i.e., it should be available over UDP
          transport without requiring EDNS0 support by the client.</t>

        <t>The optional <xref target="RFC1876">LOC record</xref>
          included in each zone apex provides information about the
          geospatial location of the node.</t>

        <t>Where software implementations support it, operational data
          should also be carried using <xref target="RFC5001">NSID</xref>.
          </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.hostname.as112.net
;
$TTL    1W
@       SOA     server.example.net. admin.example.net. (
                        1               ; serial number
                        1W              ; refresh
                        1M              ; retry
                        1W              ; expire
                        1W )            ; negative caching TTL
;
        NS      blackhole-1.iana.org.
        NS      blackhole-2.iana.org.
;
        TXT     "Name of Facility or similar" "City, Country"
        TXT     "See http://www.as112.net/ for more information."
        TXT     "Unique IP: 203.0.113.1."
;
        LOC     45 25 0.000 N 75 42 0.000 W 80.00m 1m 10000m 10m
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.hostname.as112.arpa
;
$TTL    1W
@       SOA     server.example.net. admin.example.net. (
                        1               ; serial number
                        1W              ; refresh
                        1M              ; retry
                        1W              ; expire
                        1W )            ; negative caching TTL
;
        NS      blackhole.as112.arpa.
;
        TXT     "Name of Facility or similar" "City, Country"
        TXT     "See http://www.as112.net/ for more information."
;
        LOC     45 25 0.000 N 75 42 0.000 W 80.00m 1m 10000m 10m
          </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Testing a Newly Installed Node">
        <t>The BIND9 tool "dig" can be used to retrieve the TXT
          resource records associated with the names "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET"
          and "HOSTNAME.AS112.ARPA", directed at one of the AS112
          anycast nameserver addresses.  Continuing the example
          from above, the response received should indicate the
          identity of the AS112 node that responded to the query.
          See <xref target="dns"/> for more details about the
          resource records associated with "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET".</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    % dig @prisoner.iana.org hostname.as112.net txt +short +norec
    "Name of Facility or similar" "City, Country"
    "See http://www.as112.net/ for more information."
    %
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>If the response received indicates that a different node is
          being used, then there is probably a routing problem to solve.
          If there is no response received at all, there might be a host
          or nameserver problem. Judicious use of tools such as
          traceroute and consultation of BGP looking glasses might
          be useful in troubleshooting.</t>

        <t>Note that an appropriate set of tests for a new server will
          include queries sent from many different places within the
          expected service area of the node, using both UDP and TCP
          transport, and exercising all three AS112 anycast nameserver
          addresses.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operations">
      <section title="Monitoring">
        <t>AS112 nodes should be monitored to ensure that they are
          functioning correctly, just as with any other production
          service. An AS112 node that stops answering queries correctly
          can cause failures and timeouts in unexpected places and can
          lead to failures in dependent systems that can be difficult
          to troubleshoot.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Downtime">
        <t>An AS112 node that needs to go off-line (e.g., for planned
          maintenance or as part of the diagnosis of some problem)
          should stop advertising the AS112 service prefixes to its BGP
          peers. This can be done by shutting down the routing software
          on the node altogether or by causing the routing system to
          withdraw the route.</t>

        <t>Withdrawing the service prefixes is important in order to avoid
          blackholing query traffic in the event that the DNS software on
          the node is not functioning normally.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Statistics and Measurement">
        <t>Use of the AS112 node should be measured in order to track
          long-term trends, identify anomalous conditions, and ensure
          that the configuration of the AS112 node is sufficient to handle
          the query load.</t>

        <t>Examples of free monitoring tools that might be useful to
          operators of AS112 nodes include:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>bindgraph &lt;http://www.linux.it/~md/software/&gt;</t>
            <t>dnstop &lt;http://dns.measurement-factory.com/tools/dnstop/&gt;</t>
            <t>DSC &lt;https://www.dns-oarc.net/tools/dsc/&gt;</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>Operators of AS112 nodes should also consider participating
          in collection events as part of a larger, coordinated effort
          to gather important baselines.  One example of such an effort is
          Day in the Life &lt;https://www.dns-oarc.net/oarc/data/ditl/&gt;,
          coordinated by the DNS-OARC &lt;https://www.dns-oarc.net/&gt;.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Communications" anchor="communications">
      <t>It is good operational practice to notify the community
        of users that may fall within the reach of a new AS112 node
        before it is installed. At Internet Exchanges, local
        mailing lists usually exist to facilitate such announcements.</t>

      <t>For nodes that are intended to be globally reachable,
        coordination with other AS112 operators is especially
        recommended.  The mailing list
        &lt;as112-ops@lists.dns-oarc.net&gt; is operated
        for this purpose.</t>

      <t>Information pertinent to AS112 operations is maintained
        at &lt;http://www.as112.net/&gt;.</t>

      <t>Information about an AS112 node should also be published within
        the DNS, within the "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET" and "HOSTNAME.AS112.ARPA"
        zones. See <xref target="dns"/> for more details.</t>

      <t>AS112 operators should also be aware of the measures described in
        <xref target="RFC6305"/> and direct site administrators
        appropriately.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="On the Future of AS112 Nodes">
      <t>It is recommended practice for the operators of recursive
        nameservers to answer queries for zones served by AS112
        nodes locally, such that queries never have an opportunity
        to reach AS112 servers <xref target="RFC6303"/>. Operational
        experience with AS112 nodes does not currently indicate an
        observable trend towards compliance with those recommendations,
        however.</t>

      <t>It is expected that some DNS software vendors will include
        default configuration that will implement measures such as
        those described in <xref target="RFC6303"/>.  If such
        software is widely deployed, it is reasonable to assume
        that the query load received by AS112 nodes will decrease;
        however, it is safe to assume that the query load will not
        decrease to zero, and consequently that AS112 nodes will
        continue to provide a useful service for the foreseeable
        future.</t>

      <t>The use of DNAME redirection to provide AS112 service is
        new and hence is informed by minimal operational experience.
        The use of DNAME means that queries for many source zones
        could be redirected to AS112 infrastructure with no real
        opportunity for coordination.</t>

      <t>If the DNAME redirection approach is successful, and in
        the absence of any operational concerns, the community might
        well recommend the retirement of the original Direct
        Delegation AS112 service. This document makes no such
        recommendation, however.</t>
    </section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="ianaConsiderations">
      <section title="General">
        <t>The nameservers associated with Direct Delegation AS112
          service are all named under the domain IANA.ORG (see <xref
          target="nameServers"/>). However, the anycast infrastructure
          itself is operated by a loosely coordinated, diverse mix
          of organisations across the Internet and is not an IANA
          function.</t>

        <t>The autonomous system number 112, the IPv4 prefix
          192.175.48.0/24, and the IPv6 prefix 2620:4f:8000::/48
          were assigned by ARIN.</t>

        <t>The IPv4 prefix 192.31.196.0/24 and the IPv6 prefix
          2001:4:112::/48, used for DNAME redirection AS112 service,
          were assigned by the IANA <xref target="RFC7535"/>.</t>

        <t>The three nameservers BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG, BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG,
          and PRISONER.IANA.ORG are also reachable over IPv6, as
          described in <xref target="nameServers"/>. Following a
          substantial period of pre-production testing by AS112
          operators, the IANA has added AAAA RRSets to
          those owner names in <xref target="ianaAAAA"/>, to allow
          the servers to receive queries and generate responses
          over IPv6 transport.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Actions">
        <section title="IPv6 Transport for Direct Delegation AS112 Servers"
            anchor="ianaAAAA">
          <t>The IANA has added the following AAAA resource
            records for the three Direct Delegation AS112 nameservers
            named under IANA.ORG:</t>

<?rfc compact="no"?>
          <texttable>
            <ttcol>Owner Name</ttcol><ttcol>AAAA RDATA</ttcol>

            <c>PRISONER.IANA.ORG</c><c>2620:4f:8000::1</c>
            <c>BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG</c><c>2620:4f:8000::6</c>
            <c>BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG</c><c>2620:4f:8000::42</c>
          </texttable>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
        </section>

        <section title="Registration in the Special-Purpose AS Numbers Registry">
          <t>The IANA has added AS112 to the "Special-Purpose
            AS Numbers" registry specified in <xref target="RFC7249"/>
            as follows:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="AS Numbers:">112</t>
              <t hangText="Reason for Reservation:">Used by the AS112
                project to sink misdirected DNS queries; see RFC 7534.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Registration in the IANA IPv4 Special-Purpose
            Address Registry">
          <t>The IANA has added 192.175.48.0/24 to the
            "IANA IPv4 Special-Purpose Address Registry"
            specified in <xref target="RFC6890"/>
            as follows:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Address Block:">192.175.48.0/24</t>
              <t hangText="Name:">Direct Delegation AS112 Service</t>
              <t hangText="RFC:">RFC 7534</t>
              <t hangText="Allocation Date:">1996-01</t>
              <t hangText="Termination Date:">N/A</t>
              <t hangText="Source:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Destination:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Forwardable:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Global:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Reserved-by-Protocol:">False</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Registration in the IANA IPv6 Special-Purpose 
            Address Registry">
          <t>The IANA has added 2620:4f:8000::/48 to the
            "IANA IPv6 Special-Purpose Address Registry"
            specified in <xref target="RFC6890"/>
            as follows:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Address Block:">2620:4f:8000::/48</t>
              <t hangText="Name:">Direct Delegation AS112 Service</t>
              <t hangText="RFC:">RFC 7534</t>
              <t hangText="Allocation Date:">2011-05</t>
              <t hangText="Termination Date:">N/A</t>
              <t hangText="Source:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Destination:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Forwardable:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Global:">True</t>
              <t hangText="Reserved-by-Protocol:">False</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Hosts should never normally send queries to AS112 servers;
        queries relating to private-use addresses should be answered
        locally within a site. Hosts that send queries to AS112
        servers may well leak information relating to private
        infrastructure to the public network, and this could present
        a security risk.  Additionally, AS112 operators may log this
        information, making it further subject to whatever security 
        and privacy risks that might entail.  These risks are orthogonal
        to the presence or absence of authoritative servers for these
        zones in the public DNS infrastructure, however.</t>

      <t>Queries that are answered by AS112 servers are usually
        unintentional; it follows that the responses from AS112
        servers are usually unexpected. Unexpected inbound traffic
        can trigger intrusion detection systems or alerts by
        firewalls. Operators of AS112 servers should be prepared
        to be contacted by operators of remote infrastructure who
        believe their security has been violated. Advice to those
        who mistakenly believe that responses from AS112 nodes
        constitute an attack on their infrastructure can be found
        in <xref target="RFC6305"/>.</t>

      <t>The deployment of AS112 nodes is very loosely coordinated
        compared to other services distributed using anycast. The
        malicious compromise of an AS112 node and subversion of the
        data served by the node are hence more difficult to detect
        due to the lack of central management. Since it is conceivable
        that changing the responses to queries received by AS112
        nodes might influence the behaviour of the hosts sending
        the queries, such a compromise might be used as an attack
        vector against private infrastructure.</t>

      <t>Operators of AS112 should take appropriate measures to
        ensure that AS112 nodes are appropriately protected from
        compromise, such as would normally be employed for production
        nameserver or network infrastructure. The guidance provided
        for root nameservers in <xref target="RFC2870"/> may be
        instructive.</t>

      <t>The zones hosted by AS112 servers are not signed with
        DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033"/>. Given the distributed
        and loosely coordinated structure of the AS112 service,
        the zones concerned could only be signed if the private
        key material used was effectively public, obviating any
        security benefit resulting from the use of those keys.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

    <reference  anchor='RFC1034' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1034'>
    <front>
    <title>Domain names - concepts and facilities</title>
    <author initials='P.V.' surname='Mockapetris' fullname='P.V. Mockapetris'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1987' month='November' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='STD' value='13'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1034'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='129180'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC1918' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1918'>
    <front>
    <title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>
    <author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Y. Rekhter'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='B.' surname='Moskowitz' fullname='B. Moskowitz'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='D. Karrenberg'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='G.' surname='J. de Groot' fullname='G. J. de Groot'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='E.' surname='Lear' fullname='E. Lear'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1996' month='February' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='5'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1918'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='22270'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC2870' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2870'>
    <front>
    <title>Root Name Server Operational Requirements</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Bush' fullname='R. Bush'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='D. Karrenberg'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Kosters' fullname='M. Kosters'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Plzak' fullname='R. Plzak'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2000' month='June' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='40'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2870'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='21133'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC4033' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4033'>
    <front>
    <title>DNS Security Introduction and Requirements</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Arends' fullname='R. Arends'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Austein' fullname='R. Austein'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Larson' fullname='M. Larson'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Massey' fullname='D. Massey'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Rose' fullname='S. Rose'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2005' month='March' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4033'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='52445'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC4271' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4271'>
    <front>
    <title>A Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4)</title>
    <author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Y. Rekhter' role='editor'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Li' fullname='T. Li' role='editor'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Hares' fullname='S. Hares' role='editor'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2006' month='January' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4271'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='222702'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC4786' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4786'>
    <front>
    <title>Operation of Anycast Services</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='K.' surname='Lindqvist' fullname='K. Lindqvist'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2006' month='December' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='126'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4786'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='56818'/>
    </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-dname (RFC 7535) -->
   <reference anchor="RFC7535" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7535">
     <front>
       <title>AS112 Redirection Using DNAME</title>
       <author initials='J' surname='Abley' fullname='Joe Abley'>
         <organization />
       </author>
       <author initials='B' surname='Dickson' fullname='Brian Dickson'>
         <organization />
       </author>
       <author initials='W' surname='Kumari' fullname='Warren Kumari'>
         <organization />
       </author>
       <author initials='G' surname='Michaelson' fullname='George Michaelson'>
         <organization />
       </author>
       <date month='May' year='2015' />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7535' />
   </reference>

 </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

    <reference  anchor='RFC1876' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1876'>
    <front>
    <title>A Means for Expressing Location Information in the Domain Name System</title>
    <author initials='C.' surname='Davis' fullname='C. Davis'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='P.' surname='Vixie' fullname='P. Vixie'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Goodwin' fullname='T. Goodwin'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='I.' surname='Dickinson' fullname='I. Dickinson'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1996' month='January' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1876'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='29631'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC5001' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5001'>
    <front>
    <title>DNS Name Server Identifier (NSID) Option</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Austein' fullname='R. Austein'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2007' month='August' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5001'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='23754'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC5855' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5855'>
    <front>
    <title>Nameservers for IPv4 and IPv6 Reverse Zones</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Manderson' fullname='T. Manderson'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2010' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='155'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5855'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='23027'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC6303' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6303'>
    <front>
    <title>Locally Served DNS Zones</title>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Andrews' fullname='M. Andrews'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2011' month='July' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='163'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6303'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='22503'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC6304' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6304'>
    <front>
    <title>AS112 Nameserver Operations</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='W.' surname='Maton' fullname='W. Maton'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2011' month='July' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6304'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='34002'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC6305' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6305'>
    <front>
    <title>I'm Being Attacked by PRISONER.IANA.ORG!</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='W.' surname='Maton' fullname='W. Maton'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2011' month='July' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6305'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='15287'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC6672' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6672'>
    <front>
    <title>DNAME Redirection in the DNS</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Rose' fullname='S. Rose'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='W.' surname='Wijngaards' fullname='W. Wijngaards'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2012' month='June' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6672'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='45704'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC6890' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6890'>
    <front>
    <title>Special-Purpose IP Address Registries</title>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Cotton' fullname='M. Cotton'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='L.' surname='Vegoda' fullname='L. Vegoda'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Bonica' fullname='R. Bonica' role='editor'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='B.' surname='Haberman' fullname='B. Haberman'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2013' month='April' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='153'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6890'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='48326'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC7249' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7249'>
    <front>
    <title>Internet Numbers Registries</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Housley' fullname='R. Housley'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2014' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7249'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='10070'/>
    </reference>

    </references>

    <section title="A Brief History of AS112" anchor="history">
      <t>Widespread use of the private address blocks listed in
        <xref target="RFC1918"/> followed that document's publication
        in 1996.  At that time, the IN&nbhy;ADDR.ARPA zone was served by
        root servers.</t>

     <t>The idea of offloading IN-ADDR.ARPA queries relating to
       <xref target="RFC1918"/> addresses from the root nameservers
       was first proposed by Bill Manning and John Brown.</t>

     <t>The use of anycast for distributing authoritative DNS service
       for <xref target="RFC1918"/> IN-ADDR.ARPA zones was subsequently
       proposed at a private meeting of root server operators.</t>

     <t>ARIN provided an IPv4 prefix for the anycast service and
       also the autonomous system number 112 for use in originating
       that prefix.  This assignment gave the project its name.</t>

     <t>In 2002, the first AS112 anycast nodes were deployed.</t>

     <t>In 2011, the IN-ADDR.ARPA zone was redelegated from the
       root servers to a new set of servers operated independently
       by AfriNIC, APNIC, ARIN, ICANN, LACNIC, and the RIPE NCC and
       named according to <xref target="RFC5855"/>.</t>

     <t><xref target="RFC6304"/>, the precursor to this document,
       was published in July 2011.</t>

     <t>The use of anycast nameservers in the AS112 project contributed
       to the operational experience of anycast DNS services, and
       it can be seen as a precursor to the anycast distribution
       of other authoritative DNS servers in subsequent years (e.g.,
       various root servers).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes since RFC 6304" anchor="rfc6304changes">
       <t>A number of changes and enhancements to the AS112 service
         has been introduced since the publication of <xref 
         target="RFC6304"/>.

         <list style="symbols">
           <t>The addition of IPv6 transport.</t>

           <t>The extension of the AS112 service to include the ability
             to have additional zones delegated for sinking or removed
             using the DNAME resource record.</t>

           <t>Requisite changes to the guidance regarding the configuration
             of current and future AS112 nodes.</t>

           <t>Further clarification about the leakage of information in
             the Security Considerations section.</t>

           <t>A direction to the IANA to register the AS112 project's
             prefixes in the IANA Special-Purpose Address registries.</t>
         </list>
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>This document benefited from review and suggestions from
        Leo Vegoda and Pearl Liang.</t>

      <t>The authors wish to acknowledge the assistance of Bill
        Manning, John Brown, Marco D'Itri, Daniele Arena, Stephane
        Bortzmeyer, Frank Habicht, Chris Thompson, Peter Losher,
        Peter Koch, Alfred Hoenes, S. Moonesamy, Mehmet Akcin, and
        Aleksi Suhonen in the preparation of <xref target="RFC6304"/>,
        which this document supersedes.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>

