<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="7810" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS TE Metric Extensions">IS-IS Traffic Engineering (TE)
    Metric Extensions</title>

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." role="editor"
            surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Del Serafico 200</street>

          <city>Rome</city>

          <code>00191</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sprevidi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Spencer Giacalone" initials="S." surname="Giacalone">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <email>spencer.giacalone@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Ward" initials="D." surname="Ward">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3700 Cisco Way</street>

          <city>San Jose, CA</city>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wardd@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Drake" initials="J." surname="Drake">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale, CA</city>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jdrake@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing, Jiangsu</city>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="April" year="2016"/>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>In certain networks, such as, but not limited to, financial
      information networks (e.g., stock market data providers), network-performance criteria (e.g., latency) are becoming as critical to data-path selection as other metrics.</t>

      <t>This document describes extensions to IS-IS Traffic Engineering
      Extensions (RFC 5305) such that network-performance information can be
      distributed and collected in a scalable fashion. The information
      distributed using IS-IS TE Metric Extensions can then be used to make
      path-selection decisions based on network performance.</t>

      <t>Note that this document only covers the mechanisms with which network-performance information is distributed. The mechanisms for measuring
      network performance or acting on that information, once distributed, are
      outside the scope of this document.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In certain networks, such as, but not limited to, financial
      information networks (e.g., stock market data providers), network-performance information (e.g., latency) is becoming as critical to data-path selection as other metrics.</t>

      <t>In these networks, extremely large amounts of money rest on the
      ability to access market data in "real time" and to predictably make
      trades faster than the competition. Because of this, using metrics such
      as hop count or cost as routing metrics is becoming only tangentially
      important. Rather, it would be beneficial to be able to make path-selection decisions based on performance data (such as latency) in a
      cost-effective and scalable way.</t>

      <t>This document describes extensions (hereafter called "IS-IS TE Metric
      Extensions") to the IS-IS Extended Reachability TLV defined in <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>, that can be used to distribute network-performance
      information (such as link delay, delay variation, packet loss, residual
      bandwidth, and available bandwidth).</t>

      <t>The data distributed by the IS-IS TE Metric Extensions proposed in
      this document is meant to be used as part of the operation of the
      routing protocol (e.g., by replacing cost with latency or considering
      bandwidth as well as cost), to enhance Constrained-SPF (CSPF), or for
      other uses such as supplementing the data used by an ALTO server <xref
      target="RFC7285"/>. With respect to CSPF, the data distributed by IS-IS
      TE Metric Extensions can be used to set up, fail over, and fail back data
      paths using protocols such as RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209"/>.</t>

      <t>Note that the mechanisms described in this document only disseminate
      performance information. The methods for initially gathering that
      performance information, such as described in <xref target="RFC6375"/>, or acting on
      it once it is distributed are outside the scope of this document.
      Example mechanisms to measure latency, delay variation, and loss in an
      MPLS network are given in <xref target="RFC6374"/>. While this document
      does not specify how the performance information should be obtained, the
      measurement of delay SHOULD NOT vary significantly based upon the
      offered traffic load. Thus, queuing delays SHOULD NOT be included in the
      delay measurement. For links such as Forwarding Adjacencies, care must
      be taken that measurement of the associated delay avoids significant
      queuing delay; that could be accomplished in a variety of ways,
      including either by measuring with a traffic class that experiences
      minimal queuing or by summing the measured link delays of the components
      of the link's path.</t>

    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      <t>In this document, these words will appear with that interpretation
      only when in ALL CAPS. Lowercase uses of these words are not to be
      interpreted as carrying the significance described in RFC 2119.</t>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section title="TE Metric Extensions to IS-IS">
      <t>This document registers new IS-IS TE sub-TLVs that can be announced in
      the "Sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223" registry in order to
      distribute network-performance 
      information. The extensions in this document build on the ones provided
      in IS-IS TE <xref target="RFC5305"/> and GMPLS <xref
      target="RFC4203"/>.</t>

      <t>IS-IS Extended Reachability TLV 22 (defined in <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>), Inter-AS Reachability Information TLV 141 (defined
      in <xref target="RFC5316"/>), and MT-ISIS TLV 222 (defined in <xref
      target="RFC5120"/>) have nested sub-TLVs that permit the TLVs to be
      readily extended. This document registers several sub-TLVs:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
Type    Description
----------------------------------------------------
 33     Unidirectional Link Delay

 34     Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay

 35     Unidirectional Delay Variation

 36     Unidirectional Link Loss

 37     Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth

 38     Unidirectional Available Bandwidth

 39     Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>As can be seen in the list above, the sub-TLVs described in this
      document carry different types of network-performance information. The
      new sub-TLVs include a bit called the Anomalous (or "A") bit. When the A
      bit is clear (or when the sub-TLV does not include an A bit), the
      sub-TLV describes steady-state link performance. This information could
      conceivably be used to construct a steady-state performance topology for
      initial tunnel-path computation, or to verify alternative failover
      paths.</t>

      <t>When network performance violates configurable link-local thresholds,
      a sub-TLV with the A bit set is advertised. These sub-TLVs could be used
      by the receiving node to determine whether to fail traffic to a backup
      path or whether to calculate an entirely new path. From an MPLS
      perspective, the intent of the A bit is to permit label switched path ingress nodes
      to determine whether the link referenced in the sub-TLV affects any
   of the label switched paths for which it is ingress. If they are affected,
   then they can determine whether those label switched paths still meet end-to-end performance
   objectives. If not, then the node could conceivably move affected traffic
   to a pre-established protection label switched path or establish a new
   label switched path and place the
   traffic in it.</t>
      

      <t>If link performance then improves beyond a configurable minimum value
      (reuse threshold), that sub-TLV can be re-advertised with the A bit cleared. In this case, a receiving node can conceivably do whatever
      re-optimization (or failback) it wishes to do (including nothing).</t>

      <t>Note that when a sub-TLV does not include the A bit, that sub-TLV
      cannot be used for failover purposes. The A bit was intentionally
      omitted from some sub-TLVs to help mitigate oscillations. See <xref
      target="THRESHOLDS"/> for more information.</t>

      <t>Consistent with existing IS-IS TE specification <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>, the bandwidth advertisements defined in this document
      MUST be encoded as IEEE floating-point values. The delay and delay-variation advertisements defined in this document MUST be encoded as
      integer values. Delay values MUST be quantified in units of
      microseconds, packet loss MUST be quantified as a percentage of packets
      sent, and bandwidth MUST be sent as bytes per second. All values (except
      residual bandwidth) MUST be calculated as rolling averages where the
      averaging period MUST be a configurable period of time. See <xref
      target="THRESHOLDS"/> for more information.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Interface and Neighbor Addresses">
      <t>The use of IS-IS TE Metric Extensions sub-TLVs is not confined to the
      TE context. In other words, IS-IS TE Metric Extensions sub-TLVs defined
      in this document can also be used for computing paths in the absence of
      a TE subsystem.</t>

      <t>However, as for the TE case, Interface Address and Neighbor Address
      sub-TLVs (IPv4 or IPv6) MUST be present. The encoding is defined in
      <xref target="RFC5305"/> for IPv4 and in <xref target="RFC6119"/> for
      IPv6.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Sub-TLV Details">
      <section title="Unidirectional Link Delay Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the average link delay between two directly
        connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay advertised by this sub-TLV MUST
        be the delay from the local neighbor to the remote one (i.e., the
        forward-path latency). The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="DELAYFIG">
          <artwork> 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|A|  RESERVED   |                   Delay                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
<t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 33</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>A bit: The A bit represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The A bit is set
        when the measured value of this parameter exceeds its configured
        maximum threshold. The A bit is cleared when the measured value falls
        below its configured reuse threshold. If the A bit is clear, the
        sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Delay: This 24-bit field carries the average link delay over a
        configurable interval in microseconds, encoded as an integer value.
        When set to the maximum value 16,777,215 (16.777215 sec), then the
        delay is at least that value and may be larger.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the minimum and maximum delay values
        between two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the delay from the local neighbor to the
        remote one (i.e., the forward-path latency). The format of this sub-TLV
        is shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="MINMAXFIG">
          <artwork> 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|A| RESERVED    |                   Min Delay                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   RESERVED    |                   Max Delay                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
<t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 34</t>

        <t>Length: 8</t>

        <t>A bit: This field represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The A bit is set when
        one or more measured values exceed a configured maximum threshold. The
        A bit is cleared when the measured value falls below its configured
        reuse threshold. If the A bit is clear, the sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Min Delay: This 24-bit field carries the minimum measured link delay
        value (in microseconds) over a configurable interval, encoded as an
        integer value.</t>

        <t>Max Delay: This 24-bit field carries the maximum measured link
        delay value (in microseconds) over a configurable interval, encoded as
        an integer value.</t>

        <t>Implementations MAY also permit the configuration of an offset
        value (in microseconds) to be added to the measured delay value, to
        facilitate the communication of operator-specific delay
        constraints.</t>

        <t>It is possible for the Min and Max delay to be the same value.</t>

        <t>When the delay value (Min or Max) is set to the maximum value
        16,777,215 (16.777215 sec), then the delay is at least that value and
        may be larger.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Delay Variation Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the average link delay variation between
        two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay variation advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the delay from the local neighbor to the
        remote one (i.e., the forward-path latency). The format of this sub-TLV
        is shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="DELAYVARFIG">
          <artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  RESERVED     |               Delay Variation                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>

<t>where</t>
        <t>Type: 35</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Delay Variation: This 24-bit field carries the average link delay
        variation over a configurable interval in microseconds, encoded as an
        integer value. When set to 0, it has not been measured. When set to
        the maximum value 16,777,215 (16.777215 sec), then the delay is at
        least that value and may be larger.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Link Loss Sub-TLV">

        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the loss (as a packet percentage) between
        two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The link loss advertised by
        this sub-TLV MUST be the packet loss from the local neighbor to the
        remote one (i.e., the forward-path loss). The format of this sub-TLV is
        shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="PACKETLOSSFIG">
          <artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|A|  RESERVED   |                    Link Loss                  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
<t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 36</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>A bit: The A bit represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The A bit is set
        when the measured value of this parameter exceeds its configured
        maximum threshold. The A bit is cleared when the measured value falls
        below its configured reuse threshold. If the A bit is clear, the
        sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Link Loss: This 24-bit field carries link packet loss as a
        percentage of the total traffic sent over a configurable interval. The
        basic unit is 0.000003%, where (2^24 - 2) is 50.331642%. &nbsp;This value is
        the highest packet-loss percentage that can be expressed (the
        assumption being that precision is more important on high-speed links
        than the ability to advertise loss rates greater than this, and that
        high-speed links with over 50% loss are unusable). Therefore, measured
        values that are larger than the field maximum SHOULD be encoded as the
        maximum value.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="RESBW"
               title="Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the residual bandwidth between two directly
        connected IS-IS neighbors. The residual bandwidth advertised by this
        sub-TLV MUST be the residual bandwidth from the system originating the
        Link State Advertisement (LSA) to its neighbor.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |  RESERVED     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                          Residual Bandwidth                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
<t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 37</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Residual Bandwidth: This field carries the residual bandwidth on a
        link, forwarding adjacency <xref target="RFC4206"/>, or bundled link
        in IEEE floating-point format with units of bytes per second. For a
        link or forwarding adjacency, residual bandwidth is defined to be the
        Maximum Bandwidth <xref target="RFC5305"/> minus the bandwidth
        currently allocated to RSVP-TE label switched paths. For a bundled link, residual
        bandwidth is defined to be the sum of the component link residual
        bandwidths.</t>

        <t>The calculation of residual bandwidth is different than that of
        unreserved bandwidth <xref target="RFC5305"/>. Residual bandwidth
        subtracts tunnel reservations from maximum bandwidth (i.e., the link
        capacity) <xref target="RFC5305"/> and provides an aggregated
        remainder across priorities. Unreserved bandwidth, on the other hand,
        is subtracted from the maximum reservable bandwidth (the bandwidth
        that can theoretically be reserved) and provides per-priority
        remainders. Residual bandwidth and unreserved bandwidth <xref
        target="RFC5305"/> can be used concurrently and each has a separate
        use case (e.g., the former can be used for applications like Weighted
        ECMP while the latter can be used for call admission control).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Available Bandwidth Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the available bandwidth between two
        directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The available bandwidth advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the available bandwidth from the system
        originating this sub-TLV. The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="AVAILFIG">
          <artwork> 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |  RESERVED     |    
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Available Bandwidth                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
 <t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 38</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Available Bandwidth: This field carries the available bandwidth on
        a link, forwarding adjacency, or bundled link in IEEE floating-point
        format with units of bytes per second. For a link or forwarding
        adjacency, available bandwidth is defined to be residual bandwidth
        (see <xref target="RESBW"/>) minus the measured bandwidth used for the
        actual forwarding of non-RSVP-TE label switched path packets. For a bundled link,
        available bandwidth is defined to be the sum of the component link
        available bandwidths minus the measured bandwidth used for the actual
        forwarding of non-RSVP-TE label switched path packets. For a bundled
        link, available bandwidth is defined to be the sum of the component
        link available bandwidths.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth Sub-TLV">

        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the bandwidth utilization between two
        directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The bandwidth utilization
        advertised by this sub-TLV MUST be the bandwidth from the system
        originating this sub-TLV. The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="UTILFIG">
          <artwork> 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type        |     Length    |  RESERVED     |  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Utilized Bandwidth                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>
<t>where:</t>
        <t>Type: 39</t>

        <t>Length: 4</t>

        <t>RESERVED: This field is reserved for future use. It MUST be set to
        0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t>Utilized Bandwidth: This field carries the bandwidth utilization on
	a link, forwarding
        adjacency, or bundled link in IEEE floating-point format with units of
        bytes per second. For a link or forwarding adjacency, bandwidth
        utilization represents the actual utilization of the link (i.e., as
        measured by the advertising node). For a bundled link, bandwidth
        utilization is defined to be the sum of the component link bandwidth
        utilizations.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="THRESHOLDS" title="Announcement Thresholds and Filters">
      <t>The values advertised in all sub-TLVs (except min/max delay and
      residual bandwidth) MUST represent an average over a period or be
      obtained by a filter that is reasonably representative of an average.
      For example, a rolling average is one such filter.</t>

      <t>Min and max delay MUST each be derived in one of the following ways:
      by taking the lowest and/or highest measured value over a measurement
      interval or by making use of a filter or other technique to obtain a
      reasonable representation of a min and max value representative of the
      interval, with compensation for outliers.</t>

      <t>The measurement interval, any filter coefficients, and any
      advertisement intervals MUST be configurable per sub-TLV.</t>

      <t>In addition to the measurement intervals governing re-advertisement,
      implementations SHOULD provide configurable accelerated
      advertisement thresholds per sub-TLV, such that: 
<list style="numbers">
<t>If the measured parameter falls outside a configured upper 
   bound for all but the minimum delay metric (or lower bound for 
   minimum delay metric only) and the advertised sub-TLV is not 
   already outside that bound or,</t>

<t>If the difference between the last advertised value and 
   current measured value exceeds a configured threshold then,</t>

<t>The advertisement is made immediately.</t>

<t>For sub-TLVs that include an A bit, an additional 
   threshold SHOULD be included corresponding to the 
   threshold for which the performance is considered 
   anomalous (and sub-TLVs with the A bit are sent). &nbsp;The 
   A bit is cleared when the sub-TLV's performance has 
   been below (or re-crosses) this threshold for an 
   advertisement interval(s) to permit fail back.</t>
</list>
</t>

      <t>To prevent oscillations, only the high threshold or the low threshold
      (but not both) may be used to trigger any given sub-TLV that supports
      both.</t>

      <t>Additionally, once outside the bounds of the threshold, any
      re&nbhy;advertisement of a measurement within the bounds would remain governed
      solely by the measurement interval for that sub-TLV.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="SUPPRESS" title="Announcement Suppression">
      <t>When link-performance values change by small amounts that fall under
      thresholds that would cause the announcement of a sub-TLV,
      implementations SHOULD suppress sub-TLV re-advertisement and/or lengthen
      the period within which they are refreshed.</t>

      <t>Only the accelerated advertisement threshold mechanism described in
      <xref target="THRESHOLDS"/> may shorten the re-advertisement interval.
      All suppression and re-advertisement interval backoff timer features
      SHOULD be configurable.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="STABILITY"
             title="Network Stability and Announcement Periodicity">
      <t>Sections <xref target="THRESHOLDS" format="counter"/> and <xref
      target="SUPPRESS" format="counter"/> provide
      configurable mechanisms to bound the number of re-advertisements.
      Instability might occur in very large networks if measurement intervals
      are set low enough to overwhelm the processing of flooded information at
      some of the routers in the topology. Therefore, care should be taken in
      setting these values.</t>

      <t>Additionally, the default measurement interval for all sub-TLVs
      SHOULD be 30 seconds.</t>

      <t>Announcements MUST also be able to be throttled using configurable
      inter-update throttle timers. The minimum announcement periodicity is 1
      announcement per second. The default value SHOULD be set to 120
      seconds.</t>

      <t>Implementations SHOULD NOT permit the inter-update timer to be lower
      than the measurement interval.</t>

      <t>Furthermore, it is RECOMMENDED that any underlying performance-measurement mechanisms not include any significant buffer delay, any
      significant buffer-induced delay variation, or any significant loss due
      to buffer overflow or due to active queue management.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Enabling and Disabling Sub-TLVs">
      <t>Implementations MUST make it possible to individually enable or
      disable each sub-TLV based on configuration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Static Metric Override">
      <t>Implementations SHOULD permit static configuration and/or manual
      override of dynamic measurements for each sub-TLV in order to simplify
      migration and to mitigate scenarios where dynamic measurements are not
      possible.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Compatibility">
      <t>As per <xref target="RFC5305"/>, unrecognized sub-TLVs should be
      silently ignored.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The sub-TLVs introduced in this document allow an operator to
      advertise state information of links (bandwidth, delay) that could be
      sensitive and that an operator may not want to disclose.</t>

      <t><xref target="STABILITY"/> describes a mechanism to ensure
      network stability when the new sub-TLVs defined in this document are
      advertised. Implementation SHOULD follow the described guidelines
      to mitigate the instability risk.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC5304"/> describes an authentication method for IS-IS
      Link State PDUs that allows cryptographic authentication of IS-IS Link
      State PDUs.</t>

      <t>It is anticipated that in most deployments, the IS-IS protocol is used
      within an infrastructure entirely under control of the same operator.
      However, it is worth considering that the effect of sending IS-IS
      Traffic Engineering sub-TLVs over insecure links could result in a
      man-in-the-middle attacker delaying real-time data to a given site or
      destination, which could negatively affect the value of the data for
      that site or destination. The use of Link State PDU cryptographic authentication
      allows mitigation the risk of man-in-the-middle attack.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA maintains the registry for the sub-TLVs. IANA has registered the
      following sub-TLVs in the "Sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223"
      registry: 
      <figure>
          <artwork>
Type   Description
----------------------------------------------------
 33    Unidirectional Link Delay

 34    Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay

 35    Unidirectional Delay Variation

 36    Unidirectional Link Loss

 37    Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth

 38    Unidirectional Available Bandwidth

 39    Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth
</artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5305"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4206"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5316"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5120"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5304"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7285"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6375"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4203"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6374"?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to recognize Ayman Soliman, Nabil Bitar, David
      McDysan, Les Ginsberg, Edward Crabbe, Don Fedyk, Hannes Gredler, Uma
      Chunduri, Alvaro Retana, Brian Weis, and Barry Leiba for their
      contribution and review of this document.</t>

      <t>The authors also recognize Curtis Villamizar for significant comments
      and direct content collaboration.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The following people contributed substantially to the content
      of this document and should be considered co-authors:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
Alia Atlas
Juniper Networks
United States

Email: akatlas@juniper.net


Clarence Filsfils
Cisco Systems Inc.
Belgium

Email: cfilsfil@cisco.com</artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>


  </back>
</rfc>
