<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>


<rfc number="7841"
     submissionType="IAB"
     ipr="trust200902" 
     obsoletes="5741"
     consensus="yes"
     category="info" >
  <front>


    <title abbrev="RFC Streams, Headers, Boilerplates">
      RFC Streams, Headers, and Boilerplates
    </title>
    
    <author role="editor" initials="J.M." surname = "Halpern" fullname="Joel M. Halpern">
        <organization> </organization>
        <address> <email>jmh@joelhalpern.com</email> </address>
    </author>

    <author role="editor" initials="L." surname="Daigle" fullname="Leslie Daigle">
      <organization> </organization>
      <address>
        <email>ldaigle@thinkingcat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author role="editor" initials="O.M." surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf M. Kolkman">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>kolkman@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2016" month="April"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        RFC documents contain a number of fixed elements such as the
        title page header, standard boilerplates, and copyright/IPR
        statements.  This document describes them and introduces some
        updates to reflect current usage and requirements of RFC
        publication.  In particular, this updated structure is
        intended to communicate clearly the source of RFC creation and
        review. This document obsoletes RFC 5741, moving detailed content
        to an IAB web page and preparing for more flexible output formats.
      </t>
      
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
 <middle>
   
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
        Previously, RFCs (e.g., <xref target="RFC4844" />) contained a
        number of elements that were there for historical, practical,
        and legal reasons. They also contained boilerplate material to
        clearly indicate the status of the document and possibly
        contained "Notes" to indicate how the document interacts with
        IETF Standards-Track documents.
       
     </t>
     <t>
        As the RFC Series has evolved over the years, there has been
        increasing concern over appropriate labeling of the
        publications to make clear the status of each RFC and the
        status of the work it describes.  Chiefly, there is a
        requirement that RFCs published as part of the IETF's review
        process not be easily confused with RFCs that may have had a
        very different review and approval process.  Various
        adjustments have been made over the years, including evolving
        text of "Notes" included in the published RFC.
     </t>
     <t>
        With the definition of the different RFC streams <xref
        target="RFC4844"/>, it is appropriate to formalize the
        definition of the various pieces of standard RFC boilerplate
        and introduce some adjustments to ensure better clarity of
        expression of document status, aligned with the review and
        approval processes defined for each stream.
     </t>

     <t>
        This memo identifies and describes the common elements of RFC
        boilerplate structure.  It describes the content required
        for each kind of information.  Details of the exact textual and
        layout requirements are left to a web page maintained by the
        IAB, with due consultation with the community, for ease of
        maintenance.  This document obsoletes <xref
        target="RFC5741"/>.
     </t>
        
     <t>
        The changes introduced by this memo should be implemented as
        soon as practically possible after the document has been
        approved for publication.
     </t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="standards" title="RFC Streams and Internet Standards">
     <t>
        Users of RFCs should be aware that while all Internet
        Standards-related documents are published as RFCs, not all
        RFCs are Internet Standards-related documents.
     </t>

     <t>
        The IETF is responsible for maintaining the Internet Standards
        Process, which includes the requirements for developing,
        reviewing, and approving Standards Track and BCP RFCs.  
The IETF also produces non-Standards-Track documents (Informational,
Experimental, and Historic).  All documents published as part of the IETF
Stream are reviewed by the appropriate IETF bodies.
     </t>
     <t>
        Documents published in streams other than the IETF stream are
        not generally reviewed by the IETF for such things as security,
        congestion control, or inappropriate interaction with deployed
        protocols.  They have also not been subject to approval by the
        Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), including an
        IETF-wide last call.  Therefore, the IETF disclaims, for any
        of the non-IETF stream documents, any knowledge of the fitness
        of those RFCs for any purpose.
     </t>

     <t>
        Refer to <xref target="RFC2026"/>, <xref
        target="RFC5742"/>, <xref target="RFC4844"/>, <xref
        target="RFC6410"/>, and <xref target="RFC7127"/> and their
        successors for current details of the IETF process and RFC
        streams.
     </t>

   </section>

   <section title="RFC Structural Elements">
       <t>
         This section describes the elements that are commonly found
         in RFCs published today.  This document specifies information that
         is required in these publications.  Exact specification of the
         textual values required therein are provided by an IAB web page (https://www.iab.org/documents/headers-boilerplate).</t>
       <t>As noted above, this web page is maintained by the IAB with
       due consultation with the community.  Following such
       consultation, if the IAB decides to make any changes to this
       material, the changes will be announced in a similar fashion to
       other IAB statements. 
       The initial text to be used in that web page is included in
       <xref target="details"/>.
       </t>
     <section title="The Title Page Header">
        <t> 
          The information at the front of the RFC includes the 
          name and affiliation of the authors
          as well as the RFC publication month and year.  
        </t>
        <t>
          There is a set of additional information that is needed 
          at the front of the RFC.  Historically, this has been
          presented with the information below in a left hand column,
          and the author-related information described above in the
          right.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="&lt;document source&gt;"> 
              This describes the area where the work originates.
              Historically, all RFCs were labeled "Network Working
              Group". Network Working Group refers to the original
              version of today's IETF when people from the original
              set of ARPANET sites and whomever else was interested --
              the meetings were open -- got together to discuss,
              design, and document proposed protocols <xref
              target='RFC3'/>. Here, we obsolete the term "Network
              Working Group" in order to indicate the originating
              stream.
            </t>
            <t>
              The &lt;document source&gt; is the name of the RFC
              stream, as defined in <xref target="RFC4844"/> and its
              successors.  At the time of this publication, the
              streams, and therefore the possible entries are:
              <list style='symbols'>
                <t>Internet Engineering Task Force</t> 
                <t>Internet Architecture Board</t> 
                <t>Internet Research Task Force</t>
                <t>Independent Submission</t>
              </list>
              
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Request for Comments:  &lt;RFC number&gt;">
              This indicates the RFC number, assigned by the RFC
              Editor upon publication of the document.  This element
              is unchanged.
            </t>
            <t hangText="&lt;subseries ID&gt; &lt;subseries number&gt;"> 
              Some document categories are also labeled as a subseries
              of RFCs.  These elements appear as appropriate for such
              categories, indicating the subseries and the documents
              number within that series.  Currently, there are
              subseries for BCPs <xref target="RFC2026"/> and STDs <xref
              target="RFC1311"/>.
              These subseries numbers may appear in several RFCs.  For
              example, when a new RFC obsoletes or updates an old one,
              the same subseries number is used.  Also, several RFCs
              may be assigned the same subseries number: a single STD,
              for example, may be composed of several RFCs, each of
              which will bear the same STD number.  This element is
              unchanged.
            </t>
            <t hangText="[&lt;RFC relation&gt;:&lt;RFC number[s]&gt;]"> 
              Some relations between RFCs in the series are explicitly
              noted in the RFC header.  For example, a new RFC may
              update one or more earlier RFCs.  Currently two
              relationships are defined: "Updates" and "Obsoletes"
              <xref target="RFC7322"/>. Variants like "Obsoleted by"
              are also used (e.g, in <xref target="RFC5143"/>).  Other
              types of relationships may be defined by the RFC Editor
              and may appear in future RFCs.

            </t>
            <t hangText="Category: &lt;category&gt;">
              This indicates the initial RFC document category of the
              publication.  These are defined in <xref
              target="RFC2026"/>.  Currently, this is always one of:
              Standards Track, Best Current Practice, Experimental,
              Informational, or Historic.  This element is unchanged.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

     </section>

     <section anchor="Status" title="The Status of This Memo">
        <t>
          The "Status of This Memo" describes the category of the RFC,
          including the distribution statement.  
        </t>
        
        <t>
          The "Status of This Memo" will start with a single sentence
          describing the status. It will also include a statement
          describing the stream-specific review of the material (which
          is stream dependent).  This is an important component of
          status, insofar as it clarifies the breadth and depth of
          review, and gives the reader an understanding of how to
          consider its content.
        </t>
     </section>
        
     <section title="Paragraph 1" anchor="first">
        <t>
          The first paragraph of the "Status of This Memo" section
          contains a single sentence, clearly standing out.  The
	  sentence will clearly identify the stream-specific status
          of the document.  The text to be used is defined by the 
          stream, with a review for clarity by the IAB and RFC Series Editor.
        </t>
     </section>


<section title="Paragraph 2" anchor="second">
        
        <t>
          The second paragraph of the "Status of This Memo" will 
          include a paragraph describing the type of review and
          exposure the document has received.  This is defined on a
          per-stream basis, subject to general review and oversight by
          the RFC Editor and IAB.  The IAB defines a specific structure
          defined to ensure there is clarity about review
          processes and document types.  
</t>
</section>

<section title="Paragraph 3" anchor="third">

        <t>
          The boilerplate ends with a reference to where further
          relevant information can be found.  This information may
          include, subject to the RFC Editor's discretion, information
          about whether the RFC has been updated or obsoleted, the RFC's
          origin, a listing of possible errata, information about how
          to provide feedback and suggestion, and information on how
          to submit errata as described in <xref
          target="ERRATA"/>.  The exact wording
          and URL is subject to change (at the RFC Editor's
          discretion), but the current text is:
</t>
<t><list><t>
Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to
provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/&lt;static-path&gt;/rfc&lt;rfc-no&gt;.
</t></list></t>
</section>

<section title="Noteworthy">

        <t>
          Note that the text in paragraph 1 and 2 of the boilerplate
          indicate the initial status of a document. During their
          lifetime, documents can change status to, for example, Historic. This
          cannot be reflected in the document itself and will need be
          reflected in the information referred to in <xref
          target="Structure"/>.
        </t>

</section>

        
     </section>

     <section title="Additional Notes">
        <t>
          Exceptionally, a review and publication process may
          prescribe additional notes that will appear as labeled
          notes after the "Abstract".
        </t>
        <t>
   This is no longer a common feature of recent RFCs.  It is the goal
   of this document to continue to ensure that the overall RFC structure
   is adequately clear so that such notes are unnecessary or (at least) truly 
   exceptional.
        </t>

     </section>

     <section anchor="Structure" title="Other Structural Information in RFCs">
        <t> RFCs contain other structural informational elements. The
        RFC Editor is responsible for the positioning and layout of
        these structural elements. Note also that new elements may be
        introduced or obsoleted using a process consistent with 
        <xref target="RFC4844" />.  These additions may or may not require
        documentation in an RFC.
        </t>
        <t> 
   Currently, the following structural information is available
   in RFCs:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            
            <t hangText="Copyright Notice:"> 
              A copyright notice with a reference to BCP 78 <xref
              target="BCP78"/> and an Intellectual Property statement
              referring to BCP 78 and BCP 79 <xref target="BCP79"/>. The
              content of these statements are defined by those BCPs.
            </t>

           <t hangText="ISSN:"> 
              The International Standard Serial Number <xref
              target="ISO.3297.2007"/>: ISSN&nbsp;2070-1721. The ISSN uniquely
              identifies the RFC series as title regardless of
              language or country in which it is published. The ISSN itself
              has no significance other than the unique identification
              of a serial publication.
            </t>
            
          </list>
        </t>
     </section>

   <section  title="Security Considerations">
     <t>
        This document tries to clarify the descriptions of the status
        of an RFC.  Misunderstanding the status of a memo could cause
        interoperability problems, hence security and stability
        problems.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section  title="RFC Editor Considerations">
     <t>
        The RFC Editor is responsible for maintaining the consistency
        of the RFC series. To that end, the RFC Editor maintains an
        "RFC Style Guide" <xref target="RFC7322"/>. In this memo, we mention a few
        explicit structural elements that the RFC Editor needs to maintain.
        The conventions for the content and use of all current and 
        future elements are documented in the style guide.
     </t>
     <t>
        Adding a reference to the stream in the header of RFCs is only
        one method for clarifying from which stream an RFC
        originated. The RFC Editor is encouraged to add such
        indication in, for example, indices and interfaces.
     </t>
     
       </section>

 </middle>
 <back>

   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2026" ?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5742" ?>
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">

    <?rfc include="reference.ISO.3297.2007" ?>
<!--    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0003" ?> -->
<reference  anchor='RFC3' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3'>
<front>
<title>Documentation conventions</title>
<author initials='S.D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='S.D. Crocker'><organization /></author>
<date year='1969' month='April' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0003'/>
</reference>


    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1311" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3979" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4749" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4844" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5143" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5741" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6410" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7127" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7322" ?>


<!-- draft-rfc-editor-errata-process-02: Expired -->

<reference anchor='ERRATA'>
<front>
<title>RFC Editor Proposal for Handling RFC Errata</title>

<author initials='A' surname='Hagens' fullname='Alice Hagens'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Ginoza' fullname='Sandy Ginoza'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Braden' fullname='Robert Braden'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='21' year='2008' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-rfc-editor-errata-process-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-rfc-editor-errata-process-02.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="646:headers-boilerplates.xml"?>


<reference anchor="BCP78" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp78">
    <front>
          <title>Rights Contributors Provide to the IETF Trust</title>

     <author role="editor" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
        <organization />
     </author>
     <author role="editor" initials="J." surname="Contreras">
        <organization />
     </author>

          <date month='November' year="2008"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='78' />
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5378' />
 </reference>


 <reference anchor="BCP79" >
   <front>
     <title>Intellectual Property Rights in IETF Technology</title>
     <author role="editor" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
        <organization />
     </author>
     <author role="editor" initials="T." surname="Narten">
        <organization/>
     </author>
     <date month='April' year="2007"/>
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='79' />
   <annotation>At the moment of publication: <xref target="RFC3979"/> and <xref target="RFC4749"/></annotation>
 </reference>

   </references>


   <section anchor="details" title="Initial Formatting Details">
      <t>This section contains the text the IAB used to initially populate the
      web page used to maintain the list of required verbiage.
      </t>

     <section title="RFC Title Page Header">
        <t>
          An RFC title page header can be described as follows:
          <figure>
<artwork>
------------------------------------------------------------------------
&lt;document source&gt;                                          &lt;author name&gt;
Request for Comments: &lt;RFC number&gt;                [&lt;author affiliation&gt;]
[&lt;subseries ID&gt; &lt;subseries number&gt;]    [more author info as appropriate]
[&lt;RFC relation&gt;:&lt;RFC number[s]&gt;]        
Category: &lt;category&gt;
                                                            &lt;month year&gt;

------------------------------------------------------------------------
            </artwork>
          </figure>
<!--          For example, a sample earlier RFC header is as follows: -->
For example, the header for RFC 6410 appears as follows: 

          <figure>
<artwork>
<!--
Network Working Group                                          T. Dierks
Request for Comments: 4346                                   Independent
Obsoletes: 2246                                              E. Rescorla
Category: Standards Track                                     RTFM, Inc.
-->
------------------------------------------------------------------------

Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)                        R. Housley
Request for Comments: 6410                                Vigil Security
BCP: 9                                                        D. Crocker
Updates: 2026                                Brandenburg InternetWorking
Category: Best Current Practice                                E. Burger
ISSN: 2070-1721                                    Georgetown University
                                                            October 2011

------------------------------------------------------------------------
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
     </section>
        
     <section title="Constructing a &quot;Status of This Memo&quot; Section">
        <t>The following sections describe mandated text for use in
        specific parts of the "Status of This Memo" portion of an RFC.
        For convenience, the RFC Editor maintains example expansions of 
        all permutations of the paragraphs described in this document
        (at the time of publication, at 
        http://www.rfc-editor.org/materials/status-memos.txt).
        When in conflict, these following sections are authoritative.
        </t>

        <section title="First Paragraph">
          <t>The following are the approved texts for use in the first 
          paragraph of the "Status of This Memo" portion of an RFC.
          See <xref target="first" /> of RFC 7841.</t> 
          <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="For 'Standards Track' documents:" >
              "This  is an Internet Standards Track document."
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="For 'Best Current Practices' documents:" >
              "This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice."
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="For other categories" >
              "This document is not an Internet Standards Track
              specification;  &lt;it is published for other
              purposes&gt;."
            </t>
          </list>
          </t>
         <t> For Informational, Experimental, Historic, and future
          categories of RFCs, the RFC Editor will maintain an
          appropriate text for &lt;it is published for other
          purposes&gt;. Initial values are:
        </t>
    <t>
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText="Informational: ">  "it is published for informational purposes."
          </t>
          <t hangText="Historic: ">  "it is published for the historical record."
          </t>
          <t hangText="Experimental: "> "it is published for examination,
           experimental implementation, and evaluation."
          </t>
        </list>
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Second Paragraph">
<t>See <xref target="second" /> of RFC 7841.</t>
<t>The second paragraph may include some text that is specific to the
          initial document category, as follows:
          when a document is Experimental or Historic, the 
          second paragraph opens with:
</t>
    
    <t>
          <list style='hanging'>

            <t hangText="Experimental:">
              "This document defines an Experimental Protocol for the
              Internet community."
            </t>

          
            <t hangText="Historic:">
              "This document defines a Historic Document for the Internet
              community."
            </t>
          </list>
    </t>
        
        <t>
          The text that follows is stream dependent -- 
these are initial values and may be updated by stream
definition document updates 
and recorded by the IAB on the web page.
</t>
    
    <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="IETF Stream:">
              "This document is a product of the Internet Engineering
              Task Force (IETF)."
            </t>
            <t> If there has been an IETF consensus call per IETF
            process, this additional text should be added: "It
            represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has
            received public review and has been approved for
            publication by the Internet Engineering Steering Group
            (IESG)." If there has not been such a consensus call, then this
            simply reads: "It has been approved for
            publication by the Internet Engineering Steering Group
            (IESG)."
            </t>

            <t hangText="IAB Stream:">
              "This document is a product of the Internet Architecture Board
              (IAB), and represents information that the IAB has
              deemed valuable to provide for permanent record."
            </t>
            <t> If the document represents IAB consensus, this additional text 
                should be added:
                "It represents the consensus of the Internet Architecture Board (IAB)."
            </t>
            <t hangText="IRTF Stream:">
              "This document is a product of the Internet Research Task Force
              (IRTF).  The IRTF publishes the results of
              Internet-related research and development activities.
              These results might not be suitable for deployment."
            </t>

            <t>
              In addition, a sentence indicating the consensus base
              within the IRTF may be added: "This RFC represents the
              consensus of the &lt;insert_name&gt; Research Group of
              the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF)." or
              alternatively "This RFC represents the individual
              opinion(s) of one or more members of the
              &lt;insert_name&gt; Research Group of the Internet
              Research Task Force (IRTF)".
            </t>
            <t hangText="Independent Submission Stream:">
              "This is a contribution to the RFC Series,
              independently of any other RFC stream.  The RFC Editor
              has chosen to publish this document at its discretion
              and makes no statement about its value for
              implementation or deployment."
            </t>
          </list>
    </t>

        <t>
          For non-IETF stream documents, a reference to <xref
          target="standards"/> of this RFC is added with the following
          sentence: "Documents approved for publication by the [stream
          approver -- currently, one of: "IAB", "IRSG", or "RFC
          Editor"] are not a candidate for any level of Internet
          Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 7841."
        </t>
        <t>
          For IETF stream documents, a similar reference is added:
          "Further information on (BCPs or Internet Standards) is
          available in Section 2 of RFC 7841." for BCP
          and Standard Track documents; "Not all documents approved by
          the IESG are candidate for any level of Internet Standards;
          see Section 2 of RFC 7841." for all other categories.
        </t>

     </section>
     <section title="Third Paragraph">
     <t>See <xref target="third" /> of RFC 7841.</t>
     </section>

     </section>

   </section>

   <section title="IAB Members at Time of Approval" numbered="no">

   <t>
     The IAB members at the time this memo was approved
     were (in alphabetical order):

<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<list>
<t>Jari Arkko</t>
<t>Mary Barnes</t>
<t>Marc Blanchet</t>
<t>Ralph Droms</t>
<t>Ted Hardie</t>
<t>Joe Hildebrand</t>
<t>Russ Housley</t>
<t>Erik Nordmark</t>
<t>Robert Sparks</t>
<t>Andrew Sullivan</t>
<t>Dave Thaler</t>
<t>Brian Trammell</t>
<t>Suzanne Woolf</t>
</list>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
   </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
     <t>
        Thanks to Bob Braden, Brian Carpenter, Steve Crocker, Sandy
        Ginoza, and John Klensin who provided background information
        and inspiration.
     </t>
     <t>Thanks to the members of the RFC Series Oversight Committee
     (RSOC) for assistance and review: Alexey Melnikov, Nevil Brownlee,
     Bob Hinden, Sarah Banks, Robert Sparks, Tony Hansen, and 
     Joe Hildebrand.
     </t>
     <t>Various people have made suggestions that improved the
     document. Among them are: Lars Eggert, Alfred Hoenes, and Joe Touch.
      </t>

   </section>

 </back>
</rfc>
