<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>


<rfc number="7549"
     ipr="trust200902" 
     category="std" 
     submissionType="IETF" 
     consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="3GPP 'iotl'">
	 3GPP SIP URI Inter-Operator Traffic Leg Parameter
	</title>
    <author fullname="Christer Holmberg" initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg">
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>02420</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 
    
    <author fullname="Jan Holm" initials="J.H." surname="Holm">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kistavagen 25</street>
          <city>Stockholm16480</city>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jan.holm@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roland Jesske" initials="R.J." surname="Jesske">
      <organization abbrev="Deutsche Telekom">Deutsche Telekom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Heinrich-Hertz-Strasse 3-7</street>
          <city>Darmstadt</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>64307</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+4961515812766</phone>
        <email>r.jesske@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
	</author>

	<author initials="M.D." surname="Dolly" fullname="Martin Dolly">
		<organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>718 Clairmore Ave</street>
                <code>08734</code>
                <city>Lanoka Harbor</city>
                <country>United States</country>
            </postal>
            <email>md3135@att.com</email>
        </address>
	</author>

	
    <date month="May" year="2015" />
    <area>Transport</area>


<keyword>3GPP</keyword>
<keyword>IMS</keyword>
<keyword>NNI</keyword>
<keyword>IOTL</keyword>
<keyword>CSCF</keyword>
<keyword>RAVEL</keyword>
<keyword>TRF</keyword>
<keyword>operator</keyword>
<keyword>transit</keyword>

    <abstract>
		<t>
			In 3GPP networks, the signaling path between a calling user 
			and a called user can be partitioned into segments, referred to as traffic legs. Each traffic leg 
			may span networks belonging to different operators and will have its own characteristics 
			that can be different from other traffic legs in the same call. A traffic leg might be 
			associated with multiple SIP dialogs, e.g., in case a
			Back-to-Back User Agent (B2BUA) that modifies the SIP dialog identifier is 
			located within the traffic leg. 
		</t>
		<t>   


			This document defines a new SIP URI parameter, 'iotl' (an abbreviation for Inter-Operator Traffic Leg). The parameter 
			can be used in a SIP URI to indicate that the entity associated with the
			address, or an entity responsible for the host part of the address,
			represents the end of a specific traffic leg (or multiple traffic legs).
		</t>
		<t>
			The SIP URI 'iotl' parameter defined in this document has known uses 
			in 3GPP networks. Usage in other networks is also possible.
		</t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  
    <section title="Introduction">
		<t>
			In a 3GPP network, an end-user device can be 
			attached (e.g., using a radio access network) to its own operator network (home network) 
			<xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229" pageno="false" format="default"/> or to another operator's 
			network (visited network) <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229" pageno="false" format="default"/>. 
			In the latter case, the user is referred to as a roaming user.
		</t>
		<t>
			3GPP operator networks are often not connected directly to each other. Instead, there might be 
			intermediate networks, referred to as 3GPP transit networks, between them. Such transit networks 
			act on the SIP level or the IP level.
		</t>
		<t>
			In 3GPP networks, the signaling path between a calling user and a called user can be 
			partitioned into segments, referred to as traffic legs. Each traffic leg may span networks belonging to
			different operators and will have its own characteristics that can be different from other traffic legs 
			in the same call. A traffic leg might be associated with multiple SIP dialogs, e.g., in case a 
			B2BUA <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/> that 
			modifies the SIP dialog identifier is located within the traffic leg.
		</t>
		<t>
			The traffic leg information can be used by intermediary entities to make policy decisions related
			to, e.g., media anchoring, signaling policy, insertion of media functions (e.g., transcoder), and charging.
		</t>
		<t>
			The figure below shows two users (Alice and Bob) and the different type of networks that the
			signaling might traverse. The signaling path can be divided into multiple traffic legs, and the type
			of traffic legs depends on how the signaling is routed.
		</t> 
<figure align="center" title="3GPP Operator Network Roaming Roles" anchor="xml_network">
<preamble></preamble>

<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Alice -- ORIG HNW +++++ TRANSIT NW +++++ TERM HNW -- Bob
Home           +     +                +    +   +    Home
               +     ++++++++++++++++++    +   +
               +                           +   +
               +                           +   +
               +     +++++++++++++++++++++++   +
               +     +              +          +
Alice -- ORIG VNW +++++ TRANSIT NW ++    TERM VNW -- Bob
Visited                                           Visited
         
ORIG HNW  =     Originating 3GPP Home Network
TERM HNW  =     Terminating 3GPP Home Network
ORIG VNW  =     Originating 3GPP Visited Network
TERM VNW  =     Terminating 3GPP Visited Network
TRANSIT NW =    3GPP Transit Network
]]></artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>



		<t>
			In <xref target="xml_network"/>, Alice is a user initiating communication
			with Bob. Also, consider the following information:
		</t>
		<t>
			Alice is attached to an originating network, which is either the 
			home network of Alice or a visited network (in case Alice is roaming). In both 
			cases, any originating service is provided by the home network of Alice.
		</t>
		<t>
			Bob is attached to a terminating network, which is either the home network 
			of Bob or a visited network (in case Bob is roaming). In both cases, any 
			terminating service is provided by the home network of Bob.
		</t>
		<t>
			A transit network providing transit functions (e.g., translation of free 
			phone numbers) may be included between the originating and terminating 
			networks and between visited and home networks.
		</t>
		<t>   
			This document defines a new SIP URI parameter <xref target="RFC3261" 
			pageno="false" format="default"/>, 'iotl' (an abbreviation for Inter-Operator
			Traffic Leg). The parameter can be used in a SIP URI to indicate that the 
			entity associated with the address, or an entity responsible for the host 
			part of the address, represents the end of a specific traffic leg 
			(or multiple traffic legs).
		</t>
		<t>
			This document defines the following 'iotl' parameter values:
		</t>
		<t>
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>
					homea-homeb
				</t>
				<t>
					homeb-visitedb 
				</t>
				<t>
					visiteda-homea
				</t>
				<t>
					homea-visiteda 
				</t>
				<t>
					visiteda-homeb 
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
			SIP entities that do not support the SIP URI 'iotl' parameter will simply
			ignore it, if received, as defined in <xref target="RFC3261" 
			pageno="false" format="default"/>.
		</t>
    </section>
	
    <section title="Conventions">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
			"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
			document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
		</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Applicability">
		<t>
			The SIP URI 'iotl' parameter defined in this document has known uses 
			in 3GPP networks. Usage in other networks is also possible.
		</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Traffic Leg Examples">
		<section title="General">
			<t>
				This section describes examples of different types of traffic legs in 3GPP 
				networks.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Originating Roaming Call">
			<t>
				In this case, Alice is located in a visited network. When Alice sends the initial SIP INVITE
				request for a call, one traffic leg (referred to as the 'visiteda-homea' traffic leg) 
				represents the signaling path between the
				User Agent (UA) of Alice and the home Serving
				Call Session Control Function (S-CSCF) <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/>
				of Alice.
			</t>
		</section> 
		<section title="Terminating Roaming Call">
			<t>
				In this case, Bob is located in a visited network. When the home S-CSCF of Bob forwards
				the initial SIP INVITE request for a call towards Bob, one traffic leg
				(referred to as the 'homeb-visitedb' traffic leg) represents the signaling path between 
				the home S-CSCF of Bob and the UA of Bob.
			</t>
		</section> 
		<section title="Call from Originating Home to Terminating Home">
			<t>
				In this case, the home S-CSCF of Alice forwards the initial SIP INVITE request towards
				the home S-CSCF of Bob. The signaling path between the S-CSCFs represents 
				one traffic leg (referred to as the 'homea-homeb' traffic leg).
			</t>
		</section> 				
    </section>


           
    <section title="'iotl' SIP URI Parameter">
		<section title="Usage">

			<t>
				As specified in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3261"/>, when a SIP entity 
				inserts a SIP URI in an initial request for a dialog, or in a stand-alone request, the SIP URI 
				will be used to route the request to another SIP entity, addressed by the SIP URI, or to a SIP entity 
				responsible for the host part of the SIP URI
				(e.g., a SIP registrar). If such an entity represents 
				the end of one or more traffic legs, the SIP entity inserting the SIP URI can add a SIP URI 'iotl' parameter 
				to the SIP URI to indicate the type(s) of traffic leg. Each parameter value indicates a type of 
				traffic leg.
			</t>


			<t>

			  For routing of an initial SIP request for a dialog,
			  or a stand-alone SIP request,
			  a SIP entity can add the 'iotl' parameter to (a) the
			  SIP URI of the Request-URI <xref target="RFC3261"/>
			  or (b) the SIP URI of a Route header field <xref target="RFC3261"/>
			  of the SIP request.

				SIP entities can add the 'iotl' parameter to the SIP URI of a Path header field 
				<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3327"/> or a Service-Route header 
				field <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3608"/> in order for the parameter 
				to later occur in a Route header field.
			</t>
			<t>
				When a SIP entity receives an initial request for a dialog or a stand-alone request,
				which contains one or more SIP URI 'iotl' parameters, it identifies the type of traffic 
				leg in the following way:
			</t>
			<t>
				<list style="symbols">
				<t>
					if the SIP request contains a single Route header field containing a SIP URI with an
					'iotl' parameter, that parameter identifies the type of traffic leg;
				</t>
				<t>
					if the SIP request contains multiple Route header fields containing a SIP URI with an
					'iotl' parameter, the 'iotl' parameter associated with the SIP URI of the topmost Route 
					header field (or, if the SIP URI of the topmost Route header field does not contain an 
					'iotl' parameter, the SIP URI of the Route header field closest to the topmost) identifies 
					the type of traffic leg; or
				</t>
				<t>
					if a SIP request contains an 'iotl' parameter only in the Request-URI SIP URI, the 'iotl'
					parameter identifies the type of traffic leg.
				</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				During SIP registration <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3261"/>, entities 
				can add the 'iotl' parameter to the SIP URI of a Path or Service-Route header field if the 
				entity is aware that the SIP URI will be used to indicate the end of a specific traffic leg for 
				initial requests for dialogs or stand-alone requests sent on the registration path.
			</t>
			<t>
				As defined in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3261"/>, a SIP proxy must 
				not modify or remove URI parameters from SIP URIs associated with other entities. This also 
				applies to the 'iotl' parameter.
			</t>
		</section>
	
		<section title="Parameter Values">
			<section title="General">
				<t>
					This section describes the SIP URI 'iotl' parameter values defined in this specification.
				</t>
<t>
     Note that, when a request is routed between different networks, the
        request might traverse one or more IBCFs (Interconnection Border 
	   Control Functions) acting as network border entities.
</t>
			</section>	
			<section title="homea-homeb">
				<t>
					This value indicates that a SIP entity responsible for the host part of the SIP URI 
					associated with the parameter represents the end of a traffic leg between 
					the home network (originating) of the calling user and the home network (terminating) 
					of the called user.
				</t>
				<t>
					In 3GPP, this traffic leg is between two S-CSCFs.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="homeb-visitedb">
				<t>
					This value indicates that the SIP entity addressed by the SIP URI associated with the 
					parameter represents the end of a traffic leg between the home network (terminating) 
					of the called user and the visited network (terminating) in which the called user is 
					located.
				</t>
				<t>
					In 3GPP, this traffic leg is between
					the home S-CSCF and the User Equipment
					(UE) of the called user
					or between the Service Centralization and Continuity Application Server (SCC AS) in 
					the home network of the called user and Access Transfer Control Function (ATCF) in 
					the visited network of the called user.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="visiteda-homea">
				<t>
					This value indicates that a SIP entity responsible for the host part of the SIP URI 
					associated with the parameter represents the end of a traffic leg between 
					the visited network (originating) in which the calling user is located
					and the home network (originating) of the calling user.
				</t>
				<t>
					In 3GPP, this traffic leg is between the UE and the home S-CSCF of the calling user or
					between the Proxy Call Session Control
					Function (P-CSCF) in the visited network, serving the calling user and the home S-CSCF 
					of the calling user.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="homea-visiteda">
				<t>
					This value indicates that the SIP entity addressed by the SIP URI associated with the 
					parameter represents the end of a traffic leg between the home network (originating) 
					and the visited network (originating) in which the calling user is located.
				</t>
				<t>
					In 3GPP, this traffic leg is between the home S-CSCF of the calling user and the 
					Transit and Roaming Function (TRF)
					<xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/>
					serving the calling user and exists in scenarios where the home S-CSCF of the calling user 
					forwards a request back to the visited network where the UE of the calling user is located. 
					An example of this is when the Roaming
					Architecture for Voice over IMS with Local Breakout 
					(RAVEL) <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/> feature is enabled.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="visiteda-homeb">
				<t>
					This value indicates that a SIP entity responsible for the host part of the SIP URI 
					associated with the parameter represents the end of a traffic leg between 
					the visited network (originating) of the calling user and the home
					network (terminating) of the called user.
				</t>
				<t>
					In 3GPP, this traffic leg is between the TRF 
					<xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/> serving the calling user and the home S-CSCF of the called user and 
					exists in scenarios where a request is forwarded from the visited network where the calling 
					user is located directly to the home S-CSCF of the called user. An example of this is when 
					the RAVEL <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/>
					feature is enabled.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	
	<section title="Syntax">
		<section title="General">
			<t>
				This section defines the ABNF for the 'iotl' SIP URI parameter. 
				The ABNF defined in this specification is conformant to RFC 5234
				<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5234"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification does not create an IANA registry for 'iotl' parameter values.
				A registry should be considered if new parameter values are defined in the future.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="ABNF">
			<t>
				The ABNF <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5234"/> 
				grammar for this SIP URI parameter is:
			</t>
			<figure>
<artwork type="abnf" align="left"><![CDATA[
uri-parameter =/ iotl-param
iotl-param    = iotl-tag "=" iotl-value ["." iotl-value]
iotl-tag      = "iotl"
iotl-value    = "homea-homeb" / "homeb-visitedb" / "visiteda-homea"
                 / "homea-visiteda" / "visiteda-homeb" / other-iotl
other-iotl    = 1*iotl-char
iotl-char     = alphanum / "-"
;; alphanum defined in RFC 3261
]]></artwork>
			</figure>
        </section>                 
    </section>

	
	<section title="Security Considerations">
		<t>
			The information in the 'iotl' parameter is used for making policy
			decisions. Such policies can be related to charging and triggering
			of services. In order to prevent abuse, which could cause user billing
			or service failure, the parameter SHOULD only be used for making
			policy decisions based on the role by nodes within the same trust 
			domain <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3325"/>, and 
			network boundary entities MUST NOT forward information received 
			from untrusted entities. In addition, an agreement
			MUST exist between the operators for usage of the roaming role information.
		</t>
		<t>
			General security considerations for SIP are defined in <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
			target="RFC3261"/> 
		</t>
	</section>

	
	<section title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>
			Per this specification, IANA has added one new value to
			the "SIP/SIPS URI Parameters" registry as defined in 
			<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3969"/>.
		</t>
		<figure>
<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
      Parameter Name  Predefined Values  Reference
      ____________________________________________
                iotl      Yes            RFC 7549
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
	</section>
                   
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3327"?>		
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3608"?>		
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3969"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

    <reference anchor="TS.3GPP.24.229">
		<front> 
		<title>Vocabulary for 3GPP Specifications</title>
		<author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
		<date year="2014" month="September"/>
	</front> 
	<seriesInfo value="24.229 12.6.0" name="3GPP TS"/> 
	<format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/24229.htm"/> 
    </reference>
    </references>
	
	<references title="Informative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3325"?>
	</references>
	
	<section anchor="section.example" title="3GPP Examples">
        <section title="General">
          <t>
				This section contains example call flows based on 3GPP usage of the SIP URI
				'iotl' parameter.
          </t>
        </section>
		
		<section title="The UE Registers via P-CSCF">
			<t>
				The Visited Proxy (P-CSCF) adds the 'iotl' value 'homeb-visitedb' to the Path header field
				of the REGISTER request to be used for terminating routing towards Alice. The Home Proxy (S-CSCF)
				adds the 'iotl' value 'visiteda-homea' to the Service-Route header field to be used for
				originating initial/stand-alone requests from Alice.
			</t>


			<t>
<figure anchor="example_1_figure" title="The UE Registers via P-CSCF">
<artwork><![CDATA[
             Visited Proxy    Visited Proxy      Home Proxy   Home Proxy
Alice's . . . . P-CSCF . . . . .  IBCF-V . . . . . IBCF-H . . . . S-CSCF
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   REGISTER F1  |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   REGISTER F2  |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|   REGISTER F3  |                |
  |                |                |--------------->|  REGISTER F4   |
  |                |                |                |--------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |  200 (OK) F5   |
  |                |                |                |<---------------|
  |                |                |  200 (OK) F6   |                |
  |                |                |<---------------|                |
  |                |  200 (OK) F7   |                |                |
  |                |<---------------|                |                |
  |  200 (OK) F8   |                |                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  
   
   F1 REGISTER Alice -> P-CSCF
   REGISTER sip:registrar.home1.net SIP/2.0

   F2 REGISTER P-CSCF -> IBCF-V
   REGISTER sip:registrar.home1.net SIP/2.0
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>

   F3 REGISTER IBCF-V -> IBCF-H
   REGISTER sip:registrar.home1.net SIP/2.0
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>

   F4 REGISTER IBCF-H -> S-CSCF
   REGISTER sip:registrar.home1.net SIP/2.0
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>

   F5 200 OK S-CSCF -> IBCF-H
   200 OK 
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>
   Service-Route: <s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F6 200 OK IBCF-H -> IBCF-V
   200 OK 
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>
   Service-Route: <s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F7 200 OK IBCF-V -> P-CSCF
   200 OK 
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>
   Service-Route: <s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F8 200 OK P-CSCF -> Alice
   200 OK 
   Path: <p-cscf URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb>
   Service-Route: <s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
			</t>
        </section>

		
		<section title="Originating IMS Call">
			<t>			
				In the originating INVITE request from Alice, the 'iotl' value 'visiteda-homea',
				received in the Service-Route header field during registration, is
				added to the Route header field representing the Home Proxy (S-CSCF) to indicate
				the traffic leg type between the Visited Proxy (P-CSCF) and the Home Proxy (S-CSCF).
			</t>
			<t>
            <figure anchor="example_2_figure" title="Originating IP Multimedia
						     Subsystem (IMS) Call">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
             Visited Proxy    Visited Proxy      Home Proxy   Home Proxy
Alice's . . . . P-CSCF . . . . .  IBCF-V . . . . . IBCF-H . . . . S-CSCF
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   INVITE F1    |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   INVITE F2    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|   INVITE F3    |                |
  |                |                |--------------->|   INVITE F4    |
  |                |                |                |--------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |    180   F5    |
  |                |                |    180   F6    |<---------------|
  |                |    180   F7    |<---------------|                |
  |    180   F8    |<---------------|                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |                |


   F1 INVITE Alice -> P-CSCF
   INVITE sip:Bob@homeb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <p-cscf URI>,<s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F2 INVITE P-CSCF -> IBCF-V
   INVITE sip:Bob@homeb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <ibcf-v URI>,<s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F3 INVITE IBCF-V -> IBCF-H
   INVITE sip:Bob@homeb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <ibcf-h URI>,<s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>

   F4 INVITE IBCF-H -> S-CSCF
   INVITE sip:Bob@homeb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <s-cscf URI;iotl=visiteda-homea>
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
			</t>
        </section>
		
		
		<section title="Terminating IMS Call">
			<t>			
				In the terminating INVITE request towards Alice, the 'iotl' value 'homeb-visitedb'
				provided to the Home Proxy (S-CSCF) during registration is
				added to the Route header field representing the Visited Proxy (P-CSCF) to indicate
				the traffic leg type between the Home Proxy (S-CSCF) and the Visited Proxy (P-CSCF).
			</t>
			<t>
            <figure anchor="example_3_figure" title="Terminating IMS Call">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Home Proxy    Home Proxy      Visited Proxy     Visited Proxy        
S-CSCF  . . . . IBCF-H . . . . .  IBCF-V . . . . . P-CSCF . . . . .  Bob
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   INVITE F1    |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   INVITE F2    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|   INVITE F3    |                |
  |                |                |--------------->|   INVITE F4    |
  |                |                |                |--------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |    180   F5    |
  |                |                |    180   F6    |<---------------|
  |                |    180   F7    |<---------------|                |
  |    180   F8    |<---------------|                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |                |


   F1 INVITE S-CSCF -> IBCF-H
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <ibcf-h URI>,<p-cscf-v URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb

   F2 INVITE IBCF-H -> IBCF-V
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <ibcf-v URI>,<p-cscf-v URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb

   F3 INVITE IBCF-V -> P-CSCF
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net SIP/2.0
   Route: <p-cscf-v URI;iotl=homeb-visitedb

   F4 INVITE P-CSCF -> Bob
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net SIP/2.0
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
			</t>
        </section>
		
		
		<section title="Call between Originating Home and Terminating Home Network">
			<t>			
				The S-CSCF of the originating home network adds the 'iotl' value 'homea-homeb'
				in the Request-URI of the INVITE, sent towards the S-CSCF of the terminating
				network to indicate the traffic leg type between the S-CSCFs.
			</t>
			<t>
            <figure anchor="example_4_figure" title="Call between Originating Home and Terminating Home Network">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Home-A Proxy   Home-A Proxy    Home-B Proxy    Home-B Proxy Home-B Proxy
S-CSCF-A  . . . . IBCF-A . . . . .IBCF-B . . . . .I-CSCF-B . . .S-CSCF-B
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   INVITE F1    |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   INVITE F2    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|   INVITE F3    |                |
  |                |                |--------------->|   INVITE F4    |
  |                |                |                |--------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |    180   F5    |
  |                |                |    180   F6    |<---------------|
  |                |    180   F7    |<---------------|                |
  |    180   F8    |<---------------|                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |                |


   F1 INVITE S-CSCF-A -> IBCF-A
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net;iotl=homea-homeb SIP/2.0

   F2 INVITE IBCF-a -> IBCF-B
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net;iotl=homea-homeb SIP/2.0

   F3 INVITE IBCF-B -> I-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net;iotl=homea-homeb SIP/2.0

   F4 INVITE I-CSCF-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:Bob@visitedb.net;iotl=homea-homeb SIP/2.0
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
			</t>
        </section>		
	</section>
<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>The authors wish to thank everyone in the 3GPP community that gave
   comments on the initial version of this document and contributed with
   comments and suggestions during the work.  A special thanks to Paul
   Kyziwat, Dale Worley, and Michael Hammer.  Robert Sparks performed
   the Gen-ART review of the document.</t>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
