<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd"
[]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc number="7451"
     category="info" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="EPP Extension Registry">Extension Registry for the Extensible Provisioning Protocol</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Hollenbeck" fullname="Scott Hollenbeck">
      <organization>Verisign Labs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shollenbeck@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.verisignlabs.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2015"/>


<keyword>domain</keyword>
<keyword>host</keyword>
<keyword>contact</keyword>

     <abstract>
       <t>The Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) includes features to add
       functionality by extending the protocol.
       It does not, however, describe how those extensions are managed. This
       document describes a procedure for the
       registration and management of extensions to EPP, and it specifies a
       format for an IANA registry to record those extensions.</t>
     </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>
     <section title="Introduction">      
       <t>Domain name registries implement a variety of operational and
       business models. The differences in these models
       make it impossible to develop a "one size fits all" provisioning
       protocol; the Extensible Provisioning Protocol <xref
       target="RFC5730"/> was designed to focus on a minimal set
       of common functionality with built-in extension
       capabilities that allow new features to be specified on an "as needed"
       basis. Guidelines for extending EPP are documented
       in RFC 3735 <xref target="RFC3735"/>.</t>

       <t>RFCs 3735 and 5730 do not describe how extension development can be
       managed and coordinated. This has led to a
       situation in which server operators can develop different extensions to
       address similar needs, such as the provisioning 
       of Value Added Tax (VAT) information. Clients then need to support
       multiple extensions that serve similar purposes, and
       interoperability suffers as a result. 
</t>

       <t>An IANA registry can be used to help manage and coordinate the
       development of protocol extensions. This document 
       describes an IANA registry that will be used to coordinate the
       development of EPP extensions.</t> 
     </section>

     <section anchor="spec-proc" title="Extension Specification and Registration Procedure">
       <t>This section describes the format of an IANA registry and the procedures used to populate and manage registry entries.</t>

       <section anchor="specs" title="Extension Specification">        
	 <t>This registry uses the "Specification Required" policy described in RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>. An English
	 language version of the extension specification will be referenced from the registry, though non-English versions of the
	 specification may also be provided. Note that Section 2.1 of RFC 3735 <xref target="RFC3735"/> provides specific
	 guidelines for documenting EPP extensions.</t>

	 <t>Note that the "Specification Required" policy implies review by a
	 "designated expert". Section 3 of RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>
	 describes the role of designated experts and the function they perform.</t>

	 <section anchor="expert" title="Designated Expert Evaluation Criteria">
	   <t>A high-level description of the role of the designated expert is
	   described in Section 3.2 of RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>. Specific
	   guidelines for the appointment of designated experts and the evaluation of EPP extensions are provided here.</t>

	   <t>The IESG should appoint a small pool of individuals (perhaps 3 - 5) to serve as designated experts, as described
	   in Section 3.2 of RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>. The pool should have a single administrative chair who is appointed by the IESG. The
	   designated experts should use the existing eppext mailing list (eppext@ietf.org) for public discussion of
	   registration requests. This implies that the mailing list should remain open after the work of the EPPEXT
	   working group has concluded.</t>

	   <t>Extensions should be evaluated for architectural soundness using the guidelines described in RFC 3735
	   <xref target="RFC3735"/>, including the Security Considerations section of that document. Expert evaluation
	   should explicitly include consideration of the privacy consequences of proposed extensions, and, at a minimum,
	   ensure that any privacy considerations are fully documented in the relevant specification(s).</t>        

	   <t>The results of the evaluation should be shared via email with the registrant and the eppext mailing list.
	   Issues discovered during the evaluation can be corrected by the registrant, and those corrections can be submitted
	   to the designated experts until the designated experts explicitly decide to accept or reject the registration
	   request. The designated experts must make an explicit decision and that decision must be shared via email with
	   the registrant and the eppext mailing list. If the specification for an extension is an IETF Standards Track
	   document, no review is required by the designated expert.</t>

	   <t>Designated experts should be permissive in their evaluation of requests to register extensions that have been
	   implemented and deployed by at least one registry/registrar pair. This implies that it may indeed be possible to
	   register multiple extensions that provide the same functionality. Requests to register extensions that have not
	   been deployed should be evaluated with a goal of reducing functional duplication. A potential registrant who
	   submits a request to register a new, un-deployed extension that includes similar functionality to an existing,
	   registered extension should be made aware of the existing extension. The registrant should be asked to
	   reconsider their request given the existence of a similar extension. Should they decline to do so, perceived
	   similarity should not be a sufficient reason for rejection as long as all other requirements are met.</t>
	 </section>
       </section>

       <section title="Registration Procedure">
	 <t>The registry contains information describing each registered
	 extension. Registry entries are created and managed by
	 sending forms to IANA that describe the extension and the operation
	 to be performed on the registry entry.</t> 

	 <section anchor="reqInfo" title="Required Information">
	   <t>Name of Extension: A case-insensitive, ASCII text string that contains the name of the extension specification.
	   Non-ASCII representations of the extension name can be included in the "Notes" described below.</t>

	   <t>Document Status: The document status ("Informational", "Standards Track", etc.) of the specification document.
	   For documents that are not RFCs, this will always be "Informational".</t>

	   <t>Reference: A publicly available reference to the specification
	   of this extension. This could be an RFC number or some other pointer
	   to the document defining the extension.</t>

	   <t>Registrant Name and Email Address: The name and email address of the person that is responsible for managing
	   the registry entry. If the registration is of an IETF Standards Track document, this can simply be listed as
	   "IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;".</t>

	   <t>TLDs: A text string containing the top-level domain name (or domain names), including the preceding ".", for
	   which the extension has been specified (e.g., ".org"). If there are multiple TLDs, they are given as a list of
	   domain names separated by commas, (e.g. ".com", ".net"). Internationalized Domain Name (IDN) TLDs should be specified
	   in A-label <xref target="RFC5890"/> format. If the extension is not associated with a specific top-level domain,
	   the case-insensitive text string "Any" can be used to indicate that.</t>

	   <t>IPR Disclosure: A pointer to any Intellectual Property Rights
	   (IPR) disclosure document(s) related to this extension,
	   or "None" may be used if there are no such disclosures. This can be an IPR disclosure filed with the IETF in accordance with RFC 3979
	   <xref target="RFC3979"/> as updated by RFC 4879 <xref target="RFC4879"/> if the
	   extension is part of an IETF Contribution, or it can be
	   other IPR disclosure documents identifying the claimed intellectual property rights and terms of use for extensions that
	   are not part of an IETF Contribution.</t>

	   <t>Status: Either "Active" or "Inactive". The "Active" status is used for extensions that are currently implemented and
	   in use. The "Inactive" status is used for extensions that are not implemented or are otherwise not being used.</t>

	   <t>Notes: Either "None" or other text that describes optional notes to be included with the registered extension.
	   If the Status value is "Inactive", text should be included to describe how and when this state was reached.</t>
	 </section>

	 <section anchor="form" title="Registration Form">
	   <t>The required information must be formatted consistently using
	   the following registration form. Form field names and values may
	   appear on the same line.</t>
<figure align="center">
  <artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
 -----BEGIN FORM-----
 Name of Extension:
 <text string> (quotes are optional)

 Document Status: <document status>

 Reference: <RFC number, URL, etc.>

 Registrant Name and Email Address:
 <registrant name>, <email address>

 TLDs: "Any"|<one or more TLD text strings separated by commas>

 IPR Disclosure: "None"|<URL>

 Status: "Active"|"Inactive"

 Notes: "None"|<optional text>
 -----END FORM-----
 ]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t><vspace blankLines='100'/></t>

<t>Example form with RFC specification:</t>

	   <t><figure>
	       <artwork xml:space="preserve">
 -----BEGIN FORM-----
 Name of Extension:
 "An Extension RFC for the Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)"

 Document Status:
 Standards Track

 Reference:
 RFC XXXX

 Registrant Name and Email Address:
 IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

 TLDs: Any

 IPR Disclosure: None

 Status: Active

 Notes: None
 -----END FORM-----
	       </artwork>
	     </figure></t>

	   <t>Example form with non-RFC specification:</t>

	   <t><figure>
	       <artwork xml:space="preserve">
 -----BEGIN FORM-----
 Name of Extension:
 "An Example Extension for the .example Top-Level Domain"

 Document Status:
 Informational

 Reference:
 http://www.example.com/html/example-epp-ext.txt

 Registrant Name and Email Address:
 John Doe, jdoe@example.com

 TLDs: .example

 IPR Disclosure:
 http://www.example.com/ipr/example-epp-ext-ipr.html

 Status: Active

 Notes: None
 -----END FORM-----
	       </artwork>
	     </figure></t>
	 </section>

	 <section title="Registration Processing">
	   <t>Registrants should send each registration form to IANA with a
	   single record for incorporation into the registry. Send the form
	   via email to &lt;iana@iana.org&gt; or complete the online form found on the IANA web site.  The subject line should 
	   indicate whether the enclosed form represents an insertion of a
	   new record (indicated by the word "INSERT" in the subject line) or
	   a replacement of an existing record (indicated by the word "MODIFY"
	   in the subject line). At no time can a record be deleted from the
	   registry. On receipt of the registration request, IANA will
	   initiate review by the designated expert(s), who will evaluate the
	   request using the criteria in <xref target="expert"/> in
	   consultation with the eppext mailing list.</t>
	 </section>

	 <section title="Updating Registry Entries">
	   <t>When submitting changes to existing registry entries, include
	   text in the "Notes" field of the registration form describing the
	   change. Under normal circumstances, registry entries are only to be
	   updated by the registrant. If the registrant becomes unavailable or
	   otherwise unresponsive, the designated expert can submit a
	   registration form to IANA to update the registrant
	   information. Entries can change state from "Active" to "Inactive"
	   and back again as long as state-change requests conform to the
	   processing requirements identified in this document. In addition to
	   entries that become "Inactive" due to a lack of implementation,
	   entries for which a specification becomes consistently unavailable
	   over time should be marked "Inactive" by the designated expert
	   until the specification again becomes reliably available.</t>
	 </section>
       </section>
     </section>

     <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
       <t>IANA has created the "Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning
       Protocol (EPP)" registry to manage EPP
       extensions. This registry has its own heading on IANA's
       protocol listings. The information to be registered and the procedures to be
       followed in populating the registry are described in <xref target="spec-proc"/>.</t>

       <t>Name of registry: Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning
       Protocol (EPP)</t>

       <t><figure>
	 <artwork>
  Section at http://www.iana.org/protocols:
    Registry Title: Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning 
                    Protocol (EPP)
    Registry Name: Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning 
                   Protocol (EPP)
    Registration Procedure: Specification Required
    Reference: this document
	 </artwork>
       </figure></t>

       <t>Required information: See <xref target="reqInfo"/>.</t>

       <t>Review process: "Specification Required" as described in RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>.</t>

       <t>Size, format, and syntax of registry entries: See <xref target="reqInfo"/>.</t>

       <t>Initial assignments and reservations:</t>

       <t><figure>
	 <artwork>
    -----BEGIN FORM-----
    Name of Extension:
    "Domain Registry Grace Period Mapping for the
    Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)"

    Document Status:
    Standards Track

    Reference:
    RFC 3915

    Registrant Name and Email Address:
    IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

    TLDs: Any

    IPR Disclosure: None

    Status: Active

    Notes: None
    -----END FORM-----
	 </artwork>
       </figure></t>

       <t><figure>
	 <artwork>
    -----BEGIN FORM-----
    Name of Extension:
    "E.164 Number Mapping for the
    Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)"

    Document Status:
    Standards Track

    Reference:
    RFC 4114 

    Registrant Name and Email Address:
    IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

    TLDs: Any

    IPR Disclosure: None

    Status: Active

    Notes: None
    -----END FORM-----
	 </artwork>
       </figure></t>

       <t><figure>
	 <artwork>
    -----BEGIN FORM-----
    Name of Extension:
    "ENUM Validation Information Mapping for the
    Extensible Provisioning Protocol"

    Document Status:
    Standards Track

    Reference:
    RFC 5076

    Registrant Name and Email Address:
    IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

    TLDs: Any

    IPR Disclosure: None

    Status: Active

    Notes: None
    -----END FORM-----
	 </artwork>
       </figure></t>

       <t><figure>
	 <artwork>
    -----BEGIN FORM-----
    Name of Extension:
    "Domain Name System (DNS) Security Extensions Mapping for the
    Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)"

    Document Status:
    Standards Track

    Reference:
    RFC 5910 

    Registrant Name and Email Address:
    IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;

    TLDs: Any

    IPR Disclosure: None

    Status: Active

    Notes: None
    -----END FORM-----
	 </artwork>
       </figure></t>

       <t>In addition, the form used to populate and manage the registry will
       be added to the table of Protocol Registration Forms maintained by
       IANA.
</t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">      
       <t>This document introduces no new security considerations to EPP. However, extensions should be evaluated
       according to the Security Considerations of RFC 3735 <xref target="RFC3735"/>.</t>
     </section>

   </middle>

   <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

    <reference  anchor='RFC3979' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3979'>
    <front>
    <title>Intellectual Property Rights in IETF Technology</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner, Ed.'>
    <organization /></author>
    <date year='2005' month='March' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='79'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3979'/>

    <format type='ASCII' octets='41366'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC4879' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4879'>
    <front>
    <title>Clarification of the Third Party Disclosure Procedure in RFC 3979</title>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2007' month='April' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='79'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4879'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='5570'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC5226' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5226'>
    <front>
    <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='H.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='H. Alvestrand'>
    <organization /></author>
    <date year='2008' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='26'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5226'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='66160'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC5730' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5730'>
    <front>
    <title>Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Hollenbeck' fullname='S. Hollenbeck'>
    <organization /></author>
    <date year='2009' month='August' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='STD' value='69'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5730'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='134464'/>
    </reference>

    <reference  anchor='RFC5890' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5890'>
    <front>
    <title>Internationalized Domain Names for Applications (IDNA): Definitions and Document Framework</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Klensin' fullname='J. Klensin'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2010' month='August' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5890'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='54245'/>
    </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

    <reference  anchor='RFC3735' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3735'>
    <front>
    <title>Guidelines for Extending the Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Hollenbeck' fullname='S. Hollenbeck'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2004' month='March' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3735'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='27326'/>
    </reference>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="app_acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The information described in the registry is based on a suggestion
      posted to the provreg mailing list by Jay Daley in August 2013.</t>
    </section>    
  </back>
</rfc>
