<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="7795"
     submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PW Redundancy on S-PE">Pseudowire Redundancy on the
    Switching Provider Edge (S-PE)</title>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Building, No.156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Haibo Wang" initials="H." surname="Wang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Building, No.156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rainsword.wang@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2016"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes Multi-Segment Pseudowire (MS-PW) protection
      scenarios in which pseudowire redundancy is provided on the Switching
      Provider Edge (S-PE) as defined in RFC 5659. Operations of the S-PEs
      that provide PW redundancy are specified in this document. Signaling of
      the Preferential Forwarding status as defined in RFC 6870 and RFC 6478
      is reused. This document does not require any change to the Terminating
      Provider Edges (T-PEs) of MS-PW.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC6718"/> describes the framework and requirements for
      pseudowire (PW) redundancy, and <xref target="RFC6870"/> specifies a PW
      redundancy mechanism for scenarios where a set of redundant PWs are
      configured between Provider Edge (PE) nodes in Single-Segment Pseudowire
      (SS-PW) <xref target="RFC3985"/> applications, or between Terminating
      Provider Edge (T-PE) nodes in Multi-Segment Pseudowire (MS-PW) <xref
      target="RFC5659"/> applications.</t>

      <t>In some MS-PW scenarios, there are benefits of providing PW
      redundancy on Switching Provider Edges (S-PEs), such as reducing the
      burden on the access T-PE nodes and enabling faster protection switching
      compared to the end-to-end MS-PW protection mechanisms.</t>

      <t>This document describes some scenarios in which PW redundancy is
      provided on S-PEs and specifies the operations of the S-PEs. The S-PEs
      connect to the neighboring T-PEs or S-PEs with PW segments. For the S-PE
      that provides PW redundancy for an MS-PW, there is a single PW segment
      on one side, which is called the single-homed side, and there are
      multiple PW segments on the other side, which is called the multi-homed
      side. The scenario in which the S-PE has two multi-homed sides is out of scope.
      Signaling of the Preferential Forwarding status as defined in <xref
      target="RFC6870"/> and <xref target="RFC6478"/> is reused. This document
      does not require any change to the T-PEs of MS-PW.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Typical Scenarios of PW Redundancy on S-PE">
      <t>In some MS-PW deployment scenarios, there are benefits of providing
      PW redundancy on S-PEs. This section describes typical scenarios of PW
      redundancy on S-PE.</t>

      <section title="MS-PW Redundancy on S-PE">
        <t>
          <figure anchor="fig1" title="MS-PW Redundancy on S-PE">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                                     +-----+  AC
 +---+                  +-----+      |     |  |  +---+
 |   |                  |     |------|T-PE2|-----|   |
 |   |  AC +-----+      |  ..PW-Seg2.......|     |   |
 |   |  |  |....PW-Seg1.....  |      +-----+     |   |
 |CE1|-----|T-PE1|------|S-PE1|                  |CE2|
 |   |     |     |      |  .  |      +-----+     |   |
 |   |     +-----+      |  ..PW-Seg3.......|     |   |
 |   |                  |     |------|T-PE3|-----|   |
 +---+                  +-----+      |     |  |  +---+
                                     +-----+  AC
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>As illustrated in <xref target="fig1"/>, Customer Edge (CE) node
        CE1 is connected to T-PE1 while CE2 is dual-homed to T-PE2 and T-PE3.
        T-PE1 is connected to S-PE1 only, and S-PE1 is connected to both T-PE2
        and T-PE3. The MS-PW is switched on S-PE1, and PW segments PW-Seg2 and
        PW-Seg3 provide resiliency on S-PE1 for the failure of T-PE2, T-PE3,
        or the connected Attachment Circuits (ACs). 
PW-Seg2 is selected as the primary PW segment, and PW-Seg3 is the
        secondary PW segment.</t>

        <t>MS-PW redundancy on S-PE is beneficial for the scenario in <xref
        target="fig1"/> since T-PE1 as an access node may not support PW
        redundancy. Besides, with PW redundancy on S-PE, the number of PW
        segments required between T-PE1 and S-PE1 is only half of the number
        of PW segments needed when end-to-end MS-PW redundancy is used. In
        addition, in this scenario, PW redundancy on S-PE could provide faster
        protection switching, compared with end-to-end protection switching of
        MS-PW.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MS-PW Redundancy on S-PE with S-PE Protection ">
        <t>
          <figure anchor="fig2"
                  title="MS-PW Redundancy on S-PE with S-PE Protection">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ +---+     +-----+      +-----+           +-----+
 |   |     |     |      |     |           |     |
 |   |  AC |......PW1-Seg1......PW1-Seg2........|
 |   |  |  |   . |      |  .  |           |     |
 |CE1|-----|T-PE1|------|S-PE1|-----------|T-PE2|  AC
 |   |     |   . |      |  .  | PW1-Seg3  |     |  |  +---+
 |   |     |   . |      |  .........      ......|-----|   |
 |   |     |   . |      |     |    .     .|     |     |   |
 +---+     +---.-+      +-----+     .   . +-----+     |   |
              |.                     . .              |CE2|
              |.                      ..              |   |
              |.        +-----+      .  . +-----+     |   |
              |.        |     |     .    .|     |-----|   |
              |...PW2-Seg1..........      ......|  |  +---+
              |         |  .  | PW2-Seg2  |     |  AC
              ----------|S-PE2|-----------|T-PE3|
                        |  .  |           |     |
                        |  .....PW2-Seg3........|
                        |     |           |     |
                        +-----+           +-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>As illustrated in <xref target="fig2"/>, CE1 is connected to T-PE1
        while CE2 is dual-homed to T-PE2 and T-PE3. T-PE1 is connected to both
        S-PE1 and S-PE2, and both S-PE1 and S-PE2 are connected to both T-PE2
        and T-PE3. There are two MS-PWs that are switched at S-PE1 and S-PE2,
        respectively, to provide S-PE node protection. For PW1, S-PE1 provides
        resiliency using PW1-Seg2 and PW1-Seg3. For PW2, S-PE2 provides
        resiliency using PW2-Seg2 and PW2-Seg3. PW1 is the primary MS-PW, and
        PW1-Seg2 between S-PE1 and T-PE2 is the primary PW segment. PW2 is the
        secondary MS-PW. 
</t>

        <t>MS-PW redundancy on S-PE is beneficial for this scenario because it
        reduces the number of end-to-end MS-PWs required for both T-PE and
        S-PE protection. In addition, PW redundancy on S-PE could provide
        faster protection switching, compared with end-to-end protection
        switching of MS-PW.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="S-PE Operations ">
      <t>For an S-PE that provides PW redundancy for MS-PW, it is important to
      advertise the proper preferential forwarding status to the PW segments
      on both sides and perform protection switching according to the received
      status information. Note that when PW redundancy for MS-PW is provided
      on S-PE, the optional S-PE Bypass mode as defined in <xref
      target="RFC6478"/> MUST NOT be used; otherwise, the S-PE will not
      receive the PW status messages originated by T-PEs. This section
      specifies the operations of S-PEs on which PW redundancy is provisioned.
      This section does not make any change to the T-PEs of MS-PW.</t>

      <t>The S-PEs connect to the neighboring T-PEs or other S-PEs on two
      sides with PW segments. For the S-PE that provides PW redundancy for an
      MS-PW, on one side there is a single PW segment, which is called the
      single-homed side, and on the other side there are multiple PW segments,
      which is called the multi-homed side. The scenario in which the S-PE has
      two multi-homed sides is out of scope.</t>

      <t>The S-PE that provides PW redundancy MUST work in Slave mode for the
      single-homed side, and MUST work in Independent mode for the multi-homed
      side. 
Consequently, the T-PE on the single-homed side MUST work in the Master
      mode, and the T-PEs on the multi-homed side MUST work in the Independent
      mode. The signaling of the Preferential Forwarding bit as defined in
      <xref target="RFC6870"/> and <xref target="RFC6478"/> is reused.</t>

      <t>The S-PE MUST pass the Preferential Forwarding status received from
      the single-homed side unchanged to all the PW segments on the
      multi-homed side. The S-PE MUST advertise the Standby Preferential
      Forwarding status to the single-homed side if it receives Standby status
      from all the PW segments on the multi-homed side, and it MUST advertise
      the Active Preferential Forwarding status to the single-homed side if it
      receives Active status from any of the PW segments on the multi-homed
      side. For the single-homed side, the active PW segment is determined by
      the T-PE on this side, which works in the Master mode. On the
      multi-homed side, since both the S-PE and T-PEs work in the Independent
      mode, the PW segment which has both the local and remote Up/Down status
      as Up and both the local and remote Preferential Forwarding status as
      Active MUST be selected for traffic forwarding. 
      When a switchover happens on the S-PE, if the S-PE supports the SP-PE TLV
      processing as defined in <xref target="RFC6073"/>, it SHOULD advertise
      the updated SP-PE TLVs by sending a Label Mapping message to the
      T-PEs.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Applications of PW Redundancy on S-PE">
      <t/>

      <section title="Applications in Scenario 1">
        <t>For the scenario in <xref target="fig1"/>, assume the AC from CE2
        to T-PE2 is active. In normal operation, S-PE1 would receive the
        Active Preferential Forwarding status bit on the single-homed side
        from T-PE1, then it would advertise the Active Preferential Forwarding
        status bit on both PW-Seg2 and PW-Seg3. T-PE2 and T-PE3 would
        advertise the Active and Standby Preferential Forwarding status bit to
        S-PE1, respectively, reflecting the forwarding state of the two ACs
        connected to CE2. By matching the local and remote Up/Down status and
        Preferential Forwarding status, PW-Seg2 would be used for traffic
        forwarding.</t>

        <t>On failure of the AC between CE2 and T-PE2, the forwarding state of
        AC on T-PE3 is changed to Active. T-PE3 then advertises the Active
        Preferential Forwarding status to S-PE1, and T-PE2 would advertise a
        PW status Notification message to S-PE1, indicating that the AC
        between CE2 and T-PE2 is down. S-PE1 would perform the switchover
        according to the updated local and remote Preferential Forwarding
        status and the status of "Pseudowire forwarding", and select PW-Seg3
        as the new PW segment for traffic forwarding. Since S-PE1 still
        connects to an Active PW segment on the multi-homed side, it will not
        advertise any change of the PW status to T-PE1. If S-PE1 supports the
        SP-PE TLV processing as defined in <xref target="RFC6073"/>, it would
        advertise the updated SP-PE TLVs by sending a Label Mapping message to
        T-PE1.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applications in Scenario 2">
        <t>For the scenario of <xref target="fig2"/>, assume the AC from CE2
        to T-PE2 is active. T-PE1 works in Master mode and it would advertise
        the Active and Standby Preferential Forwarding status bit to S-PE1 and
        S-PE2 respectively according to configuration. According to the
        received Preferential Forwarding status bit, S-PE1 would advertise the
        Active Preferential Forwarding status bit to both T-PE2 and T-PE3, and
        S-PE2 would advertise the Standby Preferential Forwarding status bit
        to both T-PE2 and T-PE3. T-PE2 would advertise the Active Preferential
        Forwarding status bit to both S-PE1 and S-PE2, and T-PE3 would
        advertise the Standby Preferential Forwarding status bit to both S-PE1
        and S-PE2, reflecting the forwarding state of the two ACs connected to
        CE2. By matching the local and remote Up/Down Status and Preferential
        Forwarding status, PW1-Seg2 from S-PE1 to T-PE2 would be used for
        traffic forwarding. Since S-PE1 connects to the Active PW segment on
        the multi-homed side, it would advertise the Active Preferential
        Forwarding status bit to T-PE1, and S-PE2 would advertise the Standby
        Preferential Forwarding status bit to T-PE1 because it does not have
        any Active PW segment on the multi-homed side.</t>

        <t>On failure of the AC between CE2 and T-PE2, the forwarding state of
        AC on T-PE3 is changed to Active. T-PE3 would then advertise the
        Active Preferential Forwarding status bit to both S-PE1 and S-PE2, and
        T-PE2 would advertise a PW status Notification message to both S-PE1
        and S-PE2, indicating that the AC between CE2 and T-PE2 is down. S-PE1
        would perform the switchover according to the updated local and remote
        Preferential Forwarding status and the status of "Pseudowire
        forwarding", and select PW1-Seg3 for traffic forwarding. Since S-PE1
        still has an Active PW segment on the multi-homed side, it would not
        advertise any change of the PW status to T-PE1. If S-PE1 supports the
        SP-PE TLV processing as defined in <xref target="RFC6073"/>, it would
        advertise the updated SP-PE TLVs by sending a Label Mapping message to
        T-PE1.</t>

        <t>If S-PE1 fails, T-PE1 would notice this through some detection
        mechanism and then advertise the Active Preferential Forwarding status
        bit to S-PE2, and PW2-Seg1 would be selected by T-PE1 for traffic
        forwarding. On receipt of the newly changed Preferential Forwarding
        status, S-PE2 would advertise the Active Preferential Forwarding
        status to both T-PE2 and T-PE3. T-PE2 and T-PE3 would also notice the
        failure of S-PE1 by some detection mechanism. Then by matching the
        local and remote Up/Down and Preferential Forwarding status, PW2-Seg2
        would be selected for traffic forwarding.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="VCCV Considerations ">
      <t>For PW Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV) <xref
      target="RFC5085"/>, the Control Channel (CC) type 1 "PW ACH" can be used
      with the S-PE redundancy mechanism. VCCV CC type 2 "Router Alert Label"
      is not supported for MS-PW as specified in <xref target="RFC6073"/>. If
      VCCV CC type 3 "TTL Expiry" is to be used, the PW label TTL MUST be set
      to the appropriate value to reach the target PE. The hop count from one
      T-PE to the target PE can be obtained via SP-PE TLVs, through MS-PW path
      trace, or based on management-plane information.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Since PW redundancy is provided on the S-PE nodes of MS-PWs, it is
      important that the security mechanisms as defined in <xref
      target="RFC4447"/>, <xref target="RFC6073"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC6478"/> be implemented to ensure that the S-PE nodes and the
      messages sent and received by the S-PE nodes are not compromised.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4447'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6073'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6478'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6870'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3985'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5659'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6718'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5085'?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="no" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Mach Chen, Lizhong Jin, Mustapha
      Aissaoui, Luca Martini, Matthew Bocci, and Stewart Bryant for their
      valuable comments and discussions.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
