<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc number="7894" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EST Alternative Challenge Password Attributes">Alternative&nbsp;Challenge&nbsp;Password Attributes for&nbsp;Enrollment&nbsp;over&nbsp;Secure&nbsp;Transport&nbsp;</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Pritikin" fullname="Max Pritikin">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>510 McCarthy Drive</street>
          <city>Milpitas</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95035</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pritikin@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Wallace" fullname="Carl Wallace">
      <organization>Red Hound Software, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>carl@redhoundsoftware.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2016"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <keyword>Enrollment over Secure Transport</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a set of new Certificate Signing Request
attributes for use with the Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST)
protocol.  These attributes provide disambiguation of the existing
overloaded uses for the challengePassword
attribute defined in "PKCS #9: Selected
Object Classes and Attribute Types Version 2.0" (RFC 2985). Uses include the
original certificate revocation password, common authentication password uses,
and EST-defined linking of transport security identity. 
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">

      <t>"PKCS #9: Selected Object Classes and Attribute Types
      Version 2.0" <xref target="RFC2985"/> defined a
      challengePassword attribute that has been overloaded by modern protocol
      usage with the appropriate interpretation being provided by context
      rather than OID definition. PKCS #9 defines the challengePassword
      attribute as "a password by which an entity may request certificate
      revocation". The parsing and embedding of this attribute within
      Certificate Signing Requests is well supported by common PKI toolsets,
      but many workflows leverage this supported field as a one-time password
      for authentication. For example, this is codified in many Simple
      Certificate Enrollment Protocol (SCEP) implementations as indicated by
      <xref target="SCEP"/>. Continuing this trend, Enrollment over Secure
      Transport (EST) <xref target="RFC7030"/> defines an additional semantic
      for the challengePassword attribute in Section 3.5, in order to provide
      a linking of the Certificate Signing Request (CSR) to the secure
      transport. </t>
      <t>Where the context of the protocol operation fully defined the proper
      semantic, and when only one use was required at a time, the overloading
      of this field did not cause difficulties. Implementation experience with
      EST has shown this to be a limitation though. There are plausible use
      cases where it is valuable to use either of the existing methods
      separately or in concert. For example, an EST server might require the
      client to authenticate itself using the existing client X.509
      certificate as well as the user's username and password, and to include a one-time
      password within the CSR, all while maintaining identity linking to bind
      the CSR to the secure transport. The overloading of a single attribute
      type should not be the limiting factor for administrators attempting to
      meet their security requirements.</t>

      <t>This document defines the otpChallenge attribute for use when a
      one-time password (OTP) value within the CSR is a requirement.  The
      revocationChallenge attribute is defined to allow disambiguated usage of
      the original challenge password attribute semantics for certificate
      revocation. The estIdentityLinking attribute is defined to reference
      existing EST challenge password semantics with no potential for
      confusion with legacy challenge password practices.
</t>  
<t>The attributes defined in this specification supplement existing EST mechanisms and are not intended to displace current usage of any existing EST authentication mechanisms. Conveying the authentication value itself as an attribute may be preferable to using an HTTP or Transport Layer Security (TLS) password or other TLS authentication mechanism in environments where the certificate request processing component is removed from the HTTP/TLS termination point, for example, when a web application firewall is used.
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" anchor="terms">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
        this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Alternative Challenge Password Attributes" anchor="attributes">
      <t>The following sections describe three alternative challenge password attributes for use with EST <xref target="RFC7030"/>. Appendix A provides an ASN.1 module containing the new definitions.</t>
      <t>Each attribute described below is defined as a DirectoryString with a
      maximum length of 255, which features several possible encoding options. Attribute values generated in accordance this document SHOULD use the PrintableString encoding whenever possible. If internationalization issues make this impossible, the UTF8String alternative SHOULD be used.  Attribute processing systems MUST be able to recognize and process the PrintableString and UTF8String string types in DirectoryString values. Support for other string types is OPTIONAL.</t>
    <section title="OTP Challenge Attribute" anchor="sfattribute">
    <t>The otpChallenge attribute is defined as a DirectoryString with a
    maximum length of 255. This is consistent with the challengePassword
    attribute as originally defined in PKCS #9 <xref target="RFC2985"/>. The
    otpChallenge attribute is identified by the id-aa-otpChallenge object
    identifier.  This facilitates reuse of the existing challengePassword code by associating the new object identifiers with the existing parsing and generation code.  This attribute provides a means of conveying a one-time password value as part of a CSR request. Generation, verification, storage, etc., of the value is not addressed by this specification. <xref target="RFC4226"/> and <xref target="RFC6238"/> define one-time password mechanisms that MAY be used with this attribute.
</t>  
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   ub-aa-otpChallenge INTEGER ::= 255
   id-aa-otpChallenge OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
       id-smime 56
   }   
   otpChallenge ATTRIBUTE ::= {
       WITH SYNTAX DirectoryString {ub-aa-otpChallenge}
       EQUALITY MATCHING RULE caseExactMatch
       SINGLE VALUE TRUE
       ID id-aa-otpChallenge
   }   
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>    
    </section>
    <section title="Revocation Challenge Attribute" anchor="p9attribute">
    <t>The original PKCS #9 challengePassword field has been overloaded, and
    the common use is unclear. The revocationChallenge attribute defined here
    provides an unambiguous method of indicating the original PKCS #9 intent for this attribute type. The revocationChallenge attribute is identified by the id-aa-revocationChallenge object identifier.  <xref target="RFC2985"/> discusses the original semantics for the PKCS #9 challenge password attribute.</t>  
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   ub-aa-revocationChallenge INTEGER ::= 255
   id-aa-revocationChallenge OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
       id-smime 57
   }   
   revocationChallenge ATTRIBUTE ::= {
       WITH SYNTAX DirectoryString {ub-aa-revocationChallenge}
       EQUALITY MATCHING RULE caseExactMatch
       SINGLE VALUE TRUE
       ID id-aa-revocationChallenge
   }   
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>    
    </section>
    <section title="EST Identity Linking Attribute" anchor="estattribute">
    <t>EST defines a mechanism for associating identity information from an
    authenticated TLS session with proof-of-possession information in a
    certificate request. The mechanism was labeled using the
    pkcs-9-at-challengePassword identifier from <xref target="RFC2985"/>. To
    avoid any confusion with the semantics described in <xref
    target="RFC2985"/> or any other specifications that similarly defined use
    of the PKCS #9 challenge password attribute for their own purposes, a new
    object identifier is defined here and associated with the semantics
    described in Section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC7030"/>.</t>  

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   ub-aa-est-identity-linking INTEGER ::= 255
   id-aa-estIdentityLinking OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
       id-smime 58
   }   
   estIdentityLinking ATTRIBUTE ::= {
       WITH SYNTAX DirectoryString {ub-aa-est-identity-linking}
       EQUALITY MATCHING RULE caseExactMatch
       SINGLE VALUE TRUE
       ID id-aa-estIdentityLinking
   }   
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>    
    </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Indicating Support for the Alternative Challenge Attributes" anchor="support">


    <t>The EST server MUST indicate these attributes, as the particular use
    case requires, in every CSR Attributes Response. An EST server MAY send
    both the estIdentityLinking attribute and the 
    challengePassword attribute <xref target="RFC7030"/> in a CSR Attributes
    Response to ensure support for
    legacy clients.</t>

    <t>The client MUST include every indicated attribute for which it has
    values in the subsequent CSR. If a client sees an estIdentityLinking
    attribute in a
    CSR Attributes Response, it SHOULD prefer that and not include a
    challengePassword attribute <xref target="RFC7030"/> in the
    resulting CSR. EST clients that include an unsolicited
    estIdentityLinking attribute MAY also include the 
    challengePassword attribute <xref target="RFC7030"/> to ensure support for
    legacy servers.</t> 
    

<t>EST servers MUST evaluate each challenge attribute independently.  All
challenge attributes included by an EST client MUST be successfully processed
by an EST server for a request to be considered valid. 
The EST server MAY
ignore challenge attributes according to local policy, for example, if the EST
client is an authenticated Registration Authority, the EST server may ignore the
estIdentityLinking attribute within a CSR (see Section 3.7 of <xref
target="RFC7030"/>). The EST server MAY refuse enrollment requests that are
not encoded according to the policy of the Certification Authority (CA).</t>
    
    
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
        <t>In addition to the security considerations expressed in the EST
	specification <xref target="RFC7030"/>, additional security
	considerations may be associated with the mechanism used to generate
	and verify the otpChallenge value. Where a one-time password is used,
	the security considerations expressed in "HOTP: An HMAC-Based One-Time
	Password Algorithm" <xref target="RFC4226"/> or "TOTP: Time-Based
	One-Time Password Algorithm" <xref target="RFC6238"/> 
	may be relevant. Similarly, the security considerations from <xref
	target="RFC2985"/> that apply to the challenge attribute are relevant
	as well.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
    <t><xref target="attributes"/> defines three attributes that have been
    assigned object identifiers in the "SMI Security for S/MIME
   Attributes (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.2)"
   registry <xref target="RFC7107"/>:</t>

    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
     Value     Description                        Reference
     --------  ---------------------------------  ----------
     56        id-aa-otpChallenge                 RFC 7894
     57        id-aa-revocationChallenge          RFC 7894
     58        id-aa-estIdentityLinking           RFC 7894
     ]]></artwork>
    </figure>    
    <t><xref target="asn1"/> contains an ASN.1 module. A module identifier has
    been
   assigned in the "SMI Security for PKIX Module Identifier"
   registry <xref target="RFC7299"/>.</t>
    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
     Value     Description                        Reference
     --------  ---------------------------------  ----------
     87        id-mod-EST-Alt-Challenge           RFC 7894
     ]]></artwork>
    </figure>    
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2985.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5272.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5912.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7030.xml"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4226.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6238.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7107.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7299.xml"?>

<!-- draft-gutmann-scep-02 IESG State: I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='SCEP'>
<front>
<title>Simple Certificate Enrolment Protocol</title>

<author initials='P' surname='Gutmann' fullname='Peter Gutmann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Pritikin' fullname='Max Pritikin'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='15' year='2016' />

</front>


<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-gutmann-scep-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-gutmann-scep-02.txt' />
</reference>
    </references>
    <section title="ASN.1 Module" anchor="asn1">
      <t>The following ASN.1 module includes the definitions to support usage
      of the attributes defined in this specification. Modules from <xref
      target="RFC5912"/> are imported (the original Standards Track source for
      the imported structures is <xref target="RFC5280"/> and <xref
      target="RFC5272"/>).</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Mod-EST-Alt-Challenge { 
   iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5)
      mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0) 87 
}

DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::=
BEGIN
IMPORTS

DirectoryString{}
FROM PKIX1Explicit-2009 {
   iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5)
   mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0) id-mod-pkix1-explicit-02(51) 
}
  
ATTRIBUTE
FROM PKIX-CommonTypes-2009 {
   iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5)
   mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0) id-mod-pkixCommon-02(57)
};   

ub-aa-otpChallenge INTEGER ::= 255
id-aa-otpChallenge OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
   iso(1) member-body(2) us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs9(9) 
   smime(16) aa(2) 56
}   
otpChallenge ATTRIBUTE ::= {
   TYPE DirectoryString {ub-aa-otpChallenge}
   COUNTS MIN 1 MAX 1
   IDENTIFIED BY id-aa-otpChallenge
}   
ub-aa-revocationChallenge INTEGER ::= 255
id-aa-revocationChallenge OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
   iso(1) member-body(2) us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs9(9) 
   smime(16) aa(2) 57
}   
revocationChallenge ATTRIBUTE ::= {
   TYPE DirectoryString {ub-aa-revocationChallenge}
   COUNTS MIN 1 MAX 1
   IDENTIFIED BY id-aa-revocationChallenge
}  
ub-aa-est-identity-linking INTEGER ::= 255
id-aa-estIdentityLinking OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { 
   iso(1) member-body(2) us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs9(9) 
   smime(16) aa(2) 58
}   
estIdentityLinking ATTRIBUTE ::= {
   TYPE DirectoryString {ub-aa-est-identity-linking}
   COUNTS MIN 1 MAX 1
   IDENTIFIED BY id-aa-estIdentityLinking
}    
END   
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>Thanks to Jim Schaad, Dan Harkins, Phil Scheffler, Geoff Beier, Mike Jenkins, and Deb Cooley for their feedback.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
