<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!--xml2rfc v2 used-->

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc number="7018" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" consensus="yes"
category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Auto-Discovery VPN">Auto-Discovery VPN Problem Statement and Requirements</title>
      <author initials="V." surname="Manral" fullname="Vishwas Manral">
      <organization abbrev="HP">Hewlett-Packard Co.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3000 Hanover St.</street>
          <city>Palo Alto</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94304</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>vishwas.manral@hp.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author initials="S." surname="Hanna" fullname="Steve Hanna">
      <organization abbrev="Juniper">Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shanna@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="September" year="2013"/>

    <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup>IPsecME Working Group</workgroup>

<keyword>IPsec</keyword>
<keyword>Overlay</keyword>
<keyword>SDN</keyword>
<keyword>IKE</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>  This document describes the problem of enabling a large number
 of systems to communicate directly using IPsec to protect the traffic 
 between them. It then expands on the requirements for such a solution. </t>
 
 <t> Manual configuration of all possible tunnels is too
 cumbersome in many such cases. In other cases, the IP addresses of endpoints
 change, or the endpoints may be behind NAT gateways, making 
 static configuration impossible. The Auto-Discovery VPN solution will
 address these requirements. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <!-- ================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t> IPsec <xref target="RFC4301"/> is used in several different cases, including tunnel&nbhy;mode
        site-to-site VPNs and remote access VPNs. Both tunneling modes for IPsec gateways and 
        host-to-host transport mode are supported in this document. </t>
<t> The subject of this document is the problem presented by large-scale 
        deployments of IPsec and the requirements on a solution to address the problem. 
        These may be a large collection of
 VPN gateways connecting various sites, a large number of remote endpoints
        connecting to a number of gateways or to each other, or a mix of the two.
 The gateways and endpoints may belong to a single administrative domain
 or several domains with a trust relationship.</t>
      <t> Section 4.4 of RFC 4301 describes the major IPsec databases needed for IPsec processing.
        It requires extensive configuration for each tunnel, so manually
 configuring a system of many gateways and endpoints becomes infeasible
 and inflexible.</t>
      <t>The difficulty is that a lot of configuration mentioned in RFC 4301
is required to set up a Security Association.
        The Internet Key Exchange Protocol (IKE) implementations need to know the identity and credentials of all possible peer 
        systems, as well as the addresses of hosts and/or networks behind them. A simplified 
        mechanism for dynamically establishing point-to-point tunnels is
 needed. <xref target="usecases"/> contains 
        several use cases that motivate this effort.</t>  
      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
  <t><list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Auto-Discovery Virtual Private Network (ADVPN) -">A VPN solution that enables a
        large number of systems to communicate directly, with minimal configuration and operator
        intervention, using IPsec to protect communication between them. </t>
   <t hangText="Endpoint -">A device that implements IPsec for its own traffic
      but does not act as a gateway.</t>
   <t hangText="Gateway -">A network device that implements IPsec to protect
      traffic flowing through the device.</t>
   <t hangText="Point-to-Point -">Communication between two parties without
     active participation (e.g., encryption or decryption) by
     any other parties.</t>
   <t hangText="Hub -">The central point in a star topology/dynamic full-mesh topology, or one of the
      central points in the full-mesh style VPN, i.e., a gateway to which
multiple other hubs or spokes connect. The hubs usually forward traffic coming
from encrypted links to other encrypted links, i.e., there are no devices
connected to them in the clear.</t>
   <t hangText="Spoke -">The endpoint in a star topology/dynamic full-mesh topology or gateway
      that forwards traffic from multiple cleartext devices to other hubs or spokes, and some of those
      other devices are connected to it in the clear (i.e., it encrypts data
coming from cleartext devices and forwards it to the ADVPN).</t>
   <t hangText="ADVPN Peer -">Any member of an ADVPN, including gateways,
endpoints, hubs, or spokes. </t>
   <t hangText="Star Topology -">Topology in which there is direct connectivity only
between the hub and spoke, and where communication between the 2 spokes happens
through the hub. </t>
   <t hangText="Allied and Federated Environments -">Environments where we have
multiple different organizations that have close associations and need to
connect to each other. </t>
   <t hangText="Full-Mesh Topology -">Topology in which there is direct connectivity between 
      every spoke to every other spoke, without the traffic between the spokes having to
      be redirected through an intermediate hub device. </t>
   <t hangText="Dynamic Full-Mesh Topology -">Topology in which direct
connections exist in a hub-and-spoke manner but dynamic connections are
created/removed between the spokes on an as-needed basis.</t>
   <t hangText="Security Association (SA) -">Defined in <xref target="RFC4301"/>.</t>
  </list></t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="mustshouldmay" title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
          "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
          in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
    <section anchor="usecases" title="Use Cases">
      <t> This section presents the key use cases for large-scale
  point&nbhy;to&nbhy;point VPNs.</t>
      <t> In all of these use cases, the participants (endpoints and
   gateways) may be from a single organization (administrative domain) or from multiple
   organizations with an established trust relationship. When
   multiple organizations are involved, products from multiple
   vendors are employed, so open standards are needed to provide
   interoperability. Establishing communications between participants
   with no established trust relationship is out of scope for
   this effort. </t>

      <section anchor="e2e_use_case" title="Use Case 1: Endpoint-to-Endpoint VPN">
        <t> Two endpoints wish to communicate securely via a point-to-point SA.</t>
   <t> The need for secure endpoint-to-endpoint communications
   is often driven by a need to employ high-bandwidth, low-latency 
   local connectivity instead of using slow, expensive
   links to remote gateways. For example, two users in close
   proximity may wish to place a direct, secure video or voice
   call without needing to send the call through remote gateways,
   as the remote gateways would add latency to the call, consume precious
   remote bandwidth, and increase overall costs. Such a use case
   also enables connectivity when both  users are behind NAT
   gateways. Such a use case ought to allow for seamless connectivity
   even as endpoints roam and even if they are moving out from
   behind a NAT gateway, from behind one NAT gateway to behind another,
   or from a standalone position to behind a NAT gateway. </t>
   <t> In a star topology, when two endpoints communicate,
   they need a mechanism for authentication such that they do not 
   expose themselves to impersonation by the other spoke endpoint. </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="g2g_use_case" title="Use Case 2: Gateway-to-Gateway VPN">
        <t> A typical Enterprise traffic model follows a star topology, with the gateways
         connecting to each other using IPsec tunnels. </t>
        <t> However, for voice and other rich media traffic that require a 
        lot of bandwidth or is performance sensitive, the traffic tromboning (taking a suboptimal path)
        to the hub can create traffic bottlenecks
 on the hub and can lead to an increase in cost. A fully 
        meshed solution would make best use of the available network capacity and 
        performance, but the deployment of a fully meshed solution involves considerable
        configuration, especially when a large number of nodes are involved.
It is for this purpose that
         spoke-to-spoke tunnels are dynamically created and torn down. For the reasons
        of cost and manual error reduction, it is desired that there be minimal configuration on
        each gateway. </t>
        <t> The solution ought to work in cases where the endpoints are in different 
        administrative domains that have an existing trust relationship
        (for example, two organizations that are collaborating on a project may wish to join
         their networks while retaining independent control over
configuration).
  It is highly desirable that the
         solution works for the star, full-mesh, and dynamic full-mesh topologies. </t>
        <t> The solution ought to also address the case where gateways use dynamic IP addresses. </t>
       <t>      Additionally, the routing implications of gateway-to-gateway communication need to 
       be addressed.  In the simple case, selectors provide sufficient information for a gateway
       to forward traffic appropriately.  In other cases, additional 
tunneling (e.g., Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE)) and
       routing (e.g., Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)) protocols are run over IPsec tunnels, and the configuration impact
       on those protocols needs to be considered.  There is also the case where Layer 3 Virtual Private Networks (L3VPNs) operate
       over IPsec tunnels.  </t>
         <t> When two gateways communicate, they need to use a mechanism for authentication
          such that they do not expose themselves to the risk of impersonation by the other entities.  </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="e2g_use_case" title="Use Case 3: Endpoint-to-Gateway VPN">
        <t> A mobile endpoint ought to be able to use the most efficient gateway as it roams in 
        the Internet. </t>
        <t>A mobile user roaming on the Internet may connect to a gateway
that, because of roaming, is no longer the most efficient
 gateway to use (reasons could
         be cost, efficiency, latency, or some other factor). The mobile user
 ought to be able
         to discover and then connect to the current, most efficient gateway in a seamless way 
         without having to bring down the connection. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================= -->
    <section anchor="solutions" title="Inadequacy of Existing Solutions">
      <t> Several solutions exist for the problems described above.
        However, none of these solutions is adequate, as described here.</t>
      <section anchor="exhaustive" title="Exhaustive Configuration">
        <t> One simple solution is to configure all gateways and
     endpoints in advance with all the information needed to
     determine which gateway or endpoint is optimal and to
     establish an SA with that gateway or endpoint. However,
     this solution does not scale in a large network with
     hundreds of thousands of gateways and endpoints, especially
     when multiple administrative domains are involved and things are
     rapidly changing (e.g., mobile endpoints). Such a solution is also
     limited by the smallest endpoint/gateway, as the same exhaustive
     configuration
 is to be applied on all endpoints/gateways. A more
    dynamic, secure, and scalable system for establishing
 SAs between
    gateways is needed. </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="star" title="Star Topology">
      <t> The most common way to address a part of this problem today
        is to use what has been termed a "star topology".
 In this case, one or a few 
gateways
         are defined as
 "hub gateways", while the rest of the systems
 (whether endpoints or
         gateways) are defined as "spokes". The spokes
 never connect to other spokes. They
         only open tunnels with the hub 
gateways. 
Also, for a large number of gateways in one 
         administrative domain, one gateway may be defined 
as the hub, and the rest of the 
         gateways and remote access clients connect only to that
 gateway.</t>
      <t> This solution, however, is complicated by the case where the spokes use dynamic IP 
      addresses and DNS with dynamic updates needs to be used. It is also 
       desired that there is minimal to no configuration on the hub as the number
       of spokes increases and new spokes are added and deleted randomly.</t>
      <t> Another problem with the star topology is that it creates a high load
on the hub gateways, as well as on the connection between the spokes and the
hub. This load impacts both processing power and network bandwidth. A single
packet in the hub-and-spoke scenario can be encrypted and decrypted multiple
        times. It would be much preferable if these gateways and clients could initiate tunnels
        between them, bypassing the hub gateways. Additionally, the path
bandwidth to these hub gateways may be lower than that of the path between the
spokes. For example, two remote access users may be in the same building
with high-speed WiFi (for example, at an IETF meeting). Channeling their
conversation through the hub gateways of their respective employers seems
extremely wasteful, given that a more optimal direct path exists.</t>

      <t> The challenge is to build large-scale IPsec-protected networks that 
        can dynamically change with minimal administrative overhead.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="proprietary" title="Proprietary Approaches">
        <t> Several vendors offer proprietary solutions to these problems.
        However, these solutions offer no interoperability between
        equipment from one vendor and another. This means that they
        are generally restricted to use within one organization, and it is harder
        to move away from such solutions, as the features are not standardized.
        Besides, multiple organizations cannot be expected to all choose the
        same equipment vendor. </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="requirements" title="Requirements">
      <t> This section defines the requirements on which the solution will be based. </t>

  <section anchor="gateway" title="Gateway and Endpoint Requirements">
  <t><list style="numbers">
   <t>For any network topology (star, full mesh, and dynamic full mesh),
   when a new gateway or endpoint is added, removed, or
   changed, configuration changes are minimized as follows. Adding or removing a spoke in the topology MUST NOT require 
    configuration changes to hubs other than where the spoke was
connected and SHOULD NOT require configuration changes to the hub to which the
spoke was connected. The changes also
    MUST NOT require configuration changes in other spokes.

   <vspace blankLines="1"/>Specifically, when evaluating potential proposals,
 we will compare them by looking at how many endpoints or gateways must
 be reconfigured when a new gateway or endpoint is added, removed, or
 changed and how substantial this reconfiguration is, in addition to the amount
 of static configuration required.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/> This requirement is driven by use cases 1 and 2 and
   by the scaling limitations pointed out in <xref target="exhaustive" />. </t>

    <t>ADVPN Peers MUST allow IPsec tunnels to be set up with other members
    of the ADVPN without any configuration changes, even when peer addresses
    get updated
    every time the device comes up. This implies that Security Policy Database
    (SPD) entries or
    other configuration based on a peer IP address will need to be
    automatically updated, avoided, or handled in some manner to avoid
    a need to manually update policy whenever an address changes. </t>

    <t>In many cases, additional tunneling protocols (e.g., GRE) or routing protocols 
    (e.g., OSPF) are run over the IPsec tunnels. Gateways MUST allow for the operation of
    tunneling and routing protocols operating over spoke-to-spoke IPsec tunnels with
    minimal or no configuration impact. The ADVPN solution SHOULD NOT increase the 
    amount of information required to configure protocols running over IPsec tunnels.  </t>

    <t>In the full-mesh and dynamic full-mesh topologies, spokes MUST
     allow for direct communication
 with other spoke gateways and endpoints. In the star topology
     mode, direct communication between spokes MUST be disallowed.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use cases 1 and 2
    and by the
    limitations of a star topology as pointed out in <xref target="star"/>.
    </t>

    <t>ADVPN Peers MUST NOT have a way to get the long-term
    authentication credentials for any other ADVPN Peers. The
    compromise of an endpoint MUST NOT affect the security of
    communications between other ADVPN Peers. The compromise of a
    gateway SHOULD NOT affect the security of the communications
    between ADVPN Peers not associated with that gateway.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use case 1.
    ADVPN Peers
    (especially spokes) become compromised fairly often. The compromise of one
    ADVPN Peer SHOULD NOT affect the security of other unrelated ADVPN
    Peers. </t>

    <t>Gateways SHOULD allow for seamless handoff of sessions in cases where
    endpoints are roaming, even if they cross policy boundaries. This would
    mean the
    data traffic is minimally affected even as the handoff happens. External
    factors like firewalls and NAT boxes that will be part of the overall
    solution when ADVPN is deployed will not be considered part of this
    solution.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>Such endpoint roaming may affect not only the
    endpoint-to-endpoint SA but also the relationship
    between the endpoints and gateways (such as when
    an endpoint roams to a new network that is handled
    by a different gateway).
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use case 1. Today's
    endpoints are mobile and transition often between different networks
    (from 4G to WiFi and among various WiFi networks). </t>

    <t>Gateways SHOULD allow for easy handoff of a session to another
    gateway, to optimize latency, bandwidth, load balancing, availability,
    or other factors, based on policy.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This ability to migrate traffic from one gateway
    to another applies regardless of whether the gateways
    in question are hubs or spokes. It even applies in
    the case where a gateway (hub or spoke) moves in the
    network, as may happen with a vehicle-based network.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use case 3. </t>

    <t>Gateways and endpoints MUST have the capability to participate
     in an ADVPN even when they are located behind NAT boxes. However,
     in some cases they may be deployed in such a way that they will not be
     fully reachable behind a NAT box.  It is especially difficult to handle
     cases where the hub is behind a NAT box.  When the two endpoints are both
     behind separate NATs, communication between these spokes SHOULD 
     be supported using workarounds such as port forwarding by the NAT or 
     detecting when two spokes are behind uncooperative NATs, and using a
     hub in that case.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use cases 1 and
    2. Endpoints are often behind NATs, and gateways sometimes are. IPsec
    SHOULD continue to work seamlessly regardless, using ADVPN techniques
    whenever possible and providing graceful fallback to hub-and-spoke
    techniques as needed. </t>

    <t>Changes such as establishing a new IPsec SA SHOULD be
    reportable and manageable. However, creating a MIB or other
    management technique is not within scope for this effort.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by manageability
    concerns for all the use cases, especially use case 2. As IPsec networks
    become more dynamic, management tools become more essential. </t>

    <t>To support allied and federated environments, endpoints
    and gateways from different organizations SHOULD be able to
    connect to each other.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>

    <t>The administrator of the ADVPN SHOULD allow for the configuration of
    a star, full-mesh, or partial full-mesh topology, based on which tunnels
    are allowed to be set up.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>

    <t>The ADVPN solution SHOULD be able to scale for multicast traffic.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by use case 2,
    where the amount of rich media multicast traffic is increasing. </t>

    <t>The ADVPN solution SHOULD allow for easy monitoring, logging, and
    reporting of the dynamic changes to help with troubleshooting such
    environments.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>

    <t>There is also the case where L3VPNs operate over IPsec tunnels, for 
    example, Provider-Edge-based VPNs. An ADVPN MUST support L3VPNs
    as applications protected by the IPsec tunnels.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>

    <t>The ADVPN solution SHOULD allow the enforcement of per-peer QoS in both
    the star and full-mesh topologies.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>

    <t>The ADVPN solution SHOULD take care of not letting the hub be a single
    point of failure.

    <vspace blankLines="1"/>This requirement is driven by demand for all the
    use cases in federated and allied environments. </t>
  </list></t>
  </section>
 </section>

        <!-- ============================================================== -->
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This is a problem statement and requirements document for the ADVPN solution and in itself does not
       introduce any new security concerns. The solution to the problems presented in this document may involve 
       dynamic updates to 
databases defined by RFC 4301, such as the Security Policy Database (SPD) or the Peer
        Authorization Database (PAD).</t>
      <t> RFC 4301 is silent about the way these databases are populated, and it is implied that
        these databases are static and preconfigured by a human. Allowing dynamic updates to these
        databases must be thought out carefully because it allows the protocol to alter the
        security policy that the IPsec endpoints implement.</t>
      <t> One obvious attack to watch out for is stealing traffic to a particular site. The IP
        address for www.example.com is 192.0.2.10. If we add an entry to an IPsec endpoint's SPD
        that says that traffic to 192.0.2.10 is protected through peer Gw-Mallory, then this 
        allows Gw&nbhy;Mallory to either pretend to be www.example.com or proxy and read all traffic
        to that site. Updates to this database require a clear trust model.</t>
        <t> Hubs can be a single point of failure that can cause loss of
connectivity of the entire system; this can be a big security issue.
        Any ADVPN solution design should take care of these concerns.
 </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t> Many people have contributed to the development of this problem
 statement. While we cannot thank all contributors, some have played an
 especially prominent role. Yoav Nir, Yaron Sheffer, Jorge Coronel Mendoza, 
 Chris Ulliott, and John Veizades wrote the document upon which this
 specification was based. Geoffrey Huang, Toby Mao, Suresh Melam,
 Praveen Sathyanarayan, Andreas Steffen, Brian Weis, Lou Berger, and
 Tero Kivinen provided essential input.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
  </middle>
  <!-- =================================================================== -->
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 
 
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4301" ?>

    </references>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
  </back>
</rfc>
