<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--used v2-->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc category="info"
     number="7063" consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF"
     ipr="trust200902">




  <front>
    <title abbrev="Survey Report on PIM-SM">Survey Report on Protocol
Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM)
    Implementations and Deployments</title>

    <author fullname="Lianshu Zheng" initials="L." surname="Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vero.zheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zhaohui Zhang" initials="Z." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zzhang@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rishabh Parekh" initials="R." surname="Parekh">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>riparekh@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2013"/>



    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides supporting documentation to advance the IETF stream's
   Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) protocol from
   Proposed Standard to Internet Standard.</t>


    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Motivation">
      <section title="Overview of PIM-SM">
        <t>Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) was first
        published as <xref target="RFC2117" /> in 1997.  This version was then obsoleted by
        <xref target="RFC2362" /> in 1998. The protocol was classified as Experimental in both
        documents. The protocol specification was then
        rewritten in whole and advanced to Proposed Standard as <xref target="RFC4601" /> in
        2006. Considering its multiple independent implementations developed
        and sufficient successful operational experience gained, the PIM WG
        decided to advance the PIM-SM protocol to Internet Standard.
        The conducted survey and this document are part of the work. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Requirements of RFCs 2026 and 6410">
   <t>
   <xref target="RFC2026" /> defines the stages in the standardization process, the
   requirements for moving a document between stages, and the types of
   documents used during this process.  Section 4.1.2 of <xref target="RFC2026" />
   states that:

<list>
<t>The requirement for at least two independent and
   interoperable implementations applies to all of the options and
   features of the specification.  In cases in which one or more options
   or features have not been demonstrated in at least two interoperable
   implementations, the specification may advance to the Draft Standard
   level only if those options or features are removed.</t>
</list>
   </t>
   <t>
   <xref target="RFC6410" /> updates the IETF
   Standards Process defined in <xref target="RFC2026" />.  Primarily, it reduces the
   Standards Process from three Standards Track maturity levels to two.
   The second maturity level is a combination of Draft Standard and Standard
   as specified in <xref target="RFC2026" />.  Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC6410" /> states that:


<list>
<t>(1)
   There are at least two independent interoperating implementations
   with widespread deployment and successful operational experience.</t><t>(2)...</t><t>(3)
   There are no unused features in the specification that greatly
   increase implementation complexity.</t> </list>
   </t>
   <t>
   Optional features that do not meet the aforesaid criteria have been
   identified by the PIM Working Group and will be removed.  This document provides supporting documentation to advance the IETF
 stream's Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) protocol
 from Proposed Standard to Internet Standard.


   </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Survey on Implementations and Deployments">
      <section title="Methodology">
   <t>
   A questionnaire was issued by the PIM WG co-chairs and announced
   widely to the vendors and operational community to obtain information
   on PIM-SM implementations and deployments.  The survey concluded on
   22 Oct 2012.  The responses remain confidential and only combined
   results are published here, while responders chose whether to keep their
   affiliations confidential. The raw questionnaire
   is shown in <xref target="questionnaire"/>, and a compilation of the
   responses is included in the following section.
   </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Operator Responses">
   <t>
   Nine operators responded to the survey.  They are SWITCH, National
   Research Council Canada, South Dakota School of Mines and Technology,
   Motorola Solutions, and five anonymous operators.
   </t>
        <section title="Description of PIM-SM Deployments">
   <t>
   Since 1998, PIM-SM has been deployed for a wide
   variety of applications: Campus, Enterprise, Research and WAN
   networks, Broadband ISP, and Digital TV.  There are five deployments
   based on <xref target="RFC4601" /> implementations and two on <xref target="RFC2362" />
   implementations.  PIM-SM for IPv6 has been deployed by three
   operators.  Out of the nine operators, six have deployed PIM-SM
   implementations from multiple vendors.
   </t>
   <t>
   Operators reported minor interoperability issues and these were
   addressed by the vendors.  There was no major interoperability
   concern reported by the operators.
   </t>
        </section>
        <section title="PIM-SM Deployment with Other Multicast Technologies">
   <t>
   Except for one deployment of PIM-SM with Multicast Extensions to OSPF
   (MOSPF), all other operators have deployed PIM-SM exclusively.  No
   operators acknowledged deployments of either (*,*,RP) or PIM Multicast
   Border Route (PMBR) for interconnection between PIM-SM and
   other multicast domains.
   </t>
        </section>
        <section title=" PIM-SM Rendezvous Points (RPs) and RP Discovery Mechanisms">
   <t>

   The number of PIM-SM RPs deployed by operators ranges from a few
   (e.g., sixteen) to a massively scaled number (four hundred).  Both
   static configuration and Bootstrap Router (BSR) have been deployed as
   RP discovery mechanisms.
   </t>
   <t>
   Anycast-RP has been deployed for RP redundancy.  Two operators have
   deployed Anycast-RP using the Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP) <xref target="RFC3446" />. Three operators have deployed
   Anycast-RP using both MSDP <xref target="RFC3446" /> and PIM <xref target="RFC4610" /> for different
   scenarios. The best common practice seems to be to use
   static-RP configuration with Anycast-RP for redundancy.
   </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Vendor Responses">
   <t>
   Eight vendors reported PIM-SM implementations.  They
   are XORP, Huawei Technologies, Cisco Systems, Motorola Solutions,
   Juniper Networks, and three other anonymous vendors.
   </t>
        <section title="Implementations Based on RFCs 4601 and 2362">
   <t>
   Four vendors reported PIM-SM implementations based on
   <xref target="RFC4601" /> and two reported PIM-SM implementations
   based on <xref target="RFC2362" />.  Two other reported implementations are hybrids.
   </t>
   <t>
   Minor interoperability issues have been addressed by the vendors
   over the years and no concerns were reported by any vendor.
   </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Lack of (*,*,RP) and PMBR Implementations">
   <t>
   Most vendors have not implemented (*,*,RP) state as specified in
   <xref target="RFC4601" /> either due to lack of deployment requirements or due to
   security concerns.  Similarly, most vendors have also not implemented
   PMBR due to lack of deployment requirements or because it was
   considered too complex and non-scalable.
   </t>
   <t>
   Only one vendor, XORP, reported (*,*,RP) and PMBR implementation and
   they were implemented just because these were part of the <xref target="RFC4601" />
   specification.
   </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Implementations of Other Features of RFC 4601">
   <t>

   Most vendors have implemented all of the following from the  <xref target="RFC4601" />
   specification:
   </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Source-Specific Multicast (SSM)</t>
           <t>Join suppression</t>
           <t>Explicit tracking</t>
           <t>Register mechanism</t>
           <t>Shortest Path Tree (SPT) switchover at last-hop router</t>
           <t>Assert mechanism</t>
           <t>Hashing of group to RP mappings</t>
          </list></t>
   <t>
   Some vendors do not implement explicit tracking and SSM.
   </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Key Findings">
   <t>
   PIM-SM has been widely implemented and deployed for
   different applications.  The protocol is sufficiently
   well specified in <xref target="RFC4601" /> resulting in interoperable implementation
   deployed by operators.
   </t>
   <t>
   There are no deployments and only one known implementation of
   (*,*,RP) and PMBR as specified in <xref target="RFC4601" />.  Hence, it is necessary
   to remove these features from the specification as required by
   <xref target="RFC2026" /> and <xref target="RFC6410" />.
   </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
      The PIM WG is aware of at least three (and believes there are more) PIM-SM
      implementations that support the use of IPsec to protect PIM messages.
      For at least one of them, IPsec is not part of the PIM implementation
      itself -- one just configures IPsec with Security Policy Databases (SPDs) where interface, the
      ALL_PIM_ROUTERS multicast address, etc., can be used as selectors,
      according to <xref target="RFC5796" />.
     </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Tim Chown and Bill Atwood, who helped to collect and anonymize the responses as the neutral
      third party. Special thanks are also given to Alexander Gall, William F.
      Maton Sotomayor, Steve Bauer, Sonum Mathur, Pavlin Radoslavov, Shuxue
      Fan, Sameer Gulrajani, and to the anonymous responders.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2026'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6410'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2117'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2362'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3446'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4601'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4610'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5796'?>
    </references>

  <section anchor="questionnaire" title="Questionnaire">

<t>   This section provides copies of the questionnaires exactly as distributed to operators and implementors.  </t>
   <section title="PIM Survey for Operators">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Introduction:

PIM-SM was first published as RFC2117 in 1997 and then again as
RFC2362 in 1998.  The protocol was classified as Experimental in 
both of these documents.  The PIM-SM protocol specification was then
rewritten in whole and advanced to Proposed Standard as RFC4601 in
2006.  Considering the multiple independent implementations developed
and the successful operational experience gained, the IETF has
decided to advance the PIM-SM routing protocol to Draft Standard.
This survey intends to provide supporting documentation to advance
the Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) routing
protocol from IETF Proposed Standard to Draft Standard.  (Due to
RFC6410, now the intention is to progress it to Internet Standard.
Draft Standard is no longer used.)

This survey is issued on behalf of the IETF PIM Working Group.

The responses will be collected by a neutral third-party and kept
strictly confidential if requested in the response; only the final
combined results will be published.  Tim Chown and Bill Atwood have
agreed to anonymize the response to this Questionnaire.  They have a
long experience with multicast but have no direct financial interest
in this matter, nor ties to any of the vendors involved.  Tim is
working at University of Southampton, UK, and he has been active in
the IETF for many years, including the mboned working group, and he
is a co-chair of the 6renum working group.  Bill is at Concordia
University, Montreal, Canada, and he has been an active participant
in the IETF pim working group for over ten years, especially in the
area of security.

Please send questionnaire responses addressed to them both.  The
addresses are tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk and william.atwood@concordia.ca.
Please include the string "RFC4601 bis Questionnaire" in the subject
field.

Before answering the questions, please complete the following
background information.

Name of the Respondent:

Affiliation/Organization:

Contact Email:

Provide description of PIM deployment:

Do you wish to keep the information provided confidential:

Questions:

1 Have you deployed PIM-SM in your network?

2 How long have you had PIM-SM deployed in your network?  Do you know
  if your deployment is based on the most recent RFC4601?

3 Have you deployed PIM-SM for IPv6 in your network?

4 Are you using equipment with different (multi-vendor) PIM-SM
  implementations for your deployment?

5 Have you encountered any inter-operability or backward-
  compatibility issues amongst differing implementations?  If yes, 
  what are your concerns about these issues?

6 Have you deployed both dense mode and sparse mode in your network?
  If yes, do you route between these modes using features such as
  *,*,RP or PMBR?

7 To what extent have you deployed PIM functionality, like BSR, SSM,
  and Explicit Tracking?

8 Which RP mapping mechanism do you use: Static, AutoRP, or BSR?

9 How many RPs have you deployed in your network?

10 If you use Anycast-RP, is it Anycast-RP using MSDP (RFC 3446) or
   Anycast-RP using PIM (RFC4610)?

11 Do you have any other comments on PIM-SM deployment in your
   network?
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
   </section>
   <section title="PIM Survey for Implementors">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Introduction:

PIM-SM was first published as RFC2117 in 1997 and then again as
RFC2362 in 1998.  The protocol was classified as Experimental in both
of these documents.  The PIM-SM protocol specification was then
rewritten in whole and advanced to Proposed Standard as RFC4601 in
2006.  Considering the multiple independent implementations developed
and the successful operational experience gained, the IETF has
decided to advance the PIM-SM routing protocol to Draft Standard.
This survey intends to provide supporting documentation to advance
the Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) routing
protocol from IETF Proposed Standard to Draft Standard.  (Due to
RFC6410, now the intention is to progress it to Internet Standard.
Draft Standard is no longer used.)

This survey is issued on behalf of the IETF PIM Working Group.

The responses will be collected by a neutral third-party and kept
strictly confidential if requested in the response; only the final
combined results will be published.  Tim Chown and Bill Atwood have
agreed to anonymize the response to this Questionnaire.  They have a
long experience with multicast but have no direct financial interest
in this matter, nor ties to any of the vendors involved.  Tim is
working at University of Southampton, UK, and he has been active in
the IETF for many years, including the mboned working group, and he
is a co-chair of the 6renum working group.  Bill is at Concordia
University, Montreal, Canada, and he has been an active participant
in the IETF pim working group for over ten years, especially in the
area of security.

Please send questionnaire responses addressed to them both.  The
addresses are tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk and william.atwood@concordia.ca.
Please include the string "RFC 4601 bis Questionnaire" in the subject
field.

Before answering the questions, please complete the following
background information.

Name of the Respondent:

Affiliation/Organization:

Contact Email:

Provide description of PIM implementation:

Do you wish to keep the information provided confidential:

Questions:

1 Have you implemented PIM-SM?

2 Is the PIM-SM implementation based on RFC2362 or RFC4601?

3 Have you implemented (*,*, RP) state of RFC4601?  What is the
  rationale behind implementing or omitting (*,*,RP)?

4 Have you implemented the PMBR as specified in RFC4601 and RFC2715?
  What is the rationale behind implementing or omitting PMBR?

5 Have you implemented other features and functions of RFC4601:

- SSM

- Join Suppression

- Explicit tracking

- Register mechanism

- SPT switchover at last-hop router

- Assert mechanism

- Hashing of group to RP mappings

6 Does your PIM-SM implementation support IPv6?

7 Have you encountered any inter-operability issues with other PIM
  implementations in trials or in the field?

8 Do you have any other comments or concerns about PIM-SM as
  specified in RFC4601?
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
   </section>
  </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
