<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>


<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>



<rfc number="7726" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902" updates="5884">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Clarifications to RFC 5884">
Clarifying Procedures for Establishing Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) Sessions for MPLS LSPs
    </title>

    <author fullname="Vengada Prasad Govindan" initials="V."
            surname="Govindan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>venggovi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Kalyani Rajaraman" initials="K."
            surname="Rajaraman">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>kalyanir@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Gregory Mirsky" initials="G."
            surname="Mirsky">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gregory.mirsky@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Nobo Akiya" initials="N."
            surname="Akiya">
      <organization>Big Switch Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>nobo.akiya.dev@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
 
    <author fullname="Sam Aldrin" initials="S."
            surname="Aldrin">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>aldrin.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
     <date month="January" year="2016" />

    <area>BFD Working Group</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC5884</keyword>
    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>
    <keyword>LSP Ping</keyword>
    <keyword>BFD</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>This document clarifies the procedures for establishing, maintaining,
      and removing multiple, concurrent BFD (Bidirectional Forwarding
      Detection) sessions for a given &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt; as described in RFC 5884.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Background"> 
    <t>
<xref target="RFC5884" /> defines the procedures to bootstrap and
    maintain BFD sessions for an &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt; using a Label Switched
   Path (LSP) ping. While
    Section 4 of <xref target="RFC5884"/> specifies that multiple BFD sessions
    can be established for an &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt; tuple, the procedures to
    bootstrap and maintain multiple BFD sessions concurrently over an &lt;MPLS
    LSP, FEC&gt; are not clearly specified. Additionally, the procedures of
    removing BFD sessions bootstrapped on the egress Label Switching Router
    (LSR) are unclear. This
    document provides those clarifications without deviating from the
    principles outlined in <xref target="RFC5884"/>. 
    </t>

    <t> 
<!-- [rfced] For ease of the reader, should a reference for "Segment Routing"
be added in the following?

   The ability for an ingress LSR to establish multiple BFD sessions for
   a <MPLS FEC, LSP> tuple is useful in scenarios such as Segment
   Routing based LSPs or LSPs having Equal-Cost Multipath (ECMP).
-->

The ability for an ingress LSR to establish multiple BFD sessions for
    an &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt; tuple is useful in scenarios such as LSPs based
    on Segment Routing <xref target="SEG-ROUTING" /> or LSPs having Equal-Cost Multipath (ECMP).  The
    process used by the ingress LSR to determine the number of BFD session(s)
    to be bootstrapped for an &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt; tuple and the mechanism
    used to construct those session(s) are outside the scope of this document.
    </t> 

    <section title="Requirements Language">
    <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and 
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.  </t>
    </section>


    </section>

    <section title="Theory of Operation">

    <section title="Procedures for Establishment of Multiple BFD Sessions ">
    <t>Section 4 of <xref target="RFC5884" /> specifies the procedure for
    bootstrapping BFD sessions using LSP ping. It further states that "a BFD
    session SHOULD be established for each alternate path that is discovered."
    This requirement has been the source of some ambiguity as the procedures
    of establishing concurrent, multiple sessions have not been explicitly
    specified. This ambiguity can also be attributed in part to the text in
    Section 7 of <xref target="RFC5884" /> forbidding either end to change
    local discriminator values in BFD control packets after the session
    reaches the UP state. The following procedures are described to clarify
    the ambiguity based on the interpretation of the authors' reading of the
    referenced sections:  
    </t>
    <t>
    At the ingress LSR:
    <list>
    <t>
    MPLS LSP ping can be used to bootstrap multiple BFD sessions for a
    given &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt;. Each LSP ping MUST carry a different
    discriminator value in the BFD discriminator TLV <xref target="RFC5884" />.</t> 
    </list>
    The egress LSR needs to perform the following:
    <list>
    <t>If the validation of the Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC) in the MPLS
    Echo request message succeeds, check the discriminator specified in the
    BFD discriminator TLV of the MPLS Echo request. If there is no local
    session that corresponds to the (remote) discriminator received in the
    MPLS Echo request, a new session is bootstrapped and a local discriminator
    is allocated. The validation of a FEC is a necessary condition to be
    satisfied to create a new BFD session at the egress LSR. However, the
    policy or procedure, if any, to be applied by the egress LSR before
    allowing a new BFD session to be created is outside the scope of this
    document. Such policies or procedures could consider availability of
    system resources before allowing a session to be created. When the egress
    LSR disallows the creation of a BFD session due to policy, it MUST drop
    the MPLS Echo request message.</t> 
    <t> Ensure the uniqueness of the &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC, Remote Discriminator&gt; tuple.</t>
    <t>Except for the clarification mentioned above, the remaining procedures
    of BFD session establishment are as specified in Sections 4-6 of <xref
    target="RFC5884" />.</t> 
    </list></t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Procedures for Maintenance of Multiple BFD Sessions ">
    <t>
<!-- [rfced] Please note that that "YourDiscriminator" has been udpated to
"Your Discriminator" for consistency with RFC 5880 and 5884.  Please let us
know any objections.  In addition, please consider whether "value" or "field"
should follow "Your Discriminator".  

Original:
   Both the ingress LSR and egress LSR use the YourDiscriminator of the
   received BFD packet to demultiplex BFD sessions.
-->

Both the ingress LSR and egress LSR use the Your Discriminator of the
    received BFD packet to demultiplex BFD sessions.</t> 
    </section>

    <section title="Procedures for Removing BFD Sessions at the Egress LSR">
    <t> <xref target="RFC5884" /> does not specify an explicit procedure for
    deleting BFD sessions. The procedure for removing a BFD session
    established by an out-of-band discriminator exchange using the MPLS LSP
    ping can improve resource management (e.g., memory), especially in
    scenarios involving thousands or more of such sessions. A few observations
    are made here: 
    <list>
    <t> The BFD session MAY be removed in the egress LSR if the BFD session transitions from UP to DOWN.  This can either be done immediately after the BFD session transitions from UP to DOWN  or after the  expiry of a configurable timer started after the BFD  session state  transitions from UP to DOWN at the egress LSR to reduce flapping by adding hysteresis.</t>

    <t>The BFD session on the egress LSR MAY be removed by the ingress LSR by using the BFD diagnostic code AdminDown(7) as specified in <xref target="RFC5880" />. When the ingress LSR wants to remove a session without triggering any state change at the egress, it MAY transmit BFD packets indicating the State as Down(1), diagnostic code AdminDown(7) detectMultiplier number of times. Upon receiving such a packet, the egress LSR MAY remove the BFD session, without triggering a change of state. </t>
    <t>The procedures to be followed at the egress LSR when BFD session(s) remain in the DOWN state for a significant amount of time is a local matter. Such procedures are outside the scope of this document. </t>
    <t> All BFD sessions established with the FEC MUST be removed automatically if the FEC is removed.</t>
    <t>
     The egress MUST use the discriminators exchanged when the session was
     brought UP to indicate any session state change to the ingress. The
     egress SHOULD reset this to zero after transmitting bfd.detectMult number
     of packets if the BFD session transitions to DOWN state. 
    </t>
    </list>
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changing Discriminators for a BFD Session">
    <t>The discriminators of a BFD session established over an MPLS LSP cannot
    be changed when it is in UP state. The BFD session could be removed after
    a graceful transition to AdminDown state using the BFD diagnostic code
    AdminDown. A new session could be established with a different
    discriminator. The initiation of the transition from the UP to DOWN state
    can be done by either the ingress LSR or the egress LSR.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Backwards Compatibility">

<t> The procedures clarified by this document are fully backward compatible
with an existing implementation of <xref target="RFC5884" />. While the
capability to bootstrap and maintain multiple BFD sessions may not be present
in current implementations, the procedures outlined by this document can be
implemented as a software upgrade without affecting existing sessions. In
particular, the egress LSR needs to support multiple BFD sessions per &lt;MPLS
LSP, FEC&gt; before the ingress LSR is upgraded. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>This document clarifies the mechanism to bootstrap multiple BFD
      sessions per &lt;MPLS LSP, FEC&gt;. BFD sessions, naturally, use system
      and network resources. More BFD sessions means more resources will be
      used. It is highly important to ensure that only a minimum number of BFD
      sessions are provisioned per FEC and that bootstrapped BFD sessions are
      properly deleted when they are no longer required. Additionally, security
      measures described in <xref target="RFC4379" /> and <xref
      target="RFC5884" /> are to be followed.</t> 

    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4379"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5884"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5880"?>
    </references>

<references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor='SEG-ROUTING'>
<front>
<title>Segment Routing Architecture</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2015' />

<abstract><t>Segment Routing (SR) leverages the source routing paradigm.  A node steers a packet through an ordered list of instructions, called segments.  A segment can represent any instruction, topological or service-based.  A segment can have a local semantic to an SR node or global within an SR domain.  SR allows to enforce a flow through any topological path and service chain while maintaining per-flow state only at the ingress node to the SR domain.  Segment Routing can be directly applied to the MPLS architecture with no change on the forwarding plane.  A segment is encoded as an MPLS label.  An ordered list of segments is encoded as a stack of labels. The segment to process is on the top of the stack.  Upon completion of a segment, the related label is popped from the stack.  Segment Routing can be applied to the IPv6 architecture, with a new type of routing header.  A segment is encoded as an IPv6 address.  An ordered list of segments is encoded as an ordered list of IPv6 addresses in the routing header.  The active segment is indicated by the Destination Address of the packet.  The next active segment is indicated by a pointer in the new routing header.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value='draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-07' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-06.txt' />
</reference>
</references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Marc Binderberger for performing thorough reviews and providing valuable suggestions.</t> 
      <t>The authors would like to thank Mudigonda Mallik, Rajaguru Veluchamy, and Carlos Pignataro of Cisco Systems for their review comments.</t>
      <t>The authors would like to thank Alvaro Retana and Scott Bradner for their review comments.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
