<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3315 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2131 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2131.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2132 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2132.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4361 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4361.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5508 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5508.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5961 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5961.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6056 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6056.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6335 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6335.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6346 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6346.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6269 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6269.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3927 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3927.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7341 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7341.xml">
]>

<rfc category="std" number="7618" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Dynamic Shared IPv4 Allocation">Dynamic Allocation of
    Shared IPv4 Addresses</title>

    <author fullname="Yong Cui" initials="Y." surname="Cui">
      <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100084</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-10-62603059</phone>
        <email>yong@csnet1.cs.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qi Sun" initials="Q.S" surname="Sun">
      <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100084</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-10-62785822</phone>
        <email>sunqi.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ian Farrer" initials="I.F" surname="Farrer">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>CTO-ATI, Landgrabenweg 151</street>
          <city>Bonn</city>
          <region>NRW</region>
          <code>53227</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ian.farrer@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yiu L. Lee" initials="Y.L" surname="Lee">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>
          <city>Philadelphia</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <code>19103</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>yiu_lee@cable.comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qiong Sun" initials="Q.S" surname="Sun">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Room 708, No.118, Xizhimennei Street</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100035</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-10-58552936</phone>
        <email>sunqiong@ctbri.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M.B" surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="August" year="2015" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo describes the dynamic allocation of shared IPv4 addresses
      to clients using DHCPv4. Address sharing allows a single IPv4 address to
      be allocated to multiple active clients simultaneously, with each client
      being differentiated by a unique set of transport-layer source port
      numbers. The necessary changes to existing DHCPv4 client and server
      behavior are described, and a new DHCPv4 option for provisioning clients
      with shared IPv4 addresses is included.</t>

      <t>Due to the nature of IP address sharing, some limitations to its
      applicability are necessary. This memo describes these limitations and
      recommends suitable architectures and technologies where address sharing
      may be utilized.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>The shortage of available public IPv4 addresses means that it is not
      always possible for operators to allocate a full IPv4 address to every
      connected device. This problem is particularly acute while an operator
      is migrating from their existing, native IPv4 network to a native IPv6
      network with IPv4 provided as an overlay service. During this phase,
      public IPv4 addresses are needed to provide for both existing and
      transition networks.</t>

      <t>Two main types of solutions have emerged to address the problem (see
      Appendix A of <xref target="RFC6269"></xref>):</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Deploying Carrier-Grade Network Address Translation devices
          (CGNs) <xref target="RFC6888"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Distributing the same public IPv4 address to multiple clients
          differentiated by non-overlapping Layer 4 port sets.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This memo focuses on the second category of solutions.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC7341"></xref> introduces a "DHCP 4o6 server", which
      offers dynamic leasing for IPv4 addresses to clients as described in
      DHCPv4 <xref target="RFC2131"></xref>, but transported within a
      DHCPv6 message flow. This memo specifies a new DHCPv4 option --
      OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS -- and describes how it can be used for the
      dynamic leasing of shared IPv4 addresses.</t>

      <t>Although DHCPv4 over DHCPv6 is used as the underlying DHCPv4
      transport mechanism throughout this document, OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS as a
      DHCPv4 option may also be used in other solutions, if required.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="aps" title="Applicability Statement ">
      <t>The solution allows multiple hosts to be simultaneously allocated the
      same IP address. As the IP address is no longer a unique identifier for
      a host, this solution is only suitable for specific architectures based
      on the Address plus Port model (A+P) <xref target="RFC6346"></xref>.
      Specifically, this document presents a solution that applies to <xref
      target="RFC7596"></xref> and certain configurations
      of <xref target="RFC7597"></xref> (e.g., Embedded Address bit
      (EA&nbhy;bit) length set to 0).</t>

      <t>The solution should only be used on point-to-point links, tunnels,
      and/or in environments where authentication at the link layer is
      performed before IP address assignment. It is not suitable for network
      access over shared media (e.g., Ethernet, WLAN, cable).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the following terms: <list hangIndent="22"
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Shared IPv4 address:">An IPv4 address with a restricted
          Layer 4 port&nbsp;set.</t>

          <t hangText="Port Set ID (PSID):">Identifier for a range of ports
          assigned to a DHCP client.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Functional Overview">
      <t>Functionally, the dynamic allocation of shared IPv4 addresses by the
      DHCP 4o6 server is similar to the dynamic allocation process for "full"
      IPv4 addresses as described in <xref target="RFC2131"></xref>. The
      essential difference is that the DHCP 4o6 server can allocate the same
      IPv4 address to more than one DHCP 4o6 client simultaneously, providing
      that each shared-address allocation also includes a range of Layer 4
      source ports unique to that address (i.e., the combined tuple of IPv4
      address and Port Set ID is to be unique for each active lease).</t>

      <t>The DHCP 4o6 client implements OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS (described
      below), which is a DHCPv4 option containing PSID information. The
      client includes this option within the Parameter Request List option
      <xref target="RFC2132"></xref> in its DHCPv4 DHCPDISCOVER and
      DHCPREQUEST messages, indicating its support for shared, dynamic
      address leasing to the DHCP 4o6 server.</t>

      <t>OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS is also implemented by the server to identify
      clients that support shared, dynamic address leasing. With this option,
      the server can dynamically allocate PSIDs to clients and maintain shared
      IPv4 address leases. The server then manages unique client leases based
      on the IPv4 address and PSID tuple, instead of using only the IPv4
      address.</t>

      <t>In the event that a client capable of dynamic, shared addressing
      receives more than one DHCP 4o6 offer, where a received offer does not
      contain OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS (i.e., it is an offer for a full IPv4
      address), then the client SHOULD prefer the full IPv4 offer over the
      shared IPv4 address offer(s), unless specifically configured
      otherwise.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Client-Server Interaction">
      <t>The following DHCPv4 message flow is transported within the
      DHCPv4-query and DHCPv4-response messages as described in
      DHCPv4 over DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC7341"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>When the client constructs the DHCPv4 DHCPDISCOVER message to be
          transported within the DHCPv4-query message, the DHCPDISCOVER
          message MUST include the client identifier option (constructed as
          per <xref target="RFC4361"></xref>) and the Parameter Request List
          option with the code OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS. The client MAY
          insert an OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS with preferred values in related
          fields as a suggestion to the DHCP 4o6 server.</t>

          <t>DHCP 4o6 servers that receive the DHCPDISCOVER message and
          support shared IPv4 addresses respond with a DHCPOFFER message with
          the shared IPv4 address in the yiaddr field, and they MUST add an
          OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS option containing an available restricted port
          set. If the DHCPDISCOVER included an OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS option
          containing a non-zero PSID&nbhy;len field, the DHCP 4o6 server MAY
          allocate a port set of the requested size to the client (depending
          on policy). The DHCPOFFER message is then encapsulated in the
          DHCPv4-response message and sent to the client.</t>

          <t>The client evaluates all received DHCPOFFER messages and selects
          one (e.g., based on the configuration parameters received, such as
          the size of the offered port set). The client then sends a
          DHCPREQUEST encapsulated in the DHCPv4-query message containing the
          corresponding OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS received in the DHCPOFFER
          message.</t>

          <t>The server identified in the DHCPREQUEST message creates a
          binding for the client. The binding includes the client identifier,
          the IPv4 address, and the PSID. These parameters are used by both the
          server and the client to identify a lease in any DHCP message. The
          server MUST respond with a DHCPACK message containing
          OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS for the requesting client.</t>

          <t>On receipt of the DHCPACK message with the configuration
          parameters, the client MUST NOT perform an in-use probe on the
          address, such as ARPing for a duplicate allocated address.</t>

          <t>If the client chooses to relinquish its lease by sending a
          DHCPRELEASE message, the client MUST include the leased network
          address and OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS (with the allocated PSID) to
          identify the lease to be released.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In the case where the client has stored the previously allocated
      address and restricted port set, the logic described in Section 3.2 of
      <xref target="RFC2131"></xref> MUST be followed on the condition that
      the client's source IPv6 address for DHCP 4o6 does not change.
      Note that this corresponds to the INIT-REBOOT state defined in <xref
      target="RFC2131"></xref>. The client MUST include the
      OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS with the requested port-set information in the
      message flow, which starts with a DHCPREQUEST message. If the client's
      DHCP 4o6 IPv6 source address is changed for any reason, the client MUST
      re-initiate the DHCP 4o6 shared-address provisioning process by sending
      a DHCPDISCOVER message.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="client" title="Client Behavior">
      <t>A DHCP 4o6 client sending a DHCPDISCOVER message for a shared IPv4
      address MUST include the OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS Option Code in the
      Parameter Request List option. If a client has previously been
      successfully allocated an IPv4 address and PSID, the client's
      DHCPDISCOVER message MAY include the Requested IP Address option
      along with an OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS to request that a specific
      IPv4 address and PSID be reassigned. Alternatively, the client
      MAY omit the Requested IP Address option but include an
      OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS with a non-zero value in only the
      PSID&nbhy;len field, as a hint to the server for the preferred
      size of the port set.</t>

      <t>A client that requests OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS but receives DHCPOFFER
      and DHCPACK messages without OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS SHOULD proceed as
      described in Section 9 of <xref target="RFC7341"></xref> and
      configure a full IPv4 address with no address sharing
      (see <xref target="shnsh"></xref>).</t>

      <t>When receiving a DHCPACK message containing OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, the
      client MUST use the received explicit PSID for configuring the interface
      for which the DHCP 4o6 request was made.</t>

      <t>The client MUST NOT probe a newly received IPv4 address (e.g., using
      ARP) to see if it is in use by another host.</t>

      <t>When the client renews or releases its DHCP lease, it MUST include
      the offset, PSID length, and PSID values in OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, and
      send it to the server within corresponding DHCPv4 messages.</t>

      <t>In the event that the client's DHCP 4o6 IPv6 source address is
      changed for any reason, the client MUST re-initiate the DHCP 4o6
      shared-address provisioning process by sending a DHCPDISCOVER
      message.</t>

      <section title="Restrictions to Client Usage of a Shared IPv4 Address">
        <t>As a single IPv4 address is being shared between a number of
        different clients, the allocated shared address is only suitable for
        certain uses. The client MUST implement a function to ensure that only
        the allocated Layer 4 ports of the shared IPv4 address are used for
        sourcing new connections or accepting inbound connections.</t>

        <t>The client MUST apply the following rules for all traffic destined
        to, or originating from, the shared IPv4 address:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The client MUST use only port-aware protocols (e.g., TCP, UDP,
            the Datagram Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP)) and be
            ICMP compliant with <xref target="RFC5508"></xref>.</t>

            <t>All connections originating from the shared IPv4 address MUST
            use a source port taken from the allocated restricted port
            set.</t>

            <t>The client MUST NOT accept inbound connections on ports outside
            of the allocated restricted port set.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In order to prevent addressing conflicts that could arise from the
        allocation of the same IPv4 address, the client MUST NOT use the
        received restricted IPv4 address to perform ARP operations.</t>

        <t>The mechanism by which a client implements the above rules is out
        of scope for this document.</t>

        <t>In the event that the DHCPv4-over-DHCPv6 configuration mechanism
        fails for any reason, the client MUST NOT configure an IPv4 link-local
        address <xref target="RFC3927"></xref> (taken from the 169.254.0.0/16
        range).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Server Behavior">
      <t>The DHCP 4o6 server MUST NOT reply with OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS unless
      the client has explicitly listed the Option Code in the Parameter
      Request List (Option 55) <xref target="RFC2132"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The DHCP 4o6 server SHOULD reply with OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS if the
      client includes OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS in its Parameter Request List. In
      order to achieve dynamic management of shared IPv4 addresses, the
      server is required to implement an address and port-set pool that
      provides the same function as the address pool in a regular DHCP server.
      Also, the server uses the combination of address and PSID as the key for
      maintaining the state of a lease and for searching for an available
      lease for assignment. The leasing database is required to include the
      IPv4 address, PSID, and client identifier of the requesting client.</t>

      <t>When a server receives a DHCPDISCOVER message with
      OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS in the Parameter Request List option, the server
      determines an IPv4 address with a PSID for the requesting client. If an
      IPv4 address with a PSID is available, the server SHOULD follow the
      logic below to select which specific address and PSID to provision to
      the client. The logic is similar to that described in
      Section 4.3.1 of <xref target="RFC2131"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The client's current address with the PSID, as recorded in the
          client's current lease binding, ELSE</t>

          <t>The client's previous address with the PSID, as recorded in the
          client's (expired or released) binding, if that address with PSID is
          in the server's pool of available addresses and PSIDs, and not
          already allocated, ELSE</t>

          <t>The address requested in the Requested IP Address option along
          with the PSID parameters requested in the OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, if
          that pair of address and PSID is valid and not already allocated,
          ELSE</t>

          <t>A new address with a PSID allocated from the server's pool of
          available addresses and PSIDs.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Upon receipt of a DHCPRELEASE message with OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, the
      server searches for the lease using the address in the ciaddr field
      and the PSID information in the OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, and marks the
      lease as unallocated if a record (matching that PSID) is maintained by
      the server for that client.</t>

      <t>The port-set assignment MUST be coupled with the address assignment
      process. Therefore, the server MUST assign the address and port set in
      the same DHCP message.</t>

      <t>When defining the pools of IPv4 addresses and PSIDs that are
      available to lease to clients, the server MUST implement a mechanism to
      reserve some port ranges (e.g., 0-1023) from allocation to clients. The
      reservation policy SHOULD be configurable.</t>

      <section anchor="shnsh"
               title="Leasing Shared and Non-Shared IPv4 Addresses from a Single DHCP&nbsp;4o6 Server">
        <t>A single DHCP 4o6 server may serve clients that do not support
        OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS, as well as those that do. As the rules for the
        allocation of shared addresses differ from the rules for full IPv4
        address assignment, the DHCP 4o6 server MUST implement a mechanism to
        ensure that clients not supporting OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS do not receive
        shared addresses. For example, two separate IPv4 addressing pools
        could be used, one of which allocates IPv4 addresses and PSIDs only to
        clients that have requested them.</t>

        <t>If the server is only configured with address pools for
        shared-address allocation, it MUST discard requests that do not
        contain OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS in the Parameter Request List option.</t>

        <t>A server configured with non-shared address pools can be instructed
        to honor received requests that contain OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS in the
        Parameter Request List option (that is, ignore OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS
        and serve the requesting clients with non-shared IPv4 addresses).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv4 Port Parameters Option">
      <t>The meanings of the offset, PSID-len, and PSID fields of
      the DHCPv4 Port Parameters option are identical to those of
      the offset, PSID&nbhy;len, and PSID fields of the S46 Port
      Parameters option (Section 4.5 of <xref target="RFC7598"></xref>).
      The use of the same encoding in both options is meant to ensure
      compatibility with existing port-set implementations.</t>

      <t>The format of OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS is shown in <xref
      target="img-option-portparams"></xref>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="img-option-portparams"
              title="DHCPv4 Port Parameters Option">
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                             1
 0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5 
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
|      option-code      |     option-len        |
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
|         offset        |       PSID-len        |
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
|                     PSID                      |
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+      
      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><list style="symbols">

          <t>option-code: OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS (159)</t>

          <t>option-len: 4</t>

          <t>offset: PSID offset. &nbsp;8-bit field that specifies the
          numeric value for the excluded port range/offset bits
          ('a'&nbsp;bits), as per Section 5.1
          of <xref target="RFC7597"></xref>. Allowed values are
          between 0 and 15, with the default value being 6 for
          MAP-based implementations. This parameter is unused by a
          Lightweight 4over6 client and should be set to 0.</t>

          <t>PSID-len: Bit length value of the number of significant bits in
          the PSID field (also known as 'k'). When set to 0, the PSID field is
          to be ignored. After the first 'a' bits, there are k bits in the
          port number representing the value of PSID. Subsequently, the
          address-sharing ratio would be 2^k.</t>

          <t>PSID: Explicit 16-bit (unsigned word) PSID value. The PSID value
          algorithmically identifies a set of ports assigned to a client. The
          first k bits on the left of this 2-octet field indicate the PSID
          value. The remaining (16 - k) bits on the right are padding
          zeros.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC7597"></xref> provides a
      full description of how the PSID is interpreted by the client.</t>

      <t>In order to exclude the system ports (<xref target="RFC6335"></xref>)
      or ports reserved by ISPs, the former port sets that contain well-known
      ports MUST NOT be assigned unless the operator has explicitly configured
      otherwise (e.g., by allocating a full IPv4 address).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref
      target="RFC2131"></xref> and <xref target="RFC7341"></xref> are also
      potentially applicable to this solution. Unauthorized DHCP 4o6 servers
      in the network could be used to stage an amplification attack or to
      supply an invalid configuration, leading to service disruption. The
      risks of these types of attacks can be reduced by using unicast
      DHCP 4o6 message flows (enabled by supplying DHCP 4o6 server
      unicast addresses within the OPTION_DHCP4_O_DHCP6_SERVER option
      <xref target="RFC7341"></xref>).</t>

      <t>A malicious user could attempt a DoS attack by requesting a large
      number of IPv4 address (or fractional address) and port-set allocations,
      exhausting the available addresses and port sets for other clients. This
      can be mitigated by implementing, on each applicable customer site,
      a DHCP 4o6 address allocation policy that limits the number of
      simultaneously active IPv4 leases for clients whose requests
      originate from that customer site.</t>

      <t>The purpose of the client identifier option is to ensure that the
      same client retains the same parameters over time. However, this
      interferes with the client's privacy, as it allows the server to
      track the client. Clients can manage their level of exposure by
      controlling the value of the client identifier, thereby trading off
      stability of parameter allocation for privacy. We expect that
      guidance on this trade-off will be discussed in a future version
      of <xref target="DHCP-Anonymity"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Additional security considerations are discussed in
      Section 10 of <xref target="RFC7597"></xref> and
      Section 9 of <xref target="RFC7596"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Port Randomization">
        <t>Preserving port randomization <xref target="RFC6056"></xref> may be
        more difficult because the host can only randomize the ports inside a
        fixed port range (see Section 13.4 of <xref
        target="RFC6269"></xref>).</t>

        <t>More discussion regarding improving the robustness of TCP against
        blind in-window attacks can be found in <xref
        target="RFC5961"></xref>.  To provide protection against attacks,
        means other than (IPv4) source port randomization should be used
        (e.g., use <xref target="RFC5961"></xref> to improve the robustness of
        TCP against blind in-window attacks, or use IPv6).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has assigned the following new DHCPv4 Option Code in
      the registry maintained at
<vspace/>
     &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters/&gt;:</t>

      <texttable style="headers">
        <ttcol>Option Name</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Tag</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Data Length</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>

        <c>OPTION_V4_PORTPARAMS</c>

        <c>159</c>

        <c>4</c>

        <c>This option is used to configure a set of ports bound to a shared
        IPv4 address.</c>
      </texttable>

      <t></t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7341'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6056'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5961'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4361'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2131'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2132'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-softwire-lw4over6 (RFC 7596) -->
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7596'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-softwire-map (RFC 7597) -->
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7597'?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!-- draft-ietf-softwire-map-dhcp (RFC 7598) -->
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7598'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-dhc-anonymity-profile (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='DHCP-Anonymity'>
<front>
<title>Anonymity profile for DHCP clients</title>
<author initials='C' surname='Huitema' fullname='Christian Huitema'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='T' surname='Mrugalski' fullname='Tomek Mrugalski'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Krishnan' fullname='Suresh Krishnan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='June' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-dhc-anonymity-profile-01' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6335'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6269'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5508'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3927'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6346'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6888'?>

<!-- draft-sun-dhc-port-set-option
   ("Replaced by draft-csf-dhc-dynamic-shared-v4allocation";
  However, per author reply, kept as the old draft. -->
<reference anchor='DHCP-Port-Set-Opt'>
<front>
<title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) Option for Port Set Assignment</title>
<author initials='Q' surname='Sun' fullname='Qiong Sun'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='Q' surname='Sun' fullname='Qi Sun'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='G' surname='Bajko' fullname='Gabor Bajko'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohamed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-sun-dhc-port-set-option-02' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-farrer-dhc-shared-address-lease
  ("Replaced by draft-csf-dhc-dynamic-shared-v4allocation";
  However, per author reply, kept as the old draft.) -->
<reference anchor='DHCPv4_v6-Shared-Addr'>
<front>
<title>Dynamic Allocation of Shared IPv4 Addresses using DHCPv4 over DHCPv6</title>
<author initials='I' surname='Farrer' fullname='Ian Farrer'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='June' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-farrer-dhc-shared-address-lease-00' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>This document is the result of merging <xref target="DHCP-Port-Set-Opt"></xref>
      and <xref target="DHCPv4_v6-Shared-Addr"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank Peng Wu, Gabor Bajko, Teemu
      Savolainen, Ted Lemon, Tina Tsou, Pierre Levis, Cong Liu, Marcin
      Siodelski, and Christian Huitema for their contributions.</t>

      <t>Many thanks to Brian Haberman for the review.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
