<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4656 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4656.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5618 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5618.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5357 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5357.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6038 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6038.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3168 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3168.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3260 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3260.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="7750" category="std" ipr="trust200902" updates="5357"
     submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<front>
	<title abbrev='DSCP and ECN Monitoring in TWAMP'>Differentiated
	Service Code Point and Explicit Congestion Notification Monitoring in
	the Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)</title>
	<author initials='J.' surname="Hedin" fullname='Jonas Hedin'>
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		<address>
			<email>jonas.hedin@ericsson.com</email>
		</address> 
	</author>
	<author initials='G.' surname="Mirsky" fullname='Greg Mirsky'>
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		<address>
			<email>gregory.mirsky@ericsson.com</email>
		</address> 
	</author>
 	<author initials='S.' surname=" Baillargeon" fullname='Steve  Baillargeon'>
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		<address>
			<email>steve.baillargeon@ericsson.com</email>
		</address> 
	</author>

    <date month="February" year="2016" />

    <area>Transport</area>

   <keyword>IPPM</keyword>
   
   <keyword>TWAMP </keyword>
   
   <keyword>Type-P Descriptor</keyword>
	
	<abstract>
	<t>
	This document describes an optional extension for Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)
              allowing the monitoring of the Differentiated Service Code Point and 
	Explicit Congestion Notification fields with the TWAMP-Test protocol.
	 </t>
	</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
        <t>
        The One-Way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP) <xref target
	="RFC4656"/> defines the Type-P Descriptor field and negotiation of
	its value in the OWAMP-Control protocol. 
        The Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP) <xref
	target="RFC5357"/> states that only a Differentiated Services Code
	Point (DSCP) value
        (see <xref target="RFC2474"/>, <xref target="RFC3168"/>, and <xref target="RFC3260"/>) can
        be defined by Type-P Descriptor, and the negotiated value must be used
	by both the Session-Sender and Session-Reflector. The TWAMP specification also states
        that the same DSCP value (found in the Session-Sender packet) MUST be used in the test packet reflected by the Session-Reflector. However,
        the TWAMP-Test protocol does not specify any methods to determine or report when the DSCP value has changed or is different than expected in the forward
        or reverse direction. Re-marking the DSCP (changing its original value) in IP networks is possible and often accomplished by a Differentiated Services policy configured on
         a single node along the IP path. In many cases, a change of the DSCP value indicates an unintentional or erroneous behavior. At best, the Session-Sender 
         can detect a change of the DSCP reverse direction, assuming such a change is actually detectable.
       </t>
       <t>
        This document describes an OPTIONAL feature for TWAMP. It is called DSCP and ECN Monitoring. It allows the
        Session-Sender to know the actual DSCP value received at the
	Session-Reflector. Furthermore, this feature tracks the 
        Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) value (see <xref
	target="RFC2474"/>, <xref target="RFC3168"/>, and <xref target="RFC3260"/>)
        received at the Session-Reflector. This is helpful to determine if the
	ECN is actually operating
        or if an ECN-capable node has detected congestion in the forward direction.
        </t>
         
     <section title="Conventions used in this document">
         <section title="Terminology">

            <t>DSCP:          Differentiated Services Code Point
</t>
           <t>ECN:              Explicit Congestion Notification
</t>
            <t>IPPM:            IP Performance Metrics
</t>
           <t>TWAMP:        Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol
</t>
           <t>OWAMP:       One-Way Active Measurement Protocol
</t>
 
         </section>    
         
        <section title="Requirements Language">
             <t>
	  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and 
	  "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
	  <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
             </t>
          </section>
      </section>
     </section>
      
     <section anchor="twamp-extensions" title="TWAMP Extensions">
          <t>
           TWAMP connection establishment follows the procedure defined in
           Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC4656"/> and Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC5357"/> where the Modes field
           is used to identify and select specific communication capabilities. At the same time,
           the Modes field is recognized and used as an extension mechanism <xref target="RFC6038"/>.
           The new feature requires a new flag to identify the ability of a Session-Reflector
           to return the values of received DSCP and ECN values back to a Session-Sender,
           and to support the new Session-Reflector packet format in the TWAMP-Test protocol. See
           <xref target="iana-consider"/> for details on the assigned bit position.
          </t>
          <section anchor="conn-setup" title="Setting Up Connection to Monitor DSCP and ECN">
             <t>
                The Server sets the DSCP and ECN Monitoring flag in the Modes field of the Server Greeting message
                to indicate its capabilities and willingness to monitor them.
                If the Control-Client agrees to monitor DSCP and ECN on some or all test sessions invoked with
                this control connection, it MUST set the DSCP and ECN Monitoring flag in the Modes field in the Setup
                Response
 message.  
             </t>   
           </section>
           
           <section anchor="test-extension" title="TWAMP-Test Extension">
             <t>
   Monitoring of DSCP and ECN requires support by the Session-Reflector
   and changes the test packet format in all the original modes
   (unauthenticated, authenticated, and encrypted). 
             Monitoring of DSCP and ECN does not alter the Session-Sender test packet format, but certain considerations
             must be taken when and if this mode is accepted in combination with Symmetrical Size mode <xref target="RFC6038"/>.
             </t>
             
             <section anchor="session-reflector-change" title="Session-Reflector Packet Format for DSCP and ECN Monitoring">
              <t>
              When the Session-Reflector supports DSCP and ECN Monitoring, it constructs the Sender 
              DSCP and ECN (S-DSCP-ECN) field, presented in 
              <xref target="sender-dscp-ecn-format"/>, for each
              test packet it sends to the Session-Sender according to the following procedure:
              </t>
              <t>
              <list style="symbols">
              <t>
              the six (least-significant) bits of the Differentiated Service field MUST be
              copied from the received Session-Sender test packet into the Sender DSCP (S-DSCP) field;
              </t>
              <t>
              the two bits of the ECN field MUST be copied from the
              received Session-Sender test packet into the Sender ECN (S-ECN) field.
              </t>
               </list>
               </t>
<t>
         <figure align="center" anchor="sender-dscp-ecn-format"
                title="Sender DSCP and ECN Field Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[    
   0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7 
 +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
 |         S-DSCP        | S-ECN |
 +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
            </t>

<t>

Formats of the test packet transmitted by the Session-Reflector in unauthenticated, authenticated, and encrypted modes
have been defined in Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5357"/>. For the Session-Reflector that supports 
DSCP and ECN Monitoring, these formats are displayed in Figures <xref
target="reflector-unauthenticated-format" format="counter"/>
and <xref target="reflector-authenticated-format" format="counter"/>.

</t>
               <t>
                For unauthenticated mode:


         <figure align="left" anchor="reflector-unauthenticated-format"
                title="Session-Reflector Test Packet Format with DSCP and ECN Monitoring in Unauthenticated Mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Sequence Number                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                          Timestamp                            |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Error Estimate         |             MBZ                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Receive Timestamp                         |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                  Sender Sequence Number                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Sender Timestamp                          |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Sender Error Estimate      |             MBZ               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Sender TTL    |  S-DSCP-ECN   |             MBZ               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
~                        Packet Padding                         ~
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
            </t>
             <t>
              The DSCP and ECN values (part of the Type-P Descriptor <xref target="RFC4656"/>) can be 
              provisioned through TWAMP-Control or by other means
	      (command-line interface (CLI) or Central Controller).
              The DSCP and ECN values are often copied into reflected test packets with current TWAMP implementations without TWAMP-Control protocol.
              With the DSCP and ECN Monitoring extension, the
	      Session-Reflector handles the DSCP as follows:
              <list style="symbols">
              <t>the Session-Reflector MUST extract the DSCP and ECN values from the received packet
              and MUST use them to populate the S-DSCP-ECN field of the corresponding reflected packet;</t>
              <t>the Session-Reflector MUST transmit each reflected test
	      packet with the DSCP set to the provisioned value;</t>
              <t>if the provisioned DSCP value is not known (e.g., TWAMP Light), the choice of the DSCP is implementation specific.
              For instance, the Session-Reflector MAY copy the DSCP value from the
	      received test packet and set it as the DSCP in a reflected packet.
              Alternatively, the Session-Reflector MAY set the DSCP value to CS0 (zero) <xref target="RFC2474"/>;</t>
              <t>if the provisioned ECN value is not known, ECN SHOULD be set to Not-ECT codepoint value <xref target="RFC3168"/>.
              Otherwise, the provisioned ECN value for the session SHALL be used.</t>
              </list> 
              </t>
              <t>
              A Session-Reflector in the DSCP and ECN Monitoring mode does not
	      analyze nor act on the ECN value of the 
              received TWAMP test packet; therefore, it ignores congestion indications from the network.
              It is expected that sending rates are low enough, as TWAMP deployment experience had demonstrated
              since TWAMP base (RFC 5357) was published in 2008, that ignoring these congestion indications 
              will not significantly contribute to network congestion.
              </t>
                          
            <t>
                     For authenticated and encrypted modes:
         <figure align="left" anchor="reflector-authenticated-format"
                title=" Session-Reflector Test Packet Format with DSCP and ECN Monitoring in Authenticated or Encrypted Modes">
          <artwork><![CDATA[    
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Sequence Number                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                       MBZ (12 octets)                         |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Timestamp                             |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Error Estimate          |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                        MBZ (6 octets)                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Receive Timestamp                        |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       MBZ (8 octets)                          |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                   Sender Sequence Number                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                      MBZ (12 octets)                          |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Sender Timestamp                         |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Sender Error Estimate      |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                         MBZ (6 octets)                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Sender TTL    |  S-DSCP-ECN   |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
|                         MBZ (14 octets)                       |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                        HMAC (16 octets)                       |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
~                       Packet Padding                          ~
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
                     
                     </t>

                </section>      
             
                <section anchor="session-sender-consider"
title="DSCP and ECN Monitoring with Extensions from RFC 6038">
                <t>
                <xref target="RFC6038"/> defined two extensions to TWAMP -- first, to ensure that the Session-Sender and Session-Reflector exchange
                TWAMP-Test packets of equal size; second, to specify the number of octets to be reflected by Session-Reflector. If DSCP and ECN
                Monitoring and Symmetrical Size and/or Reflects Octets modes are being negotiated between
                Server and Control-Client in Unauthenticated mode, then,
		because Sender DSCP and Sender ECN increase the size of the
                unauthenticated Session-Reflector packet by 4 octets, the
		Padding Length value SHOULD be greater than or equal to 28 octets to allow for
                the truncation process that TWAMP recommends in Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5357"/>.
                </t>
                <t>
         <figure align="left" anchor="sender-unauthenticated-format"
                title=" Session-Sender Test Packet Format with DSCP and ECN Monitoring and Symmetrical Test Packet in Unauthenticated Mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[    
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Sequence Number                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Timestamp                           |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Error Estimate        |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
|                         MBZ (28 octets)                       |
|                                                               |
+                             +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                             |                                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                 +
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                        Packet Padding                         .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
            </t>               
             </section>
 
            <section anchor="twamp-light-aspect" title="Consideration for TWAMP Light Mode">
             <t>
             Appendix I of <xref target="RFC5357"/> does not explicitly state how the value of the Type-P Descriptor
 is
             synchronized between the Session-Sender and Session-Reflector and whether different values are considered
             as error conditions and should be reported.
             
             We assume that by some means the Session-Sender and the Session-Reflector of the given TWAMP-Test
             session have been informed to use the same DSCP value.
 The same means, i.e., configuration, could be used to
             inform the Session-Reflector to support DSCP and ECN Monitoring mode by copying data from
 received TWAMP
             test packets. Then Session-Sender may be informed to use the
	     Sender DSCP and ECN field in the reflected TWAMP
             test packet.</t>
            </section>             
 
           </section>

     </section>
 
     <section anchor="iana-consider" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>
     In the TWAMP-Modes registry defined in <xref target="RFC5618"/>,
     IANA has reserved a new DSCP and ECN Monitoring Capability as follows:
     </t>

  <texttable anchor="type-p-monitor-table" title="New Type-P Descriptor Monitoring Capability">
    <ttcol align='left'>Bit Pos&nbsp;</ttcol>
    <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
    <ttcol align='left'>Semantics&nbsp;Definition</ttcol>
    <ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>
    <c>8</c>
    <c>DSCP and ECN&nbsp;Monitoring&nbsp;Capability&nbsp;</c>
    <c><xref target="twamp-extensions"/></c>
    <c>RFC 7750</c>
    </texttable>

     </section>
     
     <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>
     Monitoring of DSCP and ECN does not appear to introduce any additional security threat to hosts that
     communicate with TWAMP as defined in <xref target="RFC5357"/> and existing extensions <xref target="RFC6038"/>.
     Sections such as 3.2, 4, 4.1.2, 4.2, and 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5357"/> discuss 
     unauthenticated, authenticated, and encrypted modes in varying degrees of detail.
     The security considerations that apply to any active measurement of live networks are
     relevant here as well.  See the Security Considerations sections in <xref target="RFC4656"/> and
     <xref target="RFC5357"/>.
     </t>

     </section>
      
     
  </middle>
  
    <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
     
     &RFC2119;
 
     &RFC4656;
     
     &RFC5618;
     
     &RFC5357;
     
     &RFC6038;
     
     &RFC2474;
     &RFC3168;

     
    </references>


   <references title="Informative References">

     &RFC3260;
 
    </references>

      <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
         <t>
          
         The authors greatly appreciate thorough review and thoughtful comments by Bill Cerveny,
         Christofer Flinta, and Samita Chakrabarti.
         </t>  
      </section>


 </back>
 </rfc>   
    
