<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="7497"
     submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Rate Problem Statement">Rate Measurement Test Protocol
    Problem Statement and Requirements</title>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>

        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>

        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>

        <uri>http://home.comcast.net/~acmacm/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2015"/>

    <keyword>"Internet access", "Asymmetric Packet Size"</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo presents a problem statement for access rate measurement
      for test protocols to measure IP Performance Metrics (IPPM). Key rate
      measurement test protocol aspects include the ability to control packet
      characteristics on the tested path, such as asymmetric rate and
      asymmetric packet size.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>There are many possible rate measurement scenarios. This memo
      describes one rate measurement problem and presents a rate measurement
      problem statement for test protocols to measure IP Performance Metrics
      (IPPM).</t>

      <t>When selecting a form of access to the Internet, subscribers are
      interested in the performance characteristics of the various
      alternatives. Standardized measurements can be a basis for comparison
      between these alternatives. There is an underlying need to coordinate
      measurements that support such comparisons and to test control protocols
      to fulfill this need. The figure below depicts some typical measurement
      points of access networks.</t>

      <t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ User     /====== Fiber =======  Access Node \
 Device -|------ Copper -------  Access Node -|-- Infrastructure -- GW
 or Host  \------ Radio -------  Access Node / 
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>GW = Gateway</postamble>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>The access rate scenario or use case has received widespread
      attention of Internet-access subscribers and seemingly all
      Internet-industry players, including regulators. This problem is being
      approached with many different measurement methods. The eventual
      protocol solutions to this problem (and the systems that utilize the
      protocol) may not directly involve users, such as when tests reach from
      the infrastructure to a service-specific device, such as a residential
      gateway. However, no aspect of the problem precludes users from
      developing a test protocol controlled via command line interfaces on
      both ends. Thus, a very wide range of test protocols, active measurement
      methods, and system solutions are the possible outcomes of this problem
      statement.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Purpose and Scope">
      <t>The scope and purpose of this memo is to define the measurement
      problem statement for test protocols conducting access rate measurement
      on production networks. Relevant test protocols include <xref
      target="RFC4656"/> and <xref target="RFC5357"/>, but the problem is
      stated in a general way so that it can be addressed by any existing test
      protocol, such as <xref target="RFC6812"/>.</t>

      <t>This memo discusses possible measurement methods but does
      not specify exact methods that would normally be part of the solution.</t>

      <t>We are interested in access measurement scenarios with the following
      characteristics:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The access portion of the network is the focus of this problem
          statement. The user typically subscribes to a service with
          bidirectional access partly described by rates in bits per second.
          The rates may be expressed as raw capacity or restricted capacity,
          as described in <xref target="RFC6703"/>. These are the quantities
          that must be measured according to one or more standard metrics and
          for which measurement methods must also be agreed on as a part of
          the solution.</t>

          <t>Referring to the reference path illustrated below and defined in
          <xref target="RFC7398"/>, possible measurement points include a
          subscriber's host, the access service demarcation point, intra IP
          access (where a globally routable address is present), or the
          gateway between the measured access network and other networks.
          <figure align="center">
              <artwork><![CDATA[Subsc. -- Private -- Private -- Access -- Intra IP -- GRA -- Transit
device     Net #1     Net #2    Demarc.    Access     GW     GRA GW]]></artwork>

              <postamble>GRA = Globally Routable Address, GW =
              Gateway</postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Rates at some links near the edge of the provider's network can
          often be several orders of magnitude less than link rates in the
          aggregation and core portions of the network.</t>

          <t>Asymmetrical access rates on ingress and egress are
          prevalent.</t>

          <t>In many scenarios of interest, services of extremely large-scale access
          require low-complexity devices participating at the user
          end of the path, and those devices place limits on clock and control
          timing accuracy.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This problem statement assumes that the most likely bottleneck device
      or link is adjacent to the remote (user-end) measurement device or is
      within one or two router/switch hops of the remote measurement
      device.</t>

      <t>Other use cases for rate measurement involve situations where the
      packet switching and transport facilities are leased by one operator
      from another, and the link capacity available cannot be directly
      determined (e.g., from device-interface utilization). These scenarios
      could include mobile backhaul, Ethernet service access networks, and/or
      extensions of layer 2 or layer 3 networks. The results of rate
      measurements in such cases could be employed to select alternate
      routing, investigate whether capacity meets some previous agreement,
      and/or adapt the rate of traffic sources if a capacity bottleneck is
      found via the rate measurement. In the case of aggregated leased
      networks, available capacity may also be asymmetric. In these cases, the
      tester is assumed to have a sender and receiver location under their
      control. We refer to this scenario below as the aggregated
      leased-network case.</t>

      <t>This memo describes protocol support for active measurement methods
      consistent with the IPPM working group's traditional charter. Active
      measurements require synthetic traffic streams dedicated to testing and
      do not make measurements on user traffic. See Section 2 of <xref
      target="RFC2679"/>, where the concept of a stream is first introduced in
      IPPM literature as the basis for collecting a sample (defined in Section
      11 of <xref target="RFC2330"/>).</t>

      <t>As noted in <xref target="RFC2330"/>, the focus of access traffic
      management may influence the rate measurement results for some forms of
      access, as it may differ between user and test traffic if the test
      traffic has different characteristics, primarily in terms of the packets
      themselves (see Section 13 of <xref target="RFC2330"/> for the
      considerations on packet type, or Type-P).</t>

      <t>There are several aspects of Type-P where user traffic may be
      examined and selected for special treatment that may affect transmission
      rates. Various aspects of Type-P are known to influence Equal-Cost
      Multipath (ECMP) routing with possible rate measurement variability
      across parallel paths. Without being exhaustive, the possibilities
      include:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Packet length</t>

          <t>IP addresses</t>

          <t>Transport protocol (e.g., where TCP packets may be routed
          differently from UDP)</t>

          <t>Transport-protocol port numbers</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>This issue requires further discussion when specific
      solutions/methods of measurement are proposed; for this problem
      statement, it is sufficient to identify the problem and indicate that
      the solution may require an extremely close emulation of user traffic,
      in terms of one or more factors above.</t>

      <t>Although the user may have multiple instances of network access
      available to them, the primary problem scope is to measure one form of
      access at a time. It is plausible that a solution for the single access
      problem will be applicable to simultaneous measurement of multiple
      access instances, but treatment of this scenario is beyond the current
      scope this document.</t>

      <t>A key consideration is whether or not active measurements will be
      conducted with user traffic present. In-Service testing takes place with
      user traffic present. Out-of-Service testing occurs during pre-service
      assessment or during maintenance that interrupts service temporarily.
      Out-of-Service testing includes activities described as "service
      commissioning", "service activation", and "planned maintenance".
      Opportunistic In-Service testing (when there is no user
  traffic present throughout the test interval, such as outside normal business hours)
  is essentially equivalent to Out-of-Service testing. Both In-Service and
      Out-of-Service testing are within the scope of this problem.</t>

      <t>It is a non-goal to solve the measurement protocol specification
      problem in this memo.</t>

      <t>It is a non-goal to standardize methods of measurement in this memo.
      However, the problem statement mandates support for one category of rate
      measurement methods in the test protocol and adequate control features
      for the methods in the control protocol (assuming the control and test
      protocols are separate).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Active Rate Measurement">
      <t>This section lists features of active measurement methods needed to
      measure access rates in production networks.</t>

      <t>Coordination between source and destination devices through control
      messages and other basic capabilities described in the methods of IPPM
      RFCs <xref target="RFC2679"/> <xref target="RFC2680"/>, and assumed for
      test protocols such as <xref target="RFC5357"/> and <xref
      target="RFC4656"/>, are taken as given.</t>

      <t>Most forms of active testing intrude on user performance to some
      degree, especially In-Service testing. One key tenet of IPPM methods is
      to minimize test traffic effects on user traffic in the production
      network. Section 5 of <xref target="RFC2680"/> lists the problems with
      high measurement traffic rates ("too much" traffic); the most relevant
      for rate measurement is the tendency for measurement traffic to skew the
      results, followed by the possibility of introducing congestion on the
      access link. Section 4 of <xref target="RFC3148"/> provides additional
      considerations. The user of protocols for In-Service testing MUST
      respect these traffic constraints. Obviously, categories of rate
      measurement methods that use less active test traffic than others with
      similar accuracy are preferred for In-Service testing, and the
      specifications of this memo encourage traffic reduction through
      asymmetric control capabilities.</t>

      <t>Out-of-Service tests where the test path shares no links with
      In-Service user traffic, have none of the congestion or skew concerns.
      Both types should address practical matters common to all test efforts,
      such as conducting measurements within a reasonable time from the
      tester's point of view and ensuring that timestamp accuracy is
      consistent with the precision needed for measurement <xref
      target="RFC2330"/>. Out-of-Service tests where some part of the test
      path is shared with In-Service traffic MUST respect the In-Service
      constraints described above.</t>

      <t>The intended metrics to be measured have strong influence over the
      categories of measurement methods required. For example, using the
      terminology of <xref target="RFC5136"/>, it may be possible to measure a
      path capacity metric while In-Service if the level of background (user)
      traffic can be assessed and included in the reported result.</t>

      <t>The measurement architecture MAY be either of one-way (e.g., <xref
      target="RFC4656"/>) or two-way (e.g., <xref target="RFC5357"/>), but the
      scale and complexity aspects of end-user or aggregated access
      measurement clearly favor two-way (with a low-complexity user-end device
      and round-trip results collection, as found in <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>). However, the asymmetric rates of many access
      services mean that the measurement system MUST be able to evaluate
      performance in each direction of transmission. In the two-way
      architecture, both end devices MUST include the ability to launch test
      streams and collect the results of measurements in both (one-way)
      directions of transmission (this requirement is consistent with previous
      protocol specifications, and it is not a unique problem for rate
      measurements).</t>

      <t>The following paragraphs describe features for the roles of test
      packet SENDER, RECEIVER, and results REPORTER.</t>

      <t>SENDER:</t>

      <t>Generate streams of test packets with various characteristics as
      desired (see Section 4). The SENDER MAY be located at the user end of
      the access path or elsewhere in the production network, such as at one
      end of an aggregated leased-network segment.</t>

      <t>RECEIVER:</t>

      <t>Collect streams of test packets with various characteristics (as
      described above), and make the measurements necessary to support rate
      measurement at the receiving end of an access or aggregated
      leased-network segment.</t>

      <t>REPORTER:</t>

      <t>Use information from test packets and local processes to measure
      delivered packet rates and prepare results in the required format (the
      REPORTER role may be combined with another role, most likely the
      SENDER).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Method Categories">
      <t>A protocol that addresses the rate measurement problem MUST serve the
      test stream generation and measurement functions (SENDER and RECEIVER).
      The follow-up phase of analyzing the measurement results to produce a
      report is outside the scope of this problem and memo (REPORTER).</t>

      <t>For the purposes of this problem statement, we categorize the many
      possibilities for rate measurement stream generation as follows:<list
          style="numbers">
          <t>Packet pairs, with fixed intra-pair packet spacing and fixed or
          random time intervals between pairs in a test stream.</t>

          <t>Multiple streams of packet pairs, with a range of intra-pair
          spacing and inter-pair intervals.</t>

          <t>One or more packet ensembles in a test stream, using a fixed
          ensemble size in packets and one or more fixed intra-ensemble packet
          spacings (including zero spacing, meaning that back-to-back burst
          ensembles and constant rate ensembles fall in this category).</t>

          <t>One or more packet chirps (a set of packets with specified
          characteristics), where inter-packet spacing typically decreases
          between adjacent packets in the same chirp and each pair of packets
          represents a rate for testing purposes.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The test protocol SHALL support test packet ensemble generation
      (category 3), as this appears to minimize the demands on measurement
      accuracy. Other stream generation categories are OPTIONAL.</t>

      <t>For all supported categories, the following is a list of additional
      variables that the protocol(s) MUST be able to specify, control, and
      generate:</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>variable payload lengths among packet streams;</t>

          <t>variable length (in packets) among packet streams or
          ensembles;</t>

          <t>variable IP header markings among packet streams;</t>

          <t>choice of UDP transport and variable port numbers, or choice of
          TCP transport and variable port numbers for two-way architectures
          only, or both (see below for additional requirements on TCP
          transport generation); and</t>

          <t>variable number of packet pairs, ensembles, or streams used in a
          test session.</t>
        </list>The ability to revise these variables during an established
      test session is OPTIONAL, as multiple test sessions could serve the same
      purpose. Another OPTIONAL feature is the ability to generate streams
      with VLAN tags and other markings.</t>

      <t>For measurement systems employing TCP as the transport protocol, the
      ability to generate specific stream characteristics requires a sender
      with the ability to establish and prime the connection such that the
      desired stream characteristics are allowed. See <xref target="IPPM-METRICS"/> for more background.</t>

      <t>Beyond a simple connection handshake and the options establishment,
      an "open-loop" TCP sender requires the SENDER ability to:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>generate TCP packets with well-formed headers (all fields valid),
          including Acknowledgement aspects;</t>

          <t>produce packet streams at controlled rates and variable
          inter-packet spacings, including packet ensembles (back-to-back at
          server rate); and</t>

          <t>continue the configured sending stream characteristics despite
          all control indications except receive-window exhaust.</t>
        </list>The corresponding TCP RECEIVER performs normally, having some
      ability to configure the receive window sufficiently large so as to
      allow the SENDER to transmit at will (up to a configured target).</t>

      <t>It may also be useful (for diagnostic purposes) to provide a control
      for the bulk transfer capacity measurement with fully-specified (and
      congestion-controlled) TCP senders and receivers, as envisioned in <xref
      target="RFC3148"/>, but this would be a brute-force assessment, which
      does not follow the conservative tenets of IPPM measurement <xref
      target="RFC2330"/>.</t>

      <t>Measurements for each UDP test packet transferred between SENDER and
      RECEIVER MUST be compliant with the singleton measurement methods
      described in IPPM RFCs <xref target="RFC2679"/><xref target="RFC2680"/>.
      The timestamp information or loss/arrival status for each packet MUST be
      available for communication to the REPORTER function.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Test Protocol Control and Generation Requirements">
      <t>In summary, the test protocol must support the measurement features
      described in the sections above. This requires:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Communicating all test variables to the SENDER and RECEIVER;</t>

          <t>Results collection in a one-way architecture;</t>

          <t>Remote device control for both one-way and two-way architectures;
          and</t>

          <t>Asymmetric packet rates in a two-way measurement architecture, or
          coordinated one-way test capabilities with the same effect
          (asymmetric rates may be achieved through directional control of
          packet rate or packet size).</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The ability to control and generate asymmetric rates in a two-way
      architecture is REQUIRED. Two-way architectures are RECOMMENDED to
      include control and generation capability for both asymmetric and
      symmetric packet sizes because packet size often matters in the scope of
      this problem and test systems SHOULD be equipped to detect directional
      size dependency through comparative measurements.</t>

      <t>Asymmetric packet size control is indicated when the result of a
      measurement may depend on the size of the packets used in each
      direction, i.e., when any of the following conditions hold: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>there is a link in the path with asymmetrical capacity in
          opposite directions (in combination with one or more of the
          conditions below, but their presence or specific details may be
          unknown to the tester);</t>

          <t>there is a link in the path that aggregates (or divides) packets
          into link-level frames and may have a capacity that depends on
          packet size, rate, or timing;</t>

          <t>there is a link in the path where transmission in one direction
          influences performance in the opposite direction;</t>

          <t>there is a device in the path where transmission capacity depends
          on packet header processing capacity (in other words, the capacity
          is sensitive to packet size);</t>

          <t>the target application stream is nominally MTU size packets in
          one direction versus ACK stream in the other (noting that there are
          a vanishing number of symmetrical rate application streams for which
          rate measurement is wanted or interesting but such streams might
          have some relevance at this time);</t>

          <t>the distribution of packet losses is critical to rate
          assessment;</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>and possibly other circumstances revealed by measurements comparing
      streams with symmetrical size and asymmetrical size.</t>

      <t>Implementations may support control and generation for only symmetric
      packet sizes when none of the above conditions hold.</t>

      <t>The test protocol SHOULD enable measurement of the capacity metric
      <xref target="RFC5136"/> either Out-of-Service, In-Service, or both;
      other metrics <xref target="RFC5136"/> are OPTIONAL.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations that apply to any active measurement of
      live networks are relevant here as well. See <xref target="RFC4656"/>
      and <xref target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

      <t>Privacy considerations for measurement systems, particularly when
      Internet users participate in the tests in some way, are described in
      <xref target="LMAP-FRAMEWORK"/>.</t>

      <t>There may be a serious issue if a proprietary service level agreement
      involved with the access network segment provider were somehow leaked in
      the process of rate measurement. To address this, test protocols SHOULD
      NOT convey this information in a way that could be discovered by
      unauthorized parties.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations">


      <t>All forms of testing originate network traffic, either through their
   communications for control and results collection, from dedicated
   measurement packet streams, or from a combination of both types of
   traffic. Testing traffic primarily falls in one of two categories:
      subscriber traffic or network management traffic. There is an ongoing
      need to engineer networks so that various forms of traffic are
      adequately served, and publication of this memo does not change this
      need. Service subscribers and authorized users SHOULD obtain their
      network operator's or service provider's permission before conducting
      tests. Likewise, a service provider or third party SHOULD obtain the
      subscriber's permission to conduct tests, since they might temporarily
      reduce service quality. The protocol SHOULD communicate the permission
      status once the overall system has obtained it, either explicitly or
      through other means.</t>

      <t>Subscribers, their service providers and network operators, and
      sometimes third parties, all seek to measure network performance.
      Capacity testing with active traffic often affects the packet transfer
      performance of streams traversing shared components of the test path, to
      some degree. The degradation can be minimized by scheduling such tests
      infrequently and restricting the amount of measurement traffic required
      to assess capacity metrics. As a result, occasional short-duration
      estimates with minimal traffic are preferred to measurements based on
      frequent file transfers of many megabytes with similar accuracy. New
      measurement methodologies intended for standardization should be
      evaluated individually for potential operational issues. However, the
      scheduled frequency of testing is as important as the methods used (and
      schedules are not typically submitted for standardization).</t>

      <t>The new test protocol feature of asymmetrical packet size generation
      in two-way testing is recommended in this memo. It can appreciably
      reduce the load and packet processing demands of each test and therefore
      reduce the likelihood of degradation in one direction of the tested
      path. Current IETF standardized test protocols (e.g., <xref
      target="RFC5357"/> and <xref target="RFC6812"/>) do not possess the
      asymmetric size generation capability with two-way testing.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>

          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>

        <format octets="4723" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2330"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2330">
        <front>
          <title>Framework for IP Performance Metrics</title>

          <author fullname="V. Paxson" initials="V." surname="Paxson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Almes" initials="G." surname="Almes">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Mahdavi" initials="J." surname="Mahdavi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Mathis" initials="M." surname="Mathis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="1998"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2330"/>

        <format octets="94387" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2679"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2679">
        <front>
          <title>A One-way Delay Metric for IPPM</title>

          <author fullname="G. Almes" initials="G." surname="Almes">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kalidindi" initials="S." surname="Kalidindi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Zekauskas" initials="M." surname="Zekauskas">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="1999"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2679"/>

        <format octets="43542" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2680"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2680">
        <front>
          <title>A One-way Packet Loss Metric for IPPM</title>

          <author fullname="G. Almes" initials="G." surname="Almes">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kalidindi" initials="S." surname="Kalidindi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Zekauskas" initials="M." surname="Zekauskas">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="1999"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2680"/>

        <format octets="32266" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4656"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4656">
        <front>
          <title>A One-way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP)</title>

          <author fullname="S. Shalunov" initials="S." surname="Shalunov">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Teitelbaum" initials="B." surname="Teitelbaum">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Karp" initials="A." surname="Karp">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Boote" initials="J." surname="Boote">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Zekauskas" initials="M." surname="Zekauskas">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2006"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4656"/>

        <format octets="132303" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5357"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5357">
        <front>
          <title>A Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)</title>

          <author fullname="K. Hedayat" initials="K." surname="Hedayat">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Krzanowski" initials="R." surname="Krzanowski">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K. Yum" initials="K." surname="Yum">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Babiarz" initials="J." surname="Babiarz">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2008"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5357"/>

        <format octets="61960" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6703"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6703">
        <front>
          <title>Reporting IP Network Performance Metrics: Different Points of
          View</title>

          <author fullname="A. Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Ramachandran" initials="G."
                  surname="Ramachandran">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Maguluri" initials="G." surname="Maguluri">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2012"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6703"/>

        <format octets="60152" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC3148"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3148">
        <front>
          <title>A Framework for Defining Empirical Bulk Transfer Capacity
          Metrics</title>

          <author fullname="M. Mathis" initials="M." surname="Mathis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Allman" initials="M." surname="Allman">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2001"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3148"/>

        <format octets="36041" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6812"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6812">
        <front>
          <title>Cisco Service-Level Assurance Protocol</title>

          <author fullname="M. Chiba" initials="M." surname="Chiba">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Clemm" initials="A." surname="Clemm">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Medley" initials="S." surname="Medley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Salowey" initials="J." surname="Salowey">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Thombare" initials="S." surname="Thombare">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Yedavalli" initials="E." surname="Yedavalli">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6812"/>

        <format octets="68237" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5136"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5136">
        <front>
          <title>Defining Network Capacity</title>

          <author fullname="P. Chimento" initials="P." surname="Chimento">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Ishac" initials="J." surname="Ishac">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2008"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5136"/>

        <format octets="30682" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <!--draft-ietf-ippm-lmap-path-07: Now RFC 7398 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC7398"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7398">
        <front>
          <title>A Reference Path and Measurement Points for Large-Scale
          Measurement of Broadband Performance</title>

          <author fullname="M. Bagnulo" initials="M." surname="Bagnulo">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Burbridge" initials="T." surname="Burbridge">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Crawford" initials="S." surname="Crawford">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Eardley" initials="P." surname="Eardley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2015"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7398"/>

        <format octets="36938" type="ASCII"/>
      </reference>

      <!--draft-ietf-lmap-framework-10: Updated to draft-ietf-lmap-framework-12-->

      <reference anchor="LMAP-FRAMEWORK">
        <front>
          <title>A framework for Large-Scale Measurement of Broadband
          Performance (LMAP)</title>

          <author fullname="Philip Eardley" initials="P" surname="Eardley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A" surname="Morton">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Marcelo Bagnulo" initials="M" surname="Bagnulo">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Trevor Burbridge" initials="T" surname="Burbridge">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Paul Aitken" initials="P" surname="Aitken">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Aamer Akhter" initials="A" surname="Akhter">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in Progress,"
                    value="draft-ietf-lmap-framework-12"/>
      </reference>

      <!--draft-ietf-ippm-model-based-metrics-03: Updated to draft-ietf-ippm-model-based-metrics-04-->

      <reference anchor="IPPM-METRICS">
        <front>
          <title>Model Based Bulk Performance Metrics</title>

          <author fullname="Matt Mathis" initials="M" surname="Mathis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A" surname="Morton">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in Progress,"
                    value="draft-ietf-ippm-model-based-metrics-04"/>

        
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section numbered="no" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Dave McDysan provided comments and text for the aggregated leased use
      case. Yaakov Stein suggested many considerations to address, including
      the In-Service vs. Out-of-Service distinction and its implication on
      test traffic limits and protocols. Bill Cerveny, Marcelo Bagnulo, Kostas
      Pentikousis (a persistent reviewer), and Joachim Fabini have contributed
      insightful, clarifying comments that made this a better document. Barry
      Constantine also provided suggestions for clarification.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
