<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1035 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6891 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6891.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7525 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7525.xml">
]>

<rfc number="7830" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">

  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EDNS(0) Padding">The EDNS(0) Padding Option</title>

    <author initials="A.M." surname="Mayrhofer"
      fullname="Alexander Mayrhofer">
      <organization>nic.at GmbH</organization>
      <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Karlsplatz 1/2/9</street>
     <city>Vienna</city>
     <code>1010</code>
     <country>Austria</country>
    </postal>
    <email>alex.mayrhofer.ietf@gmail.com</email>
   </address>
   </author>
   
   <date month="April" year="2016"/>
   <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

<keyword>Domain Name System</keyword>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>EDNS</keyword>
<keyword>EDNS0</keyword>
<keyword>Security</keyword>
<keyword>Encryption</keyword>
<keyword>Padding</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>   
	  This document specifies the EDNS(0) "Padding" option, which allows DNS clients and servers to pad request and response messages 
      by a variable number of octets.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	  <t>The <xref target="RFC1035">Domain Name System (DNS)</xref> was specified to transport DNS messages in cleartext form. 
	  Since this can expose significant amounts of information about the Internet activities of an end user, the IETF has 
	  undertaken work to provide confidentiality to DNS transactions (see
	  the DPRIVE working group). Encrypting the DNS transport is 
	  considered one of the options to improve the situation.
	  </t>
	  <t>However, even if both DNS query and response messages were encrypted, metadata could still be used 
	  to correlate such messages with well-known unencrypted messages, hence jeopardizing some of the confidentiality 
	  gained by encryption. One such property is the message size.
	  </t>
	  <t> 
	  This document specifies the Extensions Mechanisms for DNS (EDNS(0))
	  "Padding" option, which allows DNS clients and servers to artificially 
	  increase the size of a DNS message by a variable number of bytes, hampering size-based correlation of the encrypted 
	  message.
	  </t>
	</section>
    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
	  <t>The terms "Requestor" and "Responder" are to be interpreted as specified in <xref target="RFC6891"/>.</t> 
      <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", 
		"NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
	 </section>
	 <section title="The &quot;Padding&quot; Option">
	 <t>
	 The <xref target="RFC6891">EDNS(0)</xref> specifies a mechanism to 
	 include new options in DNS packets, contained in the RDATA of the OPT meta-RR. 
	 This document specifies the "Padding" option in order to allow
	 clients and servers to pad DNS packets by a variable number of bytes. The "Padding" option MUST occur at most, once per OPT meta-RR (and hence, at most once per message).
	 </t>
	 
	 <t>The figure below specifies the structure of the option in the RDATA of 
	 the OPT RR:</t>
	         <figure align="center" anchor="EDNS0_Padding">
          <preamble> </preamble>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
       0                       8                      16
       +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
       |                  OPTION-CODE                  |
       +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
       |                 OPTION-LENGTH                 |
       +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
       |        (PADDING) ...        (PADDING) ...     /
       +-  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
	   <t>The OPTION-CODE for the "Padding" option is 12.</t>
	   <t>The OPTION-LENGTH for the "Padding" option is the size (in octets) of the PADDING. The minimum number of PADDING octets is 0.</t>
	   <t>The PADDING octets SHOULD be set to 0x00.  Other values MAY be used,
  for example, in cases where there is a concern that the padded message could be
  subject to compression before encryption.  PADDING
  octets of any value MUST be accepted in the messages received.</t>
	 </section>
	<section title="Usage Considerations">
	   <t>This document does not specify the actual amount
	   of padding to be used, since this depends on the situation
	   in which the option is used. However, padded DNS messages MUST NOT
	   exceed the number of octets specified in the Requestor's Payload Size field encoded in the RR Class Field (see Sections 6.2.3 and 
	   6.2.4 of <xref target="RFC6891"/>).</t>
	   <t>Responders MUST pad DNS responses when the respective DNS query 
	   included the "Padding" option, unless doing so would violate the maximum UDP payload size.</t>
	   <t>Responders MAY pad DNS responses when the respective DNS query indicated EDNS(0) support of the Requestor and the "Padding" option was not included.</t>
	   <t>Responders MUST NOT pad DNS responses when the respective DNS query did not indicate EDNS(0) support.</t>  
	</section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">

	   <t>IANA has assigned Option Code 12 for "Padding" in the "DNS EDNS0
	   Option Codes (OPT)" registry.</t>
	   <t>IANA has updated the respective registration record 
	   by changing the Reference field to RFC 7830 and the Status field to "Standard". 
	   </t>
	</section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
	  <t>Padding DNS packets obviously increases their size, and will therefore lead to increased traffic.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	  The use of the EDNS(0) padding only provides a benefit when DNS
      packets are not transported in cleartext. Further, it is possible
      that EDNS(0) padding may make DNS amplification attacks easier. Therefore,
      implementations MUST NOT use this option if the DNS transport is not encrypted.
	  </t>
	  <t>Padding length might be affected by lower-level compression. Therefore (as described in Section 3.3 of <xref target='RFC7525'/>), 
	  implementations and deployments SHOULD disable compression at the Transport Layer
	  Security (TLS) level.</t>
	  <t>The payload of the "Padding" option could (like many other fields in the DNS protocol) be used as a covert channel.</t>
	</section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      &rfc1035;
                &rfc2119;
		&rfc6891;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
		&rfc7525;
	</references>
	<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

<t>This document was inspired by a discussion with Daniel Kahn Gillmor during
IETF 93, as an alternative to the proposed padding on the TLS layer. Allison
Mankin, Andreas Gustafsson, Christian Huitema, Jinmei Tatuya, and Shane Kerr suggested text for this document.</t>
	</section>

  </back>
</rfc>
