<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" number="7737" ipr="trust200902" updates="7110"
submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="LSP Ping Reply Mode Simplification">Label Switched Path
    (LSP) Ping and Traceroute Reply Mode Simplification</title>

    <author fullname="Nobo Akiya" initials="N." surname="Akiya">
      <organization>Big Switch Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>nobo.akiya.dev@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Swallow" initials="G." surname="Swallow">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>swallow@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carlos Pignataro" initials="C." surname="Pignataro">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cpignata@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Loa Andersson" initials="L." surname="Andersson">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>loa@mail01.huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2016"/>

    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>
    <keyword>LSP Ping</keyword>
    <keyword>Reply Mode</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Path (LSP)
      Ping and Traceroute use the Reply Mode field to signal the method to be
      used in the MPLS echo reply. This document updates the procedures for
      the "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode. The value of this Reply Mode
      is 5. The update creates a simple way to indicate that the reverse LSP
      should be used as the return path. This document also adds an
      optional TLV that can carry an ordered list of Reply Mode values.</t>

      <t>This document updates RFC 7110.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="INTRO" title="Introduction">
      <t>Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Path (LSP)
      Ping, as described in <xref target="RFC4379"/>, allows an initiator
      Label Switching Router (LSR) to encode instructions (Reply Mode) on
      how a responder LSR should send the response back to the initiator
      LSR. <xref target="RFC7110"/> also allows the initiator LSR to
      encode a TLV (Reply Path TLV) that can instruct the responder LSR
      to use a specific LSP to send the response back to the initiator
      LSR. Both approaches are powerful, as they provide the ability for
      the initiator LSR to control the return path.</t>

      <t>However, it is becoming increasingly difficult for an initiator LSR
      to select a valid return path to encode in the MPLS LSP echo request
      packets. If the initiator LSR does not select a valid return path, the
      MPLS LSP echo reply will not get back to the initiator LSR. This results
      in a false failure of MPLS LSP Ping and Traceroute operations. In an
      effort to minimize such false failures, different implementations have
      chosen different default return path encoding for different LSP types
      and LSP operations. The problem with implementations having different
      default return path encoding is that the MPLS echo reply will not work
      in many cases, and the default value may not be the preferred choice
      of the operators.</t>

      <t>This document describes the following: <list style="symbols">
          <t>In <xref target="_PROB"/>, further description of the
          problems;</t>

          <t>In <xref target="_SOL"/>, a solution to minimize false failures
          while accommodating operator preferences;</t>

          <t>In <xref target="_REL_OTHER"/>, relationships to other LSP
          Ping and Traceroute features;</t>

          <t>In <xref target="_EXAMPLE"/>, examples of scenarios where the
          mechanism described in this document provides benefits.</t>
        </list>This document updates <xref target="RFC7110"/> by allowing the
      usage of the "Reply via Specified Path" (value=5) Reply Mode without
      including the Reply Path TLV. The update creates a simple way to
      indicate that the reverse LSP should be used as the return path.</t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
       target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
     </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_PROB" title="Problem Statements">
      <t>It is becoming increasingly difficult for implementations to
      automatically supply a workable return path encoding for all MPLS LSP
      Ping and Traceroute operations across all LSP types. There are several
      factors that contribute to this complication.
          <list style="symbols">
          <t>Some LSPs have a control channel, and some do not. Some LSPs have
          a reverse LSP, and some do not. Some LSPs have IP reachability in
          the reverse direction, and some do not.</t>

          <t>LSRs on some LSPs can have different available return path(s).
          Available return path(s) can depend on whether the responder LSR is
          a transit LSR or an egress LSR. In the case of a bidirectional LSP,
          available return path(s) on transit LSRs can also depend on whether
          the LSP is completely co-routed, partially co-routed, or associated
          (i.e., the LSPs in the two directions are not co&nbhy;routed).</t>

          <t>MPLS echo request packets may incorrectly terminate on an
          unintended target that can have different available return path(s)
          than the intended target.</t>

          <t>The MPLS LSP Ping operation is expected to terminate on an egress
          LSR. However, MPLS LSP Ping operations with specific TTL values
          and MPLS LSP Traceroute operations can terminate on both transit
          LSR(s) and the egress LSR.</t>
        </list>Except for the case where the responder LSR does not have an IP
      route back to the initiator LSR, it is possible to use the "Reply via an
      IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet" (value=2) Reply Mode value in all cases.
      However, some operators prefer the control channel and a reverse LSP
      as the default return path if they are both available, although this
      is not always the case.</t>

      <t>When specific return path encoding is supplied by users or
      applications, then there are no issues in choosing the return path
      encoding. When specific return path encoding is not supplied by users or
      applications, then implementations use extra logic to compute, and
      sometimes guess, the default return path encodings. If a responder LSR
      receives an MPLS echo request containing return path instructions that
      cannot be accommodated due to unavailability, then the responder LSR
      often drops such packets. This failure mode results in the initiator LSR
      not receiving the intended MPLS LSP echo reply packets. The scenario
      described here is a potentially acceptable result in some failure cases,
      like a broken LSP, where the MPLS echo request terminated on an
      unintended target. However, if the initiator LSR does not receive an
      MPLS echo reply even after the responder LSR receives the MPLS
      echo request and is able to verify the request, information is
      still sent back to the user(s); this is considered a false failure.</t>

      <t>Many operators prefer particular return path(s) over other return
      path(s) for specific LSP types. To accommodate operator-preferred paths,
      implementations may default to operator-preferred return paths for
      particular operations or allow a default return path to be configured.
      It would not be considered beneficial to use a preferred return path for
      an intended target LSR if there is previous knowledge at the initiator
      LSR that the return path is not available. Using an unavailable preferred
      return path would undesirably result in the initiator LSR not receiving
      the MPLS echo return packets. It would be considered beneficial, for
      given operations, if the sender of the MPLS echo request would be able
      to determine return path availability before the operation is
      initiated.</t>

      <t>This document (1) updates the procedures for the "Reply via Specified
      Path" Reply Mode to easily indicate the reverse LSP and (2)&nbsp;adds
      one optional TLV to describe an ordered list of Reply Modes. Based
      on operational needs, the TLV can list multiple Reply Mode values
      in a preferred order to allow the responder LSR to use the first
      available Reply Mode from the list. This eliminates the need for
      the initiator LSR to compute, or sometimes guess, the default
      return path encoding. This new mode of operation would result in
      simplified implementations across the various vendors and improve
      both usability and operational needs.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_SOL" title="Solution">
      <t>This document updates the procedures for the "Reply via
      Specified Path" Reply Mode to easily indicate the reverse LSP.
      This document also adds an optional TLV that can carry an ordered
      list of Reply Modes.</t>

      <section title="&quot;Reply via Specified Path&quot; Reply Mode Update" anchor="reply-via-spec">
        <t>Some LSP types are capable of having a related LSP in the reverse
        direction, through signaling or other association mechanisms. Examples
        of such LSP types are bidirectional Resource Reservation
        Protocol-Traffic Engineering (RSVP-TE) LSPs <xref target="RFC3473"/>
        and MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) LSPs <xref target="RFC5960"/>.
        This document uses the term "reverse LSP" to refer to the LSP in the
        reverse direction of such LSP types. Note that this document restricts
        the scope of "reverse LSP" applicability to those reverse LSPs that
        are capable and allowed to carry the IP encapsulated MPLS echo
        reply.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC7110"/> has defined the Reply Mode "Reply via
        Specified Path", which allows the initiator LSR to instruct the
        responder LSR to send the MPLS echo reply message on the reverse LSP.
        However, the instruction also requires the initiator LSR to include
        the Reply Path TLV with the B bit (Bidirectional bit) set in the
        Flags field. Additionally, <xref target="RFC7110"/> specifies that if
        the "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode is used the Reply Path TLV
        MUST be present.</t>

        <t>This document updates the procedures for the "Reply via
        Specified Path" Reply Mode as follows: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode MAY be used
            without including a Reply Path TLV.</t>

            <t>The usage of the "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode
            without the inclusion of a Reply Path TLV implies the
            reverse LSP. In other words, the usage of the "Reply via
            Specified Path" Reply Mode without the inclusion of a Reply
            Path TLV has the same semantics as the usage of the "Reply via
            Specified Path" Reply Mode with the inclusion of a
            Reply Path TLV with the B&nbsp;bit set in the Flags field.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This document updates the first sentence of
        Section&nbsp;5.1 of <xref target="RFC7110"/> as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>When sending an echo request, in addition to the rules and
            procedures defined in Section&nbsp;4.3 of <xref
            target="RFC4379"/>, the Reply Mode of the
            echo request MUST be set to "Reply via Specified Path",
            and a Reply Path TLV SHOULD be carried in the echo request
            message correspondingly; if the Reply Path TLV is not carried
            in the message, then it indicates the reverse LSP as the
            reply path.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Note that the reverse LSP is in relation to the last
        Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC) specified in the
        Target FEC Stack TLV.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reply Mode Order TLV">
        <t>This document also introduces a new optional TLV to describe a list
        of Reply Mode values. The new TLV will contain one or more Reply Mode
        values in preferred order. The first Reply Mode value is the most
        preferred, and the last Reply Mode value is the least preferred.
        The following rules apply when using the Reply Mode Order TLV: <list
            style="numbers">
            <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV MUST NOT be included in any MPLS echo
            reply. If the initiator LSR receives an MPLS echo reply with the
            Reply Mode Order TLV, the initiator LSR MUST ignore the whole
            Reply Mode Order TLV and MUST only use the value from the Reply
            Mode field of the received MPLS echo reply. It may be beneficial
            for implementations to provide counters and/or logs, with
            appropriate log dampening, to record this error case.</t>

            <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV MAY be included in MPLS echo
            requests.</t>

            <t>The Reply Mode field of an MPLS echo request MUST be set to a
            valid value even when supplying the Reply Mode Order TLV. The
            initiator LSR SHOULD set the Reply Mode field of an MPLS echo
            request to a value that corresponds to a return path that is
            most likely to be available, in case the responder LSR does not
            understand the Reply Mode Order TLV.</t>

            <t>If a responder LSR understands the Reply Mode Order TLV but the
            TLV is not valid (due to the conditions described in
            items&nbsp;6, 7, 8, and 9 below), then the responder LSR MUST
            ignore the whole Reply Mode Order TLV and MUST only use the
            value from the Reply Mode field of the received MPLS echo request.
            It may be beneficial for implementations to provide counters
            and/or logs, with appropriate log dampening, to record this
            error case.</t>

            <t>If a responder LSR understands the Reply Mode Order TLV and the
            TLV is valid, then the responder LSR MUST consider the Reply Mode
            values specified in the TLV and MUST NOT use the value specified
            in the Reply Mode field of the received MPLS echo request. In
            other words, a valid Reply Mode Order TLV overrides the value
            specified in the Reply Mode field of the received MPLS echo
            request.</t>

            <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV MUST contain at least one Reply Mode
            value.</t>

            <t>A Reply Mode value, except for Reply Mode value 5 (Reply via
            Specified Path), MUST NOT be repeated (i.e., MUST NOT appear
            multiple times) in the Reply Mode Order TLV.</t>

            <t>Reply Mode value 5 (Reply via Specified Path) MAY be included
            more than once in the Reply Mode Order TLV. However, in such a
            case, a Reply Path TLV MUST be included for all instances of
            Reply Mode value 5 that are included in the Reply Mode Order TLV.
            In other words, three instances of Reply Mode value 5 in the Reply
            Mode Order TLV will each require a Reply Path TLV.</t>

            <t>The Reply Mode value 1 (Do not reply) MUST NOT be used in the
            Reply Mode Order TLV.</t>
          </list>The responder LSR SHOULD select the first available return
        path in this TLV. The Reply Mode value corresponding to the selected
        return path MUST be set in the Reply Mode field of the MPLS echo
        reply to communicate back to the initiator LSR which return path was
        chosen.</t>

        <t>The format of the TLV is as follows:
    <figure title="Reply Mode Order TLV" anchor="fig1" align="left"> <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Reply Mode Order TLV Type     |          Length               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~ Reply Mode 1  | Reply Mode 2  | Reply Mode 3  | Reply Mode 4  ~
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>This is a variable-length optional TLV. The Reply Mode Order TLV
        Type is 32770.</t>

        <t>The Length field is 2 octets in length. It defines the length, in
        octets, of the list of Reply Mode values.</t>

        <t>Each Reply Mode field is 1 octet, and there is no padding.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_REL_OTHER"
             title="Relationships to Other LSP Ping and Traceroute Features">
      <section title="Backwards Compatibility with &quot;Reply via Specified Path&quot; Reply Mode">
        <t><xref target="RFC7110"/> introduces the "Reply via Specified Path"
        (value=5) Reply Mode. <xref target="RFC7110"/> also specifies
        that if this Reply Mode is used the Reply Path TLV MUST be included.
        This document relaxes the semantics and specifies that this
        Reply Mode MAY be used without the Reply Path TLV. This MAY be
        done to indicate that the reverse LSP SHALL be used as the
        return path. </t>

        <t>If an initiator LSR that sent an MPLS echo request message with
        the "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode but without including the
        Reply Path TLV receives back an MPLS echo reply message with a
        return code of "Malformed echo request received", then the
        initiator LSR SHOULD assume that the responder LSR does not support
        the mechanism defined in this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reply Path TLV">
        <t>A Reply Path TLV <xref target="RFC7110"/> is defined to identify
        a single return path. When the initiator LSR wants to use the Reply
        Mode Order TLV to specify multiple return paths, then the
        initiator LSR SHOULD include multiple "Reply via Specified Path"
        (value=5) Reply Mode values and multiple corresponding
        Reply Path TLV objects (one Reply Path TLV corresponding to a
        "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode and one Reply Path TLV
        identifying a return path).</t>

        <t>As described in <xref target="reply-via-spec"/>, it is valid
        to use the "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode without inclusion
        in a Reply Path TLV. For the Reply Mode Order TLV, it is also
        valid to include a "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode value
        without a corresponding Reply Path TLV; this implies that the
        reverse LSP is the preferred return path. When multiple
        consecutive "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode values are
        included but fewer corresponding Reply Path TLV objects
        exist, the responder LSR SHOULD think that the former "Reply
        via Specified Path" Reply Mode values have corresponding Reply
        Path TLVs.  The latter "Reply via Specified Path" Reply Mode values
        have no corresponding Reply Path TLVs.  For example, if the Reply
        Mode Order TLV carries Reply Modes {5, 5, 5} and only two Reply Path
        TLVs carry FEC X and FEC Y, respectively, then the reply path order
        is as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Reply via Specified Path (FEC X)</t>

            <t>Reply via Specified Path (FEC Y)</t>

            <t>Reply via Specified Path (reverse LSP)</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Example 1: Reply Mode Order TLV Usage with Reply Path TLV">
          <t>If the initiator LSR was interested in encoding the following
          return paths: <list style="numbers">
              <t>Reply via application level control channel</t>

              <t>FEC X</t>

              <t>FEC Y</t>

              <t>Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet</t>
            </list> Then the MPLS echo request message is to carry: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV carrying Reply Modes {4, 5, 5,
              2}</t>

              <t>One Reply Path TLV carrying FEC X</t>

              <t>One Reply Path TLV carrying FEC Y</t>
            </list>
         The encoding specified by the Reply Mode Order TLV and the Reply
         Path TLV in the MPLS echo request message will cause the responder
         LSR to prefer "Reply via application level control channel (4)",
         followed by FEC X, FEC Y, and then "Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP
         packet (2)".</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Example 2: Reply Mode Order TLV Usage with Reply Path TLV">
          <t>If the initiator LSR was interested in encoding the following
          return paths: <list style="numbers">
              <t>Reverse LSP</t>

              <t>Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet</t>

              <t>FEC X</t>

              <t>FEC Y</t>
            </list> Then the MPLS echo request message is to carry: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV carrying Reply Modes
              {5, 2, 5, 5}</t>

              <t>One Reply Path TLV with the B bit set</t>

              <t>One Reply Path TLV carrying FEC X</t>

              <t>One Reply Path TLV carrying FEC Y</t>
            </list>
            The encoding specified by the Reply Mode Order TLV and the Reply
            Path TLV in the MPLS echo request message will cause the
            responder LSR to prefer the reverse LSP, followed by
            "Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet (2)", FEC X, and then FEC Y.
            </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Proxy LSP Ping">
        <t>The mechanism defined in this document will work with Proxy LSP
        Ping as defined by <xref target="RFC7555"/>. The MPLS proxy ping
        request message can carry a Reply Mode value in the header and one
        or more Reply Mode values in the Reply Mode Order TLV. It is
        RECOMMENDED that Reply Mode 2 (Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet)
        be used in the Reply Mode field of the MPLS proxy ping request
        message.</t>

        <section title="Proxy LSR Sending an MPLS Echo Request">
          <t>If the proxy LSR is sending an MPLS echo request, then the proxy
          LSR MUST copy the following elements from the MPLS proxy ping
          request message to the MPLS echo request message:
        <list style="symbols">
              <t>The Reply Mode field.</t>

              <t>The Reply Mode Order TLV.</t>

              <t>The Reply Path TLV(s). If there is more than one Reply Path
              TLV, then the ordering of the TLVs MUST be preserved when
              copying.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Proxy LSR Sending an MPLS Proxy Ping Reply">
          <t>If the proxy LSR is sending an MPLS proxy ping reply, then it is
          RECOMMENDED that the Reply Mode Order TLV be ignored and the Reply
          Mode field in the MPLS proxy ping request message be used.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations specified in <xref target="RFC4379"/>
      and <xref target="RFC7110"/> also apply for this document.</t>

      <t>In addition, this document introduces the Reply Mode Order TLV. It
      provides a new way for an unauthorized source to gather more network
      information, especially information regarding the potential return
      path(s) of an LSP. To protect against unauthorized sources using MPLS
      echo request messages with the Reply Mode Order TLV to obtain network
      information, as also specified in <xref target="RFC4379"/>, it is
      RECOMMENDED that implementations provide a means of checking the
      source addresses of MPLS echo request messages against an access list
      before accepting the message.</t>

      <t>Another potential security issue is that the MPLS echo request and
      reply messages are not encrypted; the contents of the MPLS echo request
      and reply messages may therefore be potentially exposed. Although the
      exposure is within the MPLS domain, if such exposure is a concern,
      some encryption mechanisms <xref target="MPLS-OPP-ENCR"/> may be
      employed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability Considerations">
      <t><xref target="_PROB"/> described problems that increase complexity
      with respect to operations and implementations. In order to simplify
      operations and to allow LSP Ping and Traceroute to function
      efficiently whilst preserving code simplicity, it is RECOMMENDED
      that implementations allow devices to have configuration options to set
      operator-preferred Reply Modes. For example: <list style="symbols">
          <t>For those operators who are more interested in MPLS echo reply
          packets reaching the initiator LSR: <list style="numbers">
              <t>Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet (2)</t>

              <t>Reply via application level control channel (4)</t>

              <t>Reply via Specified Path (5)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>For those operators who are more interested in MPLS echo reply
          packets testing the paths related to the forward LSP: <list
              style="numbers">
              <t>Reply via Specified Path (5)</t>

              <t>Reply via application level control channel (4)</t>

              <t>Reply via an IPv4/IPv6 UDP packet (2)</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="New Reply Mode Order TLV">
        <t>IANA has assigned a new TLV type value from the "TLVs"
        sub&nbhy;registry within the "Multiprotocol Label Switching
        Architecture (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters"
        registry, for the Reply Mode Order TLV.</t>

        <t>The new TLV Type value has been assigned from the range
        32768&nbhy;49161, as specified in Sections&nbsp;3 and
        7.2 of <xref target="RFC4379"/>; this range is for optional
        TLVs that can be silently dropped if not recognized.

       <figure align="left"> <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  Type    Meaning                            Reference
  -----   -------                            ---------
  32770   Reply Mode Order TLV               RFC 7737
]]></artwork>  </figure>
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4379"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7110"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7555"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5960"?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3473'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-mpls-opportunistic-encrypt (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='MPLS-OPP-ENCR'>
<front>
<title>Opportunistic Security in MPLS Networks</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Farrel' fullname='Adrian Farrel'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Farrell' fullname='Stephen Farrell'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-mpls-opportunistic-encrypt-00' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="_EXAMPLE"
             title="Reply Mode Order TLV Beneficial Scenarios">
      <t>This section lists examples of how the Reply Mode Order TLV can
      be beneficial.</t>

      <section title="Incorrect Forwarding Scenario">
        <t>As shown in <xref target="fig2"/>, a network has an LSP with
        the forwarding path A-B-C-D-E. The LSP has a control channel.</t>

      <t><figure align="left" title="Incorrect Forwarding" anchor="fig2">
     <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                   A------B------C------D------E
                                        |
                                        |
                                        F

                   Forward Path: A-B-C-D-E
]]></artwork> </figure>

        If D is incorrectly label switching to F (instead of E), then
        LSP Traceroute with "Reply via application level
        control channel (4)" will result in the following:
         <list style="empty">
            <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

            <t>Success (Reply from B)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply from C)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply from D)</t>

            <t>Timeout...</t>

            <t>Complete</t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>This is because F does not have a
        control channel on which to send the MPLS echo reply message.
        With the extensions described in this document, the same
        procedures can be performed with the Reply Mode Order TLV
        carrying {4, 2}. When LSP Traceroute is issued, then the
        following output may be displayed without any unnecessary
        timeout: <list style="empty">
            <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

            <t>Success (Reply from B, Reply Mode: 4)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply from C, Reply Mode: 4)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply from D, Reply Mode: 4)</t>

            <t>FEC Mismatch (Reply from F, Reply Mode: 2)</t>

            <t>Complete</t>
          </list><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>The result provides more diagnostic
        information to the initiator LSR, and without any delay (i.e., timeout
        from one or more downstream LSRs).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Non-Co-Routed Bidirectional LSP Scenario">
        <t>As shown in <xref target="fig3"/>, a network has a
        bidirectional LSP where the forward LSP and the reverse LSP are not
        fully co-routed.

        <figure align="left" title="Non-Co-Routed Bidirectional LSP"
         anchor="fig3"> <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                        +----C------D----+
                       /                  \
               A------B                    G------H
                       \                  /
                        +----E------F----+

               Forward Path: A-B-C-D-G-H (upper path)
               Reverse Path: H-G-F-E-B-A (lower path)]]></artwork> </figure>

        Some operators may prefer and configure "Reply via Specified Path" as
        the default Reply Mode but without including the Reply Path TLV, to
        indicate that the reverse LSP is used as the return path when MPLS
        echo request messages are sent on bidirectional LSPs. Without the
        extensions described in this document, the following behaviors
        will be seen: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>When LSP Ping is issued from A, the reply will come back on the
            reverse LSP from H.</t>

            <t>When LSP Traceroute is issued from A, the replies will come
            back on the reverse LSP from B, G, and H but will encounter a
            timeout from C and D, as there are no reverse LSPs on those
            nodes.</t>

            <t>When LSP Ping with a specific TTL value is issued from A,
            whether a timeout will be encountered depends on the value
            of the TTL used (i.e., whether or not the MPLS echo request
            terminates on a node that has a reverse LSP).</t>
          </list>One can argue that the initiator LSR can automatically
        generate the same MPLS echo request with a different Reply Mode
        value to those nodes that time out. However, such a mechanism
        will result in an extended time for the entire operation to
        complete (i.e., multiple seconds to multiple minutes). This is
        undesirable, and perhaps unacceptable if the "user" is an
        application.</t>

        <t>With the extensions described in this document, the same
        procedures can be performed with the Reply Mode Order TLV carrying
        {5, 2}. &nbsp;When LSP Traceroute is issued, then the following output
        may be displayed without any unnecessary timeout: <list style="empty">
            <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

            <t>Success (Reply Mode: 5)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply Mode: 2)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply Mode: 2)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply Mode: 5)</t>

            <t>Success (Reply Mode: 5)</t>

            <t>Complete</t>
          </list><?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>
      The authors especially thank Tom Taylor, who passed away close to
      the time of publication of this RFC. Tom did a careful review of
      the document and provided useful comments.
      </t>

      <t>The authors would also like to thank Santiago Alvarez and
      Faisal Iqbal for discussions that motivated the creation of
      this document; Sam Aldrin, Curtis Villamizar, Ross Callon,
      Jeffrey Zhang, Jeremy Whittaker, Mustapha Alissaoui, Qin Wu,
      Jie Dong, and Adrian Farrel for providing valuable comments
      that influenced the content of the document; and Dan Frost,
      Victor Kuarsingh, and Deborah Brungard for reviewing the document
      and providing useful comments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
     <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Shaleen Saxena
Brocade

Email: ssaxena@brocade.com]]></artwork></figure>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
