<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC7841 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7841.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6949 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6949.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4845 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4845.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6635 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6635.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7322 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7749 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7749.xml">

]>

<rfc submissionType="IAB" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="7990" category="info">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>


  <front>


    <title abbrev="RFC Format Framework">RFC Format Framework</title>


    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rse@rfc-editor.org</email>
        <uri>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2647-2220</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" month="November"/>
    
    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Architecture Board</workgroup>

<keyword>Format</keyword>


    <abstract>
<t>
In order to improve the readability of RFCs while supporting their
archivability, the canonical format of the RFC Series will be transitioning
from plain-text ASCII to XML using the xml2rfc version 3 vocabulary; different
publication formats will be rendered from that base document.  With these
changes comes an increase in complexity for authors, consumers, and the
publisher of RFCs. This document serves as the framework that provides the
problem statement, lays out a road map of the documents that capture the
specific requirements, and describes the transition plan. 
</t>


    </abstract>






  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>"RFC Series Format Requirements and Future Development" <xref
target="RFC6949"/> discusses the need to improve the display of items such as
author names and artwork in RFCs as well as the need to improve the ability of
RFCs to be displayed properly on various devices.  Based on the discussions
with communities of interest, such as the IETF, the RFC Series Editor decided
to explore a change to the format of the Series <xref target="XML-ANNOUNCE"/>.
This document serves as the framework that describes the problems being solved
and summarizes the documents created to-date that capture the specific
requirements for each aspect of the change in format.  </t> 

<t>Key changes to the publication of RFCs are highlighted, and a transition
plan that will take the Series from a plain text, ASCII-only format to the new formats is described on the rfc-interest mailing list <xref target="RFC-INTEREST"/>.</t>

<t>This document is concerned with the production of RFCs, focusing on the published formats. It does not address any changes to the processes each stream uses to develop and review their submissions (specifically, how Internet-Drafts will be developed).  While I-Ds have a similar set of issues and concerns, directly addressing those issues for I-Ds will be discussed within each document stream.</t>

<t>The details described in this document are expected to change based on
experience gained in implementing the new publication toolsets.  
Revised documents
will be published capturing those changes as the toolsets are completed. Other
implementers must not expect those changes to remain backwards compatible with
the details described in this document.</t> 


</section>
<section anchor="problem-statement" title="Problem Statement">


<t>There are nearly three billion people connected to the Internet <xref
target="ISTATS"/> and individuals from at least 45 countries have regularly
attended IETF meetings over the last five years.  The Internet is now global,
and while the world has changed from when the first RFCs were published, the
Series remains critical to defining protocols, standards, best practices, and
more for this global network that continues to grow.  In order to make RFCs
easily viewable to the largest number of people possible, across a wide array
of devices, and to respect the diversity of authors and reference materials
while still recognizing the archival aspects of the Series, it is time to
update the tightly prescribed format of the RFC Series.</t> 

<t>All changes to the format of the RFC Series must be made with consideration
to the requirements of a wide set of communities over an extended length of
time.  Examples of the preferences and specific needs are those of existing
authors and implementers, lawyers that argue Intellectual Property Rights
(IPR), educators, managers, and policymakers that need to know what to list in
potential Request for Proposals (RFPs) for their organizations.  The immediate needs of today's communities must be balanced with the needs for long-term archival storage.  </t>

</section>
<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

<t>This document uses terminology from RFC 6949, repeated below for convenience.</t>
<!--Begin DNE text from RFC 6949 -->

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>ASCII: Coded Character Set - 7-bit American Standard Code for Information Interchange, ANSI X3.4-1986 <xref target="ASCII" /></t>

</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Canonical format: the authorized, recognized, accepted, and archived version of the document</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Metadata: information associated with a document so as to provide, for example, definitions of its structure, or of elements within the document such as its topic or author</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Publication format: display and distribution format as it may be read or printed after the publication process has completed</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Reflowable text: text that automatically wraps to the next line in a document as the user moves the margins of the text, either by resizing the window or changing the font size</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Revisable format: the format that will provide the information for conversion into a Publication format; it is used or created by the RFC Editor</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style='empty'>
  <t>Submission format: the format submitted to the RFC Editor for editorial revision and publication</t>
</list></t>
<!--End DNE text from RFC 6949 -->
</section>


<section anchor="overview-of-the-decision-making-process" title="Overview of the Decision-Making Process">

<t>Requirements, use cases, concerns, and suggestions were collected from the
communities of interest at every stage of the project to update the RFC format.
Input was received through the rfc-interest mailing list, as well as in
several face-to-face sessions at IETF meetings.  Regular conversations were
held with the Chairs of the IETF, IRTF, IAB, and IAOC as well as the
Independent Stream Editor to discuss high-level stream requirements.  Updates
regarding the status of the project were provided to the IETF community during
the IETF Technical Plenary as well as Format BoFs or IAB sessions at several
IETF meetings <xref target="IETF84"/> <xref target="IETF85"/> <xref
target="IETF88"/> <xref target="IETF89"/> <xref target="IETF90"/>. </t> 

<t>The output from the first year of discussion on the topic of RFC format was
published as RFC 6949, which provided the first solid documentation on 
the requirements for the Series.  RFC 6949 is a product of the IAB stream
(following the process described in "Process for Publication of IAB RFCs"
<xref target="RFC4845"/>).  This is also the case with all of the RFCs that
informed the format update work.</t> 

<t>After the high-level requirements were published, the RFC Series Editor
(RSE) brought together an RFC Format Design Team to start working out the
necessary details to develop the code needed to create new and changed
formats. The Design Team discussed moving away from the existing xml2rfc
vocabulary, but with such a strong existing support base within the community
and no clear value with other XML vocabularies or schemas, the decision was
made to work with the xml2rfc version 2 (xml2rfc v2) <xref target="RFC7749" />
model and use it as the base for the new format environment. Part of this
discussion included a decision to stop using an XML document type definition
(DTD) in favor of a Regular Language for XML Next General (RELAX NG) model
using a defined vocabulary. While the biweekly calls for this team were
limited to Design Team members, review of the decisions as documented in the
documents produced by this team was done publicly through requests for
feedback on the rfc-interest mailing list.  Several of the documents produced
by the Design Team, including those on xml2rfc v2 <xref target="RFC7749"/> and v3 <xref
target="RFC7991" /> and the SVG profile <xref target="RFC7996" />, were sent through an early GenART
review <xref target="GEN-ART"/> before starting the process to be accepted by
the IAB stream.</t> 


<t>While the IETF community provided the majority of input on the process,
additional outreach opportunities were sought to gain input from an even
broader audience.  
Informal discussions were held with participants at several
International Association of Scientific, Technical, and Medical Publisher
events <xref target="STM"/>, and presentations made at technical conferences such as the TERENA
Networking Conference 2014 <xref target="TNC2014"/> and NORDUnet 2014 <xref
target="NDN2014"/>.</t> 

<t>In order to respond to concerns regarding responses to subpoenas and to understand the legal requirements, advice was requested from the IETF Trust legal team regarding what format or formats would be considered reasonable when responding to a subpoena request for an RFC.</t>

<t>Given that several other standards development organizations (SDOs) do not
offer plain-text documents, and in fact may offer more than one format for
their standards, informal input was sought from them regarding their
experience with supporting one or more non-plain-text formats for their
standards.</t> 

<t>Finally, the entire process was reviewed regularly with the RFC Series Oversight Committee <xref target="RSOC"/> and regular updates provided to the IAB and IESG. They have offered support and input throughout the process.</t>

<t>Where consensus was not reached during the process, the RSE made any necessary final decisions, as per the guidance in "RFC Editor Model (Version 2)" <xref target="RFC6635"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="key-changes" title="Key Changes">

<t>At the highest level, the changes being made to the RFC format involve
breaking away from solely ASCII plain text and moving to a canonical format
that includes all the information required for rendering a document into a
wide variety of publication formats.  The RFC Editor will become responsible
for more than just the plain-text file and the PDF-from-text format created at
time of publication; the RFC Editor will be creating several different formats
in order to meet the diverse requirements of the community.</t> 

<t>The final XML file produced by the RFC Editor will be considered the
canonical format for RFCs; it is the lowest common denominator that holds all
the information intended for an RFC.  PDF/A-3 will be the publication format
offered in response to subpoenas for RFCs published through this new process
and will be developed with an eye towards long-term archival storage.  HTML
will be the focus of providing the most flexible set of features for an RFC,
including JavaScript to provide pointers to errata and other metadata.
Plain text will continue to be offered in order to support existing tool
chains, where practicable, and the individuals who prefer to read RFCs in this
format.</t> 


</section>

<section anchor="canonical-format-documents" title="Canonical Format Documents">
<section anchor="xml" title="XML for RFCs">

<t>Key points regarding the XML format:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>The canonical format for RFCs is XML using the xml2rfc version 3 (xml2rfc v3) vocabulary.  The XML file must contain all information necessary to render a variety of formats; any question about what was intended in the publication will be answered from this format.</t>
  <t>Authors may submit documents using the xml2rfc v2 vocabulary, but the final publication will be converted to use the xml2rfc v3 vocabulary.</t>
  <t>SVG is supported and will be embedded in the final XML file.</t>
  <t>There will be automatically generated identifiers for sections, paragraphs, figures, and tables in the final XML file.</t>
  <t>The XML file will not contain any xml2rfc v3 vocabulary elements or attributes that have been marked deprecated. </t>
  <t>A DTD will no longer be used. The grammar will be defined using RELAX NG
  <xref target="RNC"/>.
</t>
  <t>The final XML file will contain, verbatim, the appropriate boilerplate as applicable at time of publication specified by RFC 7841  <xref target="RFC7841"/> or its successors.</t>

  <t>The final XML will be self-contained with all the information known at publication time. For instance, all features that reference externally defined input will be expanded. This includes all uses of xinclude, src attributes (such as in &lt;artwork&gt; or &lt;sourcecode&gt; elements), include-like processing instructions, and externally defined entities.</t>
  <t>The final XML will not contain comments or processing instructions.</t>
  <t>The final XML will not contain src attributes for &lt;artwork&gt; or 
&lt;sourcecode&gt; elements.</t>
</list></t>

<t><xref target="RFC7749"/> describes the xml2rfc v2 vocabulary.  While in
wide use at the time of writing, this vocabulary had not been formally
documented prior to the publication of RFC 7749.  In order to understand what
needed to change in the vocabulary to allow for a more simple experience and
additional features for authors, the current vocabulary needed to be fully
described.  RFC 7749 will be obsoleted by <xref target="RFC7991" />.</t> 

<t><xref target="RFC7991"/> describes the xml2rfc v3 vocabulary.  The design
goals were to make the vocabulary more intuitive for authors and to expand the
features to support the changes being made in the publication process.  It 
obsoletes RFC 7749.</t> 

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="publication-format-documents" title="Publication Format Documents">

<section anchor="html" title="HTML">
<t><xref target="RFC7992"/> describes the semantic HTML that will be produced by the RFC Editor from the xml2rfc v3 files.</t>

<t>Key points regarding the HTML output:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>The HTML will be rendered from the XML file; it will not be derived from the plain-text publication format.</t>
  <t>The body of the document will use a subset of HTML. The documents will include Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) for default visual presentation; it can be overwritten by a local CSS file.</t> 
  <t>SVG is supported and will be included in the HTML file.</t>
  <t>Text will be reflowable.</t>
  <t>JavaScript will be supported on a limited basis.  It will not be permitted to overwrite or change any text present in the rendered HTML.  It may, on a limited basis, add text that provides post-publication metadata or pointers, if warranted.  All such text will be clearly marked as additional.</t>
</list></t>


</section>
<section anchor="pdf" title="PDF">
<t><xref target="RFC7995"/> describes the tags and profiles that will be used to create the new PDF format, including both the internal structure and the visible layout of the file.  A review of the different versions of PDF is offered, with a recommendation of what PDF standard should apply to RFCs.</t>

<t>Key points regarding the PDF output:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>The PDF file will be rendered from the XML file; it will not be derived from the plain-text publication format.</t>
  <t>The PDF publication format will conform to the PDF/A-3 standard and will embed the canonical XML source.</t>
  <t>The PDF will look more like the HTML publication format than the plain-text publication format.</t>
  <t>The PDF will include a rich set of tags and metadata within the document.</t>
  <t>SVG is supported and will be included in the PDF file.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="plaintext" title="Plain Text">
<t><xref target="RFC7994"/> describes the details of the plain-text format; in particular, it focuses on what is changing from the existing plain-text output.</t>

<t>Key points regarding the plain-text output:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>The plain-text document will no longer be the canonical version of an RFC.
  </t>
  <t>The plain-text format will be UTF-8 encoded; non-ASCII characters will be allowed.</t>
  <t>A Byte Order Mark (BOM) will be added at the start of each file.</t>
  <t>Widow and orphan control <xref target="TYPOGRAPHY"/> for the plain-text publication format will not have priority for the developers creating the rendering code.</t>
  <t>Authors may choose to have pointers to line art in other publication formats in place of ASCII art in the .txt file.</t>
  <t>An unpaginated plain-text file will be created.</t>
  <t>Running headers and footers will not be used.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="potential-future-publication-formats" title="Potential Future Publication Formats">

<section anchor="epub" title="EPUB"> 
<t>This format is intended for use by ebook readers and will be available for
RFCs after the requirements have been defined.  No document on this topic is
currently available.</t> 

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="figures-and-artwork" title="Figures and Artwork">

<section anchor="svg" title="SVG">
<t><xref target="RFC7996"/> describes the profile for SVG line art.  SVG is an XML-based vocabulary for creating line drawings; SVG information will be embedded within the canonical XML at the time of publication.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="content-and-page-layout" title="Content and Page Layout">

<section anchor="non-ascii-characters" title="Non-ASCII Characters">
<t>There are security and readability implications to moving outside the ASCII range of characters.  <xref target="RFC7997"/> focuses on exactly where and how non-ASCII characters may be used in an RFC, with an eye towards keeping the documents as secure and readable as possible, given the information that needs to be expressed.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="style-guide" title="Style Guide">
<t>The RFC Style Guide <xref target="RFC7322"/> was revised to remove as much page formatting information as possible, focusing instead on grammar, structure, and content of RFCs.  Some of the changes recommended, however, informed the XML v3 vocabulary.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="css-requirements" title="CSS Requirements">
<t><xref target="RFC7993"/> describes how the CSS classes mentioned in "HyperText Markup Language Request for Comments Format" should be used to create an accessible and responsive design for the HTML format.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="transition-plan" title="Transition Plan">

<section anchor="tooldev-phase" title="Statement of Work and RFP for Tool Development">
<t>Existing tools for the creation of RFCs will need to be updated, and new
tools created, to implement the updated format.  As the requirements-gathering
effort, described in the various documents described earlier in this document,
finishes the bulk of the work, the Tools Development Team of the IETF will
work with the RSE to develop Statements of Work (SoWs).  Those SoWs will first
be reviewed within the Tools Development Team and the Tools Management Committee,
and it will then go out for a public comment period.  After public review, the SoWs will be
attached to an RFP and posted as per the IETF Administrative Support Activity
(IASA) bid process <xref target="IASA-RFP"/>.</t> 

<t>Once bids have been received, reviewed, and awarded, coding will begin.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="testing-phase" title="Testing and Transition">

<t>   During the I-D review and approval process, authors and stream-approving bodies will select drafts to run through the proposed new
   publication process.  The RFC Editor will process these documents
   after they have been approved for publication using xml2rfc v2 and
   will simultaneously test the selected I-Ds with the xml2rfc v3
   process and tools.
While the final RFCs published during this time will
continue as plain text and immutable once published, the feedback process is
necessary to bootstrap initial testing.  These early tests will target finding
issues with the proposed xml2rfc v3 vocabulary that result in poorly formed
publication formats as well as issues that prevent proper review of submitted
documents.</t> 

<t>Feedback will result in regular iteration of the basic code and XML
vocabulary.  In order to limit the amount of time the RFC Production Center
(RPC) spends on testing and quality assurance (QA), their priority will be to edit and publish
documents; therefore, community assistance will be necessary to help move this
stage along.  A mailing list and experimental source directory on the RFC
Editor website will be created for community members willing to assist in the
detailed review of the XML and publication formats.  Editorial checks of the
publication formats by the community are out of scope; the focus will be the
QA of each available output, checking for inconsistencies across formats.</t> 

<t>The purpose of the testing phase is to work with the community to identify and fix bugs in the process and the code before producing canonical, immutable XML, and to collect additional feedback on the usability of the new publication formats.</t>

<t>Any modifications to the document review process, up to and including AUTH48, will happen with the community and the stream-approving bodies as we learn more about the features and outputs of the new publication tools. Defining those processes is out of scope for this document.</t>

<t>Success will be measured by the closure of all bugs 
identified by the RPC and the Tools Development Team as fatal in addition to reaching
rough consensus with the community on the readiness of the XML vocabulary 
and final output files for publication.  The actual rendering engine can go 
through further review and iteration, as the publication formats may be 
republished as needed.</t>

<t>Authors are not required to submit their approved drafts to the RFC Editor
in an XML format, though they are strongly encouraged to do so; plain text
will also remain an option for the foreseeable future.  However, documents
submitted as plain text cannot include such features as SVG artwork. The RPC
will generate an XML file if necessary for basic processing and subsequent
rendering into the approved output formats.</t> 

<t>A known risk at this point of the transition is the difficulty in
quantifying the resources required from the RPC.  This phase will require more
work on the part of the RPC to support both old and new publication processes
for at least six months. There is potential for confusion as consumers of
RFCs find some documents published at this time with a full set of outputs,
while older documents only have plain text.  There may be a delay in
publication as new bugs are found that must be fixed before the files can be
converted into the canonical format and associated publication formats.</t> 


</section>
<section anchor="completion" title="Completion">
<t>Authors may submit XML (preferred) or plain-text files.  The XML files submitted for publication will be converted to canonical XML format and published with all available publication formats.  All authors will be expected to review the final documents as consistent with the evolving procedures for reviewing documents.</t>

<t>Success for this phase will be measured by a solid understanding by the RSE and the IAOC of the necessary costs and resources required for long-term support of the new format model.</t>

</section>
</section>


<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>Changing the format for RFCs involves modifying a great number of components to publication.  Understanding those changes and the implications for the entire tool chain is critical so as to avoid unintended bugs that would allow unintended changes to text.  Unintended changes to text could in turn corrupt a standard, practice, or critical piece of information about a protocol.</t>

</section>



  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC6949;
&RFC7749;
<!--&I-D.iab-xml2rfc; Companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7991' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7991'>
<front>
<title>The "xml2rfc" Version 3 Vocabulary</title>

<author initials='P' surname='Hoffman' fullname='Paul E. Hoffman'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This document defines the "xml2rfc" version 3 vocabulary: an XML- based language used for writing RFCs and Internet-Drafts.  It is heavily derived from the version 2 vocabulary that is also under discussion.  This document obsoletes the v2 grammar described in RFC 2629 and its followup, RFC 7749.  Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)  Discussion of this draft takes place on the rfc-interest mailing list (rfc-interest@rfc-editor.org), which has its home page at &lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/mailman/listinfo/rfc-interest>.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7991' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7991"/>
</reference>


<!--&I-D.iab-html-rfc; Companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7992' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc792'>
<front>
<title>HyperText Markup Language Request for Comments Format</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Hildebrand' fullname='Joe Hildebrand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Hoffman' fullname='Paul E. Hoffman'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>In order to meet the evolving needs of the Internet community,
the format for RFCs is changing from a plain text, ASCII-only format to a canonical XML format that will in turn be rendered into several publication formats.  This document defines the HTML format that will be rendered for an RFC or Internet-Draft.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7992' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7992"/>

</reference>




<!--&I-D.iab-rfc-css; companion doc-->

<reference anchor='RFC7993' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7993'>
<front>
<title>Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) Requirements for RFCs</title>

<author initials='H' surname='Flanagan' fullname='Heather Flanagan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>The HTML format for RFCs, described in [I-D.iab-html-rfc] assigns style guidance to an RFC Editor-defined Cascading Style Sheet (CSS). The embedded, default CSS as included by the RFC Editor is expected to take into account accessibility needs and be built along a responsive design model.  This document describes the requirements for the default CSS used by the RFC Editor.  The class names are based on the classes defined in draft-iab-html-rfc.  Discussion of this draft takes place on the rfc-interest mailing list (rfc-interest@rfc-editor.org), which has its home page at https://www.rfc-editor.org/mailman/listinfo/rfc-interest.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7993' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7993"/>
</reference>



<!--&I-D.iab-rfc-plaintext; companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7994' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7994'>
<front>
<title>Requirements for Plain-Text RFCs</title>

<author initials='H' surname='Flanagan' fullname='Heather Flanagan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>In 2013, after a great deal of community discussion, the decision was made to shift from the plain-text, ASCII-only canonical format for RFCs to XML as the canonical format with more human-readable formats rendered from that XML.  The high-level requirements that informed this change were defined in RFC6949, "RFC Series Format Requirements and Future Development."  Plain text remains an important format for many in the IETF community, and will be one of the publication formats rendered from the XML.  This draft documents the rendering requirements for the plain-text RFC publication format.  These requirements do not apply to plain-text RFCs published before the format transition.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7994' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7994"/>
</reference>


<!--&I-D.iab-rfc-use-of-pdf;companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7995' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7995'>
<front>
<title>PDF for an RFC Series Output Document Format</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Hansen' fullname='Tony Hansen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Hardy' fullname='Matthew Hardy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This document discusses options and requirements for the PDF rendering of RFCs in the RFC Series, as outlined in RFC 6949.  It also discusses the use of PDF for Internet-Drafts, and available or needed software tools for producing and working with PDF.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7995' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7995"/>
</reference>

<!--&I-D.iab-svg-rfc; Companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7996' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7996'>
<front>
<title>SVG Drawings for RFCs: SVG 1.2 RFC</title>

<author initials='N' surname='Brownlee' fullname='Nevil Brownlee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>.  Maybe the text in section This document specifies SVG 1.2 RFC - an SVG profile for use in diagrams that may appear in RFCs - and considers some of the issues concerning the creation and use of such diagrams.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7996' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7996"/>

</reference>


<!--&I-D.iab-rfc-nonascii; companion document-->

<reference anchor='RFC7997' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7997'>
<front>
<title>The Use of Non-ASCII Characters in RFCs</title>

<author initials='H' surname='Flanagan' fullname='Heather Flanagan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>In order to support the internationalization of protocols and a more diverse Internet community, the RFC Series must evolve to allow for the use of non-ASCII characters in RFCs.  While English remains the required language of the Series, the encoding of future RFCs will be in UTF-8, allowing for a broader range of characters than typically used in the English language.  This document describes the RFC Editor requirements and guidance regarding the use of non-ASCII characters in RFCs.  This document updates RFC 7322.  Please review the PDF version of this draft.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7997' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7997"/>
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

&RFC4845;

&RFC6635;
&RFC7322;

&RFC7841;

<reference anchor="ASCII">
<front>
<title>Coded Character Set - 7-bit American Standard Code for Information Interchange</title>
<author>
<organization>American National Standards Institute</organization>
</author>
<date month="" year="1986" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ANSI" value="X3.4-1986" />

</reference>


<reference anchor="GEN-ART" target="http://www.ietf.org/iesg/directorate/gen-art.html">
  <front>
    <title>General Area Review Team (Gen-ART)</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IETF</organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="IASA-RFP" target="http://iaoc.ietf.org/rfps-rfis.html">
  <front>
    <title>RFPs and RFIs</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IETF Administrative Support Activity</organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="IETF84" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/84/rfcform.html">
  <front>
    <title>IETF 84 Proceedings: RFC Format (rfcform)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2012"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="IETF85" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/85/rfcform.html">
  <front>
    <title>IETF 85 Proceedings: RFC Format (rfcform)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2012"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="IETF88" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/88/rfcform.html">
  <front>
    <title>IETF 88 Proceedings: RFC Format (rfcform)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="IETF89" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/89/rfcform.html">
  <front>
    <title>IETF 89 Proceedings: RFC Format (rfcform)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="IETF90" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/90/rfcform.html">
  <front>
    <title>IETF 90 Proceedings: RFC Format (rfcform)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ISTATS" target="http://www.internetlivestats.com/internet-users/">
  <front>
    <title>Internet Live Stats</title>
    <author >
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="NDN2014" target="https://events.nordu.net/display/NORDU2014/BoF%27s+and+side+meetings">
  <front>
    <title>28th NORDUnet Conference 2014</title>
    <author>
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="RFC-INTEREST" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/mailman/listinfo/rfc-interest">
  <front>
    <title>rfc-interest -- A list for discussion of the RFC series and RFC Editor functions.</title>
    <author >
      <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="RNC"
	   target="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/relax-ng/compact-20021121.html">
  <front>
      <title>RELAX NG Compact Syntax</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Clark" fullname="James Clark">
        <address>
          <email>jjc@jclark.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <date month="November" year="2002"/>
  </front><seriesInfo name="OASIS" value=""/></reference>


<reference anchor="RSOC" target="http://www.iab.org/activities/programs/rfc-editor-program/">
  <front>
    <title>RFC Editor Program: The RSOC</title>
    <author >
      <organization>IAB</organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TNC2014" target="https://tnc2014.terena.org/core/presentation/84">
  <front>
    <title>IETF Update - 'What's Hot?' - RFC Update</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>



<reference anchor="STM"
	   target="http://www.stm-assoc.org/">
  <front>
    <title>The global voice of scholarly publishing</title>
    <author><organization>STM</organization></author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="TYPOGRAPHY" target="http://practicaltypography.com/widow-and-orphan-control.html">
  <front>
    <title>Butterick's Practical Typography</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Butterick" fullname="Matthew Butterick"/>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="XML-ANNOUNCE" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/pipermail/rfc-interest/2013-May/005584.html">
  <front>
    <title>Subject: [rfc-i] Direction of the RFC Format Development effort</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan">
      <organization>RFC Series Editor</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2013"/>
  </front>
<seriesInfo name="message to the" value="rfc-interest mailing list"/>
</reference>


    </references>
  

  <section title="IAB Members at the Time of Approval" numbered="no">

  <t>The IAB members at the time this memo was approved were (in alphabetical order):                                                       

<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<list>
 <t>Jari Arkko</t>
 <t>Ralph Droms</t>
 <t>Ted Hardie</t>
 <t>Joe Hildebrand</t>
 <t>Russ Housley</t>
<t>Lee Howard</t>
 <t>Erik Nordmark</t>
 <t>Robert Sparks</t>
 <t>Andrew Sullivan</t>
 <t>Dave Thaler</t>
<t>Martin Thomson</t>
 <t>Brian Trammell</t>
 <t>Suzanne Woolf</t>
</list>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  </t>
  </section>


<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>With many thanks to the RFC Format Design Team for their efforts in making
this transition successful: Nevil Brownlee (ISE), Tony Hansen, Joe Hildebrand,
Paul Hoffman, Ted Lemon, Julian Reschke, Adam Roach, Alice Russo, Robert
Sparks (Tools Team liaison), and Dave Thaler.</t> 
</section>

  </back>
</rfc>


