<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="7775" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" updates="5308">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Route Preference">IS-IS Route Preference for Extended
    IP and IPv6 Reachability</title>

    <author fullname="Les Ginsberg" initials="L" surname="Ginsberg">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>510 McCarthy Blvd.</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <code>95035</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ginsberg@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S" surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange Business Service</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S" surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Del Serafico 200</street>

          <city>Rome</city>

          <code>0144</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sprevidi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2016"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>
In existing specifications, the route preferences for IPv4/IPv6 Extended
Reachability TLVs are not explicitly stated.   
There are also inconsistencies in the definition of how the
      up/down bit applies to route preference when the prefix advertisement
      appears in Level 2 Link State Protocol Data Units (LSPs). This document
      addresses these issues.</t>

      <t>This document updates RFC 5308.</t>
    </abstract>
  
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5302" /> defines the route preference rules as they apply to TLVs
      128 and 130. <xref target="RFC5305" /> introduced the IP Extended Reachability TLV 135
      but did not explicitly adapt the route preference rules defined in
      [RFC5302] for the new TLV. [RFC5308] defines the IPv6 Reachability TLV
      236 and does include an explicit statement regarding route preference --
      but the statement introduces use of the up/down bit in advertisements
      that appear in Level 2 LSPs, which is inconsistent with statements made
      in [RFC5302] and [RFC5305]. This document defines explicit route
      preference rules for TLV 135, revises the route preference rules for
      TLV 236, and clarifies the usage of the up/down bit when it appears in
      TLVs in Level 2 LSPs. This document is a clarification (NOT
      a correction) of [RFC5302] and [RFC5305]; it is a correction of the route
      preference rules defined in <xref target="RFC5308" /> to be consistent with the rules
      for IPv4. It also makes explicit that the same rules apply to the
      Multi-Topology (MT) equivalent TLVs 235 and 237.</t>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
     <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119" />.</t>  
    </section>    
    </section>     
    <section title="Use of the Up/Down Bit in Level 2 LSPs">
      <t>The up/down bit was introduced in support of leaking prefixes
      downwards in the IS-IS level hierarchy. Routes that are leaked
      downwards have the bit set to 1. Such prefixes MUST NOT be leaked
      upwards in the hierarchy. So long as we confine ourselves to a single
      IS-IS instance and the current number of supported levels (two), it is
      impossible to have a prefix advertised in a Level 2 LSP and have the
      up/down bit set to 1. However, because [RFC5302] anticipated a future
      extension to IS-IS that might support additional levels, it allowed for
      the possibility that the up/down bit might be set in a Level 2 LSP and
      supported easy migration in the event such an extension was
      introduced. Section 3.3 of [RFC5302] states:
<list>
      <t>...it is RECOMMENDED that implementations ignore the up/down bit in
      L2 LSPs, and accept the prefixes in L2 LSPs regardless of whether the
      up/down bit is set.</t>
</list>
      </t>
      <t>[RFC5305] addressed an additional case wherein an implementation
      included support for multiple virtual routers running IS-IS in different
      areas. In such a case, it is possible to redistribute prefixes between
      two IS-IS instances in the same manner that prefixes are redistributed
      from other protocols into IS-IS. 
This introduced the possibility that a
      prefix could be redistributed from Level 1 to Level 1 (as well as
      between Level 2 and Level 2), and in the event the redistributed route
      was leaked from Level 1 to Level 2, two different routers in different
      areas would be advertising the same prefix into the Level 2 sub-domain.
      To prevent this, Section 4.1 of [RFC5305] specifies:
<list>
      <t>If a prefix is advertised from one area to another at the same
      level, then the up/down bit SHALL be set to 1.</t>
</list>
      </t>
      <t>However, the statement in [RFC5302] that the up/down bit is ignored
      in Level 2 LSPs is not altered by [RFC5305].</t>

      <t>The conclusion then is that there is no "L2 inter-area route"; indeed, no such route type is defined by [RFC5302]. However, [RFC5308]
      ignored this fact and introduced such a route type in Section 5 when it
      specified a preference for "Level 2 down prefix". This is an error
      that this document corrects. As changing the use of the up/down bit in
      TLVs 236 and 237 may introduce interoperability issues, implementors may
      wish to support transition mechanisms from the behavior described in [RFC5308] to the
      behavior described in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Types of Routes in IS-IS Supported by Extended Reachability TLVs">
      <t>[RFC5302] is the authoritative reference for the types of routes
      supported by TLVs 128 and 130. However, a number of attributes supported
      by those TLVs are NOT supported by TLVs 135, 235, 236, and 237. Distinction
      between internal/external metrics is not supported. In the case of IPv4
      TLVs (135 and 235), the distinction between internal and external route
      types is not supported. However, the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV
      defined in <xref target="PFXATTR" /> reintroduces the distinction between internal and
      external route types. The definitions below include references to the
      relevant attribute bits from [PFXATTR].</t>

      <section title="Types of Routes Supported by TLVs 135 and 235">
        <t>This section defines the types of route supported for IPv4 when
        using TLV 135 [RFC5305] and/or TLV 235 <xref target="RFC5120" />. The text follows as
        closely as possible the original text from [RFC5302].


<list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="L1 intra-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in TLV 135
        or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 0. These IP prefixes are
        directly connected to the advertising router. If the Prefix Attribute
        Flags sub-TLV is included, both the X-Flag and the R-Flag are set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L1 external routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in TLV 135 or
        TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 0. These IP prefixes are learned
        from other protocols and are usually not directly connected to the
        advertising router. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included,
        the X-Flag is set to 1, and the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L2 intra-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in TLV 135
        or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 0. These IP prefixes are
        directly connected to the advertising router. If the Prefix Attribute
        Flags sub-TLV is included, both the X-Flag and the R-Flag are set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L1-&gt;L2 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in
        TLV 135 or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 0. These IP prefixes are
        learned via L1 routing and were derived during the L1 Shortest Path
        First (SPF) computation from prefixes advertised in L1 LSPs in TLV 135
        or TLV 235. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the
        R-Flag is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L2-&gt;L2 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in
        TLV 135 or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 1 but is ignored and
        treated as if it were set to 0. These IP prefixes are learned from
        another IS-IS instance usually operating in another area. If the
        Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the X-Flag is set to 1, and
        the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L2 external routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in
	TLV 135 or TLV
         235. The up/down bit is set to 0. These IP prefixes are learned
        from other protocols and are usually not directly connected to the
        advertising router. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included,
        the X-Flag is set to 1, and the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L2-&gt;L1 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in
        TLV 135 or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 1. These IP prefixes are
        learned via L2 routing and were derived during the L2 SPF computation
        from prefixes advertised in TLV 135 or TLV 235. If the Prefix
        Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L1-&gt;L1 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in
        TLV 135 or TLV 235. The up/down bit is set to 1. These IP prefixes are
        learned from another IS-IS instance usually operating in another area.
        If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the X-Flag is set to
        1, and the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>
</list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Types of Routes Supported by TLVs 236 and 237">
        <t>This section defines the types of route supported for IPv6 when
        using TLV 236 [RFC5308] and/or TLV 237 [RFC5120].

<list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="L1 intra-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in TLV 236
        or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is set to 0.
        These IPv6 prefixes are directly connected to the advertising router.
        If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to
        0.</t>

        <t hangText="L1 external routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in TLV 236 or
        TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is set to 1.
        These IPv6 prefixes are learned from other protocols and are usually
        not directly connected to the advertising router. If the Prefix
        Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L2 intra-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in TLV 236
        or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is set to 0.
        These IPv6 prefixes are directly connected to the advertising router.
        If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to
        0.</t>

        <t hangText="L1-&gt;L2 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in
        TLV 236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is
        set to 0. These IPv6 prefixes are learned via L1 routing and were
        derived during the L1 Shortest Path First (SPF) computation from
        prefixes advertised in L1 LSPs in TLV 236 or TLV 237. If the Prefix
        Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L2 external routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in TLV 236 or
        TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is set to 1.
        These IPv6 prefixes are learned from other protocols and are usually
        not directly connected to the advertising router. If the Prefix
        Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L1-&gt;L2 external routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in TLV
        236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 0. The external bit is set
        to 1. These IPv6 prefixes are learned via L1 routing and were derived
        during the L1 Shortest Path First (SPF) computation from L1 external
        routes advertised in L1 LSPs in TLV 236 or TLV 237. If the Prefix
        Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L2-&gt;L2 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L2 LSPs, in
        TLV 236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 1 but is ignored and
        treated as if it were set to 0. The external bit is set to 1. These IP
        prefixes are learned from another IS-IS instance usually operating in
        another area. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the
        R-Flag is set to 0.</t>

        <t hangText="L2-&gt;L1 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in
        TLV 236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 1. The external bit is
        set to 0. These IPv6 prefixes are learned via L2 routing and were
        derived during the L2 SPF computation from prefixes advertised in TLV
        236 or TLV 237. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the
        R-Flag is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L2-&gt;L1 external routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in TLV
        236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 1. The external bit is set
        to 1. These IPv6 prefixes are learned via L2 routing and were derived
        during the L2 SPF computation from prefixes advertised in TLV 236 or
        TLV 237. If the Prefix Attribute Flags sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag
        is set to 1.</t>

        <t hangText="L1-&gt;L1 inter-area routes:">These are advertised in L1 LSPs, in
        TLV 236 or TLV 237. The up/down bit is set to 1. The external bit is
        set to 1. These IP prefixes are learned from another IS-IS instance
        usually operating in another area. If the Prefix Attribute Flags
        sub-TLV is included, the R-Flag is set to 0.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Order of Preference for All Types of Routes Supported by TLVs 135 and 235">
        <t>This document defines the following route preferences for IPv4
        routes advertised in TLVs 135 or 235. Note that all types of routes
        listed for a given preference are treated equally.
<list style="numbers">
        <t>L1 intra-area routes; L1 external routes</t>

        <t>L2 intra-area routes; L2 external routes; L1-&gt;L2 inter-area
        routes; L2-L2 inter-area routes</t>

        <t>L2-&gt;L1 inter-area routes; L1-&gt;L1 inter-area routes</t>
</list>      
	</t>
</section>

      <section title="Order of Preference for All Types of Routes Supported by TLVs 236 and 237">
        <t>This document defines the following route preferences for IPv6
        routes advertised in TLVs 236 or 237. Note that all types of routes
        listed for a given preference are treated equally.
<list style="numbers">
        <t>L1 intra-area routes; L1 external routes</t>

        <t>L2 intra-area routes; L2 external routes; L1-&gt;L2 inter-area
        routes; L1-L2 external routes; L2-L2 inter-area routes</t>

        <t>L2-&gt;L1 inter-area routes; L2-&gt;L1 external routes; L1-&gt;L1
        inter-area routes</t>
</list>      
	</t>
</section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>This document raises no new security considerations.  Security
      considerations for the IS-IS protocol are covered
      in <xref target="ISO10589"/>, <xref target="RFC5304"/>, and <xref target="RFC5310"/>.  
      </t>
    </section>
 
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?> 
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5120"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5302"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5305"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5308"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5304"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5310"?>


<reference anchor="ISO10589">
<front>
<title>Intermediate System to Intermediate System intra-domain routeing 
information exchange protocol for use in conjunction with the protocol for
providing the connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)</title>
<author>
<organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
</author>
<date month="" year="2002" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 10589" />

</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!-- draft-ietf-isis-prefix-attributes-4: I-D Exists -->


<reference anchor='PFXATTR'>
<front>
<title>IS-IS Prefix Attributes for Extended IP and IPv6 Reachability</title>

<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='X' surname='Xu' fullname='Xiaohu Xu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='U' surname='Chunduri' fullname='Uma Chunduri'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' day='04' year='2016' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-isis-prefix-attributes-04' />
</reference>
    </references>


    <section title="Example Interoperability Issue">
      <t>This example documents a real-world interoperability issue that occurs
      because implementations from different vendors have interpreted the use
      of the up/down bit in Level 2 LSPs inconsistently.</t>
      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        L2       L2       L2     L2|L2      L2               
 10/8 - R0 ----- R1 ----- R2 ----- R3 ----- R4 ---- 10/8
                                   |
                Figure 1
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In Figure 1, both R0 and R4 are advertising the prefix 10/8.
      Two IS-IS Level 2 instances are running on R3 to separate the network
      into two areas. R3 is performing route leaking and advertises prefixes
      from R4 to the other Level 2 process. The network is using extended
      metrics (TLV 135 defined in [RFC5305]). R0 advertises 10/8 with
      metric 2000, and R3 advertises 10/8 with metric 100. All links have a
      metric of 1. When advertising 10/8 in its Level 2 LSP, R3 sets the down
      bit as specified in [RFC5305].</t>

      <t>R1, R2, and R3 are from three different vendors (R1-&gt;Vendor1,
      R2-&gt;Vendor2, R3-&gt;Vendor3). During interoperability testing,
      routing loops are observed in this scenario.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>R2 has two possible paths to reach 10/8: Level 2 route with
          metric 2002 and up/down bit set to 0 (from R0) and Level 2 route with
          metric 101 and up/down bit set to 1 (from R3). R2 selects R1 as the next hop to
          10/8 because it prefers the route that does NOT have the up/down bit
          set.</t>

          <t>R3 has two possible paths to reach 10/8: Level 2 route with
          metric 2003 and up/down bit set to 0 (from R0) and Level 2 route with
          metric 101 and up/down bit set to 0 (from R4). R3 selects R4 as the next hop due
          to lowest metric.</t>

          <t>R1 has two possible paths to reach 10/8: Level 2 route with
          metric 2001 and up/down bit set to 0 (from R0) and Level 2 route
	  with metric 102 and
          up/down bit set to 1 (from R3). R1 selects R2 as the next hop due to lowest
          metric.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>When R1 or R2 try to send traffic to 10/8, packets loop due to
      inconsistent routing decisions between R1 and R2.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors wish to thank Ahmed Bashandy for his insightful
      review.</t>
    </section>
      
  </back>
</rfc>
