<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>  
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc number="7297" category="info" submissionType="independent"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CPP">IP Connectivity Provisioning Profile (CPP)</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Jacquenet" initials="C." surname="Jacquenet">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>christian.jacquenet@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ning Wang" initials="N." surname="Wang">
      <organization>University of Surrey</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Guildford</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>n.wang@surrey.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2014" />

<keyword>service parameter negotiation</keyword>
<keyword>service template</keyword>
<keyword>Service Level Agreement</keyword>
<keyword>Network Abstraction</keyword>
<keyword>Service Automation</keyword>
<keyword>Service and Network Management</keyword>
<keyword>Network Dimensioning and Planning</keyword>
<keyword>Application-agnostic IP Provisioning</keyword>
<keyword>IP/MPLS Transfer Guarantees</keyword>
<keyword>Service Provisioning</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the Connectivity Provisioning Profile (CPP)
      and proposes a CPP template to capture IP/MPLS connectivity requirements to
      be met within a service delivery context (e.g., Voice over IP or IP TV).
      The CPP defines the set of IP transfer parameters to be supported by the
      underlying transport network together with a reachability scope and
      bandwidth/capacity needs. Appropriate performance metrics, such as
      one-way delay or one-way delay variation, are used to characterize an IP
      transfer service. Both global and restricted reachability scopes can be
      captured in the CPP.</t>

      <t>Such a generic CPP template is meant to (1) facilitate the automation
      of the service negotiation and activation procedures, thus accelerating
      service provisioning, (2) set (traffic) objectives of Traffic
      Engineering functions and service management functions, and (3) improve
      service and network management systems with 'decision-making'
      capabilities based upon negotiated/offered CPPs.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes the Connectivity Provisioning Profile (CPP)
      and proposes a CPP template to capture IP/MPLS connectivity requirements
      to be met within a service delivery context (e.g., Voice over IP, IP TV, and
      VPN services).</t>

      <t>In this document, the IP connectivity service is the IP transfer
      capability characterized by a (Source Nets, Destination Nets, Guarantees,
      Scope) tuple where "Source Nets" is a group of unicast IP
      addresses, "Destination Nets" is a group of IP unicast and/or multicast
      addresses, and "Guarantees" reflects the guarantees (expressed in terms of
      Quality Of Service (QoS), performance, and availability, for example) to
      properly forward traffic to the said "Destination". Finally, the "Scope"
      denotes the (network) perimeter (e.g., between Provider Edge (PE)
      routers or Customer Nodes) where the said guarantees need to be
      provided.</t>

      <section title="Connectivity Provisioning Interface (CPI)">
        <t><xref target="interactions2"></xref> shows the various connectivity
        provisioning interfaces covered by CPP: the Customer-Network
        CPI, the Service-Network CPI, and the Network-Network CPI.
        Services and applications whose parameters are
        captured by means of a CPP exchanged through the Service-Network
        CPI may be provided by the same
        administrative entity that operates the underlying network or by
        another entity (for example, a Content Provider).</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="interactions2"
            title="Connectivity Provisioning Interfaces">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
               +---------+
               |Service A| 
               +---+-----+
                   |    +---------+
                   |CPI |Service B|
                   |    +-+-------+
                   |      |CPI
+----------+     +-+------+-------+     +------------+
| Customer |-----|Network Provider|-----|Peer Network|
+----------+ CPI +----------------+ CPI +------------+ 
]]></artwork>
          </figure>The interfaces depicted in <xref
        target="interactions2"></xref> can be summarized as shown in <xref
        target="interactions"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The Customer shown in <xref target="interactions"></xref> may be
        another Network Provider (e.g., an IP transit provider), a Service
        Provider (e.g., an IP telephony Service Provider) that requires the
        invocation of resources provided by a Network Provider, or an
        enterprise that wants to interconnect its various sites by
        subscribing to a VPN service provided by a Network Provider. The
        proposed CPP can be used to expose, capture, and facilitate the
        negotiation of the service parameters between these various entities,
        thereby presenting a common template for describing the available
        connectivity services.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="interactions"
            title="CPP: Generic Connectivity Provisioning Interfaces">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+----------------+
|   Customer     | 
+-------+--------+
        + CPI
+-------+--------+
|Network Provider| 
+----------------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>In the rest of this document, "Customer" is used as a
        generic term to denote the business entity that subscribes to
        connectivity services offered by a Network Provider (see <xref target="interactions"/>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Rationale">
        <t>Procedures for the design and the operation of IP services have
        become increasingly diverse and complex. The time it takes to
        negotiate service parameters and then proceed with the corresponding
        resource allocation can thus be measured in days, if not weeks. 
Yet, experience has shown that the bilateral discussions that usually take
place between a Customer and a Network Provider never rely upon some kind of
standard checklist where the Customer would be invited to tick all the
parameters that apply to its environment. These parameters would then be
negotiated with the Network Provider, as a function of
the available
        resources, the Customer's expectations, the provider's network
        planning policy, etc.</t>

        <t>The definition of a clear interface between the service (including
        third-party applications) and the network layers would therefore
        facilitate the said discussion, thereby improving the overall service
        delivery procedure by optimizing the design of the network
        infrastructures. Indeed, the CPP interface aims at exposing and
        characterizing, in a technology-agnostic manner, the IP transfer
        requirements to be met when invoking IP transfer capabilities of a
        network operated by a Network Provider between a set of Customer Nodes
        (e.g., Multimedia Gateway (Section 11.2.7 of <xref target="RFC2805"></xref>),
        Session Border Controller <xref target="RFC5853"></xref>, etc.).</t>

        <t>These requirements include: reachability scope (e.g., limited
        scope, Internet-wide), direction, bandwidth requirements, QoS
        parameters (e.g., one-way delay <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, loss
        <xref target="RFC2680"></xref>, or one-way delay variation <xref
        target="RFC3393"></xref>), protection, and high-availability guidelines
        (e.g., restoration in less than 50 ms, 100 ms, or 1 second).</t>

        <t>These requirements are then translated into IP/MPLS-related
        technical clauses (e.g., need for recovery means, definition of the
        class of service, need for control-plane protection, etc.). In a later
        stage, these various clauses will be addressed by the activation of
        adequate network features and technology-specific actions (e.g.,
        Multiprotocol Label Switching Traffic Engineering (MPLS-TE, <xref
        target="RFC3346"></xref>), Resource Reservation Protocol (RSVP, <xref
        target="RFC2205"></xref>), Open Shortest Path First (OSPF), 
        Intermediate System to Intermediate System (IS-IS), etc.), by means of
        CPP-derived configuration information.</t>

        <t>For traffic conformance purposes, a CPP also includes flow
        identification and classification rules to be followed by
        participating nodes whenever they have to process traffic according to
        a specific service as defined by the said CPP.</t>

        <t>The CPP template aims to capture connectivity needs and to
        represent and value these requirements in a standardized manner.
        Service- and Customer-specific IP provisioning rules may lead to a
        dramatic increase of the number of IP transfer classes that need to be
        (pre-)engineered in the network. Instantiating each CPP into a
        distinct class of service should therefore be avoided for the sake of
        performance and scalability.</t>

        <t>Therefore, application-agnostic IP provisioning practices should be
        recommended, since the requirements captured in the CPP can be used to
        identify which network class of service is to be used to meet those
        requirements/guarantees. From that standpoint, the CPP concept is
        meant to design a limited number of generic classes so that
        individual CPP documents, by capturing the connectivity requirements
        of services, applications, and Customers, can be easily mapped to these
        classes.</t>

        <t>CPP may also be used as a guideline for network dimensioning and
        planning teams of a Network Provider to ensure that appropriate
        resources (e.g., network cards, routers, link capacity, etc.) have
        been provisioned. Otherwise, (underlying) transport networks would not
        be able to meet the objectives expressed in all CPP requests.</t>

        <t>Such a generic CPP template:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Facilitates the automation of the service negotiation and
            activation procedures, thus improving service delivery times;</t>

            <t>Can help set Traffic Engineering function and service
            management function objectives, for
            example, as a function of the number of CPP
            templates to be processed over a specific period of time; and</t>

            <t>Improves service and network management systems by adding
            'decision-making' capabilities based upon negotiated/offered
            CPPs.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In addition, this CPP abstraction makes a clear distinction between
        the connectivity provisioning requirements and the associated
        technology-specific rules that need to be applied by participating
        nodes and that are meant to accommodate such requirements.</t>

        <t>The CPP defines the set of IP/MPLS transfer guarantees to be
        offered by the underlying transport network together with a
        reachability scope and capacity needs. Appropriate performance metrics,
        such as one-way delay or one-way delay variation, are used to
        characterize the IP transfer service. Guarantees related to
        availability and resiliency are also included in the CPP.</t>

        <t>The CPP can be used in an integrated business environment (where
        the service and network infrastructures are managed by the same
        administrative entity) or another business environment (where an
        administrative entity manages the service while another manages the
        network infrastructure). In the following sections, no assumption is
        made about the business environment (integrated or not).</t>

        <t>Service differentiation at the network layer can be enforced by
        tweaking various parameters that belong to distinct dimensions (e.g.,
        forwarding, routing, processing of incoming traffic, traffic
        classification, etc.). This document does not make any assumption on
        how network services are implemented within a networking
        infrastructure.</t>

        <t>Activating unicast or multicast capabilities to deliver a
        connectivity service can be explicitly requested by a Customer in a
        CPP or can be an engineering decision of a Network Provider based on
        the analysis of the Customer connectivity provisioning
        requirements.</t>

        <t>
Examples of CPP usage include the northbound interface
introduced by the Application-Based Network Operations (ABNO)
framework
<xref target="NET-OPS"></xref> and the technique for exposing network services
  and their characteristics defined in <xref target="RFC7149"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reference Architecture">
        <t>Customer Nodes belong to a Customer (including corporate Customers)
        or a service infrastructure (see <xref
        target="interactions2"></xref>). In some contexts, Customer Nodes can
        be provided and managed by the Network Provider. The connectivity
        between these Customer Nodes reflects the IP transfer capability
        implemented thanks to the allocation of a set of IP resources. IP
        transfer capabilities are considered by higher-layer services (such as
	transport- and application-layer services) as black
        boxes. Appropriate notifications and reports would be communicated
        (through dedicated means) to Customer Nodes to assess the compliance
        of the experienced IP transfer service against what has been
        negotiated with the corresponding CPP. These notifications may also be
        used to assess the efficiency of the various policies enforced in the
        networking infrastructure to accommodate the requirements detailed in
        the CPP.</t>

        <t>The CPP reference architectures are depicted in Figures <xref
        target="ref" format="counter"></xref>, <xref target="ref1" format="counter"></xref>, and <xref
        target="ref2" format="counter"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The Customer infrastructure can be connected over networking
        infrastructures managed by one or several Network Providers.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="ref"
            title="Reference Architecture: Connectivity Service Provided by the Same Network Provider Using Distinct Interconnection Nodes">
            <artwork><![CDATA[       .--. .--.. .--..--.
      (                   '.--.
   .-.' Customer Infrastructure'.-.
   (                                )
  +-------------+               +-------------+
  |Customer Node|.--. .--.. .--.|Customer Node| 
  +-------------+               +-------------+             
        |                            |
 +--------------+             +--------------+
 |Provider Node |.--. .--.. . |Provider Node | 
 +--------------+             +--------------+   
       (                             )
     .-.'         Network            '.-.
     (                                   )
      (      .     .    .    .    .    .)
        '.-_-.'.-_-._.'.-_-.'.-_-.'.--.'
]]></artwork>
          </figure><figure align="center" anchor="ref1"
            title="Reference Architecture: Connectivity Service Provided by the Same Network Provider Using a Single Interconnection Node">
            <artwork><![CDATA[       .--. .--.. .--..--.
      (                   '.--.
   .-.' Customer Infrastructure'.-.
   (                                )
  +-------------+               +-------------+
  |Customer Node|.--. .--.. .--.|Customer Node| 
  +-------------+               +-------------+             
        |                            |
     +-----------------------------------+
     |        Provider Node              | 
     +-----------------------------------+
       (                             )
     .-.'         Network            '.-.
     (                                   )
      (      .     .    .    .    .    .)
        '.-_-.'.-_-._.'.-_-.'.-_-.'.--.'
]]></artwork>
          </figure><figure align="center" anchor="ref2"
            title="Reference Architecture: Connectivity Services Provided by Distinct Network Providers">
            <artwork><![CDATA[       .--. .--.. .--..--.
      (                   '.--.
   .-.' Customer Infrastructure'.-.
   (                                )
  +-------------+               +-------------+
  |Customer Node|.--. .--.. .--.|Customer Node| 
  +-------------+               +-------------+             
        |                            |
 +--------------+             +--------------+
 |Provider Node |             |Provider Node | 
 +--------------+             +--------------+   
  (            .--.)           (           .--.)
.-.'   Network A  '.-.      .-.'   Network B  '.-.
  (                  )      (                    )
  (.     .    .    .)        (.     .    .     .)
   '.-_-.'.-_-._..'             '.-_-.'.-_-._..'
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope of This Document">
      <t>This document details the clauses of the CPP. Candidate protocols
      (e.g., <xref
      target="CPNP"></xref>) that
      can be used to negotiate and enforce a given CPP are not discussed in
      this document.</t>

      <t>In addition to CPP clauses, other clauses may be included in an
      agreement between a Customer and a Provider (e.g., contact point,
      escalation procedure, incidents management, billing, etc.). It is out of
      the scope of this document to detail all those additional clauses.</t>

      <t>Examples of how to translate CPP clauses into specific policies are
      provided for illustration purposes. It is out of the scope of this document
      to provide an exhaustive list of the technical means to meet the
      objectives detailed in a CPP.</t>

      <t>CPP was mainly designed to target IP connectivity services.
      Nevertheless, it can be used for other non-IP transport schemes. It is
      out of the scope of this document to assess the applicability of CPP to
      these non-IP schemes.</t>

      <t>This document covers both unicast and multicast connectivity
      services. Both Any-Source Multicast (ASM, <xref
      target="RFC1112"></xref>) and Source-Specific Multicast (SSM, <xref
      target="RFC4607"></xref>) modes can be captured in a CPP.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cpps" title="Connectivity Provisioning Profile (CPP)">
      <t>A CPP can be seen as the inventory of connectivity provisioning
      requirements with regard to the IP transfer service. CPP clauses are
      elaborated in the following sub-sections. The CPP template is provided
      in <xref target="tppt"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Customer Nodes Map">
        <t>A CPP must include the list of Customer Nodes (e.g., Customer Edges
	(CEs)) to be
        connected to the underlying IP transport network.</t>

        <t>These nodes should be unambiguously identified (e.g., using a
        unique Service_identifier, Media Access Control (MAC) addresses, etc.). For each Customer
        Node, a border link or a node that belongs to the domain that connects
        the Customer Nodes should be identified.</t>

        <t>This clause can specify geolocation information of Customer
        Nodes.</t>

        <t>Based on the location of the Customer Node, appropriate operations
        to retrieve the corresponding border link or "Provider
        Node" (e.g., PE) should be undertaken. This operation can be
        manual or automated.</t>

        <t>A "service site" would be located behind a given
        Customer Node. A site identifier may be captured in the CPP for the
        provisioning of managed VPN services <xref target="RFC4026"></xref>,
        for instance, Site_identifier.</t>

        <t>A Customer Node may be connected to several Provider Nodes. 
        Multiple Customer Nodes may be connected to the same Provider Node
        as shown in <xref target="ref1"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="scope" title="Scope">
        <t>The scope clause specifies the reachability of each of the involved
        Customer Nodes, from both incoming and outgoing traffic
        perspectives, thereby yielding specific traffic directionality
        considerations. It is defined as an unidirectional parameter. Both
        directions should be described in the CPP.</t>

        <t>The reachability scope specifies the set of destination prefixes
        that can be reached from a given Customer site (identified by a group
        of source prefixes). Both global and restricted reachability scopes
        can be captured in the CPP. A global reachability scope means that a
        Customer site can reach any destination in the Internet and can be
        reached from any remote host. A restricted reachability scope means no
        global reachability is allowed; only a set of destinations can be
        reached from a Customer site, and/or only a set of sources can reach
        the Customer site. Both incoming and outgoing reachability scopes are
        specified in the CPP.</t>

        <t>Both IPv4 and IPv6 reachability scopes may be specified.</t>

        <t>The reachability scope clause can include multicast and/or unicast
        addresses. For SSM, a group of unicast source addresses can be
        specified in addition to destination multicast addresses.</t>

        <t>The scope clause can also be used to delimit a topological (or
        geographical) network portion beyond which the performance and
        availability guarantees do not apply. A scope may be defined by a set
        of "Ingress" points and "Egress" points. Several
        types may be considered, such as: <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
            <t hangText="(1)">"1:1" Pipe model. Only point-to-point communications are
            allowed.</t>

            <t hangText="(2)">"1:N" Hose model. Only communications from one site towards
            a set of destinations are allowed.</t>

            <t hangText="(3)">"1:any" Unspecified hose model. All outbound communications
            are allowed.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The Ingress and Egress points could be Customer Nodes / Provider
        Nodes or external nodes, provided that these nodes are unambiguously
        identified (e.g., IPv6 prefix), or a set of IP destinations.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="guarantees" title="QoS Guarantees">
        <t>QoS guarantees denote a set of IP transfer performance metrics
        that characterize the quality of the IP transfer treatment to be
        experienced (when crossing an IP transport infrastructure) by a flow
        issued from or forwarded to a (set of) "Customer Node(s)".</t>

        <t>IP performance metrics can be expressed as qualitative or
        quantitative parameters (both quantitative and qualitative guarantees
        cannot be specified in the same CPP). Quantitative guarantees may be
        specified as an average value, as a maximum bound, or as a percentile
        over an interval of measurements that should be indicated in the
        measurement method.</t>

        <t>Several performance metrics have been defined, such as: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Traffic Loss <xref target="RFC2680"></xref></t>

            <t>One-way delay <xref target="RFC2679"></xref></t>

            <t>One-way delay variation <xref target="RFC3393"></xref></t>
          </list>These parameters may be specific to a given path or a given
        scope (e.g., between two Customer Nodes). IP performance metric values
        indicated in a CPP should reflect the measurement between a set of
        Customer Nodes or between a Customer Node and a set of Provider
        Nodes.</t>

        <t>Quantitative guarantees can only be specified for in-profile
        traffic (i.e., up to a certain traffic rate). A CPP can include
        throughput guarantees; when specified, these guarantees are equivalent
        to quantitative or qualitative loss guarantees.</t>

        <t>The Meta-QoS-Class concept can be used when qualitative metrics are
        used <xref target="RFC5160"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="guarantees1" title="Availability">
        <t>This clause specifies the percentage of the time during which the
        agreed IP performance guarantees apply. The clause can be expressed as
        a maximum or an average.

 The exact meaning of the clause value is defined
        during the CPP negotiation process.</t>

        <t>The guarantees cover both QoS deterioration (i.e., IP transfer
        service is available, but it is below the agreed performance bounds),
        physical failures, or service unavailability in general. In order to
        meet the availability guarantees, several engineering practices may be
        enforced at the border between the Customer and the Network Provider,
        such as multi-homing designs.</t>

        <t>The following mechanisms are provided as examples to show that
        different technical options may be chosen to meet the service
        availability objectives:<list style="symbols">
            <t>When an Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) instance is running
            between the "Customer Node" and the "Provider
            Node", activate a dedicated protocol, such as Bidirectional
	    Forwarding Detection
            (BFD, <xref
            target="RFC5881"></xref><xref target="RFC5883"></xref>), to
            control IGP availability and to ensure sub-second IGP adjacency
            failure detection.</t>

            <t>Use of the Label Switched Path Ping (LSP Ping) capability to detect
            LSP availability (check whether the LSP is in place or not) <xref
            target="RFC4379"></xref><xref target="RFC6424"></xref><xref
            target="RFC6425"></xref><xref target="RFC6426"></xref><xref
            target="RFC6829"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Pre-install backup LSPs for fast-reroute purposes when an MPLS
            network connects Customer Nodes <xref
            target="RFC4090"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Enable Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP, <xref
            target="RFC5798"></xref>).</t>

            <t>Enable IP Fast Reroute features (e.g., <xref
            target="RFC5286"></xref> or <xref target="RFC6981"></xref>).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cap" title="Capacity">
        <t>This clause characterizes the required capacity to be provided by
        the underlying IP transport network. This capacity is bound to a
        defined "Scope" (see <xref target="scope"></xref>) and IP transfer
        performance guarantees (see Sections <xref format="counter" target="guarantees"></xref> and
        <xref format="counter" target="guarantees1"></xref>).</t>

        <t>The capacity may be expressed for both traffic directions (i.e.,
        incoming and outgoing) and for every border link. The capacity clause
        defines the limits of the application of quantitative guarantees.</t>

        <t>It is up to the administrative entity, which manages the IP
        transport network, to appropriately dimension its network <xref
        target="RFC5136"></xref> to meet the capacity requirements expressed
        in all negotiated CPPs.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ct" title="Conformance Traffic">
        <t>When capacity information (see <xref target="cap"></xref>) is
        included in the CPP, requirements for out-of-profile traffic treatment
        need to be also expressed in the CPP.</t>

        <t>Shaping/policing filters may be applied so as to assess whether
        traffic is within the capacity profile or out of profile.
        Out-of-profile traffic may be discarded or assigned another class
        (e.g., using Lower Effort Per-Domain Behavior (LE PDB)
        <xref target="RFC3662"></xref>).</t>

        <t>Packet MTU conditions may also be indicated in the CPP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Overall Traffic Guarantees">
        <t>Overall traffic guarantees are defined when the Capacity (<xref
        target="cap"></xref>) and Conformance Traffic (<xref target="ct"></xref>)
        clauses are not specified. Or, if they are actually specified, then
        out-of-profile traffic is assigned another class of service but is
        not discarded. Such guarantees can only be qualitative delay and/or
        qualitative loss or throughput guarantees.</t>

        <t>If overall traffic guarantees are not specified, best effort
        forwarding is implied.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="isolation" title="Traffic Isolation">
        <t>This clause indicates if the traffic issued by or destined to
        "Customer Nodes" should be isolated when crossing the IP
        transport network. This clause can also be used to specify additional
        security protection requirements (including privacy protection
        requirements).</t>

        <t>This clause can then be translated into VPN policy provisioning
        information, such as the information pertaining to the activation of
        dedicated tunnels using IPsec, BGP/MPLS VPN facilities <xref
        target="RFC4364"></xref>, or a combination thereof. The activation of
        such features should be consistent with the availability and
        performance guarantees that have been negotiated.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Flow Identification">
        <t>To identify the flows that need to be handled within the context of
        a given CPP, flow identifiers should be indicated in the CPP. Flow
        identifiers are used for traffic classification purposes. An example
        of packet classifier is defined in <xref target="RFC2475"></xref>.</t>

        <t>A flow identifier may be composed of (but
        not limited to) the following parameters: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Source IP address,</t>

            <t>Source port number,</t>

            <t>Destination IP address,</t>

            <t>Destination port number,</t>

            <t>Type of Service (ToS) or Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) field,</t>

            <t>Tail-end tunnel endpoint, or</t>

            <t>Any combination thereof.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Distinct treatments may be implemented for elastic and non-elastic
        traffic (e.g., see the "Constraints on traffic" clause defined in
        <xref target="RFC5160"></xref>).</t>

        <t>Flow classification rules may be specific to a given link or may
        be applied for a group or all border links. This should be clearly
        captured in the CPP.</t>

        <t>Some practices such as DSCP re-marking may be indicated in the CPP.
        Re-marking action is under the responsibility of underlying nodes that
        intervene to deliver the connectivity service. Re-marking can be
        enforced for both outgoing and incoming traffic received from or destined
        to Customer Nodes. These re-marking actions must not alter the
        service-specific marking integrity (e.g., VPN service).</t>

        <t>This clause may specify policies (e.g., DSCP re-marking) to be
        enforced at the egress nodes on packets received from Customer Nodes.
        If no such policy is specified, the Network Provider enforces its
        local policies (e.g., clear DSCP marking) on packets leaving its
        administrative domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing and Forwarding">
        <t>This clause is used to specify outsourced routing actions, such as
        installing dedicated routes to convey the traffic to its (service)
        destination. These dedicated routes may be computed, selected, and
        installed for Traffic Engineering or resilience purposes. For Traffic
        Engineering, these paths can be used to intelligently divert traffic
        away from some nodes/links that may potentially suffer from congestion
        or avoid crossing competitors' networks. For resilience, backup
        paths are typically pre-installed in order to bypass nodes/links under
        protection.</t>

        <t>This clause is also used to specify intermediate functions that
        must be invoked in the forwarding path (e.g., redirect the traffic to
        a firewall, invoke topology hiding features, etc.) or specify
        geographic routing restrictions.</t>

        <t>A requirement for setting up a logical routing topology <xref target="RFC4915"></xref> <xref
        target="RFC5120"></xref> may also be
        considered, e.g., to facilitate the management of the
        nodes that are involved in the forwarding of the traffic as defined in
        the CPP.</t>

        <t>This practice should be indicated in the CPP; otherwise, path
        computation is left to the underlying IP routing capabilities. The
        forwarding behavior (e.g., Per-Domain Behavior (PDB) <xref
        target="RFC3086"></xref>) may also be specified in a CPP but remains
        optional. If indicated, consistency with the IP performance bounds
        defined in the CPP should be carefully ensured.</t>

        <t>For illustration purposes, a routing policy would avoid
        satellite links for Voice over IP (VoIP) deployments since this may
        degrade the offered service.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Activation Means">
        <t>This clause indicates the required action(s) to be undertaken to
        activate access to the IP connectivity service.</t>

        <t>Examples of these actions would be the activation of an IGP
        instance, the establishment of a BGP <xref target="RFC4271"></xref> or
        Multiprotocol BGP (MP-BGP) session <xref target="RFC4760"></xref>, Protocol
        Independent Multicast (PIM, <xref target="RFC4601"></xref>), etc.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Invocation Means">
        <t>Two types are defined:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Implicit:">This clause indicates that no explicit
            means to invoke the connectivity service is required. Access to
            the connectivity service is primarily conditioned by the requested
            network capacity.</t>

            <t hangText="Explicit:">This clause indicates the need for
            explicit means to access the connectivity service. Examples of
            such means include the use of RSVP <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>,
            RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209"></xref>, Internet Group
            Management Protocol (IGMP, <xref target="RFC3376"> </xref>), or 
            Multicast Listener Discovery (MLD, <xref target="RFC3810"></xref>).
            Appropriate admission control procedures <xref
            target="RFC6601"></xref> would have to be enforced, e.g., to check
            whether the capacity actually used is not above the agreed
            threshold.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Notifications">
        <t>For operation purposes (e.g., supervision) and service fulfillment
        needs, management platforms need to be notified about critical events
        that may impact the delivery of the service.</t>

        <t>The notification procedure should be indicated in the CPP. This
        procedure may specify the type of information to be sent, the
        interval, the data model, etc.</t>

        <t>Notifications can be sent to the management platform by using
        Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP, <xref target="RFC3416"></xref>),
        Syslog notifications <xref target="RFC5424"></xref>, Connectivity
	Provisioning Negotiation Protocol (CPNP) signals
        <xref
        target="CPNP"></xref>,
        Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF) Event Notifications <xref target="RFC5277"></xref>, or a phone
        call!</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tppt" title="CPP Template">
      <t><xref target="rbnf"></xref> provides the Routing Backus-Naur
      Form (RBNF, <xref target="RFC5511"></xref>) format of the CPP template.</t>

      <t>A CPP document includes several connectivity provisioning components;
      each of these is structured as a CPP. The CPP may include additional
      optional information elements such as metrics used for Service Assurance
      purposes, activation schedule, etc.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="rbnf" title="CPP Template">
          <artwork><![CDATA[<CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_DOCUMENT> ::= 
                           <Connectivity Provisioning Component> ...
<Connectivity Provisioning Component> ::= 
                           <CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_PROFILE> ...
<CONNECTIVITY_PROVISIONING_PROFILE> ::= 
                           <Customer Nodes Map>
                           <Scope>
                           <QoS Guarantees>
                           <Availability>
                           <Capacity>
                           <Traffic Isolation>
                           <Conformance Traffic>
                           <Flow Identification>
                           <Overall Traffic Guarantees>
                           <Routing and Forwarding>
                           <Activation Means>
                           <Invocation Means>
                           <Notifications>
                           <Optional Information Element> ...
<Customer Nodes Map> ::=  <Customer Node> ...
<Customer Node> ::=  <IDENTIFIER>
                     <LINK_IDENTIFIER>
                     <LOCALIZATION>
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The description of these clauses is provided in <xref
      target="cpps"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The CPP may also include a Customer's administrative information, such
      as a name and other contact details. An example of the RBNF format of
      the Customer's information is shown in <xref
      target="customer"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="customer"
          title="Customer Description Clause">
          <artwork><![CDATA[<Customer Description> ::= <NAME> <Contact Information>
<Contact Information> ::=  <EMAIL_ADDRESS> [<POSTAL_ADDRESS>]
                           [<TELEPHONE_NUMBER> ...]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>The CPP may include administrative information of the Network
      Provider too (name, Autonomous System number(s), and other contact details). An example
      of the RBNF format of the provider's information is shown in <xref
      target="NP"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="NP"
          title="Provider Description Clause">
          <artwork><![CDATA[<Provider Description> ::= <NAME><Contact Information>[<AS_NUMBER>]
<Contact Information> ::=  <EMAIL_ADDRESS> [<POSTAL_ADDRESS>]
                           [<TELEPHONE_NUMBER> ...]
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not define an architecture or specify a protocol.
Yet, the means to provide guarantees about the identity of a Customer and its
ability to expose connectivity requirements to a Network Provider through a
CPP need to be investigated. Likewise, the means to provide guarantees about
the identity of a Network Provider and the ability to expose its capabilities,
let alone capture the requirements of a Customer through a CPP, should be
carefully studied.
</t>

      <t>CPP documents should be protected against illegitimate modifications
      (e.g., modification, withdrawal); authorization means should be enabled.
      These means are deployment-specific.</t>

      <t>The Network Provider must enforce means to protect privacy-related
      information captured in a CPP document <xref target="RFC6462"></xref>.
      In particular, this information must not be revealed to external parties
      without the consent of Customers. Network Providers should enforce
      policies to make Customer fingerprinting more difficult to achieve. For
      more discussion about privacy, refer to <xref target="RFC6462"></xref>
      and <xref target="RFC6973"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Some of the items in this document are the result of several discussions
      with E.&nbsp;Mykoniati and D.&nbsp;Griffin. Special thanks to them.</t>

      <t>Many thanks to P.&nbsp;Georgatsos for the discussions and the detailed
      review of this document.</t>

      <t>Thanks to S.&nbsp;Shah, G.&nbsp;Huston, D.&nbsp;King, and S.&nbsp;Bryant for reviewing the document
      and providing useful comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3662'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2679'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2680'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5136'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3393'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4379'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5120'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4915'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5881'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5883'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5798'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4760'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5286'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6973'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1112'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4607'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3376'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2205'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4271'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4364'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3416'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4090'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3209'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3810'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4601'?>

<!-- draft-farrkingel-pce-abno-architecture-07: I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='NET-OPS'>
<front>
<title>A PCE-based Architecture for Application-based Network Operations</title>

<author initials='D' surname='King' fullname='Daniel King'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Farrel' fullname='Adrian Farrel'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='13' year='2014' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>



<!-- draft-boucadair-connectivity-provisioning-protocol-03: I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='CPNP'>
<front>
<title>Connectivity Provisioning Negotiation Protocol (CPNP)</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohamed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Jacquenet' fullname='Christian Jacquenet'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Zhang'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month="June" year="2014" />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>


      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5160'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3346'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7149'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6981'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6462'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6426'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6829'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4026'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3086'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5853'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2475'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6425'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5424'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6424'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6601'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2805'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5277'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5511'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
