<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4242 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4242.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5191 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5191.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6206 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6206.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7227 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7227.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="7774" submissionType="IETF"
   consensus="yes"  xml:lang="en">

  <?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPL Configuration for DHCPv6">Multicast Protocol for
 Low-Power and Lossy Networks (MPL) Parameter&nbsp;Configuration Option for DHCPv6</title>

    <author initials="Y." surname="Doi" fullname="Yusuke Doi">
      <organization>Toshiba Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Komukai Toshiba Cho 1</street>
          <street>Saiwai-Ku</street>
          <city>Kawasaki</city>
          <region>Kanagawa</region>
          <code>2128582</code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+81-45-342-7230</phone>
        <email>yusuke.doi@toshiba.co.jp</email>
        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Gillmore" fullname="Matthew Gillmore">
      <organization>Itron, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2111 N. Molter Rd.</street>
          <city>Liberty Lake</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>99019</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>matthew.gillmore@itron.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2016"/>

    <keyword>MPL, DHCPv6</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a way to configure a parameter set for MPL
      (Multicast Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks) via a DHCPv6
      option. MPL has a set of parameters to control its behavior, and the
      parameter set is often configured as a network-wide parameter because
      the parameter set should be identical for each MPL Forwarder in an MPL
      Domain. Using the MPL Parameter Configuration Option defined in this
      document, a network can easily be configured with a single set of MPL
      parameters.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction" toc="default">
      <t>The Multicast Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks <xref
      target="RFC7731" pageno="false" format="default">(MPL)</xref> defines a
      protocol to make a multicast network among low&nbhy;power and lossy
      networks, e.g., wireless mesh networks. MPL has a set of parameters to
      control an MPL Domain. The parameters control the trade-off between
      end-to-end delay and network utilization. In most environments, the
      default parameters are acceptable. However, in some environments, the
      parameter set must be configured carefully in order to meet the
      requirements of each environment. According to Section&nbsp;5.4 of <xref
      target="RFC7731"/>, each parameter in the set should be the same
      for all nodes within an MPL Domain, but <xref target="RFC7731"/> does
      not define a method to configure the MPL parameter set.</t>

      <t>Some managed wireless mesh networks may have a DHCP server to
      configure network parameters. MPL parameter sets shall be considered as
      a part of network parameters (nodes in an MPL Domain should use an
      identical parameter set). A parameter set is required to configure
      an MPL Domain.</t>

      <t>This document defines a way to distribute parameter sets for
      MPL Forwarders via a new <xref target="RFC3315" pageno="false"
      format="default">DHCPv6</xref> option. This document is intended to
      follow the guidelines provided in <xref target="RFC7227" pageno="false" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"
      pageno="false" format="default"/>.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="MPL Parameter Configuration Option" anchor="mpl-parameter-configuration-option" toc="default">
      <t>As defined in Section&nbsp;5.4 of <xref target="RFC7731"
      pageno="false" format="default"/>, there are 10 parameters per MPL
      Domain, as listed below. An MPL Domain is defined by an MPL Domain
      Address, as described in Section&nbsp;2 of <xref target="RFC7731"
      pageno="false" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>PROACTIVE_FORWARDING </t>
          <t>SEED_SET_ENTRY_LIFETIME </t>
          <t>DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN </t>
          <t>DATA_MESSAGE_IMAX </t>
          <t>DATA_MESSAGE_K </t>
          <t>DATA_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS </t>
          <t>CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN </t>
          <t>CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMAX </t>
          <t>CONTROL_MESSAGE_K </t>
          <t>CONTROL_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>One network may have multiple MPL Domains with different configurations. To configure more than one MPL Domain via DHCP, there may be more than one MPL Parameter Configuration Option given to DHCP clients by a DHCP server.</t>
      <section title="MPL Parameter Configuration Option Format" anchor="mpl-parameter-configuration-option-format" toc="default">
        <t>This document defines the OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS DHCPv6 option.
        This new option provides a means to distribute a configuration of
        an MPL Domain or a default value for all MPL Domains (a wildcard)
        within the network managed by the DHCP server. This option has
        the following format:</t>

        <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS      |          option_len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|P|     Z       |     TUNIT     |            SE_LIFETIME        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    DM_K       |         DM_IMIN               |     DM_IMAX   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         DM_T_EXP              |      C_K      |    C_IMIN     &gt;
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
&gt;(cont'ed)      |    C_IMAX     |          C_T_EXP              |     
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

(if option_len = 32)
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          MPL Domain Address  (128 bits)                       &gt;
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
&gt;          (cont'ed)                                            &gt;
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
&gt;          (cont'ed)                                            &gt;
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
&gt;          (cont'ed)                                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS:">DHCPv6 option identifier
            (104).</t>

            <t hangText="option_len:">Length of the option in octets.
            The value MUST be set&nbsp;to 16 if no MPL Domain Address is
            present, or 32 if an MPL&nbsp;Domain&nbsp;Address is present.</t>

            <t hangText="P (1 bit):">A flag to indicate
            PROACTIVE_FORWARDING. This flag is set if
            PROACTIVE_FORWARDING = TRUE.</t>

            <t hangText="Z (7 bits):">Reserved for future use. Servers MUST
            set them to zero.  Clients SHOULD ignore any bits that have been
            set.</t>

            <t hangText="TUNIT (unsigned 8-bit integer):">Unit time of timer
            parameters (SE_LIFETIME and *_IMIN) in this option. &nbsp;0 and
            0xff are reserved and MUST NOT be used.</t>

            <t hangText="SE_LIFETIME (unsigned 16-bit integer):">
            SEED_SET_ENTRY_LIFETIME/&wj;TUNIT, in milliseconds. &nbsp;0 and
            0xffff are reserved and MUST NOT be&nbsp;used.</t>

            <t hangText="DM_K (unsigned 8-bit integer):">DATA_MESSAGE_K.</t>

            <t hangText="DM_IMIN (unsigned 16-bit integer):">
            DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN/TUNIT, in&nbsp;milliseconds. &nbsp;0 and 0xffff
            are reserved and MUST NOT be used.</t>

            <t hangText="DM_IMAX (unsigned 8-bit integer):">
            DATA_MESSAGE_IMAX. The actual maximum timeout is described
            as a number of doublings of DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN, as described
            in <xref target="RFC6206" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
            Section&nbsp;4.1. &nbsp;0&nbsp;and&nbsp;0xff are reserved and
            MUST NOT be used.</t>

            <t hangText="DM_T_EXP (unsigned 16-bit integer):">
            DATA_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS. &nbsp;0 and 0xffff are
            reserved and MUST NOT be used.</t>

            <t hangText="C_K (unsigned 8-bit integer):">CONTROL_MESSAGE_K.</t>

            <t hangText="C_IMIN (unsigned 16-bit integer):">
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN/TUNIT, in&nbsp;milliseconds. &nbsp;0 and
            0xffff are reserved and MUST NOT be used.</t>

            <t hangText="C_IMAX (unsigned 8-bit integer):">
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMAX. The actual maximum timeout is described
            as a number of doublings of CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN. &nbsp;0 and
            0xff are reserved and MUST NOT be&nbsp;used.</t>

            <t hangText="C_T_EXP (unsigned 16-bit integer):"><vspace/>
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS. &nbsp;0 and 0xffff are
            reserved and MUST NOT be used.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Note that the time values (SEED_SET_ENTRY_LIFETIME,
        DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN, and CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN) in MPL are defined to
        a precision of TUNIT&nbsp;milliseconds in MPL Parameter Configuration
        Options. For example, if TUNIT is 20 and the minimum Data Message
        interval (DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN) is 1000&nbsp;ms, then DM_IMIN shall be
        set to&nbsp;50.</t>

        <t>For the maximum interval size (*_IMAX), <xref target="RFC6206"
        pageno="false" format="default"/> defines them as follows: </t>

        <t>
          <list style="empty">
            <t>The maximum interval size, Imax, is described as a number of
            doublings of the minimum interval size (the base-2
            log(max/min)). For example, a protocol might define Imax as 16.
            If the minimum interval is 100 ms, then the amount of time
            specified by Imax is 100 ms * 65,536, i.e., 6,553.6 seconds or
            approximately 109&nbsp;minutes.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Because the minimum interval size in MPL Parameter Configuration
        Options is described in TUNIT&nbhy;millisecond precision, the
        corresponding maximum interval size is also in
        TUNIT&nbhy;millisecond precision. For example, if TUNIT is 10
        and C_IMIN is 50, the minimum interval size of the Trickle timer
        for Control Messages is 500&nbsp;ms. In this case, the maximum
        interval size of the Trickle timer is 32&nbsp;seconds
        (500&nbsp;ms&nbsp;*&nbsp;2^6) if C_IMAX is 6.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-client-behavior" toc="default">
        <t>Clients MAY request the MPL Parameter Configuration Option as
        described in Sections&nbsp;17.1.1, 18.1.1, 18.1.3, 18.1.4, 18.1.5,
        and 22.7 of <xref target="RFC3315"/>. As a convenience to the
        reader, we mention here that the client includes requested
        option codes in the Option Request Option.</t>

        <t>Clients MUST support multiple MPL Parameter Configuration Options,
        which are listed in <xref target="mpl-parameter-configuration-option"/>.
</t>

        <t>If a DHCPv6 client with an MPL Forwarder configured by the MPL
        Parameter Configuration Option is unable to receive a valid response
        from a server within T2 <xref target="RFC3315"/> of the last
        valid DHCPv6 message sent from the server (if stateful) or twice
        the information refresh time <xref target="RFC4242"/> (if stateless),
        it MUST suspend the MPL Forwarders of the MPL Domains configured by
        the option.  MPL Forwarders configured by other methods (e.g., via
        a static configuration file) MUST NOT be suspended.</t>

        <t>Clients MUST ignore all MPL Parameter Configuration Options if the
        options in a DHCPv6 message contain any invalid values (e.g.,
        reserved all&nbhy;0 or all&nbhy;1 values are used in parameters).
        In this case, in the context of MPL the message is considered not
        received, and the condition described in the previous paragraph
        applies.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="MPL Forwarder Behavior" anchor="mpl-forwarder-behavior" toc="default">
        <t>If a DHCPv6 client requests and receives the MPL Parameter
        Configuration Option, the node SHOULD join the MPL Domain given by the
        option and act as an MPL Forwarder. Note that there may be cases in
        which a node may fail to join a domain (or domains) due to local
        resource constraints. Each joining node SHOULD configure its MPL
        Forwarder with the given parameter set for the MPL Domain.  Each MPL
        Domain is defined by an MPL Domain Address given by an MPL Parameter
        Configuration Option. As defined in Section&nbsp;2 of <xref
        target="RFC7731" pageno="false" format="default"/>, an MPL Domain
        Address is an IPv6 multicast address associated to a set of MPL
        network interfaces in an MPL Domain.</t>

        <t>The priority of MPL parameter configurations applied to an
        MPL Domain is as follows (high to low):</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Specific MPL parameter configuration for the MPL Domain
            (option_len&nbsp;=&nbsp;32&nbsp;bits).</t>
            <t>Wildcard MPL parameter configuration
            (option_len = 16&nbsp;bits).</t>
            <t>Default configuration as described in <xref target="RFC7731"/>.
               </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>Priorities of other configurations, such as manual configuration
        of a node, are not defined in this document.</t>

        <t>There MUST be no more than one MPL Parameter Configuration Option
        for an MPL Domain or the wildcard. Thus, the order of DHCPv6 options
        in the packet has no effect on precedence.</t>

        <t>A node MUST leave an MPL Domain if it receives updated and
        all&nbhy;valid MPL Parameter Configuration Options without a
        configuration for the MPL Domain, unless it has an overriding
        manual configuration for the MPL Domain. In other words, if a node
        is configured to work as an MPL Forwarder for an MPL Domain
        regardless of DHCPv6 options, the node MAY stay in the MPL Domain
        even if it receives an MPL Parameter Configuration Option without a
        configuration for the MPL Domain.</t>

        <t>MPL parameters may be updated occasionally. With stateful DHCPv6,
        updates can be done when the renewal timer expires.  The <xref
        target="RFC4242" pageno="false" format="default">information refresh
        time option</xref> shall be used to keep each forwarder updated.</t>

        <t>To reduce periodic update traffic, a node may try to use a very
        long interval between updates. In this case, Reconfigure messages may
        be used to keep forwarder parameter sets synchronized.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-server-behavior" toc="default">
        <t>Sections 17.2.2 and 18.2 of <xref target="RFC3315" pageno="false"
        format="default"/> govern server operation in regard to option
        assignment. As a convenience to the reader, we mention here that the
        server will send the MPL Parameter Configuration Option only if it was
        configured with specific values for the MPL Parameter Configuration
        Option and the client requested&nbsp;it.</t>

        <t>Servers MUST ignore an incoming MPL Parameter Configuration
        Option. Servers MUST support multiple MPL Parameter Configuration
        Options, which are listed in <xref
        target="mpl-parameter-configuration-option"/>.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="DHCPv6 Relay Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-relay-behavior" toc="default">
        <t>It is never appropriate for a relay agent to add options to a
        message heading toward the client, and relay agents do not actually
        construct Relay&nbhy;Reply messages anyway. There are no additional
        requirements for relays.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Operational Considerations" anchor="operational-considerations" toc="default">
        <t>This document introduces the dynamic updating of MPL parameters.
        Because the update process is not synchronized, nodes may have
        inconsistent parameter sets.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC6206" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
        Section&nbsp;6 describes various problems that occur if the Trickle
        timers do not match between communicating nodes. To keep the timers
        synchronized, it is RECOMMENDED to not update the parameters of an MPL
        Domain too often. A reasonable update rate would be once per expected
        information refresh time interval, such as T1 <xref target="RFC3315"
        pageno="false" format="default"/> or information refresh time as
        defined in <xref target="RFC4242" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t>

        <t>Inconsistent parameter sets may reduce performance. On the other
        hand, this situation will work as long as both new and old parameter
        sets are reasonable parameter sets for a given communication load.
        Because motivations for parameter updates include updates of the
        environment, node density, or communication load, operators of MPL
        networks need to be aware of nodes that are not updated and make
        sure that old and new parameter sets are reasonable for the
        expected refresh intervals.</t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations" toc="default">
      <t>IANA has assigned an option code to OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS (104)
      from the "Option Codes" table of the "Dynamic Host Configuration
      Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)" registry
      (http://www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters).</t>

    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations" toc="default">
      <t>Section&nbsp;23 of <xref target="RFC3315" pageno="false"
      format="default"></xref>, Section&nbsp;23 of <xref
      target="RFC7227" pageno="false" format="default"></xref>, and
      Section&nbsp;12 of <xref target="RFC7731"/> provide detailed
      discussions regarding security threats for DHCPv6.</t>

      <t>Note also that a forged MPL parameter configuration may cause
      excessive Layer&nbsp;2 broadcasting. Implementations should set
      reasonable bounds for each parameter -- for example, not setting
      DM/&wj;C_K too high, not setting DM/C_IMIN too low. These bounds
      may be implementation dependent or may be derived from MAC/PHY
      specifications. DHCPv6 server and client implementations need to
      take care in setting reasonable bounds for each parameter in order to
      avoid overloading the network.</t>

      <t>The DHCP server or the network itself should be trusted by some
      means, such as DHCPv6 authentication as described in Section&nbsp;21
      of <xref target="RFC3315" pageno="false" format="default"></xref>.
      However, Routing Over Low&nbhy;Power and Lossy (ROLL) network
      environments often have fewer computing resources, and
      DHCPv6 authentication may not be available in these environments.
      In such cases, other methods to protect integrity between
      DHCPv6 servers and clients should be applied to a ROLL network.
      Some specifications related to ROLL implementations, such as
      <xref target="ZigBeeIP" pageno="false" format="default">
      ZigBee&nbsp;IP</xref> and
      <xref target="RFC5191" pageno="false" format="default"></xref>,
      assume that joining nodes will be authenticated so that all nodes
      in the network can be trusted. To protect against attacks from
      outside of the network, DHCPv6 packets SHOULD be filtered on the
      border router between the ROLL network and the Internet, except for
      packets between the ROLL network and a remote DHCPv6 server or
      DHCPv6 relays configured to manage the network.</t>

    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

    &RFC2119;
    &RFC3315;
    &RFC4242;
    &RFC6206;
    &RFC7227;

<!-- draft-ietf-roll-trickle-mcast (RFC 7731; published Feb. 2016) -->
      <reference anchor="RFC7731" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7731">
        <front>
          <title>Multicast Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks (MPL)</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Hui" fullname="Jonathan Hui">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R" surname="Kelsey" fullname="Richard Kelsey">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2016"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7731' />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7731"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

    &RFC5191;

      <reference anchor="ZigBeeIP" target="http://www.zigbee.org/">
        <front>
          <title>ZigBee IP Specification</title>
          <author surname="" fullname="">
            <organization>ZigBee Alliance </organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2015"/>
          <abstract>
            <t/>
          </abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
