<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8196" 
     category="std" 
     submissionType="IETF" 
     consensus="yes" 
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Autoconfiguration">IS-IS Autoconfiguration</title>

    <author fullname="Bing Liu" initials="B." role="editor" surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q10, Huawei Campus, No.156 Beiqing Road</street>

          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing, 100095</city>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>leo.liubing@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Les Ginsberg" initials="L." surname="Ginsberg">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>821 Alder Drive</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <region/>

          <code>CA 95035</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>ginsberg@cisco.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bruno Decraene" initials="B." surname="Decraene">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ian Farrer" initials="I." surname="Farrer">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Bonn</city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ian.farrer@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mikael Abrahamsson" initials="M." surname="Abrahamsson">
      <organization>T-Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mikael.abrahamsson@t-systems.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2017"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>isis</workgroup>

    <keyword>isis auto-configuration</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies IS-IS autoconfiguration mechanisms. The key
      components are IS-IS System ID self-generation, duplication detection,
      and duplication resolution. These mechanisms provide limited IS-IS
      functions and are therefore suitable for networks where plug-and-play
      configuration is expected.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document specifies mechanisms for IS-IS <xref target="RFC1195"/> 
      <xref target="ISO_IEC10589"/> <xref target="RFC5308"/> to be
      autoconfiguring. Such mechanisms could reduce the management burden for
      configuring a network, especially where plug-and-play device
      configuration is required.</t>

      <t>IS-IS autoconfiguration is comprised of the following
      functions:<list style="numbers">
          <t hangText="-">IS-IS default configuration</t>

          <t hangText="-">IS-IS System ID self-generation</t>

          <t hangText="-">System ID duplication detection and resolution</t>

          <t hangText="-">IS-IS TLV utilization (authentication TLV, metrics in
          reachability advertisements, and Dynamic Name TLV)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document also defines mechanisms to prevent the unintentional
      interoperation of autoconfigured routers with non-autoconfigured
      routers. See <xref target="TLV"/>.</t>


     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
       NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
       and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
       BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
       when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here. When these words are 
       not in ALL CAPS (such as "should" or "Should"), they have their usual
       English meanings and are not to be interpreted as
       <xref target="RFC2119"/> key words.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Scope">
      <t>The autoconfiguration mechanisms support both IPv4 and IPv6
      deployments.</t>

      <t>These autoconfiguration mechanisms aim to cover simple deployment
      cases. The following important features are not supported:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="o">multiple IS-IS instances</t>

          <t hangText="o">multi-area and level-2 routing</t>

          <t hangText="o">interworking with other routing protocols</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>IS-IS autoconfiguration is primarily intended for use in small (i.e.,
      10s of devices) and unmanaged deployments. It allows IS-IS to be used
      without the need for any configuration by the user. It is not
      recommended for larger deployments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Specification  ">
      <t/>

      <section title="IS-IS Default Configuration">

<t>This section defines the default configuration for an autoconfigured router.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="o">IS-IS interfaces MUST be autoconfigured to an
            interface type corresponding to their Layer 2 capability. For
            example, Ethernet interfaces will be autoconfigured as broadcast
            networks and Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP) interfaces will be
            autoconfigured as Point-to-Point interfaces.</t>

            <t hangText="o">IS-IS autoconfiguration instances MUST be
            configured as level-1 so that the interfaces operate as level-1
            only.</t>

            <t hangText="o">originatingLSPBufferSize is set to 512.</t>

            <t hangText="o">MaxAreaAddresses is set to 3.</t>

            <t hangText="o">Extended IS reachability (TLV 22) and IP
	    reachability (TLV 135) TLVs
            <xref target="RFC5305"/> MUST be used, i.e., a router operating in
            autoconfiguration mode MUST NOT use any of the following
            TLVs:<list style="symbols">
                <t>IIS Neighbors (TLV 2)</t>

                <t>IP Int. Reach (TLV 128)</t>

                <t>IP Ext. Address (TLV 130)</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The TLVs listed above MUST be ignored on receipt.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="NETGen" title="IS-IS NET Generation">
        <t>In IS-IS, a router (known as an Intermediate System) is identified
        by a Network Entity Title (NET), which is a type of Network Service
        Access Point (NSAP). The NET is the address of an instance of the
        IS-IS protocol running on an IS.</t>

        <t>The autoconfiguration mechanism generates the IS-IS NET as the
        following:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="o">Area address<list style="empty">
                <t>In IS-IS autoconfiguration, this field MUST be 13 octets
                long and set to all 0s.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="o">System ID<list style="empty">
                <t>This field follows the area address field and is 6 octets
                in length. There are two basic requirements for the System ID
                generation:<list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="-">As specified by the IS-IS protocol, this
                    field must be unique among all routers in the same
                    area.</t>

                    <t hangText="-">After its initial generation, the System
                    ID SHOULD remain stable. Changes such as interface
                    enable/disable, interface connect/disconnect, device
                    reboot, firmware update, or configuration changes SHOULD
                    NOT cause the System ID to change. System ID change as
                    part of the System ID collision resolution process MUST be
                    supported. Implementations SHOULD allow the System ID to
                    be cleared by a user-initiated system reset.</t>
                  </list></t>

                <t>More specific considerations for System ID generation are
                described in <xref target="Unique"/>.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="TLV" title="Router-Fingerprint TLV">

<!--[rfced] Please resolve the following:

c) FYI - We see that "autoconfiguration", without the hyphen, is far
more common in past RFCs.  We will update to this version throughout.

-->
        <t>The Router-Fingerprint TLV is similar to the
        Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV defined in <xref target="RFC7503"/>.
        However, the TLV defined here includes a Flags field to support
        indicating that the router is in startup mode and is operating in
        autoconfiguration mode.</t>


<figure title="">
   <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |    Length     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Flags        |                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+        Router-Fingerprint (Variable)          .
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>
</artwork>
	  </figure>

<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Type:">15.</t>
<t hangText="Length:">The length, in octets, of the "Flags" and
"Router-Fingerprint" fields.</t>
<t hangText="Flags:">1 octet.</t>
</list></t>


<figure title="">
  <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |S|A| Reserved  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>

<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="S flag:">When set, indicates the router is in "startup" mode.</t>
<t hangText="A flag:">When set, indicates that the router is operating in 
     autoconfiguration mode. The purpose of the flag is so that 
     two routers can identify if they are both using autoconfiguration.
     If the A flag setting does not match in hellos, then no adjacency
     should be formed.</t>
<t hangText="Reserved:">These flags MUST be set to zero and MUST be ignored by
     the receiver.</t>
<t hangText="Router-Fingerprint:">32 or more octets.</t>
</list></t>
        <t>More specific considerations for Router-Fingerprint are described
        in <xref target="Unique"/>.</t>

	<t>The Router-Fingerprint TLV with the A flag set MUST be included in
	IS-IS Hellos (IIHs) originated by a router operating in
	autoconfiguration mode.  An autoconfiguration mode router MUST
	ignore IIHs that don't contain the Router-Fingerprint TLV with the A
	flag set.</t>

        <t>The Router-Fingerprint TLV with the A flag set MUST be included in
	Link State PDU (LSP) #0 originated by a router operating in
	autoconfiguration mode.  If an LSP #0 is received  by a router
	operating in autoconfiguration mode and the LSP either does NOT
	contain a Router-Fingerprint TLV or it does contain a
	Router-Fingerprint TLV but the A flag is NOT set, then the LSP is
	flooded as normal, but the entire LSP set originated by the sending
	router MUST be ignored when running the Decision Process.</t>


        <t>The Router-Fingerprint TLV MUST NOT be included in an LSP with a
        non-zero number and when received MUST be ignored.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Protocol Operation">
        <t>This section describes the operation of a router supporting
        autoconfiguration mode.</t>

        <section title="Startup Mode">

          <t>When a router starts operation in autoconfiguration mode, both
          the S and A flags MUST be set in the Router-Fingerprint TLV included
          in both hellos and LSP #0. During this mode, only LSP #0 is generated
          and IS or IP/IPv6 reachability TLVs MUST NOT be included in LSP #0.
          A router remains in startup mode for a minimum period of time
          (recommended to be 1 minute). This time should be sufficient to
          bring up adjacencies to all expected neighbors. A router leaves
          startup mode once the minimum time has elapsed and full LSP
          database synchronization is achieved with all neighbors in the UP
          state.</t>

          <t>When a router exits startup mode, it clears the S flag in Router-Fingerprint
          TLVs that it sends in hellos and LSP #0. The router MAY now
          advertise the IS neighbor and IP/IPv6 prefix reachability in its LSPs
          and MAY generate LSPs with a non-zero number.</t>

          <t>The purpose of startup mode is to minimize the occurrence of
          System ID changes for a router once it has become fully operational.
          Any System ID change during startup mode will have minimal impact
          on a running network because, while in startup mode, the router is
          not yet being used for forwarding traffic.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Adjacency Formation">
          <t>Routers operating in autoconfiguration mode MUST NOT form
          adjacencies with routers that are NOT operating in
          autoconfiguration mode. The presence of the Router-Fingerprint TLV
          with the A flag set indicates the router is operating in
          autoconfiguration mode.</t>

          <t>NOTE: The use of the special area address of all 0s makes it
          unlikely that a router that is not operating in autoconfiguration
          mode will be in the same area as a router operating in
          autoconfiguration mode. However, the check for the Router-Fingerprint
          TLV with the A flag set provides additional protection.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="IS-IS System ID Duplication Detection">
          <t>The System ID of each node MUST be unique. As described in <xref
          target="Unique"/>, the System ID is generated based on entropies
          (e.g., Media Access Control (MAC) address) that are generally expected to be unique.
          However, since there may be limitations to the available entropies,
          there is still the possibility of System ID duplication. This
          section defines how IS-IS detects and resolves System ID
          duplication. A duplicate system ID may occur between neighbors or
          between routers in the same area that are not neighbors.</t>

          <t>A duplicate system ID with a neighbor is detected when the System
          ID received in an IIH is identical to the local System ID and the
          Router-Fingerprint in the received Router-Fingerprint TLV does NOT
          match the locally generated Router-Fingerprint.</t>

          <t>A duplicate system ID with a non-neighbor is detected when an LSP
          #0 is received, the System ID of the originator is identical to the
          local System ID, and the Router-Fingerprint in the
          Router-Fingerprint TLV does NOT match the locally generated
          Router-Fingerprint.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="duplt"
                 title="Duplicate System ID Resolution Procedures">
          <t>When a duplicate system ID is detected, one of the systems MUST
          assign itself a different System ID and perform a protocol restart.
          The resolution procedure attempts to minimize disruption to a running
          network by choosing, whenever possible, to restart a router that is
	  in startup mode.</t>

          <t>The contents of the Router-Fingerprint TLVs for the two routers
          with duplicate system IDs are compared.</t>

          <t>If one TLV has the S flag set (the router is in startup mode) and one
          TLV has the S flag clear (the router is NOT in startup mode), the router
          in startup mode MUST generate a new System ID and restart the
          protocol.</t>

          <t>If both TLVs have the S flag set (both routers are in startup
          mode) or both TLVs have the S flag clear (neither router is in
          startup mode), then the router with the numerically smaller
          Router-Fingerprint MUST generate a new System ID and restart the
          protocol.</t>

          <t>Fingerprint comparison is performed octet by octet starting from
          the first received octet until a difference is detected. If the
	  fingerprints have different lengths and all octets up to the shortest
	  length are identical, then the fingerprint with smaller length is
	  considered smaller on the whole.</t>

          <t>If the fingerprints are identical in both content and length (and the
          state of the S flag is identical), and the duplication is detected in
          hellos, then both routers MUST generate a new System ID and
          restart the protocol.</t>

          <t>If fingerprints are identical in both content and length, and the
          duplication is detected in LSP #0, then the procedures defined in
          <xref target="DDuplct"/> MUST be followed.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Unique"
                 title="System ID and Router-Fingerprint Generation Considerations">
          <t>As specified in this document, there are two distinguishing items
          that need to be self-generated: the System ID and
          Router-Fingerprint. In a network device, normally there are some
          resources that can provide an extremely high probability of
          uniqueness (some examples listed below). These resources can be used
          as seeds to derive identifiers:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>MAC address(es)</t>

              <t>Configured IP address(es)</t>

              <t>Hardware IDs (e.g., CPU ID)</t>

              <t>Device serial number(s)</t>

              <t>System clock at a certain, specific time</t>

              <t>Arbitrary received packet(s) on an interface(s)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This document recommends the use of an IEEE 802 48-bit MAC
          address associated with the router as the initial System ID. This
          document does not specify a specific method to regenerate the
          System ID when duplication happens.</t>

          <t>This document also does not specify a method to generate
          the Router-Fingerprint.</t>

          <t>There is an important concern that the seeds listed above (except
          MAC address) might not be available in some small devices such as
          home routers. This is because of hardware/software limitations and
          the lack of sufficient communication packets at the initial stage in
          home routers when doing IS-IS autoconfiguration. In this case, this
          document suggests using the MAC address as the System ID and generating
          a pseudorandom number based on another seed (such as the memory
          address of a certain variable in the program) as the
          Router-Fingerprint. The pseudorandom number might not have a very
          high probability of uniqueness in this solution but should be
          sufficient in home network scenarios.</t>

          <t>The considerations surrounding System ID stability described in
          <xref target="NETGen"/> also need to be applied.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="DDuplct"
                 title="Duplication of Both System ID and Router-Fingerprint">
          <t>As described above, the resources for generating a System
          ID / Router-Fingerprint might be very constrained during the initial stages.
          Hence, the duplication of both System ID and Router-Fingerprint
          need to be considered. In such a case, it is possible that a router
          will receive an LSP with a System ID and Router-Fingerprint identical
          to the local values, but the LSP is NOT identical to the locally
          generated copy, i.e., the sequence number is newer or the sequence number is
          the same, but the LSP has a valid checksum that does not match. The
          term DD-LSP (Duplication Detection LSP) is used to describe such an LSP.</t>

          <t>In a benign case, this will occur if a router restarts and it
          receives copies of its own LSPs from its previous incarnation. This
          benign case needs to be distinguished from the pathological case
          where there are two different routers with the same System ID and
          the same Router-Fingerprint.</t>

          <t>In the benign case, the restarting router will generate a new
          version of its own LSP with a higher sequence number and flood the new
          LSP version. This will cause other routers in the network to update
          their LSP Database (LSPDB) and synchronization will be achieved.</t>

          <t>In the pathological case, the generation of a new version of an
          LSP by one of the "twins" will cause the other twin to generate the
          same LSP with a higher sequence number -- and oscillation will
          continue without achieving LSPDB synchronization.</t>

          <t>Note that a comparison of the S flag in the Router-Fingerprint TLV
          cannot be performed, as in the benign case it is expected that the S
          flag will be clear. Also note that the conditions for detecting a
          duplicate system ID will NOT be satisfied because both the System ID
          and the Router-Fingerprint will be identical.</t>

          <t>The following procedure is defined:</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[    DD-state is a boolean that indicates if a 
      DD-LSP #0 has been received.
    DD-count is the count of the number of occurrences
      of reception of a DD-LSP.
    DD-timer is a timer associated with reception of 
     DD-LSPs; the recommended value is 60 seconds.
    DD-max is the maximum number of DD-LSPs allowed 
     to be received in DD-timer interval; 
     the recommended value is 3.

When a DD-LSP is received:

  If DD-state is FALSE:
    DD-state is set to TRUE.
    DD-timer is started.
    DD-count is initialized to 1.

  If DD-state is TRUE:
    DD-count is incremented.
    If DD-count is >= DD-max:
       The local system MUST generate a new System ID 
        and Router-Fingerprint and restart the protocol.
       DD-state is (re)initialized to FALSE and
        DD-timer is canceled.

  If DD-timer expires:
    DD-state is set to FALSE.
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Note that to minimize the likelihood of duplication of both System
          ID and Router-Fingerprint reoccurring, routers SHOULD have more
          entropies available. One simple way to achieve this is to add the
          LSP sequence number of the next LSP it will send to the
          Router-Fingerprint.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Additional IS-IS TLVs Usage Guidelines">
        <t>This section describes the behavior of selected TLVs when used by a
        router supporting IS-IS autoconfiguration.</t>

        <section anchor="AuthTLV" title="Authentication TLV">
          <t>It is RECOMMENDED that IS-IS routers supporting this
          specification offer an option to explicitly configure a single
          password for HMAC-MD5 authentication as specified in <xref
          target="RFC5304"> </xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Metric Used in Reachability TLVs">
          <t>It is RECOMMENDED that IS-IS autoconfiguration routers use a
          high metric value (e.g., 100000) as default in order to allow
          manually configured adjacencies to be preferred over
          autoconfigured.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Dynamic Name TLV">
          <t>IS-IS autoconfiguration routers MAY advertise their Dynamic Name TLV
          (TLV 137 <xref target="RFC5301"/>). The hostname could be
          provisioned by an IT system or just use the name of vendor, device
          type, or serial number, etc.</t>

          <t>To guarantee the uniqueness of the hostname, the System ID
          SHOULD be appended as a suffix in the names.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>In the absence of cryptographic authentication, it is possible for an
      attacker to inject a PDU falsely indicating there is a duplicate
      system ID. This may trigger automatic restart of the protocol using the
      duplicate-id resolution procedures defined in this document.</t>

      <t>Note that the use of authentication is incompatible with
      autoconfiguration as it requires some manual configuration.</t>

      <t>For wired deployment, the wired connection itself could be considered
      as an implicit authentication in that unwanted routers are usually not
      able to connect (i.e., there is some kind of physical security in place
      preventing the connection of rogue devices); for wireless deployment,
      the authentication could be achieved at the lower wireless link
      layer.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document details a new IS-IS TLV 
      reflected in the "IS-IS TLV Codepoints" registry:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
Value  Name                             IIH LSP SNP Purge
----  ------------                      --- --- --- -----
15    Router-Fingerprint                 Y   Y   N    Y

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1195'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5301'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5304'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5305'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5308'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <reference anchor="ISO_IEC10589">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Telecommunications and information
	  exchange between systems -- Intermediate System to Intermediate
	  System intra-domain routeing information exchange protocol for use
	  in conjunction with the protocol for providing the
	  connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)</title>

          <author><organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization></author>

          <date month="November" year="2002"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC 10589:2002," value="Second Edition"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7503'?>

      
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>This document was heavily inspired by <xref target="RFC7503"/>.</t>

      <t>Martin Winter, Christian Franke, and David Lamparter gave essential
      feedback to improve the technical design based on their implementation
      experience.</t>

      <t>Many useful comments were made by Acee Lindem, Karsten Thomann,
      Hannes Gredler, Peter Lothberg, Uma Chundury, Qin Wu, Sheng Jiang, and
      Nan Wu, etc.</t>

    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>


