<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5012 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5012.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6881 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.6881.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6442 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.6442.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5962 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5962.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5491 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5491.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5069 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5069.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4481 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.4481.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5031 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7303 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.7303.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6838 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.6838.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4119 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.4119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6443 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.6443.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7378 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.7378.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7852 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.7852.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6086 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.6086.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>


<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" number="8148" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Vehicle-Initiated Emergency Calls">Next-Generation Vehicle-Initiated Emergency Calls</title>

    <author initials="R." surname="Gellens" fullname="Randall Gellens">
      <organization>Core Technology Consulting</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rg+ietf@coretechnologyconsulting.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.coretechnologyconsulting.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="B." surname="Rosen" fullname="Brian Rosen">
      <organization>NeuStar, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>470 Conrad Dr</street>
          <city>Mars</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <code>16046</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone> </phone>
        <email>br@brianrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
        <organization>Individual</organization>
        <address>
            <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
            <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2017"/>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time (ART)</area>
    <workgroup>ECRIT</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes how to use IP-based emergency services mechanisms to support the next generation of emergency calls placed by vehicles (automatically in the event of a crash or serious incident, or manually invoked by a vehicle occupant) and conveying vehicle, sensor, and location data related to the crash or incident.  Such calls are often referred to as "Automatic Crash Notification" (ACN), or "Advanced Automatic Crash Notification" (AACN), even in the case of manual trigger.  The "Advanced" qualifier refers to the ability to carry a richer set of data.</t>

<t>This document also registers a MIME media type and Emergency Call Data Type for the vehicle, sensor, and location data (often referred to as "crash data" even though there is not necessarily a crash) and an INFO package to enable carrying this and related data in SIP INFO requests.  An external specification for the data format, contents, and structure is referenced in this document.</t> 

<t>This document reuses the technical aspects of next-generation Pan-European
eCall (a mandated and standardized system for emergency calls by in-vehicle
systems (IVSs) within Europe and other regions).  However, this document
specifies use of a different set of vehicle (crash) data, specifically, the
Vehicle Emergency Data Set (VEDS) rather than the eCall Minimum Set of Data
(MSD).  This document is an extension of the IETF eCall document, with the
primary differences being that this document makes the MSD data set optional
and VEDS mandatory, and it adds attribute values to the metadata/control
object to permit greater functionality.  This document registers a new
INFO package (identical to that registered for eCall but with the addition of
the VEDS MIME type).  This document also describes legacy (circuit-switched)
ACN systems and their migration to next-generation emergency calling, to
provide background information and context. 
</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>


  
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Emergency calls made by in-vehicle systems (e.g., automatically in the event of a crash or serious incident or manually by a vehicle occupant) assist in significantly reducing road deaths and injuries by allowing emergency services to respond quickly and appropriately to the specifics of the incident, often with better location accuracy.</t>

    <t>Drivers often have a poor location awareness, especially outside of major cities, at night, and when away from home (especially abroad).  In the most crucial cases, the victim(s) might not be able to call because they have been injured or trapped.</t>

    <t>For more than two decades, some vehicles have been equipped with telematics systems that, among other features, place an emergency call automatically in the event of a crash or manually in response to an emergency call button.  Such systems generally have on-board location determination systems that make use of satellite-based positioning technology, inertial sensors, gyroscopes, etc., which can provide an accurate position for the vehicle.  Such built-in systems can take advantage of the benefits of being integrated into a vehicle, such as more power capacity, ability to have larger or specialized antenna, ability to be engineered to avoid or minimize degradation by vehicle glass coatings, interference from other vehicle systems, etc.  Thus, the Public Safety Answering Point (PSAP) can be provided with a good estimate of where the vehicle is during an emergency.  Vehicle manufacturers are increasingly adopting such systems, both for the safety benefits and for the additional features and services they enable (e.g., remote engine diagnostics, remote door unlock, stolen vehicle tracking and disabling, etc.).</t>

    <t>A common term for such systems is Automatic Crash Notification (ACN) or Advanced Automatic Crash Notification (AACN).  Sometimes the word "Collision" is used instead of "Crash."  In this document, "ACN" is used as a general term.  ACN systems transmit some amount of data specific to the incident, referred to generally as "crash data" (the term is commonly used even though there might not have been a crash).   While different systems transmit different amounts of crash data, standardized formats, structures, and mechanisms are needed to provide interoperability among systems and PSAPs.</t>

    <t>As of the date of this document, currently deployed in-vehicle telematics systems are circuit-switched and lack a standards-based ability to convey crash data directly to the PSAP (generally relying on either a human advisor or an automated text-to-speech system to provide the PSAP call taker with some crash data orally, or in some cases via a proprietary mechanism).  In most cases, the PSAP call taker needs to first realize that the call is related to a vehicle incident, and then listen to the data and transcribe it.  Circuit-switched ACN systems are referred to here as "CS&nbhy;ACN".</t>

    <t>The transition to next-generation emergency calling provides an
   opportunity to vastly improve the scope, breadth, reliability, and
   usefulness of crash data by transmitting a standardized set during
   call setup; the data can be processed by the PSAP in an integrated,
   automated way and made available to the call taker at call
   presentation.  It also provides the ability for the call taker to
   request that a vehicle take certain actions, such as flashing lights
   or unlocking doors. In addition, vehicle manufacturers are provided an opportunity to take advantage of the same standardized mechanisms for data transmission and request processing for internal use if they wish (such as telemetry between the vehicle and a service center for both emergency and non-emergency uses, including location-based services, multimedia entertainment systems, remote door unlocking, remote diagnostics, and roadside assistance applications).</t>

    <t>Next-generation ACN provides an opportunity for such calls to be recognized and processed as such during call setup, and routed to an equipped PSAP where the vehicle data is available to assist the call taker in assessing and responding to the situation.  Next-generation (IP-based) ACN systems are referred to here as NG&nbhy;ACN.</t>

    <t>An ACN call can be initiated by a vehicle occupant or automatically
    initiated by vehicle systems in the event of a serious incident.  (The "A"
    in "ACN" does stand for "Automatic", but the term is broadly used to refer
    to the class of calls that are placed by an in-vehicle system (IVS) or by Telematics Service
    Providers (TSPs) and that carry incident-related data as well as voice.)
    Automatically triggered calls indicate a car crash or some other serious
    incident (e.g., a fire).  Manually triggered calls include reports of
    observed crashes or serious hazards (such as impaired drivers or roadway
    debris), requests for medical assistance, etc.</t> 

    <t>The Association of Public-Safety Communications Officials (APCO) and the National Emergency Number Association (NENA) have jointly developed a standardized set of incident-related vehicle data for ACN use, called the Vehicle Emergency Data Set (VEDS) <xref target="VEDS"/>.  Such data is often referred to as crash data although it is applicable in incidents other than crashes.</t>

    <t>This document describes how the IETF mechanisms for IP-based emergency
    calls are used to provide the realization of next-generation ACN.
    Although this specification is designed with the requirements for North
    America ACN in mind (and both APCO and NENA are based in the U.S.), it is
    specified generically such that the technology can be reused or extended
    to suit requirements in other regions.</t> 
    
    <t>This document reuses the technical aspects of next-generation Pan-European eCall (a mandated and standardized system for emergency calls by in-vehicle systems within Europe), as described in <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  However, this document specifies use of a different  set of vehicle (crash) data, specifically, VEDS rather than the eCall Minimum Set of Data (MSD).  This document is an extension of <xref target="RFC8147"/>, with the differences being that this document makes the MSD data set optional and VEDS mandatory, and it adds new attribute values to the metadata/control object defined in that document.  This document also registers a new INFO package (identical to that defined in <xref target="RFC8147"/> with the addition of the VEDS MIME type).</t>

<t>This document registers the application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml MIME
media type, the VEDS Emergency Call Data Type, and the EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO package to enable carrying this and related data in SIP INFO requests.</t> 

<t><xref target="vehicle-data"/> introduces VEDS.  <xref target="data-transport"/> describes how VEDS data and metadata/control blocks are transported within NG&nbhy;ACN calls.  <xref target="call-setup"/> describes how such calls are placed.</t>

<t>These mechanisms are used to place emergency calls that are identifiable as ACN calls and that carry standardized crash data in an interoperable way.</t>

<t>Calls by in-vehicle systems are placed using cellular networks, which might ignore location information sent by an originating device in an emergency call INVITE, instead substituting their own location information (although often determined in cooperation with the originating device).  Standardized crash data structures typically include location as determined by the IVS.  A benefit of this is that it allows the PSAP to see both the location as determined by the cellular network and the location as determined by the IVS.</t>

<t>This specification inherits the ability to utilize test call functionality from Section 15 of <xref target="RFC6881"/>.</t>

</section>

  <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>. </t> 

      <t>This document reuses terminology defined in Section 3 of <xref
          target="RFC5012"/>.</t>

      <t>Additionally, we use the following abbreviations:</t>
<!-- Dear [RFCed], please delete the two extra blank lines here -->
    <t><list>
        <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="9">
            <t hangText="3GPP:  ">3rd Generation Partnership Project</t>
            <t hangText="AACN:  ">Advanced Automatic Crash Notification</t>
            <t hangText="ACN:   ">Automatic Crash Notification</t>
            <t hangText="APCO:  ">Association of Public-Safety Communications Officials</t>
            <t hangText="EENA:  ">European Emergency Number Association</t>
            <t hangText="ESInet:">Emergency Services IP network</t>
            <t hangText="GNSS:  ">Global Navigation Satellite System (which includes various systems such as the Global Positioning System or GPS)</t>
            <t hangText="IVS:   ">In-Vehicle System</t>
            <t hangText="MNO:   ">Mobile Network Operator</t>
            <t hangText="MSD:   ">Minimum Set of Data</t>
            <t hangText="NENA:  ">National Emergency Number Association</t>
            <t hangText="NG:    ">Next Generation</t>
            <t hangText="POTS:  ">Plain Old Telephone Service (normal, circuit-switched voice calls)</t>
            <t hangText="PSAP:  ">Public Safety Answering Point</t>
            <t hangText="TSP:   ">Telematics Service Provider</t>
            <t hangText="VEDS:  ">Vehicle Emergency Data Set</t>
        </list></t>
    </list></t>
      

        <t>Because the endpoints of a next-generation ACN call are a PSAP and either an IVS or a TSP, to avoid repetitively writing "IVS or TSP", the term "IVS" is used to represent either an IVS or a TSP when discussing signaling behavior (e.g., sending VEDS data, sending a SIP INVITE request, receiving a SIP INFO request, etc.).</t>
    </section>


<section title="Document Scope">

<t>This document is focused on how an ACN emergency call is set up and incident-related data (including vehicle, sensor, and location data) is transmitted to the PSAP using IETF specifications.  For the direct model, this is the end-to-end description (between the vehicle and the PSAP).  For the TSP model, this describes the call leg between the TSP and the PSAP, leaving the call leg between the vehicle and the TSP up to the entities involved (i.e., IVS and TSP vendors) who are free to use the same mechanism for both legs, or not.
</t>

<t>Note that Europe has a mandated and standardized system for emergency calls
by in-vehicle systems.  This Pan-European system is known as "eCall" and is
the subject of a separate document, <xref target="RFC8147"/>, which this
document builds on.  Vehicles designed to operate in multiple regions might
need to support eCall as well as NG&nbhy;ACN as described here.  A vehicle IVS
might determine whether to use eCall or ACN by first determining the region or
country in which it is located (e.g., from a GNSS location estimate and/or
identity of or information from an MNO).  If other regions adopt other data
formats, a multi-region vehicle might need to support those as well.  This
document adopts the call setup and other technical aspects of <xref
target="RFC8147"/>, which uses <xref target="RFC7852"/>; this makes it
straightforward to use a different data set while keeping other technical
aspects unchanged.  Hence, both next-generation eCall (NG&nbhy;eCall) and the NG&nbhy;ACN mechanism
described here are compatible, differing primarily in the specific data block
that is sent (the eCall MSD in the case of NG&nbhy;eCall
and VEDS in this document) and some additions to the
metadata/control data block.  If other regions adopt their own vehicle data
sets, this can be similarly accommodated without changing other technical
aspects.  Note that any additional data formats require a new INFO package
to permit transport within SIP INFO requests. 
</t>

</section>


<section title="Overview of Legacy Deployment Models">

<t>Legacy (circuit-switched) systems for placing emergency calls by in-vehicle systems generally have some ability to convey at least location and in some cases telematics data to the PSAP.  Most such systems use one of three architectural models, which are described here as: "TSP", "direct", and "paired". These three models are illustrated below.</t>

<t>In the TSP model, both emergency and routine TSP service calls are placed to a TSP; a proprietary technique (e.g., a proprietary in-band modem) is used for data transfer between the TSP and the vehicle.</t>

<t>In an emergency, typically a TSP agent verifies the emergency, bridges in the PSAP, and communicates location, crash data (such as impact severity and trauma prediction), and other data (such as the vehicle description) to the PSAP call taker orally (in some cases, a proprietary out-of-band interface is used).  Since the TSP knows the location of the vehicle (from on-board GNSS and sensors), location-based routing is usually used to route to the appropriate PSAP.  In some cases, the TSP is able to transmit location automatically, using similar techniques as for wireless calls.  A three-way voice call is generally established between the vehicle, the TSP, and the PSAP, allowing communication between the PSAP call taker, the TSP agent, and the vehicle occupants (who might be unconscious).</t>
<t>
        <figure anchor="tsp-model" title="Legacy TSP Model">
        <?rfc needLines="5" ?>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   ///----\\\  proprietary  +-----+  911 trunk or POTS   +------+
  ||| IVS |||-------------->+ TSP +--------------------->+ PSAP |
   \\\----///  crash data   +-----+  location via trunk  +------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>



<t>In the paired model, the IVS uses a local link (typically Bluetooth <xref target="Bluetooth"/>) with a previously paired handset to establish an emergency call with the PSAP (by dialing a standard emergency number; 9-1-1 in North America) and then communicates location data to the PSAP via text-to-speech; crash data might or might not be conveyed also using text-to-speech.  Some such systems use an automated voice prompt menu for the PSAP call taker (e.g., "this is an automatic emergency call from a vehicle; press 1 to open a voice path to the vehicle; press 2 to hear the location read out") to allow the call taker to request location data via text&nbhy;to&nbhy;speech.</t>
<t>
       <figure anchor="paired-model" title="Legacy Paired Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   ///----\\\   +----+   911/etc. voice call via handset  +------+
  ||| IVS |||-->| HS +----------------------------------->+ PSAP |
   \\\----///   +----+   location via text-to-speech      +------+

(Note: "HS" is handset.)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>



<t>In the direct model, the IVS directly places an emergency call with the PSAP by dialing a standard emergency number (9-1-1 in North America).  Such systems might communicate location data to the PSAP via text-to-speech; crash data might or might not be conveyed using text-to-speech.  Some such systems use an automated voice prompt menu (e.g., "this is an automatic emergency call from a vehicle; press 1 to open a voice path to the vehicle; press 2 to hear the location read out") to allow the call taker to request location data via text&nbhy;to&nbhy;speech.</t>
<t>
        <figure anchor="direct-model" title="Legacy Direct Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   ///----\\\      911/etc. voice call via IVS         +------+
  ||| IVS  |||---------------------------------------->+ PSAP |
   \\\----///     location via text-to-speech          +------+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

</section>


<section title="Migration to Next Generation">

<t>The migration of emergency calls placed by in-vehicle systems to next-generation (all-IP) technology per this document provides a standardized mechanism to identify such calls and to convey crash data with the call setup, as well as enabling additional communications modalities and enhanced functionality.  This allows ACN calls and crash data to be automatically processed by the PSAP and made available to the call taker in an integrated, automated way.  Because the crash data is carried in the initial SIP INVITE (per <xref target="RFC7852"/>) the PSAP can present it to the call taker simultaneously with the appearance of the call.  The PSAP can also process the data to take other actions (e.g., if multiple calls from the same location arrive when the PSAP is busy and a subset of them are NG&nbhy;ACN calls, a PSAP might choose to store the information and reject the calls, since the IVS will receive confirmation that the information has been successfully received; a PSAP could also choose to include a message stating that it is aware of the incident and responders are on the way, and a PSAP could call the vehicle back when a call taker is available).</t>

<t>The migration of origination devices and networks, PSAPs, emergency services networks, and other telephony environments to next generation technology provides enhanced interoperability and functionality, especially for emergency calls carrying additional data such as vehicle crash data.  (In the U.S., a network specifically for emergency responders is being developed.  This network, FirstNet, will be next generation from the start, enhancing the ability for data exchange between PSAPs and responders.)</t>

<t>NG&nbhy;ACN calls can be recognized as such during call set-up; they can
   be routed to a PSAP that is prepared both technically and
   operationally to handle such calls, and the vehicle-determined location
   and crash data can be processed automatically by the PSAP and made
   available to the call taker simultaneously with the call appearance.
   Enhanced functionality includes the ability for the PSAP call taker
   to request the vehicle to take an action, such as sending an updated
   set of data, conveying a message to the occupants, flashing lights,
   unlocking doors, etc.</t>

<t>Vehicle manufacturers using the TSP model can choose to take advantage of the same mechanism to carry telematics data and requests and responses between the vehicle and the TSP for both emergency and non-emergency calls as are used for the interface with the PSAP.</t>

<t>An IVS establishes a next-generation emergency call (see <xref target="RFC6443"/> and <xref target="RFC6881"/>) with an initial INVITE containing a Request-URI indicating an ACN emergency call and Call-Info header fields indicating that both vehicle crash and capabilities data are included; the IVS typically does not perform routing or location queries (relying on the MNO for this).</t>

<t><xref target="RFC8147"/> registers new service URN children within the "sos" subservice.  These URNs request NG&nbhy;ACN resources and differentiate between manually and automatically triggered NG&nbhy;ACN calls (which might be subject to different treatment depending on policy). The two service URNs registered in <xref target="RFC8147"/> are "urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic" and "urn:service:sos.ecall.manual".  The same service URNs are used for ACN as for eCall since in any region only one of these is supported, making a distinction unnecessary.  (Further, PSAP equipment might support multiple data formats, allowing a PSAP to handle a vehicle that erroneously sent the wrong data object.)</t>

<t>Note that in North America, routing queries performed by clients outside of an ESInet typically treat all sub-services of "sos" identically to "sos" with no sub-service.  However, the Request-URI header field retains the full sub-service; route and handling decisions within an ESInet or PSAP can take the sub-service into account.  For example, in a region with multiple cooperating PSAPs, an NG&nbhy;ACN call might be routed to a PSAP that is NG&nbhy;ACN capable, or one that specializes in vehicle-related incidents.</t>

<t>Migration of the three architectural models to next generation (all&nbhy;IP) is described below.</t> 

<t>In the TSP model, the IVS transmits crash and location data to the TSP either by reusing the mechanisms and data objects described in this document or by using a proprietary mechanism.  In an emergency, the TSP bridges in the PSAP, and the TSP transmits crash and other data to the PSAP using the mechanisms and data objects described in this document.  There is a three-way call between the vehicle, the TSP, and the PSAP, allowing communication between the PSAP call taker, the TSP agent, and the vehicle occupants (who might be unconscious).  The TSP relays PSAP requests and vehicle responses.</t>
<t>
        <figure anchor="tsp-model2" title="Next-Generation TSP Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                proprietary
  ///----\\\    or standard     +-----+     standard       +------+
 ||| IVS |||------------------->+ TSP +------------------->+ PSAP |
  \\\----///  crash+other data  +-----+  crash+other data  +------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
</t>

<t>The vehicle manufacturer and the TSP can choose to use the same mechanisms and data objects on the left call leg in <xref target="tsp-model2"/> as on the right.  (Note that the TSP model can be more difficult when the vehicle is in a different country than the TSP (e.g., a US resident driving in Canada) because of the additional complexity in choosing the correct PSAP based on vehicle location performed by a TSP in a different country.)</t>


<t>In the direct model, the IVS communicates crash data to the PSAP directly using the mechanisms and data objects described in this document.</t>
<t>
        <figure anchor="direct-model2" title="Next-Generation Direct Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  ///----\\\           NG emergency call              +------+
 ||| IVS |||----------------------------------------->+ PSAP |
  \\\----///          crash + other data              +------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>


<t>In the paired model, the IVS uses a local link to a
previously paired handset to establish an emergency call with the
PSAP; it is unclear what facilities are or will be available for
transmitting crash data through the link to the handset for inclusion in an NG emergency call and receiving additional data items from the response.  Hence, manufacturers that use the paired model for legacy calls might choose to adopt either the direct or TSP model for next-generation calls.</t>
<t>
        <figure anchor="paired-model2" title="Next-Generation Paired Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   ///----\\\   (undefined)    +----+      standard        +------+
  ||| IVS |||----------------->| HS +--------------------->+ PSAP |
   \\\----///   (undefined)    +----+  crash + other data  +------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>


<t>Regardless of model, if the call is routed to a PSAP that is not NG&nbhy;ACN capable, the PSAP ignores (or does not receive) the vehicle data.  This is detectable by the IVS or TSP when the status response to the INVITE (e.g., 200 OK) lacks a metadata/control structure acknowledging receipt of the data <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  The IVS or TSP then proceeds as it would for a CS&nbhy;ACN call (e.g., oral conveyance of data).</t>

</section>

<section anchor="vehicle-data" title="Vehicle Data">

    <t>APCO and NENA have jointly developed a standardized set of incident-related vehicle data for ACN use, called the Vehicle Emergency Data Set (VEDS) <xref target="VEDS"/>.  Such data is often referred to as crash data although it is applicable in incidents other than crashes.</t>

    <t>VEDS provides a standard data set for the transmission, exchange, and interpretation of vehicle-related data.  A standard data format allows the data to be generated by an IVS or TSP and interpreted by PSAPs, emergency responders, and medical facilities. It includes incident-related information such as airbag deployment, location and compass orientation of the vehicle, spatial orientation of the vehicle (e.g., upright, on a side, roof, or bumper), sensor data that can indicate the potential severity of the crash and the likelihood of severe injuries to the vehicle occupants, etc.  This data better informs the PSAP and emergency responders as to the type of response that might be needed. Some of this information has been included in U.S. government guidelines for field triage of injured patients <xref target="triage-2008"/> <xref target="triage-2011"/>. These guidelines are designed to help responders identify the potential existence of severe internal injuries and to make critical decisions about how and where a patient needs to be transported.</t>

<t>VEDS is an XML structure (see <xref target="VEDS"/>) transported in SIP using the application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml MIME media type.</t>

<t>
If new data blocks are needed (e.g., in other regions or for enhanced data), the steps required during standardization are briefly summarized below:
    <list style="symbols">
        <t>A set of data is standardized by a Standards Development Organization (SDO) or appropriate organization.</t>
        <t>A MIME media type for the crash data set is registered with IANA
            <list style="symbols">
            <t>If the data is specifically for use in emergency calling, the MIME media type is normally under the application type with a subtype starting with EmergencyCallData.</t>
            <t>If the data format is XML, then by convention the name has a suffix of "+xml".</t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>The item is registered in the "Emergency Call Data Types" registry, as defined in Section 11.1.9 of <xref target="RFC7852"/>.
            <list style="symbols">
            <t>For emergency-call-specific formats, the registered name is the root of the MIME media type (not including the EmergencyCallData prefix and any suffix such as "+xml") as described in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC7852"/>.</t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>A new INFO package is registered that permits carrying the new media type, the metadata/control object (defined in <xref target="RFC8147"/>), and for compatibility, the MSD and VEDS objects, in SIP INFO requests.</t>
    </list>
</t>

</section>


<section anchor="data-transport" title="Data Transport">

<t><xref target="RFC7852"/> establishes a general mechanism for including blocks of data within a SIP emergency call.  This document makes use of that mechanism.  This document also registers an INFO package (in <xref target="info"/>) to enable NG&nbhy;ACN-related data blocks to be carried in SIP INFO requests (per <xref target="RFC6086"/>, new SIP INFO method usages require the definition of an INFO package).</t>

<t>VEDS is an XML structure defined by APCO and NENA <xref target="VEDS"/>. It is carried in a body part with MIME media type application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml.</t>

<t>An IVS transmits a VEDS data block (see <xref target="VEDS"/>) by including
it as a body part of a SIP message per <xref target="RFC7852"/>. The body part
is identified by its MIME media type
(application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml) in the Content-Type header field of
the body part.  The body part is assigned a unique identifier that is listed
in a Content-ID header field in the body part.  The SIP message is marked as
containing the VEDS data by adding (or appending to) a Call-Info header field
at the top level of the SIP message.  This Call-Info header field contains a
Content Identifier (CID) URL referencing the body part's unique identifier and a "purpose"
parameter identifying the data as a VEDS data block per the "Emergency Call
Data Types" registry entry; the "purpose" parameter's value is
"EmergencyCallData.VEDS".   A VEDS data block is carried in a SIP INFO request
by using the INFO package defined in <xref target="info"/>.</t> 

<t>A PSAP or IVS transmits a metadata/control object (see <xref target="RFC8147"/>) by including it in a SIP message as a MIME body part per <xref target="RFC7852"/>. The body part is identified by its MIME media type (application/EmergencyCallData.Control+xml) in the Content-Type header field of the body part.  The body part is assigned a unique identifier that is listed in a Content-ID header field in the body part.  The SIP message is marked as containing the metadata/control block by adding (or appending to) a Call-Info header field at the top level of the SIP message.  This Call-Info header field contains a CID URL referencing the body part's unique identifier and a "purpose" parameter identifying the data as a metadata/control block per the "Emergency Call Data Types" registry entry; the "purpose" parameter's value is "EmergencyCallData.Control".  A metadata/control object is carried in a SIP INFO request by using the INFO package defined in <xref target="info"/>.</t>

<t>A body part containing a VEDS or metadata/control object has a Content-Disposition header field value containing "By-Reference" and is always enclosed in a multipart body part (even if it would otherwise be the only body part in the SIP message).</t>

<t>An IVS initiating an NG&nbhy;ACN call includes in the initial INVITE a VEDS data block and a metadata/control object informing the PSAP of its capabilities.  The VEDS and metadata/control body parts (and Presence Information Data Format Location Object (PIDF-LO)) have a Content-Disposition header field with the value "By-Reference; handling=optional".  Specifying handling=optional prevents the INVITE from being rejected if it is processed by a legacy element (e.g., a gateway between SIP and circuit-switched environments) that does not understand the VEDS or metadata/control (or PIDF-LO) objects.  The PSAP creates a metadata/control object acknowledging receipt of the VEDS data and includes it in the SIP final response to the INVITE.  The metadata/control object is not included in provisional (e.g., 180) responses.</t>

<t>If the IVS receives an acknowledgment for a VEDS data object with received=false, this indicates that the PSAP was unable to properly decode or process the VEDS. The IVS action is not defined (e.g., it might only log an error).  Since the PSAP is able to request an updated VEDS during the call, if an initial VEDS is unsatisfactory in any way, the PSAP can choose to request another one. </t>

<t>A PSAP can request that the vehicle send an updated VEDS data block during a call.  To do so, the PSAP creates a metadata/control object requesting VEDS data and includes it as a body part of a SIP INFO request sent within the dialog.  The IVS then includes an updated VEDS data object as a body part of a SIP INFO request and sends it within the dialog.  If the IVS is unable to send the VEDS for any reason, it instead sends a metadata/control object containing an &lt;ack&gt; element acknowledging the request and containing an &lt;actionResult&gt; element with the "success" parameter set to "false" and a "reason" parameter (and optionally a "details" parameter) indicating why the request cannot be accomplished.  Per <xref target="RFC6086"/>, metadata/control objects and VEDS data are sent using the INFO package defined in <xref target="info"/>.  In addition, to align with the way a VEDS or metadata/control block is transmitted in a SIP message other than a SIP INFO request, one or more Call-Info header fields are included in the SIP INFO request referencing the VEDS or metadata/control block.  See <xref target="info"/> for more information on the use of SIP INFO requests within NG&nbhy;ACN calls.</t>

<t>Any metadata/control object sent by a PSAP can request that the vehicle perform an action (such as sending a data block, flashing lights, providing a camera feed, etc.).  The IVS sends an acknowledgment for any request other than a successfully executed send-data action.  Multiple requests with the same "action:" value MUST be sent in separate metadata/control body parts (to avoid any ambiguity in the acknowledgment).  For each metadata/control block received containing one or more &lt;request&gt; elements (except for successfully executed send-data requests), the IVS sends a metadata/control object containing an &lt;ack&gt; element acknowledging the received metadata/control block, containing an &lt;actionResult&gt; element per &lt;request&gt; element.</t>

<t>If the IVS is aware that VEDS data it sent previously has changed, it MAY send an unsolicited VEDS in any convenient SIP message, including a SIP INFO request during the call.  The PSAP sends an acknowledgment for an unsolicited VEDS object; if the IVS sent the unsolicited VEDS in a SIP INFO request, the acknowledgment is sent in a new SIP INFO request; otherwise, it is sent in the reply to the SIP request containing the VEDS.</t>

</section> 


<section anchor="call-setup" title="Call Setup">

<t>An IVS initiating an NG&nbhy;ACN call sends a SIP INVITE request
using one of the SOS sub-services "SOS.ecall.automatic" or "SOS.ecall.manual"
in the Request-URI.  This SIP INVITE request includes standard sets of both
crash and capabilities data as described in <xref
target="data-transport"/>.</t> 

<t>Entities along the path between the vehicle and the PSAP are able to
identify the call as an ACN call and handle it appropriately.  The PSAP is
able to identify the crash and capabilities data included in the SIP INVITE
request by examining the Call-Info header fields for "purpose" parameters
whose values start with EmergencyCallData.  The PSAP is able to access the
data it is capable of handling and is interested in by checking the "purpose"
parameter values.</t> 

<t>This document extends <xref target="RFC8147"/> by reusing the call setup
and other normative requirements with the exception that in this document,
support for the eCall MSD is OPTIONAL and support for VEDS is REQUIRED.  This
document also adds new attribute values to the metadata/control object defined
in <xref target="RFC8147"/>.</t> 

</section> 

<section anchor="control_block" title="New Metadata/Control Values">
    
    <t>This document adds new attribute values to the metadata/control
    structure defined in <xref target="RFC8147"/>.</t> 

        <t>In addition to the base usage from the PSAP to the IVS to acknowledge receipt of crash data, the &lt;ack&gt; element is also contained in a metadata/control block sent by the IVS to the PSAP.  This is used by the IVS to acknowledge receipt of a request by the PSAP and indicate if the request was carried out when that request would not otherwise be acknowledged (if the PSAP requests the vehicle to send data and the vehicle does so, the data serves as a success acknowledgment); see <xref target="call-setup"/> for details.</t>
        <t>The &lt;capabilities&gt; element is used in a metadata/control block sent from the IVS to the PSAP (e.g., in the initial INVITE) to inform the PSAP of the vehicle capabilities.  Child elements contain all actions and data types supported by the vehicle and all available lamps (lights) and cameras.</t>
        <t>New request values are added to the &lt;request&gt; element to enable the PSAP to request the vehicle to perform additional actions.</t>


    <t>
    Mandatory Actions (the IVS and the PSAP MUST support):
        <?rfc compact="yes"?>
        <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Transmit data object (VEDS MUST be supported; MSD MAY be supported)</t>
        </list>
        <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        <?rfc compact="no"?>
    Optional Actions (the IVS and the PSAP MAY support):
        <?rfc compact="no"?>
        <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Display and/or play static (pre-defined) message</t>
        <t>Display and/or speak dynamic text (text supplied in action)</t>
        <t>Flash or turn on or off a lamp (light)</t>
        <t>Honk horn</t>
        <t>Lock or unlock doors</t>
        <t>Enable a camera</t>
        </list>
        <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        <?rfc compact="no"?>
    </t>

    <t>
    The &lt;ack&gt; element indicates the object being acknowledged (i.e., a data object or a metadata/control block containing &lt;request&gt; elements) and reports success or failure.
    </t>

    <t>
    The &lt;capabilities&gt; element has child &lt;request&gt; elements indicating the actions (including data types, lamps (lights), and cameras) supported by the IVS.
    </t>

    <t>
    The &lt;request&gt; element contains attributes to indicate the request and to supply any needed information, and it MAY contain a &lt;text&gt; child element to contain the text for a dynamic message.  The "action" attribute is mandatory and indicates the specific action.  <xref target="RFC8147"/> established an IANA registry to contain the allowed values; this document adds new values to that registry in <xref target="control-values"/>.
    </t>

        <section anchor="action_extensions" title="New Values for the &quot;action&quot; Attribute">
        
        <t>The following new "action" values are defined:</t>

        <t>
        <list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="msg-static:">displays or plays a pre-defined message
        (translated as appropriate for the language of the vehicle's
        interface).  A registry is created in <xref
        target="eCall-msg-registry"/> for messages and their IDs.
        Vehicles include the highest registered message in their
        &lt;capabilities&gt; element to indicate support for all messages
        up to and including the indicated value.  A registry of message
        identification values is defined in <xref
        target="eCall-msg-registry"/>.  There is only one static message
        initially defined (listed in <xref
        target="eCall-msg-registry-values"/>).  Because all compliant
        vehicles are expected to support all static messages translated
        into all languages supported by the vehicle, it is important to
        limit the number of such messages. Therefore, this registry
        operates under "Specification Required" rules as defined in <xref
        target="RFC5226"/>, which requires a stable, public document and
        implies expert review of the publication.</t> 

        <t hangText="msg-dynamic:">displays or speaks (via text-to-speech) a message contained in a child &lt;text&gt; element within the request.</t>
        <t hangText="honk:">sounds the horn.</t>
        <t hangText="lamp:">flashes a lamp (light) or turns it on or off.  The lamp is identified by a lamp ID token contained in an "element-id" attribute of the request.  The desired state of the lamp is either "on", "off", or "flash" as indicated in a "requested-state" attribute.  The duration of the lamp's requested state is specified in a "persistence" attribute.  A registry of lamp identification values is defined in <xref target="eCall-lamp-id-registry"/>.  The initial values (listed in <xref target="eCall-lamp-id-registry-values"/>) are head, interior, fog-front, fog&nbhy;rear, brake, brake-center, position-front, position-rear, turn-left, turn-right, and hazard.</t>

        <t hangText="enable-camera:">adds a one-way media stream (established via SIP re&nbhy;INVITE sent by the vehicle) to enable the PSAP call taker to view a feed from a camera.  A registry of camera identification values is defined in <xref target="eCall-camera-id-registry"/>.  The initial values (listed in <xref target="eCall-camera-id-registry-values"/>) are backup, left-rear, right-rear, forward, rear-wide, lane, interior, night-front, night-rear, night-left, and night-right.</t>

        <t hangText="door-lock:">locks or unlocks all door locks.  A "requested-state" attribute contains either "locked" or "unlocked" to indicate if the doors are to be locked or unlocked.</t>

        </list>
        </t>

        <t>Note that there is no "request" action to play dynamic media (such as an audio message).  The PSAP can send a SIP re-INVITE to establish a one-way media stream for this purpose.</t>

        </section> 

        <section anchor="request_example" title="Example &lt;request&gt; Element">
        <figure anchor="request-example" title="&lt;request&gt; Example">
            <artwork>
                <![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <EmergencyCallData.Control
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:EmergencyCallData:control"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">

    <request action="send-data" datatype="VEDS"/>
    <request action="lamp" element-id="hazard"
             requested-state="flash" persistence="PT1H"/>
    <request action="msg-static" int-id="1"/>
    <request action="msg-dynamic">
        <text>Remain calm.  Help is on the way.</text>
    </request>

    </EmergencyCallData.Control>
                ]]>
            </artwork>
        </figure>
        </section>


        <section anchor="ack_element" title="The &lt;ack&gt; Element">

        <t>
        The &lt;ack&gt; element is transmitted by the PSAP to acknowledge unsolicited data sent by the IVS and transmitted by the IVS to acknowledge receipt of a &lt;request&gt; element other than a successfully performed "send-data" request (e.g., a request to display a message to the vehicle occupants is acknowledged, but a request to transmit VEDS data is not, since the transmitted VEDS serves as acknowledgment).  An &lt;ack&gt; element sent by an IVS references the unique ID of the metadata/control object containing the request(s), and for each request being acknowledged, it indicates whether the request was successfully performed, and if not, it indicates why not.
        </t>

        <section anchor="ack_example" title="Examples of the &lt;ack&gt; Element">

        <figure anchor="ack-example-ivs" title="Example &lt;ack&gt; from IVS to PSAP">
            <artwork>
                <![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <EmergencyCallData.Control
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:EmergencyCallData:control"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">

    <ack ref="1234567890@atlanta.example.com">
        <actionResult action="msg-dynamic" success="true"/>
        <actionResult action="lamp" success="false" reason="unable"
                      details="The requested lamp is inoperable"/>
    </ack>

    </EmergencyCallData.Control>
                ]]>
            </artwork>
        </figure>

        </section>

        </section> 

        <section anchor="capabilities_element" title="The &lt;capabilities&gt; Element">

        <t>
        The &lt;capabilities&gt; element <xref target="RFC8147"/> is transmitted by the IVS to indicate its capabilities to the PSAP.
        </t>

        <t>The &lt;capabilities&gt; element contains a &lt;request&gt; child element per action supported by the vehicle.  The vehicle MUST support sending the VEDS data object and so includes at a minimum a &lt;request&gt; child element with the "action" attribute set to "send-data" and the "supported-values" attribute containing all data blocks supported by the IVS, which MUST include "VEDS".  All other actions are OPTIONAL.</t>
       
                <t>If the "msg-static" action is supported, a &lt;request&gt; child element with the "action" attribute set to "msg-static" is included, with the "int-id" attribute set to the highest supported static message supported by the vehicle.  A registry is created in <xref target="eCall-msg-registry"/> to map "int-id" values to static text messages.  By sending the highest supported static message number in its &lt;capabilities&gt; element, the vehicle indicates its support for all static messages in the registry up to and including that value.</t>
                <t>If the "lamp" action is supported, a &lt;request&gt; child element with the "action" attribute set to "lamp" is included, with the "supported-values" attribute set to all supported lamp IDs.  A registry is created in <xref target="eCall-lamp-id-registry"/> to contain lamp ID values.</t>
                <t>If the "enable-camera" action is supported, a &lt;request&gt; child element with the "action" attribute set to "enable-camera" is included, with the "supported-values" attribute set to all supported camera IDs.  A registry is created in <xref target="eCall-camera-id-registry"/> to contain camera ID values.</t>

        <section anchor="capabilities_example" title="Example &lt;capabilities&gt; Element">
        <figure anchor="capabilities-example" title="&lt;capabilities&gt; Example">
            <artwork>
                <![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <EmergencyCallData.Control
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:EmergencyCallData:control"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">

    <capabilities>
        <request action="send-data" supported-values="VEDS"/>
        <request action="lamp"
                 supported-values="head;interior;fog-front;
                 fog-rear;brake;position-front;position-rear;
                 turn-left;turn-right;hazard"/>
        <request action="msg-static" int-id="3"/>
        <request action="msg-dynamic"/>
        <request action="honk"/>
        <request action="enable-camera"
                 supported-values="backup; interior"/>
        <request action="door-lock"/>
    </capabilities>

    </EmergencyCallData.Control>
                ]]>
            </artwork>
        </figure>
        </section> 

        </section> 

</section> 

<section anchor="test-calls" title="Test Calls">

    <t>An NG&nbhy;ACN test call is a call that is recognized and treated to some extent as an NG&nbhy;ACN call but is not given emergency call treatment nor handled by a PSAP call taker.  The specific handling of test NG&nbhy;ACN calls is outside the scope of this document; typically, the test call facility allows the IVS, user, or TSP to verify that an NG&nbhy;ACN call can be successfully established with voice and/or other media communication.  The IVS might also be able to verify that the crash data was successfully received.</t>
   
   <t>This document builds on <xref target="RFC8147"/>, which inherits the ability to utilize test call functionality from Section 15 of <xref target="RFC6881"/>.  A service URN starting with "test." indicates a test call. Per <xref target="RFC8147"/>, "urn:service:test.sos.ecall" is used for test NG&nbhy;ACN calls.</t>
   
   <t>MNOs, emergency authorities, ESInets, and PSAPs handle a vehicle call requesting the "test" service URN so that the desired functionality is tested, but this is outside the scope of this document.  (One possibility is that MNOs route such calls as non-emergency calls to an ESInet, which routes them to a PSAP that supports NG&nbhy;ACN calls; the PSAP accepts test calls, sends a crash data acknowledgment, and plays an audio clip (for example, saying that the call reached an appropriate PSAP and the vehicle data was successfully processed) in addition to supporting media loopback per <xref target="RFC6881"/>.)</t>

    <t>Note that since test calls are placed using "test" as the parent service URN and "sos" as a child, such calls are not treated as an emergency call, so some functionality might not apply (such as preemption or availability for devices lacking service ("non&nbhy;service&nbhy;initialized" (NSI) devices) if those are available for emergency calls).</t>

</section> 

<section anchor="example" title="Example Call Initiation">

      <t><xref target="fig1"/> shows an NG&nbhy;ACN call initiation.  The vehicle initiates an NG&nbhy;ACN call using an MNO.  The MNO routes the call to an ESInet, as for any emergency call.  The ESInet routes the call to an appropriate NG&nbhy;ACN-capable PSAP (using location information and the fact that it is an NG&nbhy;ACN call). The call is processed by the Emergency Services Routing Proxy (ESRP), as the entry point to the ESInet. The ESRP routes the call to an appropriate NG&nbhy;ACN-capable PSAP, where the call is handled by a call taker.  (In deployments where there is no ESInet, the MNO itself routes the call directly to an appropriate NG&nbhy;ACN-capable PSAP.)</t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig1" title="Example Call Initiation">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                            +---------------------------------------+
                            |                                       |
            +------------+  |                  +-------+            |
            |            |  |                  | PSAP2 |            |
            |            |  |                  +-------+            |
            | Originating|  |                                       |
            |   Mobile   |  |  +------+    +---------------------+| |
  Vehicle-->|   Network  |--+->| ESRP |--->| PSAP1 --> Call Taker | |
            |            |  |  +------+    +---------------------+| |
            |            |  |                                       |
            +------------+  |                  +-------+            |
                            |                  | PSAP3 |            |
                            |                  +-------+            |
                            |                                       |
                            |                                       |
                            |                                       |
                            |                ESInet                 |
                            +---------------------------------------+
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t><xref target="fig2"/> illustrates an example SIP emergency call INVITE request as
   generated by the IVS.  It includes a PIDF-LO with vehicle-determined
   location information, a VEDS block with crash data, and a
   metadata/control block with capabilities data.  The INVITE has a
   request URI containing the urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic service
   URN.  For brevity, the example VEDS block does not show VEDS location
   information, although this is generally present.</t>

      <t>The example VEDS data structure shows information about a crashed vehicle.  The example communicates that the car is a model year 2015 Saab 9-5 (a car that does not exist). The front airbag deployed as a consequence of the crash.  The &lt;VehicleBodyCategoryCode&gt; indicates that the crashed vehicle is a passenger car (the code is set to "101") and that it is not a convertible (the &lt;ConvertibleIndicator&gt; value is set to "false").</t>

    <t>The &lt;VehicleCrashPulse&gt; element provides further information about the crash, namely that the force of impact based on the change in velocity over the duration of the crash pulse was 100 MPH. The principal direction of the force of the impact is set to "12" (which refers to 12 o'clock, corresponding to a frontal collision). This value is in the &lt;CrashPulsePrincipalDirectionOfForceValue&gt; element.</t>

    <t>The &lt;CrashPulseRolloverQuarterTurnsValue&gt; indicates the number of quarter turns in concert with a rollover expressed as a number; in our case 1.</t>

    <t>No roll bar was deployed, as indicated in &lt;VehicleRollbarDeployedIndicator&gt; being set to "false".</t> 

    <t>Next, there is information indicating seat belt and seat sensor data for individual seat positions in the vehicle.  In our example, information from the driver seat is available (value "1" in the &lt;VehicleSeatLocationCategoryCode&gt; element) showing that the seat belt was monitored (&lt;VehicleSeatbeltMonitoredIndicator&gt; element), the seat belt was fastened (&lt;VehicleSeatbeltFastenedIndicator&gt; element), and the seat sensor determined that the seat was occupied (&lt;VehicleSeatOccupiedIndicator&gt; element).</t>

    <t>The weight of the vehicle when empty is listed as 600 kilograms in our example.</t>
    
    <t>The &lt;SevereInjuryIndicator&gt; element is set to "true", indicating a likelihood that a vehicle occupant has suffered a severe injury requiring immediate trauma care.</t>

    <t>Additional information is provided, including the presence of fuel leakage (&lt;FuelLeakingIndicator&gt; element), an indication whether the vehicle was subjected to multiple impacts (&lt;MultipleImpactsIndicator&gt; element), the orientation of the vehicle at final rest (&lt;VehicleFinalRestOrientationCategoryCode&gt; element), and an indication that no parts of the vehicle are currently detected as being on fire (the &lt;VehicleFireIndicator&gt; element).</t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig2" title="SIP INVITE for a Vehicle-Initiated Emergency Call">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   INVITE urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic SIP/2.0
   To: urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic 
   From: <sip:+13145551111@example.com>;tag=9fxced76sl
   Call-ID: 3848276298220188511@atlanta.example.com
   Geolocation: <cid:target123@example.com>
   Geolocation-Routing: no
   Call-Info: <cid:1234567890@atlanta.example.com>;
              purpose=EmergencyCallData.VEDS
   Call-Info: <cid:1234567892@atlanta.example.com>;
              purpose=EmergencyCallData.Control
   Accept: application/sdp, application/pidf+xml,
           application/EmergencyCallData.Control+xml
   Recv-Info: EmergencyCallData.eCall
   Allow: INVITE, ACK, PRACK, INFO, OPTIONS, CANCEL, REFER, BYE,
          SUBSCRIBE, NOTIFY, UPDATE
   CSeq: 31862 INVITE
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1
   Content-Length: ...

   --boundary1
   Content-Type: application/sdp

   ...Session Description Protocol (SDP) goes here

   --boundary1
    Content-Type: application/pidf+xml
    Content-ID: <target123@atlanta.example.com>
    Content-Disposition: by-reference;handling=optional

    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <presence
       xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf"
       xmlns:dm="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:data-model"
       xmlns:gp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10"
       xmlns:dyn="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:dynamic"
       xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml"
       xmlns:gs="http://www.opengis.net/pidflo/1.0"
       entity="sip:+13145551111@example.com">
       <dm:device id="123">
           <gp:geopriv>
               <gp:location-info>
                   <gml:Point srsName="urn:ogc:def:crs:EPSG::4326">
                      <gml:pos>-34.407 150.883</gml:pos>
                   </gml:Point>
                    <dyn:Dynamic>
                       <dyn:heading>278</dyn:heading>
                       <dyn:direction><dyn:direction>
                    </dyn:Dynamic>
               </gp:location-info>
               <gp:usage-rules/>
               <method>gps</method>
           </gp:geopriv>
           <timestamp>2012-04-5T10:18:29Z</timestamp>
           <dm:deviceID>1M8GDM9A_KP042788</dm:deviceID>
       </dm:device>
</presence>

    --boundary1
    Content-Type: application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml
    Content-ID: <1234567890@atlanta.example.com>
    Content-Disposition: by-reference;handling=optional

    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <AutomatedCrashNotification xmlns="http://www.veds.org/acn/1.0"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    
    <Crash>    
        <CrashVehicle>
            <ItemMakeName xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                Saab
            </ItemMakeName>
            <ItemModelName xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                9-5
            </ItemModelName>
            <ItemModelYearDate
                xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                2015
            </ItemModelYearDate>   
            <Airbag>
                <AirbagCategoryCode>FRONT</AirbagCategoryCode>
                <AirbagDeployedIndicator>true
                </AirbagDeployedIndicator>
            </Airbag>
            <ConvertibleIndicator>false</ConvertibleIndicator>
            <PowerSourceCategoryCode>MAIN</PowerSourceCategoryCode>
            <VehicleBodyCategoryCode
                xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/domains/jxdm/4.1">
                101
            </VehicleBodyCategoryCode>
            <VehicleCrashPulse>
                <CrashPulseChangeInVelocityMeasure>
                    <MeasurePointValue
                        xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                        100
                    </MeasurePointValue>
                    <MeasureUnitText
                        xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                        MPH</MeasureUnitText>
                 </CrashPulseChangeInVelocityMeasure>
                        <CrashPulsePrincipalDirectionOfForceValue>12
                        </CrashPulsePrincipalDirectionOfForceValue>
                <CrashPulseRolloverQuarterTurnsValue>1
                </CrashPulseRolloverQuarterTurnsValue>
            </VehicleCrashPulse>
            <VehicleRollbarDeployedIndicator>false
            </VehicleRollbarDeployedIndicator>
            <VehicleSeat>
                <VehicleSeatLocationCategoryCode>1
                </VehicleSeatLocationCategoryCode>
                <VehicleSeatOccupiedIndicator>true
                </VehicleSeatOccupiedIndicator>
                <VehicleSeatbeltFastenedIndicator>true
                </VehicleSeatbeltFastenedIndicator>
                <VehicleSeatbeltMonitoredIndicator>true
                </VehicleSeatbeltMonitoredIndicator>                
            </VehicleSeat>
            <VehicleUnladenWeightMeasure
                xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                <MeasurePointValue
                    xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                    600
                    </MeasurePointValue>
                <MeasureUnitText
                    xmlns="http://niem.gov/niem/niem-core/2.0">
                    kilogram
                </MeasureUnitText>                
            </VehicleUnladenWeightMeasure>            
        </CrashVehicle>
        <FuelLeakingIndicator>true</FuelLeakingIndicator>
        <MultipleImpactsIndicator>false</MultipleImpactsIndicator>
        <SevereInjuryIndicator>true</SevereInjuryIndicator>
        <VehicleFinalRestOrientationCategoryCode>Driver
        </VehicleFinalRestOrientationCategoryCode>
        <VehicleFireIndicator>false</VehicleFireIndicator>
    </Crash>
</AutomatedCrashNotification>

    --boundary1
    Content-Type: application/EmergencyCallData.Control+xml
    Content-ID: <1234567892@atlanta.example.com>
    Content-Disposition: by-reference;handling=optional

    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <EmergencyCallData.Control
         xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:EmergencyCallData:control"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">

     <capabilities>
         <request action="send-data" supported-datatypes="VEDS"/>
         <request action="lamp"
                  supported-values="head;interior;fog-front;fog-rear;
                  brake;position-front;position-rear;turn-left;
                  turn-right;hazard"/>
         <request action="msg-static" int-id="3"/>
         <request action="msg-dynamic"/>
         <request action="honk"/>
         <request action="enable-camera"
                  supported-values="backup;interior"/>
         <request action="door-lock"/>
     </capabilities>

    </EmergencyCallData.Control>

    --boundary1--
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>Since this document relies on <xref target="RFC8147"/> and <xref
      target="RFC7852"/>, the security considerations described in those
      specifications apply here. The security considerations of
      <xref target="RFC5069"/> apply as well.  Implementors are cautioned to read
      and understand the discussion in those documents.</t> 
      
      <t>In emergency service systems where location data is supplied or determined with the assistance of an end host, it is possible that the location is incorrect, either intentionally (e.g., in a denial-of-service attack against the emergency services infrastructure) or due to a malfunctioning device. The reader is referred to <xref target="RFC7378"/> for a discussion of some of these vulnerabilities. </t>

      <t>In addition to the security considerations discussion specific to the metadata/control object in <xref target="RFC8147"/>, note that vehicles MAY decline to carry out any requested action (e.g., if the vehicle requires but is unable to verify the certificate used to sign the request).  The vehicle MAY use any value in the reason registry to indicate why it did not take an action (e.g., the generic "unable" or the more specific "security-failure").  Because some actions carry more potential risk than others (e.g., unlocking a door versus flashing lights), vehicle policy MAY decline to carry out some requests in some circumstances (e.g., decline a request to unlock doors, send an updated VEDS, or enable a camera received in a vehicle-terminated call while carrying out such requests received in a vehicle-initiated emergency call).</t>

</section>

<section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
    
    <t>Since this document builds on <xref target="RFC8147"/>, which itself builds on <xref target="RFC7852"/>, the data structures specified there, and the corresponding privacy considerations discussed there, apply here as well.  The VEDS data structure contains optional elements that can carry identifying and personal information, both about the vehicle and about the owner, as well as location information, so it needs to be protected against unauthorized disclosure, as discussed in <xref target="RFC7852"/>.  Local regulations may impose additional privacy protection requirements.</t>
    
    <t>The additional functionality enabled by this document, such as access to vehicle camera streams, carries a burden of protection, so implementations need to be careful that access is only provided within the context of an emergency call or to an emergency services provider (e.g., by verifying that the request for camera access is signed by a certificate issued by an emergency services registrar).</t>
    
</section> 

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
    
    <t>This document registers the application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml
    MIME media type and adds "VEDS" to the "Emergency Call Data Types" registry.
    This document adds to and creates sub-registries in the "Emergency Call
    Metadata/Control Data" registry created in <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  In
    addition, this
    document registers a new INFO package.</t> 

    <section title="MIME Media Type Registration for application/EmergencyCall.VEDS+xml">
    
        <t>IANA has registered a new MIME media type according to the procedures of <xref target="RFC6838"/> and guidelines in <xref target="RFC7303"/>.</t> 

        <t>
        <list style="empty">
            <t>
            <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="MIME media type name:">application</t>
            <t hangText="MIME subtype name:">EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml</t>
            <t hangText="Mandatory parameters:">none</t>
            <t hangText="Optional parameters:">charset<vspace/>
                    Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.</t>
            <t hangText="Encoding considerations:"><vspace/>
                Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
                character encoding used.  
                See Section 3.2 of RFC 7303 <xref target="RFC7303"/>.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Security considerations:">

                <list>
                    <t>This media type is designed to carry vehicle crash data during an emergency call.</t>

                    <t>This data can contain personal information including vehicle VIN, location, direction, etc.  Appropriate precautions need to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer to Sections 9 and 10 of <xref target="RFC7852"/> for more information.</t>

                    <t>When this media type is contained in a signed or encrypted body part, the enclosing multipart (e.g., multipart/signed or multipart/encrypted) has the same Content-ID as the data part.  This allows an entity to identify and access the data blocks it is interested in without having to dive deeply into the message structure or decrypt parts it is not interested in.  (The "purpose" parameter in a Call-Info header field identifies the data, and the CID URL points to the data block in the body, which has a matching Content-ID body part header field.)
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">None</t>
            <t hangText="Published specification:"><xref target="VEDS"/></t>
            <t hangText="Applications which use this media type:">Emergency Services</t>
            <t hangText="Additional information:">None</t>
            <t hangText="Magic Number:">None</t>
            <t hangText="File Extension:">.xml</t>
            <t hangText="Macintosh file type code:">TEXT</t>
            <t hangText="Persons and email addresses for further information:"><vspace/>
      Randall&nbsp;Gellens,&nbsp;rg+ietf@randy.pensive.org; Hannes&nbsp;Tschofenig,&nbsp;Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</t>
            <t hangText="Intended usage:">LIMITED USE</t>
            <t hangText="Author:"><vspace/>This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.</t>
            <t hangText="Change controller:">The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;</t>

            </list>
            </t>
        </list>
        </t>

    </section> 

    <section title="Registration of the &quot;VEDS&quot; Entry in the Emergency Call Data Types Registry"> 
    
      <t>IANA has added "VEDS" to the
      "Emergency Call Data Types" registry, with a reference to this document;
      the "Data About" value is "The Call".  
      The "Emergency Call Data Types" registry was established by <xref target="RFC7852"/>. </t>
         
    </section> 


        <section anchor="action-extensions" title="New Action Values">
    <t>This document adds new values for the "action" attribute of the
    &lt;request&gt; element in the "Emergency Call Action" registry created by
    <xref target="RFC8147"/>. 
    </t>

        <texttable anchor="control-values" title="Emergency Call Action Registry New Values">
    <ttcol align='center'>Name</ttcol>
    <ttcol align='center'>Description</ttcol>
    <c>msg-static</c>   <c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
    <c>msg-dynamic</c>  <c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
    <c>honk</c>         <c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
    <c>lamp</c>         <c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
    <c>enable-camera</c><c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
    <c>door-lock</c><c><xref target="action_extensions"/> of RFC 8148</c>
        </texttable>

        </section>

        <section anchor="eCall-msg-registry" title="Emergency Call Static Messages Registry">
        <t>This document creates a new sub-registry called "Emergency Call
    Static Messages" in the "Emergency Call Metadata/Control Data" registry
    established by <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  Because compliant
    vehicles are expected to support all static messages translated into
    all languages supported by the vehicle, it is important to limit the
    number of such messages. As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this
    registry operates under "Specification Required", which requires
    a stable, public document and implies expert review of the
    publication.  The expert should determine that the document has been
    published by an appropriate emergency services organization (e.g.,
    NENA, EENA, or APCO) or by the IETF with input from an emergency
    services organization, and that the proposed message is sufficiently
    distinguishable from other messages.</t> 

        <t>The contents of this registry are:

            <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ID:"> An integer identifier to be used in the
        "int-id" attribute of a metadata/control &lt;request&gt;
        element.</t> 
            <t hangText="Message:">The text of the message.  Messages are
        listed in the registry in English; vehicles are expected to
        implement translations into languages supported by the
        vehicle.</t> 
            </list> 
        </t>

        <t>When new messages are added to the registry, the message text is
    determined by the registrant; IANA assigns the IDs.  Each message is
    assigned a consecutive integer value as its ID.  This allows an IVS to
    indicate by a single integer value that it supports all messages with
    that value or lower.  The value 0 is reserved; usable messages start with 1.</t> 


        <t>The initial set of values is listed in <xref target="eCall-msg-registry-values"/>.</t>

        <texttable anchor="eCall-msg-registry-values" title="Emergency Call Static Messages Registry Initial Values">
        <ttcol align='center'>ID</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>Message</ttcol>


        <c>0</c>
        <c>Reserved</c>

        <c>1</c>
        <c>Emergency services has received your information and location but cannot speak with you right now.  We will get help to you as soon as possible.</c>
        </texttable>

        </section> 

        <section anchor="eCall-lamp-id-registry" title="Emergency Call Vehicle Lamp IDs Registry">
        <t>

This document creates a new sub-registry called "Emergency Call
    Vehicle Lamp IDs" in the "Emergency Call Metadata/Control Data"
    registry established by <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  This new
    sub-registry uniquely identifies the names of automotive lamps
    (lights).  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
    operates under "Expert Review" rules.  The expert should determine
    that the proposed lamp name is clearly understandable and is
    sufficiently distinguishable from other lamp names.</t>    

        <t>The contents of this registry are:

            <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Name:"> The identifier to be used in the "element-id"
        attribute of a metadata/control &lt;request&gt; element.</t> 
            <t hangText="Description:">A description of the lamp (light).</t>
            </list> 
        </t> 

        <t>The initial set of values is listed in <xref
    target="eCall-lamp-id-registry-values"/>.</t> 

        <texttable anchor="eCall-lamp-id-registry-values" title="Emergency Call Lamp ID Registry Initial Values">
        <ttcol align='left'>Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
        <c>head</c>         <c>The main lamps used to light the road ahead</c>
        <c>interior</c>     <c>Interior lamp, often at the top center</c>
        <c>fog-front</c>    <c>Front fog lamps</c>
        <c>fog-rear</c>     <c>Rear fog lamps</c>
        <c>brake</c>        <c>Brake indicator lamps</c>
        <c>brake-center</c> <c>Center high-mounted stop lamp</c>
        <c>position-front</c> <c>Front position/parking/standing lamps</c>
        <c>position-rear</c> <c>Rear position/parking/standing lamps</c>
        <c>turn-left</c>     <c>Left turn/directional lamps</c>
        <c>turn-right</c>    <c>Right turn/directional lamps</c>
        <c>hazard</c>        <c>Hazard/four-way lamps</c>
        </texttable>

        </section>  

        <section anchor="eCall-camera-id-registry" title="Emergency Call Vehicle Camera IDs Registry">

        <t>This document creates a new sub-registry called "Emergency Call
    Vehicle Camera IDs" in the "Emergency Call Metadata/Control Data"
    registry established by <xref target="RFC8147"/>.  This new
    sub-registry uniquely identifies automotive cameras.  As defined in
    <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry operates under "Expert Review"
    rules.  The expert should determine that the proposed camera name is
    clearly understandable and is sufficiently distinguishable from other
    camera names.</t>    

        <t>The contents of this registry are:

            <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Name:"> The identifier to be used in the "element-id"
        attribute of a control &lt;request&gt; element.</t> 
            <t hangText="Description:">A description of the camera.</t>
            </list> 
        </t> 

        <t>The initial set of values is listed in <xref
    target="eCall-camera-id-registry-values"/>.</t> 

        <texttable anchor="eCall-camera-id-registry-values" title="Emergency Call Vehicle Camera IDs Registry Initial Values">
        <ttcol align='left'>Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
      <c>backup</c>      <c>Shows what is behind the vehicle, e.g., often
    used for driver display when the vehicle is in reverse.  Also known as
    rearview, reverse, rear visibility, etc.</c> 
      <c>left-rear</c>    <c>Shows view to the left and behind (e.g., left-side rearview mirror or blind spot view)</c> 
      <c>right-rear</c>   <c>Shows view to the right and behind (e.g., right-side rearview mirror or blind spot view)</c> 
      <c>forward</c>      <c>Shows what is in front of the vehicle</c>
      <c>rear-wide</c>    <c>Shows what is behind the vehicle (e.g., used by
    rear-collision detection systems), separate from backup view</c> 
      <c>lane</c>         <c>Used by systems to identify road lane and/or
    monitor the vehicle's position within lane</c> 
      <c>interior</c>     <c>Shows the interior (e.g., driver)</c>
      <c>night-front</c>  <c>Night-vision view of what is in front of the vehicle</c>
      <c>night-rear</c>  <c>Night-vision view of what is behind the vehicle</c>
      <c>night-left</c>  <c>Night-vision view of what is to the left of the vehicle</c>
      <c>night-right</c>  <c>Night-vision view of what is to the right of the vehicle</c>
        </texttable>

        </section> 

    <section anchor="info" title="The EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO Package">
    <t>
    This document registers the EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO
    package in the "Info Packages Registry".</t>
    
    <t>Both endpoints (the IVS and the PSAP equipment) include
    "EmergencyCallData.VEDS" in a Recv-Info header field per <xref
    target="RFC6086"/> to indicate the ability to receive SIP INFO messages
    carrying data as described here. 
    </t>
    
    <t>
    Support for the EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO package indicates
    the ability to receive NG&nbhy;ACN-related body parts as specified in this document.
    </t>
    
    <t>A SIP INFO request message carrying data related to an emergency call
    as described in this document has an Info-Package header field set
    to "EmergencyCallData.VEDS" per <xref target="RFC6086"/>. 
    </t>

    <t>The requirements of Section 10 of <xref target="RFC6086"/> are
    addressed in the following sections.</t> 
    
        <section title="Overall Description">     
        <t>This section describes what type of information is carried in INFO
    requests associated with the INFO package and for what types of
    applications and functionalities User Agents (UAs) can use the INFO
    package.</t> 
        
        <t>SIP INFO requests associated with the
    EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO package carry data associated
    with emergency calls as defined in this document.  The
    application is vehicle-initiated emergency calls established using
    SIP.  The functionality is to carry vehicle data and metadata/control
    information between vehicles and PSAPs.</t>

        </section> 

        <section title="Applicability">
        
        <t>This section describes why the INFO package mechanism, rather than
    some other mechanism, has been chosen for the specific use case.</t> 
        
        <t>The use of the SIP INFO method is based on an analysis of the
    requirements against the intent and effects of the INFO method versus
    other approaches (which included the SIP MESSAGE method, SIP OPTIONS
    method, SIP re-INVITE method, media-plane transport, and non-SIP
    protocols).  In particular, the transport of emergency call data
    blocks occurs within a SIP emergency dialog, per <xref
    target="data-transport"/>, and is normally carried in the initial
    INVITE request and its response; the use of the INFO method only
    occurs when emergency-call-related data needs to be sent mid call.
    While the SIP MESSAGE method could be used, it is not tied to a SIP
    dialog as is the INFO method and thus might not be associated with the
    dialog.  Both the SIP OPTIONS or re&nbhy;INVITE methods could also be
    used, but they are seen as less clean than the INFO method.  The SIP
    SUBSCRIBE/NOTIFY method could be coerced into service, but the
    semantics are not a good fit, e.g., the subscribe/notify mechanism
    provides one-way communication consisting of (often multiple)
    notifications from notifier to subscriber indicating that certain
    events in the notifier have occurred, whereas what's needed here is
    two-way communication of data related to the emergency dialog.  Use of
    media-plane mechanisms was discounted because the number of
    messages needing to be exchanged in a dialog is normally zero or very
    few, and the size of the data is likewise very small.  The overhead
    caused by user-plane setup (e.g., to use the Message Session Relay
    Protocol (MSRP) as transport) would be disproportionately large.</t> 

    <t>Based on the analyses, the SIP INFO method was chosen to provide for
    mid-call data transport.</t> 
    
    </section> 

    <section title="INFO Package Name">

    <t>The INFO package name is EmergencyCallData.VEDS.</t>
    
    </section>

    <section title="INFO Package Parameters">
    
    <t>None</t>
    
    </section> 
    
    <section title="SIP Option-Tags">
    
    <t>None</t>
    
    </section>

    <section title="INFO Request Body Parts">
    
        <t>The body of an EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO package is a
    multipart body containing zero or one
    application/EmergencyCallData.VEDS+xml parts (containing a VEDS data
    block), zero or more application/EmergencyCallData.Control+xml
    (containing a metadata/control object) parts, and zero or one
    application/EmergencyCallData.eCall.MSD parts (containing an MSD).
    At least one VEDS, MSD, or metadata/control body part is expected; the
    behavior upon receiving a SIP INFO request with none is undefined.</t> 

    <t>The body parts are sent per <xref target="RFC6086"/>; in addition,
    to align with how these body parts are sent in non-INFO messages, each
    associated body part is referenced by a Call-Info header field at the top
    level of the SIP message.  The body part has a Content-Disposition header
    field set to "By-Reference".</t> 

    <t>A VEDS, metadata/control block, or MSD is always enclosed in a multipart
    body part (even if it would otherwise be the only body part in the SIP
    message).  The outermost multipart that contains only body parts
    associated with the INFO package has a Content-Disposition value of
    "Info-Package".</t> 

    <t>Service providers in the call path are not expected to add Additional Data <xref target="RFC7852"/> to SIP INFO requests (as they would to an initial INVITE request).</t> 

    </section>



    <section title="INFO Package Usage Restrictions">
    
    <t>Usage is limited to vehicle-initiated emergency calls as defined in
    this document.</t> 
    
    </section> 

    <section title="Rate of INFO Requests">
    
    <t>The SIP INFO request is used within an established emergency call
    dialog to send requests, updated data, or an acknowledgment.  Because requests are normally sent only on manual
    action of the PSAP call taker (who suspects some aspect of the vehicle
    state has changed) and updated data is sent only when an aspect of previously sent data has changed, the rate of SIP INFO requests associated with
    the EmergencyCallData.VEDS INFO package is normally quite low
    (most dialogs are likely to contain zero SIP INFO requests, while others
    can be expected to carry an occasional request).</t> 
    
    </section> 

    <section title="INFO Package Security Considerations">
    
    <t>The MIME media type registrations for the data blocks that can be
    carried using this INFO package contains a discussion of the security
    and/or privacy considerations specific to that data block.  
See Sections <xref target="security" format="counter"/> and <xref target="privacy" format="counter"/> for information on the security and privacy considerations of the data carried in vehicle-initiated emergency calls.</t> 
    
    </section> 

    <section title="Implementation Details">
    
    <t>See Sections <xref target="data-transport" format="counter"/> and <xref target="call-setup" format="counter"/> for protocol details.</t>
    
    </section>


    <section title="Examples">
    
    <t>See <xref target="example"/> for protocol examples.</t>
    
    </section>
 
    
    </section> 

</section> 


  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC6881;
      &RFC7303;
      &RFC6838;
      &RFC5226;
      &RFC7852;
      &RFC6086;


<reference anchor='RFC8147' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8147">
<front>
<title>Next-Generation Pan-European eCall</title>
<author initials='R' surname='Gellens' fullname='Randall Gellens'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='May' year='2017' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8147' />
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8147' />
</reference>

    <reference anchor="VEDS" target="https://www.apcointl.org/resources/telematics/aacn-and-veds.html">
      <front>
       <title>Vehicular Emergency Data Set (VEDS)</title>
       <author><organization>APCO International</organization> </author>
       <date year="2012" month="February"/>
      </front>
     <seriesInfo name='Version 3.0,' value='Prepared by the Advanced Automatic Crash Notification (AACN) Joint APCO/NENA Data Standardization Working Group' />
    </reference>


</references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      &RFC5012;
      &RFC5069;
      &RFC7378;
      &RFC6443;
      
      <reference anchor="triage-2008" target="https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/5304/">
        <front>
            <title>Recommendations from the Expert Panel: Advanced Automatic Collision Notification and Triage of the Injured Patient</title>
            <author><organization>National Center for Injury Prevention and Control</organization></author>
            <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
     <seriesInfo name='Centers for Disease Control' value='and Prevention' />
    </reference>
 
          <reference anchor="triage-2011"
 target="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/rr6101a1.htm">
        <front>
            <title>Guidelines for Field Triage of Injured Patients: Recommendations of the National Expert Panel on Field Triage</title>
            <author><organization>National Center for Injury Prevention and Control</organization></author>
            <date year="2012" month="January"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name='Centers for Disease Control' value='and Prevention' />
    </reference>
    
              <reference anchor="Bluetooth" target="https://www.bluetooth.com/specifications">
        <front>
            <title>Bluetooth Specifications</title>
            <author><organization>Bluetooth Special Interest Group (SIG)</organization></author>
            <date />
        </front>
    </reference>

 </references>

<section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>We would like to thank Lena Chaponniere, Alissa Cooper, Stephen Edge,
      Christer Holmberg, Allison Mankin, and Dan Romascanu for their review
      and suggestions; Robert Sparks and Paul Kyzivat for their help with the
      SIP mechanisms; Michael Montag, Arnoud van Wijk, Ban Al-Bakri, Wes
      George, Gunnar Hellstrom, and Rex Buddenberg for their feedback; and
      Ulrich Dietz for his help with preliminary draft versions of the original
      document that later evolved into this document.</t> 
</section>


  </back>
</rfc>
