<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="8287" category='std' ipr='trust200902' consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF" >

<front>

<title abbrev="LSP Ping/Trace for SR-MPLS">Label&nbsp;Switched&nbsp;Path&nbsp;(LSP)&nbsp;Ping/Traceroute&nbsp;for&nbsp;Segment&nbsp;Routing&nbsp;(SR)
IGP&nbhy;Prefix&nbsp;and&nbsp;IGP-Adjacency&nbsp;Segment&nbsp;Identifiers&nbsp;(SIDs)
with&nbsp;MPLS&nbsp;Data&nbsp;Planes</title>

<author role="editor" initials="N." surname="Kumar" fullname="Nagendra Kumar">
        <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
                <postal>
                <street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
                <city>Research Triangle Park</city> <region>NC</region> <code>27709-4987</code>
                <country>United States of America</country>
                </postal>
        <email>naikumar@cisco.com</email>
        </address>
</author>

<author role="editor" initials="C." surname="Pignataro" fullname="Carlos Pignataro">
        <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
                <postal>
                <street>7200-11 Kit Creek Road</street>
                <city>Research Triangle Park</city> <region>NC</region> <code>27709-4987</code>
                <country>United States of America</country>
                </postal>
        <email>cpignata@cisco.com</email>
        </address>
</author>

<author initials="G." surname="Swallow" fullname="George Swallow">
        <organization >Southend Technical Center</organization>
        <address>
        <email>swallow.ietf@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
</author>

<author initials="N." surname="Akiya" fullname="Nobo Akiya">
        <organization>Big Switch Networks</organization>
        <address>
                <postal>
                <street></street>
                <city></city> <region></region> <code></code>
                <country></country>
                </postal>
        <email>nobo.akiya.dev@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Kini" fullname="Sriganesh Kini">
        <organization>Individual</organization>
        <address>
                <postal>
                <street></street>
                <city></city> <region></region> <code></code>
                <country></country>
                </postal>
        <email>sriganeshkini@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
</author>

<author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
 
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
 
          <city/>
 
          <region/>
 
          <code/>
 
          <country/>
        </postal>
 
        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
<date month="December" year="2017"/>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>Network Work group</workgroup>

<abstract>

<t>A Segment Routing (SR) architecture leverages source routing and
tunneling paradigms and can be directly applied to the use of a
Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) data plane. A node steers a
packet through a controlled set of instructions called "segments" by
prepending the packet with an SR header. </t>

<t> The segment assignment and forwarding semantic nature of SR raises additional considerations for connectivity verification
and fault isolation for a Label Switched Path (LSP) within an SR
architecture. This document illustrates the problem and defines
extensions to perform LSP Ping and Traceroute for Segment Routing IGP-Prefix and IGP-Adjacency Segment Identifiers (SIDs) with an MPLS data
plane.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
        
<section title="Introduction">

                <t>"Detecting Multiprotocol Label Switched (MPLS)
                Data-Plane Failures" <xref target="RFC8029" /> defines
                a simple and efficient mechanism to detect data-plane
                failures in Label Switched Paths (LSPs) by specifying
                information to be carried in an MPLS "echo request"
                and "echo reply" for the purposes of fault detection
                and isolation. Mechanisms for reliably sending the
                echo reply are defined.  The functionality defined in
                <xref target="RFC8029" /> is modeled after the
                Ping/Traceroute paradigm (ICMP echo request <xref
                target="RFC0792" />) and is typically referred to as
                "LSP Ping" and "LSP Traceroute". <xref
                target="RFC8029" /> supports hierarchical and
                stitching LSPs.
                </t>

                                        <t><xref target="SR" />
					introduces and describes an SR architecture
                that leverages the source routing and tunneling paradigms. A node steers a packet through a 
                controlled set of instructions called "segments" by
		prepending the packet with an SR header. A
                detailed definition of the SR architecture is available in 
                <xref target="SR" />.</t>

                <t>As described in <xref target="SR" /> and <xref
                target="SR-MPLS" />, the SR architecture can
                be directly applied to an MPLS data plane, the SID will be 20 bits, and
                the SR header is the label stack.
                Consequently, the mechanics of data-plane validation
                of <xref target="RFC8029" /> can be directly applied
                to SR MPLS.</t>
                
                <t>Unlike LDP or RSVP, which are the other well-known
                MPLS control plane protocols, the basis of Segment ID
                assignment in SR architecture is not
                always on a hop-by-hop basis. Depending on the type of
                Segment ID, the assignment can be unique to the node
                or within a domain.</t>
                <t>This nature of SR raises additional
                considerations for validation of fault detection and
                isolation in an SR network. This document
                illustrates the problem and describes a mechanism to
                perform LSP Ping and Traceroute for Segment Routing
                IGP-Prefix and IGP-Adjacency
                SIDs within an MPLS data plane.
                </t>

    <section title="Coexistence of SR-Capable and Non-SR-Capable Node Scenarios">
<t>
<xref target="INTEROP" />
   describes how SR operates in a network where SR-capable and non-SR-capable
   nodes coexist. In such a network, one or more SR-based LSPs and
   non-SR-based LSPs are stitched together to achieve an end-to-end LSP.
   This is similar to a network where LDP and RSVP nodes coexist and the
   mechanism defined in Section 4.5.2 of <xref target="RFC8029" /> is applicable for LSP
   Ping and Trace.
</t>
<t>
   <xref target="backward" /> of this document explains one of the potential gaps that is
   specific to SR-Capable and non-SR-capable node scenarios and explains
   how the existing mechanism defined in <xref target="RFC8029" /> handles it.
</t>

            </section>
            </section>
         
    <section title="Requirements Notation">


        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Terminology">
            <t>This document uses the terminology defined in <xref
	    target="SR" /> and
            <xref target="RFC8029" />; readers are expected to be familiar with those terms.
            </t>
    </section>
    
<section title="Challenges with Existing Mechanisms">
<t>The following example describes the challenges with using the current MPLS
Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) mechanisms on an SR network.
</t>
        <section title="Path Validation in Segment Routing Networks">
        <t><xref target="RFC8029" /> defines the MPLS OAM mechanisms
        that help with fault detection and isolation for an MPLS
        data-plane path by the use of various Target Forwarding
        Equivalence Class (FEC) Stack sub-TLVs that are carried in
        MPLS echo request packets and used by the responder for FEC
        validation. While it is obvious that new sub-TLVs need to be
        assigned for SR, the unique nature of the SR architecture raises the need for additional
        operational considerations for path validation. This section
        discusses the challenges.
        </t>
                                        <figure>
                                                <artwork><![CDATA[
                                
                      L1
                  +--------+
                  |   L2   |
                  R3-------R6
                 /           \
                /             \
        R1----R2               R7----R8
                \             /  
                 \           /
                  R4-------R5

          Figure 1: Segment Routing Network

 The Node Segment IDs for R1, R2, R3, R4, R5, R6, R7, and R8 are 5001, 
 5002, 5003, 5004, 5005, 5006, 5007, and 5008, respectively.
 
    9136 --> Adjacency Segment ID from R3 to R6 over link L1.
    9236 --> Adjacency Segment ID from R3 to R6 over link L2.
    9124 --> Adjacency segment ID from R2 to R4.
    9123 --> Adjacency Segment ID from R2 to R3.
                        ]]></artwork>
                                        </figure>

<t>The forwarding semantic of the Adjacency Segment ID is to pop the
Segment ID and send the packet to a specific neighbor over a specific
link. A malfunctioning node may forward packets using the Adjacency
Segment ID to an incorrect neighbor or over an incorrect link. The
exposed Segment ID (of an incorrectly forwarded Adjacency Segment ID)
might still allow such a packet to reach the intended destination,
even though the intended strict traversal was broken.</t>

<t>In the topology above, assume that R1 sends traffic with a segment
stack as {9124, 5008} so that the path taken will be
R1-R2-R4-R5-R7-R8. If the Adjacency Segment ID 9124 is misprogrammed
in R2 to send the packet to R1 or R3, the packet may still be
delivered to R8 (if the nodes are configured with the same SR
Global Block (SRGB)) <xref target="SR"/> but not via the expected path.
</t>


<t>MPLS traceroute may help with detecting such a deviation in the
above-mentioned scenario. However, in a different example, it may not
be helpful, for example, if R3 forwards a
packet with Adjacency Segment ID 9236 via link L1 (due to misprogramming) when it was
expected to be forwarded over link L2.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title="Segment ID Sub-TLV">
<t>The format of the following Segment ID sub-TLVs follows the philosophy of
the Target FEC Stack
   TLV carrying FECs corresponding to each label in the label stack.
   When operated with the procedures defined in <xref target="RFC8029" />, this allows LSP
   Ping/Traceroute operations to function when the Target FEC Stack TLV
   contains more FECs than received label stacks at the responder nodes.</t>
   

<t>Three new sub-TLVs are defined for the Target FEC Stack TLV (Type 1), 
the Reverse-Path Target FEC Stack TLV (Type 16), and the Reply Path TLV (Type 21).
</t>

<figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
        Sub-Type    Sub-TLV Name
        --------  ---------------
          34      IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID
          35      IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID
          36      IGP-Adjacency Segment ID
                                                                                                ]]></artwork>
                                                                                </figure>
                <t>See <xref target="proto" /> for the registry for the Protocol field specified within these sub-TLVs.</t>
        <section title="IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID" anchor="IPv4">
<t>
The IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID is defined in
<xref target="SR" />.
The format is as specified below:
</t>
        <figure>
                                                <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                         IPv4 Prefix                           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |Prefix Length  |    Protocol   |         Reserved              |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               
          ]]></artwork>
                                        </figure>
                <t>IPv4 Prefix
                        <list><t>This field carries the IPv4 Prefix to which the Segment 
                        ID is assigned. In case of an Anycast Segment ID, this field will
                        carry the IPv4 Anycast address. If the prefix is shorter than 32 bits, trailing bits
                        SHOULD be set to zero.</t>
                        </list>
                </t>                
                <t>Prefix Length
                        <list><t>The Prefix Length field is one octet. It gives the length of
                        the prefix in bits (values can be 1-32).</t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                <t>Protocol
                        <list><t>This field is set to 1, if the responder MUST perform FEC
			validation using OSPF as the IGP protocol. Set to 2, if the responder MUST perform
			Egress FEC validation using the Intermediate System to
			Intermediate System (IS-IS) 
                        as the IGP protocol. Set to 0, if the responder can
			use any IGP protocol for Egress FEC validation.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                <t>Reserved
                        <list><t>The Reserved field MUST be set to 0 when sent and MUST be ignored on receipt.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID" anchor="IPv6">
<t>
The IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID is defined in
<xref target="SR"/>.
The format is as specified below:
</t>
        <figure>
                                                <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                         IPv6 Prefix                           |
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |Prefix Length  |    Protocol   |              Reserved         |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
                                        </figure>
                <t>IPv6 Prefix
                        <list><t>This field carries the IPv6 prefix to which the Segment 
                        ID is assigned. In case of an Anycast Segment ID, this field will
                        carry the IPv4 Anycast address. If the prefix is shorter than 128 bits, trailing
                        bits SHOULD be set to zero.</t>
                        </list>
                </t>                
                <t>Prefix Length
                        <list><t>The Prefix Length field is one octet, it gives the length of
                        the prefix in bits (values can be 1-128).</t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                <t>Protocol
                        <list><t>Set to 1 if the responder MUST perform FEC
			validation using OSPF as the IGP protocol. Set to 2 if the responder MUST perform Egress FEC validation using IS-IS 
                        as the IGP protocol. Set to 0 if the responder can use any IGP protocol for Egress FEC validation.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                <t>Reserved
                        <list><t>MUST be set to 0 on send and MUST be ignored on receipt.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>

        </section>
        <section title="IGP-Adjacency Segment ID" anchor="igp">
        <t>This sub-TLV is applicable for any IGP-Adjacency defined in 
        <xref target="SR" />. The format is as specified below:
        </t>
        <figure>
                                                <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |   Adj. Type   |    Protocol   |          Reserved             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~                                                               ~
  |               Local Interface ID (4 or 16 octets)             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~                                                               ~
  |              Remote Interface ID (4 or 16 octets)             |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~                                                               ~
  |          Advertising Node Identifier (4 or 6 octets)          |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  ~                                                               ~
  |           Receiving Node Identifier (4 or 6 octets)           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
                                        </figure>
                <t>Adj. Type (Adjacency Type)
                        <list><t>Set to 1 when the Adjacency Segment is a Parallel Adjacency as defined in
                        <xref target="SR" />. Set to 4
                        when the Adjacency Segment is IPv4 based and is not a Parallel Adjacency. Set to 
                        6 when the Adjacency Segment is IPv6 based and is not a Parallel Adjacency.
                        Set to 0 when the Adjacency Segment is over an unnumbered interface.</t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                
                <t>Protocol
                        <list><t>Set to 1 if the responder MUST perform FEC
			validation using OSPF as the IGP
                        protocol. Set to 2 if the responder MUST perform Egress FEC validation using IS-IS 
                        as the IGP protocol. Set to 0 if the responder can use any IGP protocol for Egress FEC validation.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>

                <t>Reserved
                        <list><t>MUST be set to 0 on send and MUST be ignored on receipt.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                
                <t>Local Interface ID
                        <list><t>An identifier that is assigned by the local
			Label Switching Router (LSR) for a link to which the Adjacency 
                        Segment ID is bound. This field is set to a local link address (IPv4 or IPv6). For IPv4, this field is 4 octets; for IPv6, this field is 16 octets.
                        If unnumbered, this field is 4 octets and
			includes a 32-bit link identifier as defined in <xref
			target="RFC4203" /> and
                        <xref target="RFC5307" />.
                        If the Adjacency Segment ID represents Parallel Adjacencies 
                        <xref target="SR" />, this field is 4 octets and MUST be set 
                        to 4 octets of zeroes.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                <t>Remote Interface ID
                        <list><t>An identifier that is assigned by the remote
			LSR for a link on which the Adjacency
                        Segment ID is bound. This field is set to the remote (downstream neighbor)
                        link address (IPv4 or IPv6). For IPv4, this field is 4 octets; for IPv6, this field is 16 octets.
                        If unnumbered, this field is 4 octets and
			includes a 32-bit link identifier as defined in <xref
			target="RFC4203" /> and
                        <xref target="RFC5307" />.
                        If the Adjacency Segment ID represents Parallel Adjacencies
                        <xref target="SR" />, this field is 4 octets and MUST be set
                        to 4 octets of zeroes.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                </t>                
                
                <t>Advertising Node Identifier
                        <list><t>This specifies the Advertising Node
			Identifier. When the Protocol field is set to 1, 
                        then this field is 4 octets and carries the 32-bit
			OSPF Router ID. If the Protocol field is set to 
                        2, then this field is 6 octets and carries the 48-bit
			IS-IS System ID. If the Protocol field
                        is set to 0, then this field is 4 octets and MUST be set to zero.</t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                
                <t>Receiving Node Identifier
                        <list><t>This specifies the downstream node
			identifier. When the Protocol field is set to 1,
                        then this field is 4 octets and carries the 32-bit OSPF
			Router ID. If the Protocol field is set to
                        2, then this field is 6 octets and carries the 48-bit
			IS-IS System ID. If the Protocol field
                        is set to 0, then this field is 4 octets and MUST be set to zero.</t>
                        </list>
                </t>
                
</section>
</section>


<section title="Extension to Downstream Detailed Mapping TLV">
<t>In an echo reply, the Downstream Detailed Mapping TLV <xref target="RFC8029" /> is used to
   report for each interface over which a FEC could be forwarded.  For
   a FEC, there are multiple protocols that may be used to distribute
   label mapping.  The Protocol field of the Downstream Detailed Mapping TLV is
   used to return the protocol that is used to distribute the 
   label carried in the Downstream Label field.  The following protocols are defined 
   in <xref target="RFC8029" />:
</t>
    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   Protocol #        Signaling Protocol
   ----------        ------------------
     0               Unknown
     1               Static
     2               BGP
     3               LDP
     4               RSVP-TE
                                          ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
<t>With SR, OSPF or IS-IS can be used for label
   distribution. This document adds two new protocols as follows:
</t>
    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   Protocol #        Signaling Protocol
   ----------        ------------------
     5               OSPF
     6               IS-IS
                                          ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
<t>See <xref target="ds" />.</t>
</section>
<section title="Procedures">
<t>This section describes aspects of LSP Ping and Traceroute
operations that require further considerations beyond <xref
target="RFC8029" />.</t>

<section title="FECs in Target FEC Stack TLV">

<t>When LSP echo request packets are generated by an initiator, FECs
carried in the Target FEC Stack TLV may need to differ to support an SR architecture. The following defines the Target FEC
Stack TLV construction mechanics by an initiator for SR scenarios.

<list>
    <t>Ping
    <list>
        <t>The initiator MUST include FEC(s) corresponding to the destination segment.</t>
        <t>The initiator MAY include FECs corresponding to some or all
        of the segments imposed in the label stack by the initiator to
        communicate the segments traversed.</t>
    </list>
    </t>
    <t>Traceroute
    <list>
        <t>The initiator MUST initially include FECs corresponding to all segments imposed in the label stack.</t>
        <t>When a received echo reply contains the FEC Stack Change
        TLV with one or more of the original segments being popped,
        the initiator MAY remove a corresponding FEC(s) from the Target
        FEC Stack TLV in the next (TTL+1) traceroute request, as
        defined in Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC8029" />.</t>
        <t>When a received echo reply does not contain the FEC Stack
        Change TLV, the initiator MUST NOT attempt to remove any FECs
        from the Target FEC Stack TLV in the next (TTL+1) traceroute
        request. </t>
    </list>
    </t>
</list>	
</t>

<t>As defined in <xref target="SR-OSPF" /> and 
	<xref target="SR-IS-IS" />, the Prefix SID can be advertised
	as an absolute value, an index, or as a range. In any of these cases,
	the initiator MUST derive the
	Prefix mapped to the Prefix SID and use it in the IGP-Prefix Segment ID
	defined in Sections <xref target="IPv4" format="counter" /> and <xref
	target="IPv6" format="counter" />. 

How the responder uses the details in the SR-FEC sub-TLV to perform
the validation is a local implementation matter.
	</t>

</section>

<section title="FEC Stack Change Sub-TLV">

<t><xref target="RFC8029" /> defines a FEC Stack Change sub-TLV that a
router must include when the FEC stack changes.</t>

<t>The network node that advertised the Node Segment ID is responsible
for generating a FEC Stack Change sub-TLV with the Post Office
Protocol (POP) operation type for the Node Segment ID, regardless of
whether or not Penultimate Hop Popping (PHP) is enabled.</t>

<t>The network node that is immediately downstream of the node that
advertised the Adjacency Segment ID is responsible for generating the FEC
Stack Change sub-TLV for POP operation for the Adjacency Segment ID.</t>

</section>

<section title="Segment ID POP Operation">



<t>The forwarding semantic of the Node Segment ID with the PHP flag is equivalent to
usage of Implicit Null in MPLS protocols. The Adjacency Segment ID is also
similar in a sense that it can be thought of as a locally allocated segment
that has PHP enabled when destined for the next-hop IGP Adjacency Node. Procedures described in 
Section 4.4 of <xref target="RFC8029" /> rely on the Stack-D and Stack-R
explicitly having the Implicit Null value. Implementations SHOULD use the
Implicit Null for the Node Segment ID PHP and Adjacency Segment ID PHP cases.

</t>

</section>

<section title="Segment ID Check">

<t>This section modifies the procedure defined in Section 4.4.1 of <xref target="RFC8029" />.
Step 4 defined in Section 4.4.1 of  <xref target="RFC8029" /> is modified as below:
</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
     4. If the label mapping for FEC is Implicit Null, set the 
        FEC-status to 2 and proceed to step 4a.  Otherwise,
        if the label mapping for FEC is Label-L, proceed to step 4a.
        Otherwise, set the FEC-return-code to 10 ("Mapping for this
        FEC is not the given label at stack-depth"), set the 
        FEC-status to 1, and return.
                                          ]]></artwork>
                </figure>


<t><list>
<t>4a. Segment Routing IGP-Prefix and IGP-Adjacency SID Validation:
<list>
<t>If the Label-stack-depth is 0 and the Target FEC Stack sub-TLV at
FEC-stack-depth is 34 (IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID), {
	<list>
		<t>Set the Best-return-code to 10, "Mapping for this FEC is not the given label at stack-depth 
	&lt;RSC&gt;" if any below conditions fail:</t>

 <t>/* The responder LSR is to check if it is the egress of the IPv4
 IGP-Prefix Segment ID described in the Target FEC Stack sub-TLV, and
 if the FEC was advertised with the PHP bit set.*/</t>

<t>
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised for the IPv4 Prefix by IGP Protocol {
            <list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4
                    IGP-Prefix Segment ID sub-TLV is 0, use any
                    locally enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is an unrecognized value, it MUST be
		    treated as a Protocol value of 0.</t>
            </list>
    }</t>
    
    <t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised with the No-PHP flag. {
            <list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol is OSPF, the NP-Flag defined in
		    Section 5 of <xref target="SR-OSPF" /> MUST be set to 0.</t>

                    <t>When the Protocol is IS-IS, the P-Flag defined
                    in Section 6.1 of <xref target="SR-IS-IS" /> MUST be
                    set to 0.</t>
    </list> 
    } </t>
    </list>
</t>
	    <t>If it can be determined that no protocol associated with the
	    Interface-I would have advertised the FEC-Type at FEC-stack-depth, 
		set the Best-return-code to 12, "Protocol not associated with interface at FEC-stack-depth" and return.</t>
	    <t>Set FEC-Status to 1 and return.</t>

	</list>
	}</t>

<t>Else, if the Label-stack-depth is greater than 0 and the Target FEC
Stack sub-TLV at FEC-stack-depth is 34 (IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID), {

	<list>
	<t>Set the Best-return-code to 10 if any below conditions fail:</t>
    <t>
    	<list style="symbols">
    	<t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised for the IPv4 Prefix by
	the IGP protocol {
            <list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4
                    IGP-Prefix Segment ID sub-TLV is 0, use any
                    locally enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv4 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is an unrecognized value, it MUST be
		    treated as a Protocol value of 0.</t>
            </list>
    }</t>
    </list>
    </t>
    	<t>If it can be determined that no protocol associated with
    	Interface-I would have advertised the FEC-Type at
    	FEC-stack-depth, set the Best-return-code to 12, "Protocol not
    	associated with interface at FEC stack-depth" and return.</t>
    	<t>Set FEC-Status to 1 and return.</t>
    </list>
	}</t>


<t>Else, if the Label-stack-depth is 0 and the Target FEC sub-TLV at
FEC-stack-depth is 35 (IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID), {

	<list>
		<t>Set the Best-return-code to 10 if any of the below conditions fail:</t>
	    <t>/* The LSR needs to check if it is being a tail-end for the LSP
	    and have the prefix advertised with the PHP bit set*/</t>

<t>
    <list style="symbols">
<t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised for the IPv6 Prefix by the IGP protocol {
            <list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6
                    IGP-Prefix Segment ID sub-TLV is 0, use any
                    locally enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is an unrecognized value, it MUST be
		    treated as a Protocol value of 0.</t>
            </list>
    }</t>    <t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised with the No-PHP flag. {
    				<list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol is OSPF, the NP-flag defined in Section 5 of <xref target="SR-OSPFV3" /> MUST be set to 0.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol is IS-IS, the P-Flag defined in Section 6.1 of <xref target="SR-IS-IS" /> MUST be set to 0.</t>
    				</list> 
    	
    		 }</t>
    </list>
</t>
	<t>If it can be determined that no protocol associated with
	Interface-I would have advertised the FEC-Type at FEC-stack-depth, set
	the Best-return-code to 12, "Protocol not associated with interface at FEC stack-depth" and return.</t>
	<t>Set the FEC-Status to 1 and return.</t>
    </list>
	}</t>

<t>Else, if the Label-stack-depth is greater than 0 and the Target FEC sub-TLV
at FEC-stack-depth is 35 (IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID), {

	<list>
		<t>Set the Best-return-code to 10 if any below conditions fail:</t>
    <t>
    	<list style="symbols">
			<t>Validate that the Node Segment ID is advertised for
			the IPv4 Prefix by the IGP protocol {
            	<list style="symbols">
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6
                    IGP-Prefix Segment ID sub-TLV is 0, use any
                    locally enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received IPv6 IGP-Prefix
		    Segment ID sub-TLV is an unrecognized value, it MUST be
		    treated as a Protocol value of 0.</t>
            	</list>
    		}</t>    
    	</list>
	</t>
	<t>If it can be determined that no protocol associated with
	Interface-I would have advertised the FEC-Type at
	FEC-stack-depth, set the Best-return-code to 12, "Protocol not
	associated with interface at FEC stack-depth" and return.</t>
	<t>Set the FEC-Status to 1 and return.</t>
    </list>
	}</t>
	
<t>Else, if the Target FEC sub-TLV at FEC-stack-depth is 36 (IGP-Adjacency Segment ID), {

	<list>
		<t>Set the Best-return-code to 35 (<xref target="return" />) if any below conditions fail:</t>
		
    	<t>
    		<list>
    		<t>When the Adj. Type is 1 (Parallel Adjacency):
            	<list style="symbols">
                    <t>Validate that the Receiving Node Identifier is the local IGP identifier.</t>
                    <t>Validate that the IGP-Adjacency Segment ID is
		    advertised by the Advertising Node Identifier of the Protocol
		    in the local IGP database {
                            <list style="symbols">
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the
                                    received IGP-Adjacency Segment ID
                                    sub-TLV is 0, use any locally
                                    enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use
				    OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use
				    IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is an
				    unrecognized value, it MUST be treated as
				    a Protocol value of 0.</t>
                            </list>
                    }</t>
            	</list></t>
    
    		<t>When the Adj. Type is 4 or 6 (IGP Adjacency or LAN Adjacency):
            	<list style="symbols">
                    <t>Validate that the Remote Interface ID matches
                    the local identifier of the interface
                    (Interface-I) on which the packet was
                    received.</t>
                    <t>Validate that the Receiving Node Identifier is the local IGP identifier.</t>
                        <t>Validate that the IGP-Adjacency Segment ID is
			advertised by the Advertising Node Identifier of
			Protocol in the local IGP database {
                            <list style="symbols">
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the
                                    received IGP-Adjacency Segment ID
                                    sub-TLV is 0, use any locally
                                    enabled IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is 1, use
				    OSPF as the IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is 2, use
				    IS-IS as the IGP protocol.</t>
                                    <t>When the Protocol field in the received
				    IGP-Adjacency Segment ID sub-TLV is an
				    unrecognized value, it MUST be treated as
				    a Protocol value of 0.</t>
                            </list>
                    	}</t>   
            </list></t>
            
    	</list>
    
</t> 
	<t>Set the FEC-Status to 1 and return.</t>
 
</list> 
	}</t>
</list>
</t>
</list></t>
</section>

        <section title="TTL Consideration for Traceroute">
        <t>The LSP Traceroute operation can properly traverse every hop of the
	SR network for the Uniform Model as described in <xref target="RFC3443" />. If one or 
more LSRs employ a Short Pipe Model, as  described in <xref target="RFC3443"
/>, then the LSP 
Traceroute may not be able to properly traverse every hop of the SR network due to the absence of TTL copy operation when the outer label 
is popped. The Short Pipe is one of the most commonly used models. The following TTL manipulation technique MAY 
be used when the Short Pipe Model is used.
        </t>
        
        <t>When tracing an LSP according to the procedures in <xref target="RFC8029" />, the TTL
   is incremented by one in order to trace the path sequentially along
   the LSP.  However, when a source-routed LSP has to be traced, there are
   as many TTLs as there are labels in the stack.  The LSR that
   initiates the traceroute SHOULD start by setting the TTL to 1 for the
   tunnel in the LSP's label stack it wants to start the tracing from,
   the TTL of all outer labels in the stack to the max value, and the
   TTL of all the inner labels in the stack to zero.  Thus, a typical
   start to the traceroute would have a TTL of 1 for the outermost label
   and all the inner labels would have a TTL of 0.  If the FEC Stack TLV is
   included, it should contain only those for the inner-stacked tunnels.
   The Return Code/Subcode and FEC Stack Change TLV should be
   used to diagnose the tunnel as described in <xref target="RFC8029" />.  When the
   tracing of a tunnel in the stack is complete, then the next tunnel in
   the stack should be traced.  The end of a tunnel can be detected from
   the Return Code when it indicates that the responding LSR is an
   egress for the stack at depth 1.  Thus, the traceroute procedures in
   <xref target="RFC8029" /> can be recursively applied to traceroute a source-routed
   LSP.
        </t>
        </section>
</section>

<section title="Backward Compatibility with Non-SR Devices" anchor="backward">
        <t><xref target="INTEROP" /> describes how 
        SR operates in a network where SR-capable and non-SR-capable nodes
        coexist. In such networks, there may not be any FEC mapping in the responder
         when the initiator is SR-capable, while the responder is not (or vice-versa). But this is 
         not different from RSVP and LDP interoperation scenarios. When LSP Ping is triggered, the responder
          will set the FEC-return-code to Return 4, "Replying router has no mapping for the FEC at 
         stack-depth".  
        </t>
        
        <t>Similarly, when an SR-capable node assigns Adj-SID for a
	non-SR-capable node, the LSP traceroute may
        fail as the non-SR-capable node is not aware of the "IGP Adjacency Segment ID" sub-TLV and
        may not reply with the FEC Stack Change sub-TLVs. 

This may result in any further downstream nodes
        replying back with a Return Code of 4, "Replying router has no mapping for the FEC at stack-depth".
        </t>
</section>

                <section title="IANA Considerations">
                        <section title="New Target FEC Stack Sub-TLVs">
                        <t>IANA has assigned three new sub-TLVs from
			the "sub-TLVs for TLV Types 1,
                        16, and 21" subregistry of the "Multi-Protocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label 
                        Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters" registry
<xref target="IANA" />.
                        </t>
                        <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Sub-Type    Sub-TLV Name                 Reference
--------    -----------------            ------------
  34        IPv4 IGP-Prefix Segment ID   Section 5.1 
  35        IPv6 IGP-Prefix Segment ID   Section 5.2
  36        IGP-Adjacency Segment ID     Section 5.3
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
 
                        </section>
                        
                        <section anchor="proto" title="Protocol in the Segment ID Sub-TLV">
                                <t>
    IANA has created a new "Protocol in the Segment ID sub-TLV" (see Section 5) registry under the
    "Multi-Protocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs)
    Ping Parameters" registry. Code points in the range of 0-250
    will be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>. The range of 251-254 is
    reserved for experimental use and will not be assigned. The value of 255 is marked "Reserved".  The
    initial entries into the registry are:

</t>
                                <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value           Meaning              Reference
----------        ----------------     ------------
  0               Any IGP protocol     This document
  1               OSPF                 This document
  2               IS-IS                This document
                                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

</section>

                        <section anchor="adj-iana" title="Adjacency Type in the IGP-Adjacency Segment ID">
                                <t>
    IANA has created a new "Adjacency Type in the IGP-Adjacency
    Segment ID" registry (see <xref target="igp"/>) under the "Multi-Protocol
    Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping
    Parameters" registry. Code points in the range of 0-250 will be
    assigned by Standards Action. The range of 251-254 is reserved for
    experimental use and will not be assigned. The value of 255 is marked "Reserved".  The initial entries
    into the registry are:

</t>
                                <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value           Meaning         
----------        ----------------
  0               Unnumbered Interface Adjacency
  1               Parallel Adjacency
  4               IPv4, Non-parallel Adjacency
  6               IPv6, Non-parallel Adjacency
                                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>


</section>

<section anchor="ds" title="Protocol in the Label Stack Sub-TLV of the Downstream Detailed Mapping TLV">

<t>IANA has created a new "Protocol in the Label Stack sub-TLV of
the Downstream Detailed Mapping TLV" registry under the "Multi-Protocol
Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters"
registry. Code points in the range of 0-250 will be assigned by
Standards Action. The range of 251-254 is reserved for experimental
use and will not be assigned. The value of 255 is marked "Reserved".  The initial entries into the registry are:


                                </t>
                                
                                <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value        Meaning              Reference
----------     ----------------     ------------
  0            Unknown              Section 3.4.1.2 of RFC 8029
  1            Static               Section 3.4.1.2 of RFC 8029
  2            BGP                  Section 3.4.1.2 of RFC 8029
  3            LDP                  Section 3.4.1.2 of RFC 8029
  4            RSVP-TE              Section 3.4.1.2 of RFC 8029
  5            OSPF                 Section 6 of this document
  6            IS-IS                Section 6 of this document
  7-250        Unassigned        
  251-254      Reserved for 
               Experimental Use     This document
  255          Reserved             This document
                                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                
                        </section>
                        
                        <section title="Return Code" anchor="return">
                                <t>IANA has assigned a new Return Code from the "Multi-Protocol Label 
                                Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters" in the 0-191 (Standards Action) range from the "Return Codes" 
                                subregistry.
                                </t>
                                
                                <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Value     Meaning                                  Reference
----------  -----------------                        ------------
  35        Mapping for this FEC is not associated   Section 7.4 of
            with the incoming interface              this document
     
                                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                
                        </section>
                </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
                <t>This document defines additional MPLS LSP Ping sub-TLVs and follows the mechanisms defined
                in <xref target="RFC8029" />. All the security considerations defined in
                <xref target="RFC8029" /> will be applicable for this document and, in addition,
                they do not impose any additional security challenges to be considered.</t>
                </section>
    </middle>
        
<back>

<references title="Normative References">
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8029"?>

    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3443"?>
    
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4203"?>
    
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5307"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>


    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>

<!--draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-13; In Last Call -->
<reference anchor='SR'>
<front>
<title>Segment Routing Architecture</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='28' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-13' />

</reference>
        
<!--draft-ietf-ospf-ospfv3-segment-routing-extensions-10; I-D exists -->
<reference anchor='SR-OSPFV3'>
<front>
<title>OSPFv3 Extensions for Segment Routing</title>

<author initials='P' surname='Psenak' fullname='Peter Psenak'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Gredler' fullname='Hannes Gredler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Henderickx' fullname='Wim Henderickx'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='5' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ospf-ospfv3-segment-routing-extensions-10' />

</reference>
<!--draft-ietf-ospf-segment-routing-extensions-24; RFC Ed Queue  -->

<reference anchor='SR-OSPF'>
<front>
<title>OSPF Extensions for Segment Routing</title>

<author initials='P' surname='Psenak' fullname='Peter Psenak'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Gredler' fullname='Hannes Gredler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Henderickx' fullname='Wim Henderickx'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' day='14' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>Segment Routing (SR) allows a flexible definition of end-to-end paths within IGP topologies by encoding paths as sequences of topological sub-paths, called "segments".  These segments are advertised by the link-state routing protocols (IS-IS and OSPF).  This draft describes the OSPFv2 extensions required for Segment Routing.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ospf-segment-routing-extensions-24' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-ospf-segment-routing-extensions-24.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions-14; I-D exists -->

<reference anchor='SR-IS-IS'>
<front>
<title>IS-IS Extensions for Segment Routing</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Bashandy' fullname='Ahmed Bashandy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Gredler' fullname='Hannes Gredler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' day='15' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions-14' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions-14.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls-11; AD Evaluation:: AD Followup -->
    
<reference anchor='SR-MPLS'>
<front>
<title>Segment Routing with MPLS data plane</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Bashandy' fullname='Ahmed Bashandy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='30' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls-11' />

</reference>
        
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0792"?>

<!--draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-ldp-interop-09; Publication Requested -->
<reference anchor='INTEROP'>
<front>
<title>Segment Routing interworking with LDP</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Bashandy' fullname='Ahmed Bashandy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='29' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-ldp-interop-09' />

</reference>


<reference anchor="IANA" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/mpls-lsp-ping-parameters/mpls-lsp-ping-parameters.xhtml">
  <front>
    <title>Multi-Protocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters</title>
    <author><organization>IANA</organization></author>
    <date/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>
                <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
                                        <t> The authors would like to thank Stefano Previdi, Les Ginsberg,
                                        Balaji Rajagopalan, Harish Sitaraman, Curtis Villamizar, Pranjal Dutta, 
                                        Lizhong Jin, Tom Petch, Victor Ji, Mustapha Aissaoui, Tony Przygienda,
                                        Alexander Vainshtein, and Deborah Brungard for their review and comments.</t>
                                        <t> The authors would like to thank Loa Andersson for his comments and
                                        recommendation to merge documents.</t>
                    
                </section>
        
        <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
        
<t>The following are key contributors to this document:
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<list>
                <t>Hannes Gredler, RtBrick, Inc.</t>
                <t>Tarek Saad, Cisco Systems, Inc.</t>
                <t>Siva Sivabalan, Cisco Systems, Inc.</t>
                <t>Balaji Rajagopalan, Juniper Networks</t>
                <t>Faisal Iqbal, Cisco Systems, Inc.</t>
</list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>

    </section>

</back>

</rfc>
