<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--	$Id: rfc8556.xml,v 1.3 2019/03/11 18:00:23 erosen Exp $	-->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4364 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5331 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5331.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6513 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6513.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6514 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6514.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6625 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6625.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7524 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7524.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7900 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7900.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8279 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8279.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8296 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8296.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8534 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8534.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc number="8556" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902"> 

  <front>

    <title abbrev="MVPN with BIER">Multicast VPN Using Bit Index Explicit
    Replication (BIER)</title>

    <author fullname="Eric C. Rosen" initials="E." role="editor"
            surname="Rosen">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Technology Park Drive</street>
          <city>Westford</city>
          <region>Massachusetts</region>
          <code>01886</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>erosen52@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mahesh Sivakumar" initials="M." 
            surname="Sivakumar">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1137 Innovation Way</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sivakumar.mahesh@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="T." 
            surname="Przygienda">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1137 Innovation Way</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>prz@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    

    <author fullname="Sam K Aldrin" initials="S." 
            surname="Aldrin">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code></code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>aldrin.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>    

    <author fullname="Andrew Dolganow" initials="A." 
            surname="Dolganow">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>438B Alexandra Rd #08-07/10</street>
          <street>Alexandra Technopark</street>
          <code>119968</code>
          <region>Singapore</region>
        </postal>
        <email>andrew.dolganow@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2018" />


    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Multicast</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The Multicast Virtual Private Network (MVPN) specifications require
        the use of multicast tunnels ("P-tunnels") that traverse a
        service provider's backbone network.  The P-tunnels are used
        for carrying multicast traffic across the backbone.  A variety of
        P-tunnel types are supported.  Bit Index Explicit Replication
        (BIER) is a new architecture that provides optimal multicast
        forwarding through a "multicast domain", without requiring
        intermediate routers to maintain any per-flow state or to engage in
        an explicit tree&nbhy;building protocol.  This document specifies the
        protocol and procedures that allow MVPN to use BIER as the method of
        carrying multicast traffic over a service provider's backbone network.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC6513"/> and <xref target="RFC6514"/> specify the
        protocols and procedures that a Service Provider (SP) can use to
        provide Multicast Virtual Private Network (MVPN) service to its
        customers.  Multicast tunnels are created through an SP's backbone
        network; these are known as "P-tunnels".  The P-tunnels
        are used for carrying multicast traffic across the backbone.  The
        MVPN specifications allow the use of several different kinds of
        P-tunnel technology.
      </t>
      <t>
        Bit Index Explicit Replication (BIER) (<xref target="RFC8279"/>)
        is an architecture that provides optimal multicast forwarding
        through a "multicast domain", without requiring intermediate routers
        to maintain any per-flow state or to engage in an explicit
        tree-building protocol.  The purpose of the current document is to
        specify the protocols and procedures needed in order to provide MVPN
        service using BIER to transport the multicast traffic over the
        backbone. 
      </t>
      <t>
        Although BIER does not explicitly build and maintain multicast
        tunnels, one can think of BIER as using a number of implicitly
        created tunnels through a "BIER domain".  In particular, one can
        think of there as being one Point-to-Multipoint (P2MP) tunnel from
        each Bit Forwarding Ingress Router (BFIR) to all the Bit Forwarding
        Egress Routers (BFERs) in the BIER domain, where a BIER domain is
        generally co-extensive with an IGP network. These "tunnels" are not
        specific to any particular VPN.  However, the MVPN architecture
        provides protocols and procedures that allow the traffic of multiple
        MVPNs to be aggregated on a single P-tunnel.  In this document, we
        specify how to use these multi-VPN aggregation procedures to enable
        BIER to transport traffic from multiple MVPNs.
      </t>
      <t>
        MVPN traffic must sometimes traverse more than one IGP domain,
        whereas BIER only carries multicast traffic within a single IGP
        domain.  However, the MVPN specifications allow P-tunnels to be
        segmented (the concept of MVPN segmentation is defined in <xref
        target="RFC6513"/> and <xref target="RFC6514"/>), where the
        segmentation points may either be Autonomous System Border Routers
        (ASBRs) as described in <xref target="RFC6514"/>, or Area Border
        Routers (ABRs) as described in <xref target="RFC7524"/>.  As long as
        the segmentation points are capable of acting as BFIRs and BFERs,
        BIER can be used to provide some or all of the segments of a
        P-tunnel.
      </t>
      <t>
        Procedures to support MVPN customers who are using Bidirectional PIM
        (BIDIR-PIM) are outside the scope of this document.
      </t>
      <t>
      This document uses the following terminology from <xref
      target="RFC8279"/>:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          BFR: Bit-Forwarding Router.
        </t>
        <t>
          BFIR: Bit-Forwarding Ingress Router.
        </t>
        <t>
          BFER: Bit-Forwarding Egress Router.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        This document uses the following terminology from <xref
        target="RFC6513"/>:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            MVPN: Multicast Virtual Private Network -- a VPN <xref
            target="RFC4364"/> in which multicast service is offered.
          </t>
          <t>
            P-tunnel: A multicast tunnel through the network of one or
            more SPs.  P-tunnels are used to transport MVPN multicast
            data
          </t>
          <t>
            PMSI: Provider Multicast Service Interface.  PMSI is an
            abstraction that represents a multicast service for carrying
            packets.  A PMSI is instantiated via one or more P-tunnels.
          </t>
          <t>
            C-S: A multicast source address, identifying a multicast
            source located at a VPN customer site.
          </t>
          <t>
            C-G: A multicast group address used by a VPN customer.
          </t>
          <t>
            C-flow: A customer multicast flow.  Each C-flow is
            identified by the ordered pair (source address, group address),
            where each address is in the customer's address space.  The
            identifier of a particular C-flow is usually written as
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G).
            <vspace/>
            <vspace/>
            Sets of C-flows can be identified by the use of the
            "C-*" wildcard (see <xref target="RFC6625"/>), e.g.,
            (C-*,C-G).
          </t>
          <t>
            I-PMSI A-D Route: Inclusive PMSI Auto-Discovery route.
            Carried in BGP Update messages, these routes are used to
            advertise the default P-tunnel for a particular MVPN.
          </t>
          <t>
            S-PMSI A-D route: Selective PMSI Auto-Discovery route.
            Carried in BGP Update messages, these routes are used to
            advertise the fact that particular C-flows are bound to
            (i.e., are traveling through) particular P-tunnels.
          </t>
          <t>
            x-PMSI A-D route: A route that is either an
            I-PMSI A-D route or an S-PMSI A-D route.
          </t>
          <t>
            Leaf A-D route: A route that a multicast egress node sends
            in order to join a particular P-tunnel.
          </t>
          <t>
            PMSI Tunnel attribute (PTA): In an x-PMSI A-D route, the
            Network Layer Reachability Information (NLRI) of the route
            identifies a PMSI.  The BGP attribute known as the PMSI Tunnel
            attribute is attached to such a route in order to identify a
            particular P-tunnel that is associated with the PMSI.  When
            C-flows of multiple VPNs are carried in a single P-tunnel, this
            attribute also carries the information needed to multiplex and
            demultiplex the C-flows. A PTA can also be carried by a Leaf A-D
            root.  In this case, it contains information that is needed in
            order for the originator of the route to join the specified
            P-tunnel.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
        only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t></section>

    <section title="Use of the PMSI Tunnel Attribute in x-PMSI A-D Routes"
             anchor="PTA_x_PMSI"> 
      <t>
        As defined in <xref target="RFC6514"/>, the PMSI Tunnel attribute
        (PTA) carried by an x-PMSI A-D route identifies the P-tunnel
        that is used to instantiate a particular PMSI. If a PMSI is to be
        instantiated by BIER, the PTA is constructed by a BFIR.
      </t>
      <t>
        If segmented P-tunnels are not being used, the PTA attached to a
        given x-PMSI A-D route is constructed by the router that originated
        the route (typically by the ingress Provider Edge (PE) router), and
        the PTA is not changed as the route is propagated.
      </t>
      <t>
        If segmented P-tunnels are being used, the PTA attached to a
        given x-PMSI A-D route by the route's originator may be
        replaced at a segmentation point (a BFER) by a PTA identifying the
        next segment of the P-tunnel.  If the next segment of the
        P-tunnel is instantiated by BIER, the segmentation point serves
        as the BFIR for that next segment.
      </t>
      <t>
        In either case, a PTA is constructed by a BFIR as follows (see <xref
        target="bier_pta"/>):
      </t>
      <t>
        The PTA contains the following fields:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Tunnel Type:  IANA has assigned 0x0B as the tunnel type
              codepoint for "BIER" in the "P-Multicast Service
              Interface Tunnel (PMSI Tunnel) Tunnel Types" registry.  This
              codepoint is used to indicate that the PMSI is instantiated by
              BIER.
              <vspace/>
              <vspace/>
              Although BIER does not actually create tunnels, the MVPN
              procedures treat BIER as if it were a type of tunnel.
            </t>
            <t>
              Tunnel Identifier:  When the tunnel type is BIER,
              this field contains three subfields:
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>
                  The first subfield is a single octet, containing a BIER
                  sub&nbhy;domain-id (see <xref target="RFC8279"/>).
                  This indicates that packets sent on the PMSI will be sent
                  on the specified BIER sub&nbhy;domain. How that
                  sub-domain is chosen is outside the scope of this
                  document.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The second subfield is a two-octet field containing the
                  BFR&nbhy;id in the sub-domain identified in the
                  first subfield of the router that is constructing the
                  PTA.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The third subfield is the BFR-prefix (see <xref
                  target="RFC8279"/>) of the router (a BFIR) that is
                  constructing the PTA.  The BFR-prefix will either be
                  a /32 IPv4 address or a /128 IPv6 address.  Whether the
                  address is IPv4 or IPv6 can be inferred from the total
                  length of the PTA.
                  <vspace/>
                  <vspace/>
                  The BFR-prefix need not be the same IP address that
                  is carried in any other field of the x-PMSI A-D
                  route, even if the BFIR is the originating router of the
                  x-PMSI A-D route.
                </t>
              </list>
              Failure to properly set the Tunnel Identifier field cannot be
              detected by the protocol and will result in improper delivery
              of the data packets sent on the PMSI.
            </t>
            <t>
              MPLS Label:  This field MUST contain an upstream-assigned
              non&nbhy;zero MPLS label.  It is assigned by the router (a BFIR)
              that constructs the PTA. Constraints on the way in which a
              BFIR selects this label are discussed in <xref
              target="mpls_label"/>.
              <vspace/>
              <vspace/>
              Failure to follow the constraints on label assignment cannot
              be detected by the protocol and may result in improper
              handling of data packets by the egress PE routers.
            </t>
            <t>
              Flags:  When the tunnel type is BIER, two of the flags in
              the PTA Flags field are meaningful.  Details about the use of
              these flags can be found in <xref target="Explicit-Tracking"/>.
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>
                  Leaf Information Required per Flow (LIR&nbhy;pF):  This flag is
                  introduced in <xref target="RFC8534"/>.  A BFIR
                  SHOULD NOT set this flag UNLESS it knows that all the
                  BFERs in the BIER domain (or at least all the BFERs to
                  which it needs to transmit) support this flag.  (How this
                  is known is outside the scope of this document.)
                  Procedures for the use of this flag are given in <xref
                  target="lir-pf"/>.  Support for this flag is OPTIONAL.

                </t>
                <t>
                  Leaf Information Required (LIR): see <xref target="lir"/>.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
<figure align="center" anchor="bier_pta" title="PMSI Tunnel Attribute for BIER">
    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

+---------------------------------+
|  Flags (1 octet)                |
+---------------------------------+
|  Tunnel Type = 0x0B (1 octet)   |
+---------------------------------+
|  MPLS Label (3 octets)          |
+---------------------------------+
|  Sub-domain-id (1 octet)        |  <---
+---------------------------------+     |
|  BFR-id (2 octets)              |     |-- Tunnel 
+---------------------------------+     |   Identifier
|  BFR-prefix (4 or 16 octets)    |  <---
+---------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
</figure>        
      <t>
        If a PTA specifying tunnel type BIER is attached to an x-PMSI
        A-D route, the route MUST NOT be distributed beyond the
        boundaries of a BIER domain.  That is, any routers that receive the
        route must be in the same BIER domain as the originator of the
        route.  If the originator is in more than one BIER domain, the route
        must be distributed only within the BIER domain in which the
        BFR-prefix in the PTA uniquely identifies the originator.  As
        with all MVPN routes, distribution of these routes is controlled by
        the provisioning of Route Targets (RTs).  Thus, the requirement expressed
        in this paragraph is really a requirement on the way the Route
        Targets are provisioned.
      </t>
      <section title="MPLS Label" anchor="mpls_label">
        <t>
          The MPLS Label carried in the PTA is an upstream-assigned label.  
        </t>
        <t>
          If two PTAs contain the same BFR-prefix in their respective Tunnel
          Identifier fields, then the labels carried in those PTAs MUST come
          from the same label space (see Section 7 of <xref
          target="RFC5331"/>).  An implementation may choose to use this
          fact when setting up the tables it uses to interpret the
          upstream-assigned labels.  
        </t>
        <t>
          Suppose that a BFIR attaches a PTA to each of two x-PMSI A-D
          routes, and both PTAs specify a tunnel type of BIER.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              If the two routes do not carry the same set of RTs, then their
              respective PTAs MUST contain different MPLS label values.
            </t>
            <t>
              If the two routes do not have the same Address Family
              Identifier (AFI) value, then their respective PTAs MUST
              contain different MPLS label values.  This ensures that when
              an egress PE receives a data packet with the given label,
              the egress PE can infer from the label whether the payload
              is an IPv4 packet or an IPv6 packet.
            </t>
            <t>
              If the BFIR is an ingress PE supporting MVPN extranet (<xref
              target="RFC7900"/>) functionality, and if the two routes
              originate from different VPN Routing and Forwarding tables (VRFs) on this ingress PE, then the
              respective PTAs of the two routes MUST contain different
              MPLS label values.
            </t>
            <t>
              If the BFIR is an ingress PE supporting the "Extranet
              Separation" feature of MVPN extranet (see Section 7.3 of
              <xref target="RFC7900"/>), and if one of the routes carries
              the "Extranet Separation" extended community but the other
              does not, then the respective PTAs of the two routes MUST
              contain different MPLS label values.
            </t>
            <t>
              If segmented P-tunnels are being used, then the
              respective PTAs of the two routes MUST contain different MPLS
              label values whenever the respective NLRIs of the two routes
              are not identical.  The MPLS label can then be used at the
              next segmentation point to switch packets from one
              P-tunnel segment directly to the next, without requiring
              the segmentation points to contain any other multicast
              forwarding state.  This is explained further below; see also
              <xref target="dataplane"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          When segmented P-tunnels are being used, a segmentation point,
          call it "B1", may receive an x-PMSI A-D route whose PTA specifies
          BIER from within a given BIER domain.  This means that BIER is
          being used for the previous segment of a segmented P-tunnel.  If
          the next segment is also of type BIER, B1 will be the BFIR for the
          next segment. That is, B1 is a BFER of one BIER domain
          (corresponding to the previous segment) and a BFIR of another BIER
          domain (corresponding to the next segment).  B1 needs to replace
          the PTA of the x-PMSI A-D route with a new PTA, specifying its own
          BFR-prefix and specifying an upstream-assigned label assigned by
          B1 itself.
        </t>
        <t>
          Suppose that B1 has received two x-PMSI A-D routes, R1 and
          R2, where:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              R1 and R2 each have a PTA specifying BIER.
            </t>
            <t>
              R1's PTA specifies BFR-prefix B2 and Label L2.
            </t>
            <t>
              R2's PTA specifies BFR-prefix B3 and Label L3.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Suppose B1 decides to propagate both R1 and R2, replacing each PTA
          with a new PTA specifying BIER.  Suppose these new PTAs specify
          labels L4 and L5,respectively.  Then L4 and L5 MUST be different
          (upstream-assigned) label values, UNLESS both of the following
          conditions hold:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              R1 and R2 have the same value in the Originating Router field
              of their respective NLRIs, and
            </t>
            <t>
              B2 is equal to B3, and
            </t>
            <t>
              L2 is equal to L3.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The segmentation point (B1, in this example) MUST also program its
          data plane appropriately. For example, when:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              B1 receives a BIER packet for which it is a BFER, and
            </t>
            <t>
              the BIER header specifies the BFIR-id that corresponds to
              B2, and
            </t>
            <t>
              the BIER payload is an MPLS packet with upstream-assigned
              label, and
            </t>
            <t>
              the top label value is L2,
            </t>
          </list>
          then the data plane must be programmed to replace L2 with L4 and
          to re-encapsulate the packet in a BIER header with B1's
          BFR-id in the BFIR-id field. 
The BitString of the new BIER header is determined by applying the
procedures for MVPN explicit tracking (see <xref
target="Explicit-Tracking"/>) in the BIER domain of the next segment, i.e.,
in the BIER domain for which B1 is the BFIR).
        </t>
        </section>
      
      <section title="Explicit Tracking" anchor="Explicit-Tracking">
        <t>
          When using BIER to transport an MVPN data packet through a BIER
          domain, an ingress PE functions as a BFIR (see <xref
          target="RFC8279"/>).  The BFIR must determine the set of BFERs
          to which the packet needs to be delivered.  This can be done in
          either of two ways:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Using the explicit tracking mechanism based on the "Leaf Information
              Required" flag specified in <xref target="RFC6513"/> and <xref
              target="RFC6514"/>.  This method is further described in <xref
              target="lir"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              Using the OPTIONAL explicit tracking mechanism based on the
              LIR&nbhy;pF flag specified in <xref target="RFC8534"/>.
              This method, further described in <xref target="lir-pf"/>, may
              be used if (and only if) segmented P-tunnels are not
              being used.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <section title="Using the LIR Flag" anchor="lir">
          <t>
            To determine the set of BFERs to which the packets of a given
            C-flow must be sent, a BFIR MUST originate a (C-S,C-G) S-PMSI
            A-D route for the given C-flow.  It MUST attach a PTA to that
            route and MUST set the Leaf Information Required (LIR) flag in
            the PTA.  Per <xref target="RFC6514"/>, the BFERs that need to
            receive that C&nbhy;flow will respond with (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G)
            Leaf A&nbhy;D routes.  By matching the received Leaf A&nbhy;D
            routes to the originated S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D routes, the
            originator of the S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route determines the set
            of BFERs that need to receive the multicast data flow that is
            identified in the NLRI of S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route.
          </t>
          <t>
            Suppose that an ingress PE has originated an I&nbhy;PMSI
            A&nbhy;D route or a wildcard S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route <xref
            target="RFC6625"/> with a PTA specifying a tunnel type of BIER.
            Now suppose that the ingress PE originates an S&nbhy;PMSI
            A&nbhy;D route specifying (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G), where
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) "matches" (according to the rules of <xref
            target="RFC6625"/>) the wildcard S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route or
            the I&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route. Instead of attaching a PTA
            specifying BIER to the (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) route, the ingress PE
            MAY attach a PTA specifying a tunnel type of "no tunnel
            information".  This is equivalent to attaching the same PTA
            attached to the matching "less specific" route.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Using the LIR&nbhy;pF Flag" anchor="lir-pf">
          <t>
            If segmented P&nbhy;tunnels are not being used, the BFIR can
            determine the set of BFERs that need to receive the packets of a
            given (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) C&nbhy;flow as follows.  The BFIR MUST
            originate a wildcard S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route (either
            (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;*), (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;G), or
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G)), and the PTA of that route MUST use the
            following settings:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                The LIR&nbhy;pF flag MUST be set.
              </t>
              <t>
                The tunnel type MUST be set to BIER.
              </t>
              <t>
                A non-zero MPLS label MUST be specified.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Per <xref target="RFC8534"/>, a BFER that needs to
            receive (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) traffic from the BFIR will respond
            with a Leaf A&nbhy;D route.
          </t>
          <t>
            A BFIR MUST NOT use this method of finding the set of BFERs
            needing to receive a given C&nbhy;flow unless it knows that all
            those BFERs support the LIR&nbhy;pF flag.  How this is known is
            outside the scope of this document.
          </t>
          <t>
            This method greatly reduces the number of S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D
            routes that a BFIR needs to originate; it can now originate as
            few as one such route (a (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;*) S&nbhy;PMSI
            A&nbhy;D route), rather than one for each C&nbhy;flow.  However,
            the method does not provide a way for the BFIR to assign a
            distinct label to each C&nbhy;flow.  Therefore, it cannot be used
            when segmented P&nbhy;tunnels are in use (see <xref
            target="dataplane"/> for an explanation).
          </t>
          <t>
            Note: If a BFIR originates a (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;*) S&nbhy;PMSI
            A&nbhy;D route with the LIR&nbhy;pF flag set but also originates a
            more specific wildcard route that matches a particular
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G), the BFERs will not originate Leaf A&nbhy;D
            routes for that (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) unless the LIR&nbhy;pF flag is
            also set in the more specific wildcard route.  If the BFIR also
            originates a (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route
            without the LIR flag set, the BFERs will not originate Leaf
            A&nbhy;D routes for that (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) unless the LIR flag
            is also set in that route.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of the PMSI Tunnel Attribute in Leaf A-D Routes"
             anchor="PTA_Leaf">
      <t>
        Before an egress PE can receive a (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) flow from a
        given ingress PE via BIER, the egress PE must have received one of
        the following x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D routes from the ingress PE:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
<!-- [rfced] Where should the closing parenthesis appear?

Original:
   o  A (C-S,C-G) S-PMSI A-D route (i.e., an S-PMSI A-D route whose NLRI
      encodes (C-S,C-G) and whose PTA specifies a tunnel type of "BIER".
      If such a route is found, we refer to it as the "matching x-PMSI
      A-D route."

Perhaps:
   o  A (C-S,C-G) S-PMSI A-D route (i.e., an S-PMSI A-D route) whose NLRI
      encodes (C-S,C-G) and whose PTA specifies a tunnel type of "BIER".
      If such a route is found, we refer to it as the "matching x-PMSI
      A-D route."
-->

<!-- I have fixed this below -->
            A (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route (i.e., an
            S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route whose NLRI encodes
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G)) and whose PTA specifies a tunnel type of
            BIER. If such a route is found, we refer to it as the
            "matching x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route."
          </t>
          <t>
            A "less specific" x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route (one specifying
            (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;*), (C&nbhy;*,C&nbhy;G), or
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G)) whose PTA specifies a tunnel type of
            BIER, and that is the egress PE's "match for reception" of
            (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G).
            <vspace/>
            <vspace/>
            The rules for determining which x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route is
            the match for reception are given in <xref target="RFC6625"/>.
            However, these rules are modified here to exclude any
            x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route that does not have a PTA or whose
            PTA specifies "no tunnel type".
            <vspace/>
            <vspace/>
            If such a route is found, we refer to it as the "matching
            x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route."
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        If no matching x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route for (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) is
        found, the egress PE cannot receive the (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) flow from the
        ingress PE via BIER until such time as a matching route is received.
      </t>
      <t>
        When an egress PE determines that it needs to receive a
        (C&nbhy;S,C&nbhy;G) flow from a particular ingress PE via BIER, it
        originates a Leaf A&nbhy;D route.  Construction of the Leaf A&nbhy;D
        route generally follows the procedures specified in <xref
        target="RFC6514"/> or, optionally, the procedures specified in <xref
        target="RFC8534"/>. However, when BIER is being used, the
        Leaf A&nbhy;D route MUST carry a PTA that is constructed as follows:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            The tunnel type MUST be set to BIER.
          </t>
          <t>
            The MPLS Label field SHOULD be set to zero.
          </t>
          <t>
            The sub-domain-id subfield of the Tunnel Identifier field (as
            defined in <xref target="PTA_x_PMSI"/>) MUST be set to the
            corresponding value from the PTA of the matching x-PMSI
            A-D route.
          </t>
          <t>
            The BFR&nbhy;id subfield of the Tunnel Identifier field MUST be
            set to the BFR&nbhy;id in the sub&nbhy;domain identified by the
            sub&nbhy;domain&nbhy;id subfield of the egress PE (BFER).
          </t>
          <t>
            The BFR&nbhy;prefix field of the Tunnel Identifier field (as
            defined in <xref target="PTA_x_PMSI"/>) MUST be set to the
            egress PE's (BFER's) BFR&nbhy;prefix.
            <vspace/>
            <vspace/>
            The BFR&nbhy;prefix need not be the same IP address that is carried
            in any other field of the Leaf A&nbhy;D route.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        When an ingress PE receives such a Leaf A&nbhy;D route, it learns
        the BFR&nbhy;prefix of the egress PE from the PTA.  The ingress PE does
        not make any use the value of the PTA's MPLS label field.
      </t>
      <t>
        Failure to properly construct the PTA cannot always be detected by
        the protocol and will cause improper delivery of the data packets.
      </t>
      

    </section>
    
    <section title="Data Plane" anchor="dataplane">
      <t>
        The MVPN application plays the role of the "multicast flow overlay"
        as described in <xref target="RFC8279"/>.
      </t>
      <section title="Encapsulation and Transmission" anchor="dp_bfir">
        <t>
          To transmit an MVPN data packet, an ingress PE follows the rules
          of <xref target="RFC6625"/> to find the x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route
          that is a "match for transmission" for that packet.  (In applying
          the rules of <xref target="RFC6625"/>, any S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D
          route with a PTA specifying "no tunnel information" is ignored.)
          If the matching route has a PTA specifying BIER, the
          (upstream-assigned) MPLS label from that PTA is pushed on the
          packet's label stack.  Then the packet is encapsulated in a BIER
          header.  That is, the ingress PE functions as a BFIR. The BIER
          sub&nbhy;domain used for transmitting the packet is specified in the
          PTA of the above-mentioned x&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route.
        </t>
        <t>
          In order to create the proper BIER header for a given packet, the
          BFIR must know all the BFERs that need to receive that packet.  It
          determines this by finding all the Leaf A&nbhy;D routes that
          correspond to the S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route that is the packet's
          match for transmission.  There are two different cases to
          consider:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              The S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route that is the match for
              transmission carries a PTA that has the LIR flag set but does
              not have the LIR&nbhy;pF flag set.
              <vspace/>
              <vspace/>
              In this case, the corresponding Leaf A&nbhy;D routes are those
              whose "route key" field is identical to the NLRI of the
              S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route.
            </t>
            <t>
              The S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route that is the match for
              transmission carries a PTA that has the LIR&nbhy;pF flag.
              <vspace/>
              <vspace/>
              In this case, the corresponding Leaf A&nbhy;D routes are those
              whose "route key" field is derived from the NLRI of the
              S&nbhy;PMSI A&nbhy;D route according to the procedures
              described in Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC8534"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Leaf A&nbhy;D route from a given BFER will contain a PTA that
          specifies the BFER's BFR&nbhy;prefix.  With this information, the
          BFIR can construct the BIER BitString.
        </t>
        <t>
          However, if the PTA of the Leaf A&nbhy;D route from a given BFER
          specifies a sub&nbhy;domain other than the one being used for
          transmitting the packet, the bit for that BFER cannot be
          determined and that BFER will not receive the packet.
        </t>
        <t>
          The BIER-encapsulated packet is then forwarded, according to the
          procedures described in <xref target="RFC8279"/> and <xref
          target="RFC8296"/>. (See especially Section 3, "Imposing and
          Processing the BIER Encapsulation" in <xref
          target="RFC8296"/>.)
        </t>
      </section> 
      <section title="Disposition" anchor="dp_disposition">
        <t>
          When a BFER receives an MVPN multicast data packet that has been
          BIER&nbhy;encapsulated, the BIER layer passes the following information
          to the multicast flow overlay:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The sub&nbhy;domain&nbhy;id and the BFIR&nbhy;id from the BIER
              header. (As the sub&nbhy;domain&nbhy;id is inferred from the
              BIFT&nbhy;id field of the BIER header, an implementation might
              choose to pass the BIFT&nbhy;id rather than the
              sub&nbhy;domain&nbhy;id; this is an implementation matter.)
            </t>
            <t>
              The "payload", which is an MPLS packet whose top label is an
              upstream-assigned label.  In the data plane, the BFIR&nbhy;id
              and the sub&nbhy;domain&nbhy;id provide the context in which
              the upstream-assigned label is interpreted.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          By looking up the upstream-assigned label in the appropriate
          context, the multicast flow overlay determines whether the BFER is
          an egress PE for the packet.
        </t>
        <t>
          Note that if segmented P&nbhy;tunnels are in use, a BFER might be
          a P&nbhy;tunnel segmentation border router rather than an egress
          PE, or a BFER might be both an egress PE and a P&nbhy;tunnel
          segmentation border router.  Depending upon the role of the BFER
          for the given packet, it may need to follow the procedures of <xref
          target="dp_egress_bfer"/>, the procedures of <xref
          target="dp_transit_bfer"/>, or both.
        </t>
        
        <section title="At a BFER That is an Egress PE"
                 anchor="dp_egress_bfer">
          <t>
            From looking up the packet's upstream-assigned label in the
            context of the packet's BFIR&nbhy;prefix, the egress PE determines
            the egress VRF for the packet.  From the IP header of the
            payload, the multicast states of the VRF, the upstream-assigned
            label, and the BFR&nbhy;prefix, the egress PE can determine whether
            the packet needs to be forwarded out one or more VRF interfaces.
          </t>
        </section> 
        <section title="At a BFER That is a P&nbhy;tunnel Segmentation Boundary"
                 anchor="dp_transit_bfer">
          <t>
            When segmented P&nbhy;tunnels are being used, a BFER that
            receives a BIER-encapsulated MVPN multicast data packet may need
            to be forwarded on its next P&nbhy;tunnel segment.  The choice
            of the next P&nbhy;tunnel segment for the packet depends upon
            the C&nbhy;flow to which the packet belongs.  As long as the
            BFIR has assigned the MPLS label according to the constraints
            specified in <xref target="mpls_label"/>, the BFIR will have
            assigned distinct upstream-assigned MPLS labels to distinct
            C&nbhy;flows.  The BFER can thus select the proper "next
            P&nbhy;tunnel segment" for a given packet simply by looking up
            the upstream-assigned label that immediately follows the BIER
            header.
          </t>
        </section> 
      </section> 
    </section>


      <section title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>
          IANA has assigned the codepoint 0x0B to BIER in the "P&nbhy;Multicast
          Service Interface Tunnel (PMSI Tunnel) Tunnel Types" registry.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
          The procedures of this document do not, in themselves, provide
          privacy, integrity, or authentication for the control plane or the
          data plane. For a discussion of the security considerations
          regarding the use of BIER, please see <xref target="RFC8279"/> and
          <xref target="RFC8296"/>. Security considerations regarding VPN
          technology based on <xref target="RFC4364"/>, <xref
          target="RFC6513"/>, and <xref target="RFC6514"/> can be found in
          those RFCs.


        </t>
      </section>

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

  </middle>


  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC4364;
      &RFC5331;
      &RFC6513;
      &RFC6514;
      &RFC6625;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC8279;
      &RFC8296;
      &RFC8534;
      
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC7524;
      &RFC7900;
    </references>



    <section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
        <t>
          The authors wish to thank Jeffrey Zhang for his ideas and
          contributions to this work.  We also thank Stig Venaas for his
          review and comments.
        </t>
      </section>

<section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
<t><figure align="left"><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
IJsbrand Wijnands
Cisco Systems, Inc.
De Kleetlaan 6a
Diegem  1831
Belgium

Email: ice@cisco.com
]]></artwork></figure>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
