<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
"http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2475 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2475.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3260 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3260.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<rfc category="std" number="8436" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="2474" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA Registration Procedures for DSCP Pool 3">Update to IANA Registration Procedures for Pool 3 Values
in the Differentiated Services Field Codepoints (DSCP) Registry</title>

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G." surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Engineering</street>

          <street>Fraser Noble Building</street>

          <city>Aberdeen</city>

          <code>AB24 3UE</code>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>

        <uri>http://www.erg.abdn.ac.uk/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="August" year="2018" />

    <area>Transport Area</area>

    <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Diffserv</keyword>

    <keyword>DSCP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Differentiated Services (Diffserv) architecture specifies use of
      the DS field in the IPv4 and IPv6 packet headers to carry one of 64 distinct differentiated services field codepoint
      (DSCP) values. The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) maintains
      a registry of assigned DSCP values.</t>

      <t>This update to RFC 2474 changes the IANA registration policy for Pool 3
      of the registry (i.e., DSCP values of the form xxxx01) to Standards
      Action, i.e., values are assigned through a Standards Track or Best
      Current Practice RFC. The update also removes permission for
      experimental and local use of the codepoints that form Pool 3 of the
      DSCP registry; Pool 2 Codepoints (i.e., DSCP values of the form xxxx11)
      remain available for these purposes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Differentiated Services (Diffserv) <xref target="RFC2475"></xref>
      architecture (updated by <xref target="RFC3260"></xref>) provides
      scalable service differentiation in the Internet. Diffserv uses the six
      most significant bits of the former IPv4 Type of Service (TOS) octet or
      the former IPv6 Traffic Class octet to convey the field, which is used
      to carry the DSCP. This DSCP value is used to
      select a Diffserv per-hop behavior (PHB).</t>

      <t>The six-bit field is capable of conveying 64 distinct codepoints, and
      this codepoint space has been divided into three pools for the purpose
      of codepoint assignment and management (as shown in <xref target="FieldFormat" />). Pool 1
      comprises 32 codepoints <xref target="RFC2474"></xref>. These are
      assigned by Standards Action, as defined in <xref
      target="RFC8126"></xref>. Pool 2 comprises a pool of 16 codepoints
      reserved for Experimental or Local Use (EXP/LU) as defined in <xref
      target="RFC2474"></xref>.  Pool 3 comprises 16 codepoints, which were
      originally specified as "initially available for experimental or local use, but
      which should be preferentially utilized for standardized assignments if
      Pool 1 is ever exhausted" by <xref target="RFC2474"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="FieldFormat" title="Format of the Field for Codepoints Allocated in the
	Three IANA Pools (Where &quot;x&quot; Refers to Either &quot;0&quot; or &quot;1&quot;)">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
               +------+-----------------+
               | Pool | Codepoint Space |
               +------+-----------------+
               |  1   |      xxxxx0     |
               +------+-----------------+
               |  2   |      xxxx11     |
               +------+-----------------+
               |  3   |      xxxx01     |
               +------+-----------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>At the time of writing this document, 22 of the 32 Pool 1 codepoints
      have been assigned.</t>

      <t>Although Pool 1 has not yet been completely exhausted, there is a
      need to assign codepoints for particular PHBs that are unable to use any
      of the unassigned values in Pool 1. This document changes the IANA
      registration policy of Pool 3 to assignment by Standards Action.
      (Section 4.9 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref> defines this as
      "assigned only through Standards Track or Best Current Practice RFCs in
      the IETF Stream".)</t>

      <t>An example is the need to assign a suitable recommended default
   codepoint for the Lower Effort (LE) PHB <xref target="LE-PHB"></xref>. The LE PHB is designed to
      protect best-effort (BE) traffic (packets forwarded with the default
      PHB) from LE traffic in congestion situations (when resources
      become scarce, best-effort traffic has precedence over LE traffic and is
      allowed to preempt it). In deployed networks, bleaching
      (i.e. intentionally setting to zero) of the IP Precedence field
      continues to be used. (Setting the IP Precedence field to zero disables any class-based
      flow management by routers configured with TOS-based packet processing.)
      This causes the first three bits of the former TOS byte (now the upper
      part of the DSCP field) to become zero. Therefore, there is a need to
      avoid this remapping of the DSCP for the LE PHB by assigning a codepoint
      that already has a zero value in the first three bits <xref
      target="LE-PHB"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Furthermore, if the LE PHB were to have been assigned one of the
      currently unused Pool 1 codepoints with a zero value in the first three
      bits, any bleaching of the IP Precedence field would result in other
      (higher assurance) traffic being also remapped to the assigned DSCP.
      This remapping could then cause Diffserv-marked traffic to receive an
      unintentional LE treatment for the remainder of the Internet path. Therefore, it is
      important to avoid the resulting priority inversion. The
      absence of unassigned codepoints in Pool 1 that exhibit these important
      properties motivates assigning a Pool 3 codepoint as the default that is
      recommended for use with this PHB.</t>

      <t>To allow the IETF to utilize Pool 3 codepoints, this document
      requests IANA to manage Pool 3 assignments for DSCP values in Pool 3
      via the Standards Action policy <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
      <t>This document assumes familiarity with the terminology used in <xref
      target="RFC2475"></xref> updated by <xref target="RFC3260"></xref>.</t>
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="The Updates to RFC 2474">
      <t>This document updates Section 6 of <xref target="RFC2474"></xref> in
      the following ways.</t>

      <t>It updates the following text concerning the assignment policy:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="OLD:">which are initially available for experimental or
          local use, but which should be preferentially utilized for
          standardized assignments if Pool 1 is ever exhausted.</t>

          <t hangText="NEW:">which are utilized for standardized assignments
          (replacing the previous availability for experimental or local
          use).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>It removes the footnote in RFC 2474 relating to Pool 3:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="DELETE:">"(*) may be utilized for future Standards
          Action allocations as necessary"</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>

      <t>The new registry assignment policy is shown in <xref target="Policy" />.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Policy" title="Updated Assignment Policy for the DSCP Registry">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    Pool  Codepoint Space  Assignment Policy 
    ----  --------------- ------------------
     1         xxxxx0      Standards Action
     2         xxxx11      EXP/LU            
     3         xxxx01      Standards Action
              
     Note for Pool 2: "Reserved for Experimental or Local Use"
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="seccons" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations for the use of DSCP values are described in
      the RFCs that define their usage. This document does not present new
      security considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has changed the use of Pool 3 in the "Differentiated Services Field Codepoints (DSCP)"
      registry and will manage this pool using Standards Action, as defined as
      Section 4.9 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>.</t>

      <t>IANA has made the following changes to the
      "Differentiated Services Field Codepoints (DSCP)" registry, made available
      at <xref target="Registry"></xref>.</t>

      <t>IANA has referenced RFC 2474 and Section 4 of RFC 3260 for
      the overall format of this registry.</t>

      <t>IANA has referenced RFC 2474 and Section 4 of RFC 3260 for
      Pool 1.</t>

   

      <t>This document does not modify the IANA registry text for Pool 2. This
      pool continues to preserve the note shown in <xref target="Policy" />.</t>

      <t>The previous registry text for Pool 3:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>3 xxxx01 Experimental or local use may be utilized for future
          Standards Action allocations as necessary.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>is replaced with the following registry text:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>3 xxxx01 Standards Action.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>To manage codepoints in Pool 3, IANA has created and will
      maintain the "DSCP Pool 3 Codepoints" subregistry. Pool 3 of the registry has
      been created initially empty, with a format identical to that used for
      "DSCP Pool 1 Codepoints".</t>

      <t>IANA has referenced RFC 2474, Section 4 of RFC 3260, and the
      current document for Pool 3.</t>


      <t>The registration procedure for use of Pool 3 is Standards Action, as
      defined as Section 4.9 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>. IANA is
      expected to normally make assignments from Pool 1, until this Pool is
      exhausted, but it MAY make assignments from Pool 3 when the format of the
      codepoint has properties that are needed for a specific PHB. The
      required characteristics for choosing a requested DSCP value MUST be
      explained in the IANA Considerations section of the document that requests any
      assignment from Pool 3.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC8174;

      &RFC2474;

      &RFC3260;

      &RFC8126;

      <reference anchor="Registry"
		 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/dscp-registry/">
        <front>
          <title>Differentiated Services Field Codepoints (DSCP)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!-- draft-ietf-tsvwg-le-phb-05 exists  -->
<reference anchor='LE-PHB'>
<front>
<title>A Lower Effort Per-Hop Behavior (LE PHB)</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Bless' fullname='Roland Bless'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='2' year='2018' />


</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-tsvwg-le-phb-05' />
</reference>


      &RFC2475;
    </references>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>Godred Fairhurst received funding from the European Union's Horizon 2020
      research and innovation program 2014-2018 under grant agreement No.
      644334 (NEAT).</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
