<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3963 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3963.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5094 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5094.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5213 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5844 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5844.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5845 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5845.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6088 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6088.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6089 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6089.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6275 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6275.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7148 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7148.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2473 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2473.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4213 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4908 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4908.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>
<rfc number="8278" consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF" category="std">
        <?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="o*+-"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
	<front>
	<title abbrev="MAG Multipath Binding Options">Mobile Access Gateway
	(MAG) Multipath Options</title>

	<author fullname="Pierrick Seite" initials="P." surname="Seite">
	<organization>Orange</organization>
	<address><postal><street>4, rue du Clos Courtel, BP 91226</street>
	<street>Cesson-Sevigne  35512</street>
	<street>France</street>
	</postal>
	<email>pierrick.seite@orange.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Alper Yegin" initials="A." surname="Yegin">
	<organization>Actility</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Turkey</street>
	</postal>
	<email>alper.yegin@actility.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Sri Gundavelli" initials="S." surname="Gundavelli">
	<organization>Cisco</organization>
	<address><postal><street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
	<street>San Jose, CA  95134</street>
	<street>United States of America</street>
	</postal>
	<email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>


  
 <date month="January" year="2018"/>
	<workgroup>Distributed Mobility Management Working Group</workgroup>

	<abstract><t>
   This specification defines extensions to the Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6)
   protocol that allow a mobile access gateway (MAG) to register more than
   one proxy care-of address (pCoA) with the local mobility anchor (LMA) and to
   simultaneously establish multiple IP tunnels with the LMA.  This capability allows the MAG to utilize
   all the available access networks to route the mobile node's IP
   traffic. This document defines the following two new mobility header
   options: the MAG Multipath Binding option and the MAG Identifier option.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	<section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
   Multihoming support on IP hosts can greatly improve the user
   experience.  With the simultaneous use of multiple access networks,
   multihoming brings better network connectivity, reliability, and
   improved quality of communication.  The following are some of the goals
   and benefits of multihoming support:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>Redundancy/Fault-Recovery</t>

	<t>Load balancing</t>

	<t>Load sharing</t>

	<t>Preference settings</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   According to <xref target="RFC4908"/>, users of small-scale networks can
   benefit from a mobile and fixed multihomed architecture using mobile IP
   <xref target="RFC6275"/> and Network Mobility (NEMO) <xref target="RFC3963"/>. 
 </t>
 
 
 <t>
   The motivation for this work is to extend the PMIPv6 protocol
   with multihoming extensions <xref target="RFC4908"/> for realizing the following
   capabilities:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>Using GRE as mobile tunneling, possibly with its key extension
      <xref target="RFC5845"/>.</t>

	<t>Using UDP encapsulation <xref target="RFC5844"/> in order to support NAT
      traversal in an IPv4 networking environment.</t>

	<t>Using the prefix delegation mechanism <xref target="RFC7148"/>.</t>

	<t>Using the Vendor Specific Mobility Option <xref target="RFC5094"/>, for example,
      to allow the MAG and LMA to exchange information (e.g., WAN
      interface QoS metrics), which allows the appropriate traffic-steering decisions to be made.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   PMIPv6 relies on two mobility entities: the
   MAG, which acts as the default gateway for
   the end node (either a mobile or a fixed node) attached to the MAG's access links, and the
   LMA, which acts as the topological anchor point.  IP tunnel is created with
   any one of the supported encapsulation mode between the MAG and the LMA. 

   Then, the MAG and LMA
   distribute the end node's traffic over these tunnels.  All PMIPv6 operations
   are performed on behalf of the end node and its correspondent node. Thus,
   it makes PMIPv6 well adapted to multihomed architecture as
   considered in <xref target="RFC4908"/>.  Taking the LTE and WLAN networking
   environments as examples, the PMIPv6-based multihomed architecture
   is depicted in <xref target="Fig1"/>. In this example,
   IP flows, Flow-1 and Flow-3 are routed over Tunnel-1 and Flow-2 is routed
   over Tunnel-2. However, IP traffic belonging to Flow-4 is distributed on both
   Tunnel-1 and Tunnel-2 paths.
   </t>

	<figure title="Multihomed MAG Using Proxy Mobile IPv6" anchor="Fig1"><artwork><![CDATA[
  Flow-1
   |
   |Flow-2              _----_
   | |         CoA-1  _(      )_   Tunnel-1  Flow-1
   | |    .---=======(   LTE    )========\   Flow-3
   | |    |           (_      _)          \  Flow-4
   | |    |             '----'             \
   | | +=====+                              \  +=====+    _----_
   | '-|     |                               \ |     |  _(      )_
   '---| MAG |                                 | LMA |-( Internet )--
   .---|     |                                 |     |  (_      _)
   | .-|     |                               / |     |    '----'
   | | +=====+                              /  +=====+
   | |    |             _----_             /
   | |    |    CoA-2  _(      )_ Tunnel-2 /
   | |    .---=======(   WLAN  )========/    Flow-2
   | |                (_     _)              Flow-4
   | |                  '----'
   |Flow-3
   |
  Flow0-4
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   The current version of PMIPv6 does not allow a MAG to
   register more than one pCoA to the LMA.  In other
   words, only one MAG/LMA link, i.e., IP-in-IP tunnel, can be used at
   the same time.  This document overcomes this limitation by defining
   the multiple pCoAs extension for PMIPv6.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Conventions and Terminology" anchor="section-2">

<section title="Conventions" anchor="section-2.1">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
</section>
     	<section title="Terminology" anchor="section-2.2"><t>
   All mobility-related terms used in this document are to be
   interpreted as defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/>, <xref target="RFC5844"/>, and <xref target="RFC7148"/>.
   Additionally, this document uses the following term:</t>

	<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="3"><t hangText="IP-in-IP">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	IP-within-IP encapsulation <xref target="RFC2473"/> <xref target="RFC4213"/>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

      </section>
	<section title="Overview" anchor="section-3"><section title="Example Call Flow" anchor="section-3.1"><t>
   <xref target="Fig2"/> is the call flow detailing multi-access support with PMIPv6.
   The MAG in this example scenario is equipped with both WLAN and LTE
   interfaces and is also configured with the multihoming functionality.
   The steps of the call flow are as follows:</t>

	<t>
   Steps (1) and (2): The MAG attaches to both WLAN and LTE networks. Then,
   the MAG obtains two different pCoAs, respectfully.</t>

	<t>

   Step (3): The MAG sends, over the LTE access, a Proxy Binding Update
   (PBU) message with the new MAG Multipath Binding (MMB) and MAG
   Network Access Identifier (MAG-NAI) options to the LMA.  The request can be for a
   physical mobile node attached to the MAG or for a logical mobile
   node configured on the mobile access gateway.  A logical mobile node is a logical
   representation of a mobile node in the form of a configuration that is always enabled 
   on the MAG. The mobility session that is created (i.e., create a Binding Cache Entry (BCE)) on the
   LMA will be marked with multipath support.</t>

	<t>
   Step (4): The LMA sends back a Proxy Binding Acknowledgement (PBA)
   including the Home Network Prefix (HNP) and other session parameters allocated for that
   mobility session.</t>

<t>Step (5): IP tunnel is created between the MAG and the LMA over LTE access
with any one of the supported encapsulation modes.</t>

	<t>
   Steps (6) to (8): The MAG repeats steps (3) to (5) on the WLAN access.
   The MAG includes the HNP, received on step (4) in the PBU.  The LMA
   updates its binding cache by creating a new mobility session for this
   MAG.</t>

	<t>
   Steps (9) and (10): The IP hosts MN_1 and MN_2 are assigned IP
   addresses from the mobile network prefix delegated to the MAG by the LMA.</t>

	<figure title="Functional Separation of the Control and User Planes" anchor="Fig2"><artwork><![CDATA[
+=====+ +=====+     +=====+      +=====+      +=====+         +=====+
| MN_1| | MN_2|     | MAG |      | WLAN|      | LTE |         | LMA |
+=====+ +=====+     +=====+      +=====+      +=====+         +=====+
   |       |           |            |            |               |
   |       |           |            |            |               |
   |       |           | (1) ATTACH |            |               |
   |       |           | <--------> |            |               |
   |       |           | (2) ATTACH              |               |
   |       |           | <---------------------->|               |
   |       |           | (3) PBU (MAG-NAI, MMB, ...)             |
   |       |           | ------------------------*-------------->|
   |       |           |                                         |
   |       |           |                                   Accept PBU
   |       |           |                               (allocate HNP,
   |       |           |                                  create BCE)
   |       |           | (4) PBA (MMB, ...)                      |
   |       |           | <-----------------------*---------------|
   |       |           | (5) TUNNEL INTERFACE CREATION over LTE  |
   |       |           |-============== TUNNEL ==*==============-|
   |       |           |                                         |
   |       |           | (6) PBU (MAG-NAI, MMB, ...)             |
   |       |           | -----------*--------------------------->|
   |       |           |                                         |
   |       |           |                                   Accept PBU
   |       |           |                                 (update BCE)
   |       |           | (7) PBA (MMB, ...)                      |
   |       |           | <----------*--------------------------- |
   |       |           | (8) TUNNEL INTERFACE CREATION over WLAN |
   |       |           |-===========*== TUNNEL =================-|
   |   (9) ATTACH      |                                         |
   | <---------------> |                                         |
   |       |(10) ATTACH|                                         |
   |       |<--------> |                                         |
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	</section>

	<section title="Traffic Distribution Schemes" anchor="section-3.2"><t>

   When the MAG has registered a multipath binding with the LMA, there
   will be multiple established overlay tunnels between them.  The MAG
   and the LMA can use any one, or more, of the available tunnel paths
   for routing the mobile node's IP traffic.  This specification does
   not recommend or define any specific traffic distribution scheme. 
   However, it identifies two well-known approaches that implementations
   can potentially use.  These approaches are per-flow and per-packet
   traffic distribution schemes.</t>

	<t>
   Per-Flow Traffic Distribution:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>In this approach, the MAG and the LMA associate each of the IP
      flows (upstream and downstream) with a specific tunnel path.  The
      packets in a given IP flow are always routed on the same overlay
      tunnel path; they are never split and routed concurrently on more
      than one tunnel path.  It is possible for a given flow to be moved
      from one tunnel path to another, but the flow is never split.  The
      decision to bind a given IP flow to a specific tunnel path is
      based on the traffic distribution policy.  This traffic distribution
      policy is either statically configured on both the MAG and the
      LMA or dynamically negotiated over PMIPv6 signaling.
      The Flow Binding extension <xref target="RFC6089"/> and Traffic Selectors for
      Flow Bindings <xref target="RFC6088"/> define the mechanism and the semantics
      for exchanging the traffic policy between two tunnel peers; the
      same mechanism and the mobility options are used here.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   Per-Packet Traffic Distribution:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>In this approach, packets belonging to a given IP flow will be split
      and routed across more than one tunnel path.  The exact approach
      for traffic distribution or the distribution weights is outside
      the scope of this specification.  In a very simplistic approach,
      assuming that the established tunnel paths have symmetric
      characteristics, the packets can be equally distributed on all the
      available tunnel paths.  In a different scenario, when the links
      have different speeds, the chosen approach can be based on
      weighted distribution (e.g., n:m ratio).  However, in any of these
      chosen approaches, implementations have to be sensitive to issues
      related to asymmetric link characteristics and the resulting
      issues such as reordering, buffering, and the impact on application performance.  Care must be taken to ensure that there is no
      negative impact on the application performance due to the use of
      this approach.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Protocol Extensions" anchor="section-4">
<section title="MAG Multipath Binding Option" anchor="section-4.1"><t>
   The MAG Multipath Binding option is a new mobility header option
   defined for use with PBU and PBA messages exchanged between the LMA
   and the MAG.</t>

	<t>
   This mobility header option is used for requesting multipath support.
   It indicates that the MAG is requesting that the LMA register the current CoA associated
   with the request as one of the many CoAs through which the
   MAG can be reached.  It is also used for carrying the
   information related to the access network associated with the CoA.</t>

	<t>
   The MAG Multipath Binding option does not have any alignment requirement.  Its
   format is as shown in <xref target="Fig3"/>:</t>

	<figure title="MAG Multipath Binding Option" anchor="Fig3"><artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |    If-ATT     |    If-Label   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Binding ID   |B|O|             Reserved                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="3"><t hangText="Type">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Type: MAG Multipath Binding (63)
	</t>

	<t hangText="Length">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	8-bit unsigned integer indicating the length of the option in
      octets, excluding the Type and Length fields.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Interface Access-Technology Type (If-ATT)">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This 8-bit field identifies the Access-Technology type of the
      interface through which the mobile node is connected.  The
      permitted values for this are from the Access Technology Type
      registry <eref
      target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters/" /> defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/>.

	</t>

	<t hangText="Interface Label (If-Label)">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This 8-bit unsigned integer represents the interface label.
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	The interface label is an identifier configured on the WAN
      interface of the MAG.  All the WAN interfaces of the MAG that are
      used for sending PBU messages are configured with a label.  The
      labels merely identify the type of WAN interface and are primarily
      used in application-routing policies.  For example, a Wi-Fi
      interface can be configured with a label "9" and an LTE interface
      with a label "11".  Furthermore, the same label may be configured
      on two WAN interfaces of similar characteristics (e.g., two Ethernet
      interfaces with the same label).
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Interface labels are signaled from the MAG to the LMA in the PBU
      messages and both the LMA and MAG will be able to mark each of the
      dynamically created Binding/Tunnel with the associated label.
      These labels are used in generating consistent application-routing
      rules on the both the LMA and the MAG.  For example, there can be
      a policy requiring HTTP packets to be routed over an interface that
      has the interface label of "9", and if any of the interfaces with interface label "9" are not available,
      the traffic needs to be routed over the interface with the interface label "11".  The MAG
      and the LMA will be able to apply this routing rule with the
      exchange of interface labels in PBU messages and by associating the
      application flows to tunnels with the matching interface labels.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Binding Identifier (BID)">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This 8-bit unsigned integer is used for identifying the binding.
      The permitted values are 1 through 254.  The values 0 and 255 are
      reserved.
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	The MAG identifies each of the mobile node's bindings with a unique
      identifier.  The MAG includes the identifier in the PBU message;
      when the PBU request is accepted by the LMA, the resulting
      binding is associated with this BID in the mobile node's Binding Cache entry.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Bulk Re-registration Flag (B)">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	If set to a value of (1), this flag notifies the LMA to consider this as
	a request to update the binding lifetime of all the mobile node's bindings upon
      accepting this specific request.  The (B) flag MUST NOT be set to a
      value of (1) if the value of the Registration Overwrite (O) flag is set to a value of (1).
	</t>

	<t hangText="Registration Overwrite (O)">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This flag, if set to a value of (1), notifies the LMA that upon accepting this request, it should replace all of
      the mobile node's existing bindings with this binding.  This flag
      MUST NOT be set to a value of (1) if the value of the Bulk Re-registration Flag (B) is set to a value of (1).  This flag MUST be
      set to a value of (0) in De-Registration requests.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Reserved">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This field is unused in this specification.  The value MUST be set
      to zero (0) by the sender and MUST be ignored by the receiver.
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="MAG Identifier Option" anchor="section-4.2"><t>
   The MAG Identifier option is a new mobility header option defined for
   use with PBU and PBA messages exchanged between the LMA and the MAG.  This mobility header option is used for conveying
   the MAG's identity.</t>

	<t>
   This option does not have any alignment requirements.</t>

	<figure title="MAG Identifier Option" anchor="ref-mag-identifier-option"><artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |  Subtype      |  Reserved     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Identifier ...                      ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="3"><t hangText="Type">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Type: MAG Identifier (64)
	</t>

	<t hangText="Length">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	8-bit unsigned integer indicating the length of the option in
      octets, excluding the Type and Length fields.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Subtype">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	One-byte unsigned integer used for identifying the type of the
      Identifier field.  Accepted values for this field are the
      registered type values from the "Mobile Node Identifier Option
      Subtypes" registry <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters/"/>.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Reserved">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This field is unused in this specification.  The value MUST be set
      to zero (0) by the sender and MUST be ignored by the receiver.
	</t>

	<t hangText="Identifier">
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	A variable-length identifier of the type indicated in the Subtype
      field.
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="New Status Code for Proxy Binding Acknowledgement" anchor="section-4.3"><t>
   This document defines the following new Status Code value for use in
   PBA messages.</t>

	<t>
   The LMA SHOULD use this error code when rejecting a PBU message from a MAG requesting a multipath binding.  The following
   is the potential reason for rejecting the request:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The LMA does not support multipath binding.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   CANNOT_SUPPORT_MULTIPATH_BINDING (Cannot Support Multipath Binding): 180</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Signaling Considerations" anchor="section-4.4"><t><list style="symbols"><t>The MAG, when requesting multipath support, MUST include the MAG
      Multipath Binding option (<xref target="section-4.1"/>) in each of the PBU messages
      that it sends through the different WAN interfaces.  The inclusion
      of this option serves as a hint that the MAG is requesting
      multipath support.  Furthermore, the MAG Identifier option MUST
      also be present in the PBU message.</t>

	<t>If the MAG is aware that the LMA supports the multipath binding option
      defined in this specification and if it chooses to use multiple
      paths, then it can send the PBU packets for each of the
      paths, either sequentially or concurrently.  However, if the MAG
      is not aware of the LMA capability, then it SHOULD first discover
      the LMA capability by sending PBU packets with multipath on only
      one path first.  This will ensure that the LMA will not be overwriting
      the binding of one path with the other path.</t>

	<t>If the LMA supports multipath capability as defined in this
      specification and if it enables the same for a mobile node's
      session per the MAG's request, then the LMA MUST include the
      Multipath Binding option (<xref target="section-4.1"/>) without the MAG-NAI option
      (<xref target="section-4.2"/>) in the corresponding PBA reply.</t>

	<t>If the LMA is a legacy LMA that does not support this
      specification, the LMA will skip the MAG Multipath Binding option
      (and MAG-NAI option) and process the rest of the message as
      specified in the base PMIPv6 specification (<xref target="RFC5213"/>).
      Furthermore, the LMA will not include the MAG Multipath Binding
      option (or the MAG-NAI option) in the PBA message.  The MAG, upon
      receiving the PBA message without the MAG Multipath Binding option,
      SHOULD disable multipath support for the mobile node.</t>

	<t>If the mobile node is not authorized for multipath support, then
      the LMA will reject the request by sending a PBA message with the
      Status field value set to CANNOT_SUPPORT_MULTIPATH_BINDING
      (<xref target="section-4.3"/>).  The LMA MUST echo the MAG Multipath Binding option
      (without the MAG-NAI option) in the PBA message.  The MAG, upon receiving
      this message, SHOULD disable multipath support for the mobile node.</t>


	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-5">

<t>This specification defines a new mobility option: the
      MAG Multipath Binding option.  The format of this option is
      described in <xref target="section-4.1"/>.  The type value 63 has been allocated for this mobility option from the "Mobility Options"
      registry at <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters"/>.</t>

	<t>This specification defines a new mobility option: the
      MAG Identifier option.  The format of this option is described in
      <xref target="section-4.2"/>.  The type value 64 has been allocated for this mobility option 
      from the "Mobility Options" registry at
      <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters"/>.</t>

	<t>This document defines a new status value:
      CANNOT_SUPPORT_MULTIPATH_BINDING (180) for use in PBA messages, as described in <xref target="section-4.3"/>.
      This value has been assigned from the "Status Codes" registry at
      <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters"/>.</t>



	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="section-6"><t>
   This specification allows a MAG to establish
   multiple PMIPv6 tunnels with an LMA by
   registering a care-of address for each of its connected access
   networks.  This essentially allows the mobile node's IP traffic to be
   routed through any of the tunnel paths based on the negotiated flow
   policy.  This new capability has no impact on the protocol security.
   Furthermore, this specification defines two new mobility header
   options: the MAG Multipath Binding option and the MAG Identifier option.
   These options are carried like any other mobility header option as
   specified in <xref target="RFC5213"/>.  Therefore, it inherits security guidelines
   from <xref target="RFC5213"/>.  Thus, this specification does not weaken the
   security of the PMIPv6 Protocol and does not introduce any
   new security vulnerabilities.</t>

	</section>


	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
	&RFC2119;
	&RFC3963;
	&RFC5094;
	&RFC5213;
	&RFC5844;
	&RFC5845;
	&RFC6088;
	&RFC6089;
	&RFC6275;
	&RFC7148;
        &RFC8174;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	&RFC2473;
	&RFC4213;
	&RFC4908;
	</references>
	<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="section-7" numbered="no"><t>
   The authors of this document would like to acknowledge the discussions
   and feedback on this topic from the members of the  Distributed Mobility
   Management Working Group. The authors would also like to thank Jouni Korhonen, Jong Hyouk Lee,
   Dirk Von-Hugo, Seil Jeon, Carlos Bernardos, Robert Sparks, Adam
   Roach, Kathleen Moriarty, Hilarie Orman, Ben Campbell, Warren Kumari, and Dhananjay Patki
   for their review feedback.  Special thanks to Mirja Kuehlewind for a
   very thorough review and suggesting many text improvements.</t>

	</section>

	</back>


	</rfc>
	
