<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3471 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3471.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3473 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3473.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5920 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5920.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6205.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" updates="3471, 3473, 6205" number="8359">


 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>


   <title abbrev="Network Assigned Upstream-Label">Network-Assigned Upstream Label
   </title>

 

   <author fullname="Xian Zhang" initials="X.Z" role="editor"
           surname="Zhang">
     <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

     <address>
       <email>zhang.xian@huawei.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram" initials="V.P.B" role="editor"
           surname="Beeram">
     <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

     <address>
       <email>vbeeram@juniper.net</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Igor Bryskin" initials="I.B"
           surname="Bryskin">
     <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

     <address>
       <email>igor.bryskin@huawei.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Daniele Ceccarelli" initials="D.C"
           surname="Ceccarelli">
     <organization>Ericsson</organization>

     <address>
       <email>daniele.ceccarelli@ericsson.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Oscar Gonzalez de Dios" initials="O.G.D"
           surname="Gonzalez de Dios">
     <organization>Telefonica</organization>

     <address>
       <email>ogondio@tid.es</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date month="March" year="2018" />


   <area>Routing</area>

   <workgroup>TEAS Working Group</workgroup>

   <keyword>template</keyword>


<keyword>example</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>This document discusses a Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching 
    (GMPLS) Resource reSerVation Protocol with Traffic Engineering 
    (RSVP-TE) mechanism that enables the network to assign an upstream 
    label for a bidirectional Label Switched Path (LSP).  This is useful in scenarios where a 
    given node does not have sufficient information to assign the 
    correct upstream label on its own and needs to rely on the 
    downstream node to pick an appropriate label. This document updates 
    RFCs 3471, 3473, and 6205 as it defines processing for a special label
    value in the UPSTREAM_LABEL object. </t>
   </abstract>


 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
    A functional description of the Generalized Multi-Protocol
    Label Switching (GMPLS) signaling extensions for setting up
    a bidirectional Label Switched Path (LSP) is provided in
    <xref target="RFC3471"/>. The GMPLS Resource
    reSerVation Protocol with Traffic Engineering (RSVP-TE) extensions 
    for setting up a bidirectional LSP are specified in <xref target="RFC3473"/>.
    The bidirectional LSP setup is indicated by the presence of an 
    UPSTREAM_LABEL object in the Path message.  As per the existing 
    setup procedure outlined for a bidirectional LSP, each upstream node 
    must allocate a valid upstream label on the outgoing interface 
    before sending the initial Path message downstream.  However, there 
    are certain scenarios (see <xref target="use_case"/>) where it is not desirable or possible for a 
    given node to pick the upstream label on its own.  This document 
    defines the protocol mechanism to be used in such scenarios.  This 
    mechanism enables a given node to offload the task of assigning the 
    upstream label for a given bidirectional LSP to nodes downstream 
    in the network. It is meant to be used only for bidirectional LSPs 
    that assign symmetric labels at each hop along the path of the LSP. 
    Bidirectional Lambda Switch Capable (LSC) LSPs use symmetric lambda
    labels (format specified in <xref target="RFC6205"/>) at each hop along 
    the path of the LSP. 
    </t>

    <t>
    As per the bidirectional LSP setup procedures specified in <xref
    target="RFC3471"/> and <xref target="RFC3473"/>, the
    UPSTREAM_LABEL object must indicate a label that is valid for
    forwarding.  This document updates that by allowing the
    UPSTREAM_LABEL object to indicate a special label that isn't valid
    for forwarding. As per the bidirectional LSC LSP setup procedures
    specified in <xref target="RFC6205"/>, the LABEL_SET object and
    the UPSTREAM_LABEL object must contain the same label value. This
    document updates that by allowing the UPSTREAM_LABEL object to
    carry a special label value that is different from the one used in
    the LABEL_SET object.
    </t>

   </section>

   <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
    capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
   </section>
     

   <section title="Unassigned Upstream Label">
    <t>This document defines a special label value -- "0xFFFFFFFF" (for
    a 4-octet label) -- to indicate an Unassigned Upstream Label.
    Similar "all-ones" patterns are expected to be used for labels of
    other sizes.
    </t>

     <figure align="center" anchor="figure_1" title="Unassigned UPSTREAM_LABEL - &quot;all-ones&quot; Pattern">
       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1|
   |                              ...                              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
           ]]></artwork>
     </figure>

    <t>
    The presence of this value in the UPSTREAM_LABEL object of a Path
    message indicates that the upstream node has not assigned an
    upstream label on its own and has requested the downstream node to
    provide a label that it can use in both the forward and reverse
    directions.  The presence of this value in the UPSTREAM_LABEL
    object of a Path message MUST also be interpreted by the receiving
    node as a request to mandate symmetric labels for the LSP.</t>
    <section title="Procedures">
    <t>The scope of the procedures is limited to the exchange and
    processing of messages between an upstream node and its immediate
    downstream node.  The Unassigned Upstream Label is used by an
    upstream node when it is not in a position to pick the upstream
    label on its own.  In such a scenario, the upstream node sends a
    Path message downstream with an Unassigned Upstream Label and
    requests the downstream node to provide a symmetric label.  If the
    upstream node desires to make the downstream node aware of its
    limitations with respect to label selection, it MUST specify a
    list of valid labels via the LABEL_SET object as specified in
    <xref target="RFC3473"/>.</t>

    <t>In response, the downstream node picks an appropriate symmetric 
    label and sends it via the LABEL object in the Resv message.  The 
    upstream node would then start using this symmetric label for both 
    directions of the LSP.  If the downstream node cannot pick the 
    symmetric label, it MUST issue a PathErr message with a "Routing 
    Problem/Unacceptable Label Value" indication. If the upstream node
    that signals an Unassigned Upstream Label receives a label with the
    "all-ones" pattern or any other unacceptable label in the LABEL
    object of the Resv message, it MUST issue a ResvErr message with
    a "Routing Problem/Unacceptable Label Value" indication. </t>

    <t>The upstream node will continue to signal the Unassigned Upstream 
    Label in the Path message even after it receives an appropriate 
    symmetric label in the Resv message.  This is done to make sure that 
    the downstream node would pick a different symmetric label if and 
    when it needs to change the label at a later time. If the
    upstream node receives an unacceptable changed label, then it MUST
    issue a ResvErr message with a "Routing Problem/Unacceptable Label Value"
    indication. </t>
 
     <figure align="center" anchor="figure_2" title="Signaling Sequence">
       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

               +----------+                    +------------+ 
            ---| Upstream |--------------------| Downstream |---
               +----------+                    +------------+ 
                                           
                           Path 
                            Upstream Label (Unassigned) 
                            Label-Set (L1, L2 ... Ln)         
                           -------------------> 
                                           
                           Resv 
                            Label (Assigned - L2) 
                           <------------------- 
           ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
                                           
    </section>
    <section title="Backwards Compatibility">
    <t>If the downstream node is running an implementation that doesn't
    support the semantics of an Unassigned UPSTREAM LABEL, it will
    either (a) reject the special label value and generate an error as
    specified in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC3473"/> 
    or (b) accept it and treat it as a valid label. </t>
    <t>If the behavior that is exhibited is (a), then there are
    no backwards compatibility concerns.  If the behavior that is exhibited
    is (b), then the downstream node will send a label with the "all-ones"
    pattern in the LABEL object of the Resv message. In response, the
    upstream node will issue a ResvErr message with a "Routing Problem/Unacceptable Label Value"
    indication.
    </t> 
    </section>
   </section>

   <section title="Use-Case: Wavelength Setup for IP over Optical Networks" anchor="use_case">
    <t>Consider the network topology depicted in <xref target="figure_3"/>.  Nodes A and B 
    are client IP routers that are connected to an optical Wavelength Division Multiplexing (WDM)
    transport network.  F and I represent WDM nodes.  The transponder sits on 
    the router and is directly connected to the add-drop port on a WDM 
    node.</t> 
      
    <t>The optical signal originating on "Router A" is tuned to a 
    particular wavelength.  On "WDM-Node F", it gets multiplexed with 
    optical signals at other wavelengths.  Depending on the 
    implementation of this multiplexing function, it may not be 
    acceptable to have the router send the signal into the optical network 
    unless it is at the appropriate wavelength.  In other words, having 
    the router send signals with a wrong wavelength may adversely impact 
    existing optical trails.  If the clients do not have full visibility 
    into the optical network, they are not in a position to pick the 
    correct wavelength in advance.</t>  

    <t>The rest of this section examines how the protocol mechanism proposed
    in this document allows the optical network to select and communicate
    the correct wavelength to its clients.</t> 

    <section title="Initial Setup">

     <figure align="center" anchor="figure_3" title="Initial Setup Sequence">
       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

      +---+                 /-\             /-\                 +---+ 
      | A |----------------( F ) ~~~~~~~~~ ( I )----------------| B | 
      +---+                 \-/             \-/                 +---+ 
          
         Path  
           Upstream Label (Unassigned/0xFFFFFFFF) 
         ---------------------> 
                               -- ~~ -- ~~ --> 
                                               Path   
                                               --------------------> 
                                               Resv 
                                               <--------------------
                               <-- ~~ -- ~~ -- 
         Resv  
           Label (Assigned) 
         <--------------------- 

           ]]></artwork>

     </figure>
            
         
    <t>Steps:
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>"Router A" does not have enough information to pick an 
         appropriate client wavelength.  It sends a Path message 
         downstream requesting the network to assign an appropriate 
         symmetric label for its use.  Since the client wavelength is 
         unknown, the laser is off at the ingress client.</t> 
       <t>The downstream node (Node F) receives the Path message, chooses 
         the appropriate wavelength values, and forwards them in 
         appropriate label fields to the egress client ("Router B").</t> 
       <t>"Router B" receives the Path message, turns the laser ON and 
         tunes it to the appropriate wavelength (received in the 
         UPSTREAM_LABEL/LABEL_SET of the Path) and sends a Resv 
         message upstream.</t>  
       <t>The Resv message received by the ingress client carries a valid 
         symmetric label in the LABEL object.  "Router A" turns on the 
         laser and tunes it to the wavelength specified in the network 
         assigned symmetric LABEL. </t> 
       </list></t>
      
    <t>For cases where the egress-node relies on RSVP signaling to 
    determine exactly when to start using the LSP, implementations
    may choose to integrate the above sequence with any of the existing
    graceful setup procedures:
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>"ResvConf" setup procedure (<xref target="RFC2205"/>)</t>
      <t>Two-step "ADMIN STATUS" based setup procedure ("A" bit set in the 
        first step; "A" bit cleared when the LSP is ready for use) (<xref target="RFC3473"/>)</t> 
      </list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Wavelength Change">
    <t>After the LSP is set up, the network may decide to change the 
    wavelength for the given LSP.  This could be for a variety of 
    reasons including policy reasons, restoration within the core, preemption, 
    etc.</t> 

    <t>In such a scenario, if the ingress client receives a changed label 
    via the LABEL object in a modified Resv message, it retunes the laser at 
    the ingress to the new wavelength.  Similarly, if the egress client 
    receives a changed label via UPSTREAM_LABEL/LABEL_SET in a modified Path 
    message, it retunes the laser at the egress to the new 
    wavelength.</t>
    </section>
   </section>


   <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
    IANA maintains the "Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Signaling 
    Parameters" registry.  IANA has added a new subregistry titled "Special 
    Purpose Generalized Label Values". New values are assigned according to Standards
    Action <xref target="RFC8126"/>.

    <figure >
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Special Purpose Generalized Label Values

Pattern/    Label Name            Applicable        Reference
Value                             Objects
--------    ----------------      --------------    ----------
all-ones    Unassigned            UPSTREAM_LABEL    [RFC8359]
            Upstream Label

                ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
    </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>This document defines a special label value to be carried in the 
    UPSTREAM_LABEL object of a Path message.  This special label value 
    is used to enable the function of requesting network assignment of 
    an upstream label.  The changes proposed in this document pertain to 
    the semantics of a specific field in an existing RSVP object and the 
    corresponding procedures.  Thus, there are no new security
    implications raised by this document and the security considerations 
    discussed by <xref target="RFC3473"/> still apply.</t> 

    <t>For a general discussion on MPLS and GMPLS related security issues, 
    see the MPLS/GMPLS security framework <xref target="RFC5920"/>.</t>
   </section>

 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>


   <references title="Normative References">

     &RFC2119;

     &RFC2205;

     &RFC3471;

     &RFC3473;

     &RFC6205;

     &RFC8174;

  

   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     

     &RFC5920;

         <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>

   </references>


      <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
    <t>The authors would like to thank Adrian Farrel and Chris Bowers for 
    their inputs. </t>
      </section>


        <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
     <t>
     <vspace blankLines="1" />

     John Drake
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Juniper Networks     
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Email: jdrake@juniper.net
     
     <vspace blankLines="1" />
     
     Gert Grammel
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Juniper Networks     
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Email: ggrammel@juniper.net
    
     <vspace blankLines="1" />
     
     Pawel Brzozowski
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     ADVA Optical Networking    
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Email: pbrzozowski@advaoptical.com

     <vspace blankLines="1" />
     
     Zafar Ali
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Cisco Systems, Inc.
     <vspace blankLines="0" />
     Email: zali@cisco.com
 
     </t>


   </section>
 </back>

</rfc>
