<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" number="8258">

  <front>



    <title abbrev="Generalized SCSI">
      Generalized SCSI: A Generic Structure for Interface Switching Capability
      Descriptor (ISCD) Switching Capability Specific Information (SCSI)
    </title>

    <author initials="D." surname="Ceccarelli" fullname="Daniele Ceccarelli">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Torshamnsgatan 21</street>
          <code></code>
          <city>Kista - Stockholm</city>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniele.ceccarelli@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger'>
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
          <address>                          <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
           </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2017" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>TEAS Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>OSPF-TE</keyword>
    <keyword>GMPLS</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines a generic information structure for
        information carried in routing protocol Interface Switching
        Capability Descriptor (ISCD) Switching Capability Specific
        Information (SCSI) fields.  This "Generalized SCSI" can be used
        with routing protocols that define GMPLS ISCDs and any specific
        technology.  This document does not modify any existing
        technology-specific formats and is defined for use in
        conjunction with new GMPLS Switching Capability types.
        The context for this document is Generalized MPLS, and the
        reader is expected to be familiar with the GMPLS architecture
        and associated protocol standards.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec-intro">
      <t>
        The context for this document is Generalized MPLS, and the
        reader is expected to be familiar with the GMPLS architecture,
        associated terminology, and protocol standards: notably, but
        not limited to, <xref target="RFC3945"/>, <xref
        target="RFC4202"/>, <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5307"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Interface Switching Capability Descriptor (ISCD) <xref
        target="RFC4202"/> allows routing protocols such as OSPF and
        ISIS to carry technology-specific information in the 
        Switching Capability-specific information field, see
        <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref target="RFC5307"/>.  The
        format of an SCSI field is dictated by the specific technology
        being represented as indicated by the ISCD Switching Capability
        field.  Existing Switching Capabilities are managed by
        IANA in the "Switching
        Types" registry &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/gmpls-sig-parameters&gt; and the related "IANA-GMPLS-TC-MIB"
        definitions.
      </t>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC7138"/> introduced a "sub-TLV" structure to its
        technology-specific SCSI field.  The sub-TLV-based approach allows for greater flexibility in the structure,
        ordering, and ability to support extensions of the SC-specific format.  This Sub-TLV approach is also
        used in <xref target="RFC7688"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document generalizes this approach and defines a new
        generalized SCSI field format for use by future specific
        technologies and Switching Capability types.  The generalized
        SCSI carries SCSI-TLVs that may be defined within the scope of a
        specific technology or shared across multiple technologies
        (e.g., <xref
        target="AVAIL-EXT"/>).  This
        document also establishes a registry for SCSI-TLV definitions
        that may be shared across multiple technologies.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" anchor="sec-definitions">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

      <t>
        The reader is expected to be familiar with GMPLS terminology
        (e.g., as found in <xref target="RFC3945"/>) as well as the
        terminology used in <xref target="RFC4202"/>, <xref
        target="RFC4203"/>, and <xref target="RFC5307"/>.
      </t>

    </section>

    <!--2-->
    <section title="Generalized SCSI Formats" anchor="sec-format">
      <t>
        The Generalized SCSI is composed of zero or more variable-length
        TLV fields each of which is called an "SCSI-TLV".
        There are no specific size restrictions on these SCSI-TLVs.  Size
        and other formatting restrictions may be imposed by the routing
        protocol ISCD field (refer to <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5307"/>). Please refer to <xref target="RFC3630"/> for
        the treatment of malformed Link TLVs.
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure title="TLV Format" anchor="fig-a">
          <preamble>The SCSI-TLV format is:</preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |             Type              |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ...                           Value                           ...
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]>
          </artwork>
          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>
               <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type (2 octets):"><vspace blankLines="0" />

          This field indicates the type and structure of the information
          contained in the Value field. 
          </t>
          <t hangText="Length (2 octets):"><vspace blankLines="0" />

          This field MUST be set to the size, in octets (bytes), of the
          Value field.  The value of the field MUST be zero or divisible
          by 4.  Note that this implies that the Value field can be
          omitted or contain padding.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Value (variable):"><vspace blankLines="0" />

          A variable-length field, formatted according to the definition
          indicated by value of the Type field.  This field can be
          omitted for certain types.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Procedures" anchor="sec-proc">
      <t>
        The ISCD can include a Generalized SCSI when advertising technologies
        whose Switching Capability definition references this document.
        The corollary of this is that the Generalized SCSI MUST NOT be
        used for ISCDs of technologies whose Switching Capability
        definition do not reference this document.
      </t>      <t>
        The Generalized SCSI MAY contain a sequence of zero or more
        SCSI-TLVs.  Sub-TLV parsing (format) errors MUST be treated as a malformed ISCD.  SCSI-TLVs MUST
        be processed in the order received and, if re-originated,
        ordering MUST be preserved.  Unknown SCSI-TLVs MUST be ignored
        and transparently processed, i.e., re-originated when appropriate.
        Processing related to multiple SCSI-TLVs of the same type may be
        further refined based on the definition on the type.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--4-->
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-secu">
      <t>
        This document does not introduce any security issue beyond those
        discussed in <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5307"/>. As discussed there, the information carried
        in ISCDs is not used for Shortest Path First (SPF) computation or normal routing, and
        the extensions here defined do not have a direct effect on IP
        routing. Tampering with GMPLS Traffic Engineering (TE) Link State Advertisements (LSAs) may have an effect on the
        underlying transport network.  Mechanisms such as those described in <xref
        target="RFC2154"/> and <xref target="RFC5304"/> to protect the
        transmission of this information are suggested.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--5-->
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec-iana">
      <t>
        This document defines a new SCSI-TLV that is carried in the SCSI
        field of the ISCDs defined in <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5307"/>.  The SCSI-TLV includes a 16-bit type
        identifier (the Type field).  The same Type field values are
        applicable to the new SCSI-TLV.
      </t>

      <t>
        IANA has created and will maintain a new registry, the
        "Generalized SCSI (Switching Capability Specific Information)
        TLV Types" registry under the "Generalized
        Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Signaling Parameters"
        registry. 
      </t>
      <t>
        The initial contents of this registry are as follows:
      </t>
      <t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
    Value       SCSI-TLV                Switching Type   Reference
    ---------   ----------------------- --------------   ---------
    0           Reserved                                 [RFC8258]
    1-65535     Unassigned              (value list)     
        ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        New allocation requests to this registry must indicate the
        value or values to be used in the Switching Type column.
      </t>
      <t>
        The registry should be established with registration policies of
        "Specification Required", see <xref
        target="RFC8126"/>.   </t>
 
    </section>


  </middle>


  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3630"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4202"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4203"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5307"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
<!--      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ccamp-ospf-availability-extension.xml"?>; IESG Evaluation-->



<reference anchor='AVAIL-EXT'>
<front>
<title>OSPF-TE Link Availability Extension for Links with Variable Discrete Bandwidth</title>

<author initials='H' surname='Long' fullname='Hao Long'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Ye' fullname='Min Ye'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Mirsky' fullname='Gregory Mirsky'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='D&apos;Alessandro' fullname='Alessandro D&apos;Alessandro'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Shah' fullname='Himanshu Shah'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='August' day='7' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>A network may contain links with variable discrete bandwidth, e.g., copper, radio, etc. The bandwidth of such links may change discretely in reaction to changing external environment. Availability is typically used for describing such links during network planning. This document defines a new type of the Generalized Switching Capability-specific information (SCSI) TLV to extend the Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Open Shortest Path First (OSPF) routing protocol. The extension can be used for route computation in a network that contains links with variable discrete bandwidth. Note, this document only covers the mechanisms by which the availability information is distributed. The mechanisms by which availability information of a link is determined and the use of the distributed information for route computation are outside the scope of this document. It is intended that technology- specific documents will reference this document to describe specific uses.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ccamp-ospf-availability-extension-10' />

</reference>



      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2154"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3945"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5304"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7138"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7688"?>
    </references>
    <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="sec-ack" numbered="no">
      <t>
        The authors would like to thank Adrian Farrel and Julien Meuric
        for the careful review and suggestions.  Thomas Heide Clausen
        provided useful comments as part of the Routing Directorate
        review. 
      </t>

    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>



