<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="8234" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902" updates="7271">

<front>
 <title abbrev="Updates to MPLS-TP LP in APS Mode">
                Updates to MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) Linear Protection  
                in Automatic Protection Switching (APS) Mode </title>

 <author fullname="Jeong-dong Ryoo" initials="J" surname="Ryoo">
   <organization>ETRI</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street/>
       <region/>
       <code/>
       <country/>
     </postal>
     <phone/>
     <facsimile/>
     <email>ryoo@etri.re.kr</email>
  </address>
 </author>

 <author fullname="Taesik Cheung" initials="T" surname="Cheung">
   <organization>ETRI</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street/>
       <region/>
       <code/>
       <country/>
     </postal>
     <phone/>
     <email>cts@etri.re.kr</email>
  </address>
 </author>

 <author fullname="Huub van Helvoort" initials="H" surname="van Helvoort">
   <organization>Hai Gaoming BV</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street/>
       <city/>
       <region/>
       <code/>
       <country/>
    </postal>
    <phone/>
    <facsimile/>
    <email>huubatwork@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
 </author>

 <author fullname="Italo Busi" initials="I" surname="Busi">
   <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street/>
       <city/>
       <region/>
       <code/>
       <country/>
    </postal>
    <phone/>
    <facsimile/>
    <email>Italo.Busi@huawei.com</email>
  </address>
 </author>

 <author fullname="Guangjuan Wen" initials="G" surname="Wen">
   <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street/>
       <city/>
       <region/>
       <code/>
       <country/>
    </postal>
    <phone/>
    <facsimile/>
    <email>wenguangjuan@huawei.com</email>
  </address>
 </author>

 <date month="August" year="2017"/>

 <workgroup>MPLS Working Group</workgroup>

<keyword>APS mode</keyword>
<keyword>initialization</keyword>

 <abstract>
   <t>
   This document contains updates to MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) linear 
   protection in Automatic Protection Switching (APS) mode defined in RFC 7271.
The updates provide rules related to the initialization of the Protection
State Coordination (PSC) Control Logic (in which the state machine resides)
when operating in APS mode and clarify the operation related to state
transition table lookup. 
   </t>
 </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
 <section title="Introduction">
   <t>
   MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) linear protection in Automatic Protection 
   Switching (APS) mode is defined in RFC 7271 <xref target="RFC7271"/>. 
   It defines a set of alternate and additional mechanisms to perform 
   some of the functions of linear protection described in 
   RFC 6378 <xref target="RFC6378"/>.
   The actions performed at initialization of 
   the Protection State Coordination (PSC) Control Logic are not described in 
   either <xref target="RFC7271"/> or <xref target="RFC6378"/>. 
   Although it is a common perception that the state machine starts 
   at the Normal state, this is not explicitly specified in any of 
   the documents and various questions have been raised by implementers and in discussions on
   the MPLS working group mailing list concerning the detailed actions 
   that the PSC Control Logic should take.
   </t>
   <t>
   The state machine described in <xref target="RFC7271"/> operates under the
   assumption that both end nodes of a linear protection domain start
   in the Normal state. 
   In the case that one node reboots while the other node is still in 
   operation, various scenarios may arise resulting in problematic situations.  
   This document resolves all the problematic cases and 
   minimizes traffic disruptions related to initialization,
   including both cold and warm reboots 
   that require re-initialization of the PSC Control Logic.
   </t>
   <t>
   This document contains updates to the MPLS-TP linear 
   protection in APS mode defined in
   <xref target="RFC7271"/>.
   The updates provide rules related to initialization of the PSC Control 
   Logic (in which the state machine resides) when operating in APS mode. 
   The updates also include modifications to the state transition table 
   defined in Section 11.2 of <xref target="RFC7271"/>. 
   The changes in the state transition table have been examined to make sure 
   that no new problems are introduced.
   </t>
   <t>
   This document does not introduce backward compatibility issues with
   implementations of <xref target="RFC7271"/>.
   In case a node implementing this document restarts, 
   the new state changes will not cause problems at the remote node 
   implementing <xref target="RFC7271"/>,
   and the two ends will converge to the same local and remote states.
   In case a node implementing <xref target="RFC7271"/> restarts, 
   the two ends behave as they do today.
   </t>
   <t>
   This document also provides some clarifications on the operation 
   related to state transition table lookup.
   </t>
   <t>
   The reader of this document is assumed to be familiar with 
   <xref target="RFC7271"/>.  
<!--
   This document shares the acronyms defined in Section 3 of 
   <xref target="RFC7271"/>.
-->
   </t>
 </section> <!-- End of Introduction section -->

 <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
<t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="secAcr" title="Abbreviations">
    <texttable align="left" style="none">

      <preamble>This document uses the following abbreviations:</preamble>

      <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>     <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>
      <c>APS</c>     <c>Automatic Protection Switching</c>
      <c>DNR</c>     <c>Do-not-Revert</c>
      <c>E::R</c>    <c>Exercise state due to remote EXER message</c>
      <c>EXER</c>    <c>Exercise</c>
      <c>MS-P</c>    <c>Manual Switch to Protection path</c>
      <c>MS-W</c>    <c>Manual Switch to Working path</c>
      <c>MPLS-TP</c> <c>MPLS Transport Profile</c>
      <c>NR</c>      <c>No Request</c>
      <c>PF:DW:R</c> <c>Protecting Failure state due to remote SD-W message</c>
      <c>PF:W:L</c>  <c>Protecting Failure state due to local SF-W</c>
      <c>PF:W:R</c>  <c>Protecting Failure state due to remote SF-W message</c>
      <c>PSC</c>     <c>Protection State Coordination</c>
      <c>RR</c>      <c>Reverse Request</c>
      <c>SA:MP:R</c> <c>Switching Administrative state due to remote MS-P message</c>
      <c>SA:MW:R</c> <c>Switching Administrative state due to remote MS-W message</c>
      <c>SD</c>      <c>Signal Degrade</c>
      <c>SD-W</c>    <c>Signal Degrade on Working path</c>
      <c>SF</c>      <c>Signal Fail</c>
      <c>SF-P</c>    <c>Signal Fail on Protection path</c>
      <c>SF-W</c>    <c>Signal Fail on Working path</c>
      <c>UA:P:L</c>  <c>Unavailable state due to local SF-P</c>
      <c>WTR</c>     <c>Wait-to-Restore</c>

    </texttable>	  
 </section>


 <section anchor="secUpdates" title="Updates">
   <t>This section specifies 
   the actions that will be performed at the initialization of 
   the PSC Control Logic and 
   the modifications of the state transition table 
   defined in Section 11.2 of <xref target="RFC7271"/>.
   Some clarifications on the operation
   related to state transition table lookup are also provided.
   </t>
 <section anchor="secInitBeh" title="Initialization Behavior"> 
   <t>This section defines initialization behavior that is not described in 
   <xref target="RFC7271"/>. </t> 
   <t>
   When the PSC Control Logic is initialized, 
   the following actions MUST be performed:
   <list style="symbols">
     <t>Stop the WTR timer if it is running.  
     </t>
     <t>Clear any operator command in the Local Request Logic.  
     </t>
     <t>If an SF-W or SF-P exists as the highest local request, 
     the node being initialized starts at the PF:W:L or UA:P:L state, 
     respectively.
     </t>
     <t>If the node being initialized has no local request:
     <list style="symbols">
        <t>If the node being initialized does not remember the active path or 
        if the node being initialized remembers the working path as 
        the active path, the node starts at the Normal state. 
        </t>
        <t>Else (the node being initialized remembers the protection path 
        as the active path), the node starts at the WTR state sending NR(0,1) 
        or at the DNR state sending DNR(0,1) depending on the configuration
        that allows or prevents automatic reversion to the Normal state. 
        </t>
     </list>
     </t>
<!--
     <t>In case any local SD exists, the local SD MUST be considered 
     as an input to the Local Request Logic only after the local node 
     responds to the first protocol message from the remote node.
     Therefore, the local SD input is delayed 
     until the local node completes the initialization and 
     responds to the first protocol message from the remote node. 
     </t>
-->
<!--
     <t>In case any local SD exists, the local SD MUST be ignored 
     until the local node completes the initialization and 
     processes the first protocol message from the remote node. 
     More specifically, 
     when the local node receives the first protocol message, 
     the remote request becomes the top-priority global request
     without considering the local SD, and  
     the state transition is determined by the remote request to obtain
     an intermediate state. 
     This intermediate state is introduced to facilite the description 
     of behavior, 
     and no protocol massages are genarated at the intermediate state.
     Assuming the node is in the intermediate state, 
     the local SD is accepted as an input to the Local Request 
     and compared with the remote request to decide
     the top-priority global request, which is used to determine 
     the final state. 
     According to the final state, the protocol messages are generated.
     </t>
-->
<!-- WHAT WE HAD IN 01 VERSION:
     <t>Any local SD MUST be ignored and 
     the detection of a local SD MUST be (re-)started 
     after the local node completes the initialization and 
     responds to the first protocol message received from the remote node. 
     </t>
-->
     <t>In case any local SD exists, the local SD MUST be considered 
     as an input to the Local Request Logic only after the local node 
     has received the first protocol message from the remote node 
     and completed the processing 
     (i.e., updated the PSC Control Logic and decided which action, if any, 
     is to be sent to the PSC Message Generator).
     </t>
     <t>If the local node receives an EXER message 
     as the first protocol message after initialization and 
     the remote EXER becomes the top-priority global request, 
     the local node MUST set the position of the bridge and selector 
     according to the Path value in the EXER message 
     and transit to the E::R state.
     </t>
   </list>
   </t>
   <t>
   In the case of no local request, remembering the active path minimizes
   traffic switchovers when the remote node is still in
   operation.  This approach does not cause a problem 
   even if the remembered active path is no longer valid
   due to any local input that occurred at the remote node 
   while the initializing node was out of operation.
   </t>
<!--  WHAT WE HAD IN 01 VERSION:
   <t>
   Note that while the local SD input is being ignored 
   and there exist no other local requests, 
   the local node restarts with no local request.
   Since the equal priority resolution stated in Section 7.4 of 
   <xref target="RFC7271"/> 
   does not converge when the active paths that two nodes remember are 
   different from each other.
   an SD detection needs to be (re-)started 
   after both nodes converge to the same view on their active paths.
   </t>
-->
   <t>
   Note that in some restart scenarios (e.g., cold rebooting),
   no valid SF/SD indications may be present at the input of the Local Request 
   Logic. 
   In this case, the PSC Control Logic restarts
   as if no local requests are present. 
   If a valid SF/SD indication is detected later, 
   the PSC Control Logic is notified and state change is triggered.
   </t>
 </section>

 <section title="State Transition Modification"> 
   <t>In addition to the initialization behavior described in 
   <xref target="secInitBeh"/>, 
   four cells of the remote state transition table need to be changed
   to make two end nodes converge after initialization.
   State transition by remote message as defined in Section 11.2 of
   <xref target="RFC7271"/> is modified as follows
   (only modified cells are shown):
   </t>
  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
        | MS-W    | MS-P    | WTR | EXER | RR | DNR  | NR
--------+---------+---------+-----+------+----+------+----
N       |         |         | (13)|      |    | DNR  | 
PF:W:R  |         |         |     |      |    | DNR  |     
PF:DW:R |         |         |     |      |    | DNR  |       
      ]]></artwork>
  </figure>
  <t>The changes in two rows of remote protecting failure states
  lead to the replacement of note (10) with DNR; therefore,
  note (10) is no longer needed. 
  The resultant three rows read:
  </t>
    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
        | MS-W    | MS-P    | WTR | EXER | RR | DNR  | NR
--------+---------+---------+-----+------+----+------+----
N       | SA:MW:R | SA:MP:R | (13)| E::R | i  | DNR  | i
PF:W:R  | SA:MW:R | SA:MP:R | (9) | E::R | i  | DNR  | (11)
PF:DW:R | SA:MW:R | SA:MP:R | (9) | E::R | i  | DNR  | (11)
       ]]></artwork>
  </figure>
  <t>In the tables above, the letters 'i' and 'N' stand for 
  "ignore" and "Normal state", respectively. 
  Other abbreviations can be found in <xref target="secAcr"/>. 
  </t>
 </section>

 <section title="Operation Related to State Transition Table Lookup"> 
  <t>In addition to the rules related to the state transition table 
  lookup listed in Section 11 of <xref target="RFC7271"/>, 
  the following rule is also applied to the operation related to 
  the state transition table lookup:   
   <list style="symbols">
    <t>When the local SF-P is cleared and the priorities of the 
    local and remote requests are re-evaluated, 
    the last received remote message may no longer be valid
    due to the previous failure of the protection path.
    Therefore, the last received message MUST be treated 
    as if it were NR and only the local request shall be evaluated. 
    </t>
   </list>
  </t>
  <t>The last paragraph in Section 11 of <xref target="RFC7271"/>
  is modified as follows: 
  </t>
  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
---------
Old text:
---------
In the state transition tables below, the letter 'i' stands for
"ignore" and is an indication to remain in the current state and
continue transmitting the current PSC message.

---------
New text:
---------
In the state transition tables below, the letter 'i' is the 
"ignore" flag; if it is set, it means that the top-priority
global request is ignored.

If re-evaluation is triggered, the ignore flag is checked. If it 
is set, the state machine will transit to the supposed state, which 
can be Normal or DNR as indicated in the footnotes to the state 
transition table in Section 11.1 of [RFC7271].  If the ignore flag 
is not set, the state machine will transit to the state indicated 
in the cell of the state transition table.
 
If re-evaluation is not triggered, the ignore flag is checked. If 
it is set, the state machine will remain in the current state, and 
the current PSC message continues to be transmitted. If the ignore 
flag is not set, the state machine will transit to the state 
indicated in the cell of the state transition table.
      ]]></artwork>
  </figure>

 </section>

 </section>

 <section anchor="secSec" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>No specific security issue is raised in addition to those ones
  already documented in <xref target="RFC7271"/>.
  Note that tightening the description of the initializing behavior 
  may help to protect networks from restart attacks.
   </t>
  </section>


  <section anchor="secIANA" title="IANA Considerations">
   <t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
 </section>


</middle>

<back>
 <references title="Normative References">
   <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
   <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7271'?>
   <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>
 </references>

 <references title="Informative References">
   <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6378'?>
 </references>


 <section anchor="secAck" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
  <t>The authors would like to thank Joaquim Serra for raising
  the issue related to initialization of the PSC Control Logic
  at the very beginning. The authors would also like to thank Adrian Farrel and Loa Andersson
  for their valuable comments and suggestions on this document.
  </t>
 </section>


</back>
</rfc>
