<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC2781 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2781.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC3629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3688 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC3986 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5322 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC5646 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5730 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5730.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC5733 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5733.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC7451 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7451.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC8126 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml'>
    
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt'?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" number="8543" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">

  <front> 
    <title abbrev="EPP Organization Mapping">Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) Organization Mapping</title>  
    <author fullname="Linlin Zhou" initials="L" surname="Zhou"> 
      <organization>CNNIC</organization>  
      <address> 
        <postal> 
          <street>4 South 4th Street, Zhongguancun, Haidian District</street>  
          <city>Beijing</city>  
          <region>Beijing</region>  
          <code>100190</code>  
          <country>China</country> 
        </postal>  
        <email>zhoulinlin@cnnic.cn</email> 
      </address> 
    </author>  

    <author fullname="Ning Kong" initials="N" surname="Kong"> 
      <organization>Consultant</organization>  
      <address> 
        <email>ietfing@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author>  

    <author fullname="Jiankang Yao" initials="J" surname="Yao"> 
      <organization>CNNIC</organization>  
      <address> 
        <postal> 
          <street>4 South 4th Street, Zhongguancun, Haidian District</street>  
          <city>Beijing</city>  
          <region>Beijing</region>  
          <code>100190</code>  
          <country>China</country> 
        </postal>  
        <email>yaojk@cnnic.cn</email> 
      </address> 
    </author>  

    <author fullname="James Gould" initials="J.G" surname="Gould">
      <organization>VeriSign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jgould@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.verisign.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Guiqing Zhou" initials="G" surname="Zhou">  
      <address>  
        <email>qing.joe@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author>  

    <date month="February" year="2019"/>  
    <area>Internet</area>  
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>  
    <keyword>epp registry organization object mapping</keyword>  
    <abstract> 
      <t>This document describes an Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) mapping for provisioning and management of organization objects stored in a shared central repository.</t> 
    </abstract> 
  </front>  
  <middle> 
    <section title="Introduction"> 
      <t>There are many entities, such as registrars, resellers, DNS service
      operators, and privacy proxies, involved in the domain registration
      business. These kinds of entities have not been formally defined as
      having an object in Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP). This
      document provides a way to specify them as "organization" entities.</t>

      <t>This document describes an organization object mapping for version
      1.0 of the EPP <xref target="RFC5730"/>. This mapping is specified using
      XML 1.0 as described in <xref target="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"/> and XML Schema notation
      as described in <xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-1-20041028"/> and <xref
      target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"/>.
      </t> 
    </section>  
    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document"> 
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

      <t>In examples, "C:" represents lines sent by a protocol client, and "S:"
      represents lines returned by a protocol server. Indentation and white
      space in examples are provided only to illustrate element relationships
      and are not a required feature of this specification.</t>

      <t>XML is case sensitive. Unless stated otherwise, XML specifications
      and examples provided in this document MUST be interpreted in the
      character case presented.</t>  

      <t>The XML namespace prefix "org" is used for the namespace
      "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0", but implementations MUST NOT
      depend on it; instead, they should employ a proper namespace-aware XML parser and
      serializer to interpret and output the XML documents.</t> 
    </section>  
    <section title="Object Attributes"> 
      <t>An EPP organization object has attributes and associated values that
      can be viewed and modified by the sponsoring client or the server. This
      section describes each attribute type in detail. The formal syntax for
      the attribute values described here can be found in the "Formal Syntax"
      section of this document and in the appropriate normative
      references.</t>  

      <section title="Organization Identifier" anchor="org-identifier"> 
        <t>All EPP organizations are identified by a server-unique
	identifier. Organization identifiers are character strings with a
	specified minimum length, a specified maximum length, and a specified
	format. Organization identifiers use the "clIDType" client identifier
	syntax described in <xref target="RFC5730"/>. The corresponding
	element is &lt;org:id&gt;.
        </t> 
      </section>  

      <section title="Organization Roles" anchor="org-role"> 
        <t>The organization roles are used to represent the relationship an
	organization could have. The corresponding element is
	&lt;org:role&gt;. An organization object MUST always have at least one
	associated role. Roles can be set only by the client that sponsors an
	organization object. A client can change the role of an organization
	object using the EPP &lt;update&gt; command (see <xref target="org-update"/>).</t>  

        <section title="Role Type" anchor="role-type"> 
          <t>An organization role MUST have a type field, which may have any of
	  the values listed in <xref target="role"/>. The corresponding
	  element is &lt;org:type&gt;. An organization could
	  have multiple roles with different role types. 
          </t> 
        </section>  

        <section title="Role Status" anchor="role-status"> 
          <t>A role of an organization object MAY have its own statuses. The
	  corresponding element is &lt;org:status&gt;. The possible values for the role
	  status are defined in <xref target="role-status-value"/>.
          </t> 
        </section>  

        <section title="Role Identifier" anchor="role-identifier"> 
          <t>A role MAY have a third-party-assigned identifier such as the IANA ID for registrars. The corresponding element is &lt;org:roleID&gt;.</t>  
          <t>Example of organization role identifier:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
<org:role> 
  <org:type>registrar</org:type> 
  <org:status>ok</org:status>
  <org:status>linked</org:status>
  <org:roleID>1362</org:roleID> 
</org:role>
]]> </artwork> 
          </figure> 
        </section> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Contact and Client Identifiers"> 
        <t>All EPP contacts are identified by server-unique
	identifiers. Contact identifiers are character strings with a
	specified minimum length, a specified maximum length, and a specified
	format. Contact identifiers use the "clIDType" client identifier
	syntax described in <xref target="RFC5730"/>.
        </t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Organization Status Values" anchor="org-state"> 
        <t>An organization object MUST always have at least one associated
	status value. Status values can be set only by the client that
	sponsors an organization object and by the server on which the object
	resides. A client can change the status of an organization object
	using the EPP &lt;update&gt; command. Each status value MAY be
	accompanied by a string of human-readable text that describes the
	rationale for the status applied to the object.</t>  

        <t>A client MUST NOT alter server status values set by the server. A
	server MAY alter or override status values set by a client, subject to
	local server policies. The status of an object MAY change as a result
	of either a client-initiated transform command or an action performed
	by a server operator.</t>  

        <t>Status values that can be added or removed by a client are prefixed
	with "client". Corresponding server status values that can be added or
	removed by a server are prefixed with "server". The "hold" and
	"terminated" status values are server managed when the organization
	has no parent identifier (<xref target="parent-identifier"/>) and
	otherwise MAY be client managed based on server policy. Other status
	values that do not begin with either "client" or "server" are
	server managed.
        </t>  
        <t>Status Value Descriptions:</t>  
        <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>ok: This is the normal status value for an object that has no
	    operations pending or active prohibitions. This value is set and
	    removed by the server as other status values are added or
	    removed.</t>  
            <t>hold: Organization transform commands and new links MUST be
	    rejected.</t>  
            <t>terminated: The organization that has been terminated MUST NOT
	    be linked. Organization transform commands and new links MUST be
	    rejected.</t>  
            <t>linked: The organization object has at least one active
	    association with another object. The "linked" status is not
	    explicitly set by the client. Servers should provide services to
	    determine existing object associations.</t>  
            <t>clientLinkProhibited, serverLinkProhibited: Requests to add new
	    links to the organization MUST be rejected.</t>  
            <t>clientUpdateProhibited, serverUpdateProhibited: Requests to
	    update the object (other than to remove this status) MUST be
	    rejected.</t>  
            <t>clientDeleteProhibited, serverDeleteProhibited: Requests to delete the object MUST be rejected.</t>  
            <t>pendingCreate, pendingUpdate, pendingDelete: A transform
	    command has been processed for the object, but the action has not
	    been completed by the server. Server operators can delay action
	    completion for a variety of reasons, such as to allow for human
	    review or third-party action. A transform command that is
	    processed, but whose requested action is pending, is noted with
	    response code 1001.</t> 
          </list> 
        </t>  
        <t>"pendingCreate", "ok", "hold", and "terminated" are mutually
	exclusive statuses. An organization MUST have exactly one of these
	statuses set.</t>  
        <t>"ok" status MAY only be combined with "linked" status.</t>  
        <t>A client or server MAY combine "linked" with either
	"clientLinkProhibited" or "serverLinkProhibited" if new links must be
	prohibited.</t>  
        <t>"pendingDelete" status MUST NOT be combined with either
	"clientDeleteProhibited" or "serverDeleteProhibited" status.</t>  
        <t>The "pendingCreate", "pendingDelete", and "pendingUpdate" status values
	MUST NOT be combined with each other.</t>  
        <t>If "clientUpdateProhibited" or "serverUpdateProhibited" is set, the
	client will not be able to update the object. For
	"clientUpdateProhibited", the client will first need to remove
	"clientUpdateProhibited" prior to attempting to update the object. The
	server can modify the object at any time.</t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Role Status Values" anchor="role-status-value"> 
        <t>A role SHOULD have at least one associated status value. Valid
	values include "ok", "linked", "clientLinkProhibited", and
	"serverLinkProhibited".</t>  
        <t>Status Value Descriptions:</t>  
        <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>ok: This is the normal status value for a role that has no
	    operations pending or active prohibitions. This value is set and
	    removed by the server as other status values are added or
	    removed.</t>  
            <t>linked: The role of an organization object has at least one
	    active association with another object. The "linked" status is not
	    explicitly set by the client. Servers SHOULD provide services to
	    determine existing object associations.</t>  
            <t>clientLinkProhibited, serverLinkProhibited: Requests to add new
	    links to the role MUST be rejected.</t> 
          </list> 
        </t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Parent Identifier" anchor="parent-identifier">

        <t>Organizations can have more than one layer. The parent identifier,
	as defined with the
	&lt;org:parentId&gt; element, represents the parent organization
	identifier in a child organization.</t>  

        <t>The case of reseller organizations provides an example. The parent
	identifier is not defined for the top-level reseller, namely the
	registrar of the registry. An N-tier reseller has a parent reseller
	and at least one child reseller. A reseller customer has a parent
	reseller and no child resellers.</t>  

        <t>Loops MUST be prohibited. For example: if organization A has
	organization B as
	its parent identifier, organization B cannot have organization A as
	its parent identifier. The same is true for larger loops involving
	three or more organizations.</t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="URL" anchor="org-url"> 
        <t>The URL represents the organization web home page, as defined with the &lt;org:url&gt; element.</t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Dates and Times" anchor="org-date"> 
        <t>Date and time attribute values MUST be represented in Coordinated
	Universal Time (UTC) using the Gregorian calendar. The extended
	date-time form using uppercase "T" and "Z" characters defined in
	<xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"/> MUST be used to represent date-time
	values, as XML Schema does not support truncated date-time forms or
	lowercase "T" and "Z" characters.
        </t> 
      </section> 
    </section>  

    <section title="EPP Command Mapping"> 
      <t>A detailed description of the EPP syntax and semantics can be found
      in the EPP core protocol specification <xref target="RFC5730"/>. The
      command mappings described here are specifically for use in provisioning
      and managing organization information via EPP.
      </t>  

      <section title="EPP Query Commands"> 
        <t>EPP provides two commands to retrieve organization information:
	&lt;check&gt; to determine if an organization object can be
	provisioned within a repository and &lt;info&gt; to retrieve detailed
	information associated with an organization object. This document does
	not define a mapping for the EPP &lt;transfer&gt; command to retrieve
	organization-object transfer status information.</t>  

        <section title="EPP &lt;check&gt; Command"> 
          <t>The EPP &lt;check&gt; command is used to determine if an object
	  can be provisioned within a repository. It provides a hint that
	  allows a client to anticipate the success or failure of provisioning
	  an object using the &lt;create&gt; command, as object-provisioning
	  requirements are ultimately a matter of server policy.</t>  

          <t>In addition to the standard EPP command elements, the
	  &lt;check&gt; command MUST contain an &lt;org:check&gt;
	  element. This element or its ancestor element MUST identify the
	  organization namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The
	  &lt;org:check&gt; element contains the following child elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>One or more &lt;org:id&gt; elements that contain the
	      server-unique identifier of the organization objects to be
	      queried.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;check&gt; command:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <check>
C:      <org:check
C:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
C:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
C:        <org:id>re1523</org:id>
C:        <org:id>1523res</org:id>
C:      </org:check>
C:    </check>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>When a &lt;check&gt; command has been processed successfully, the
	  EPP &lt;resData&gt; element MUST contain a child &lt;org:chkData&gt;
	  element. This element or its ancestor element MUST identify the
	  organization namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The
	  &lt;org:chkData&gt; element contains one or more &lt;org:cd&gt;
	  elements that contain the following child elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that identifies the queried
	      object. This element MUST contain an "avail" attribute whose
	      value indicates object availability (can it be provisioned or
	      not) at the moment the &lt;check&gt; command was completed. A
	      value of "1" or "true" means that the object can be
	      provisioned. A value of "0" or "false" means that the object
	      cannot be provisioned.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:reason&gt; element that may be provided
	      when an object cannot be provisioned. If present, this element
	      contains server-specific text to help explain why the object
	      cannot be provisioned. This text MUST be represented in the
	      response language previously negotiated with the client; an
	      OPTIONAL "lang" attribute as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>
	      may be present to identify the language if the negotiated value
	      is something other than the default value of "en"(English).
              </t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;check&gt; response:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:chkData
S:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:cd>
S:          <org:id avail="1">res1523</org:id>
S:        </org:cd>
S:        <org:cd>
S:          <org:id avail="0">re1523</org:id>
S:          <org:reason lang="en">In use</org:reason>
S:        </org:cd>
S:        <org:cd>
S:          <org:id avail="1">1523res</org:id>
S:        </org:cd>
S:      </org:chkData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54322-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>An EPP error response MUST be returned if a &lt;check&gt; command cannot be processed for any reason.</t> 
        </section>  
        <section title="EPP &lt;info&gt; Command"> 
          <t>The EPP &lt;info&gt; command is used to retrieve information
	  associated with an organization object. In addition to the standard
	  EPP command elements, the &lt;info&gt; command MUST contain an
	  &lt;org:info&gt; element. This element or its ancestor element MUST
	  identify the organization namespace
	  "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The &lt;org:info&gt; element
	  contains the following child element:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique identifier of the organization object to be queried.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;info&gt; command:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <info>
C:      <org:info
C:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
C:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
C:      </org:info>
C:    </info>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>When an &lt;info&gt; command has been processed successfully, the
	  EPP &lt;resData&gt; element MUST contain a child &lt;org:infData&gt;
	  element. This element or its ancestor element MUST identify the
	  organization namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The
	  &lt;org:infData&gt; element contains the following child
	  elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique
	      identifier of the organization object, as defined in <xref
	      target="org-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:roid&gt; element that contains the Repository
	      Object Identifier assigned to the organization object when the
	      object was created.</t>  

              <t>One or more &lt;org:role&gt; elements that contain the role
	      type, role statuses, and optional role ID of the organization. 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:type&gt; element that contains the type of the
		  organization, as defined in <xref target="org-role"/>.
                  </t>  
                  <t>One or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the
		  role statuses. The values of the role status are defined in
		  <xref target="role-status-value"/>.
                  </t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:roleID&gt; element that contains a
		  third-party-assigned identifier, such as IANA ID for
		  registrars, as defined in <xref target="role-identifier"/>.
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>One or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the
	      operational status of the organization, as defined in <xref
	      target="org-state"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:parentId&gt; element that contains the
	      identifier of the parent object, as defined in <xref
	      target="parent-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>Zero to two &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; elements that contain
	      postal-address information. Two elements are provided so that
	      address information can be provided in both internationalized
	      and localized forms; a "type" attribute is used to identify the
	      two forms. If an internationalized form (type="int") is
	      provided, element content MUST be represented in a subset of
	      Unicode <xref target="UNICODE"/> in the range U+0020 -
	      U+007E. If a localized form
	      (type="loc") is provided, element content MAY be represented in
	      unrestricted UTF-8.	      
	      The &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; element contains
	      the following child elements: 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:name&gt; element that contains the name of the organization.</t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:addr&gt; element that contains
		  address information associated with the organization. An
		  &lt;org:addr&gt; element contains the following child
		  elements: 
                    <list style="symbols"> 
                      <t>One, two, or three &lt;org:street&gt; elements that
		      contain the organization's street address.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:city&gt; element that contains the organization's city.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:sp&gt; element that contains the
		      organization's state or province.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:pc&gt; element that contains the organization's postal code.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:cc&gt; element that contains the alpha-2
		      organization's country code. The detailed format of this
		      element is described in Section 2.4.3 of <xref
		      target="RFC5733"/>.
                      </t> 
                    </list> 
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:voice&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's voice telephone number. The detailed format of
	      this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:fax&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's facsimile telephone number. The detailed format
	      of this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:email&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's email address. The detailed format of this
	      element is described in <xref target="RFC5322"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:url&gt; element that contains the URL to
	      the website of the organization. The detailed format of this
	      element is described in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:contact&gt; elements that contain
	      identifiers for the contact objects to be associated with the
	      organization object. Contact object identifiers MUST be known to
	      the server before the contact object can be associated with the
	      organization object. The required "type" is used to represent
	      contact types. The type values include "admin", "tech",
	      "billing", "abuse", and "custom". The OPTIONAL "typeName"
	      attribute is used to define the name of a "custom" type.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:clID&gt; element that contains the
	      organization identifier of the sponsoring client. There is no
	      &lt;org:clID&gt; element if the organization is managed by the
	      registry.</t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:crID&gt; element that contains the identifier of
	      the client that created the organization object.</t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:crDate&gt; element that contains the date and time of organization object creation.</t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:upID&gt; element that contains the identifier of
	      the client that last updated the organization object. This
	      element MUST NOT be present if the organization has never been
	      modified.</t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:upDate&gt; element that contains the date and time
	      of the most recent organization object modification. This
	      element MUST NOT be present if the organization object has never
	      been modified.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;info&gt; response for "Example Registrar Inc."
	  organization object with identifier "registrar1362":</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:infData
S:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:id>registrar1362</org:id>
S:        <org:roid>registrar1362-REP</org:roid>
S:        <org:role>
S:          <org:type>registrar</org:type>
S:          <org:status>ok</org:status>
S:          <org:status>linked</org:status>
S:          <org:roleID>1362</org:roleID>
S:        </org:role>
S:        <org:status>ok</org:status>
S:        <org:postalInfo type="int">
S:          <org:name>Example Registrar Inc.</org:name>
S:          <org:addr>
S:            <org:street>123 Example Dr.</org:street>
S:            <org:street>Suite 100</org:street>
S:            <org:city>Dulles</org:city>
S:            <org:sp>VA</org:sp>
S:            <org:pc>20166-6503</org:pc>
S:            <org:cc>US</org:cc>
S:          </org:addr>
S:        </org:postalInfo>
S:        <org:voice x="1234">+1.7035555555</org:voice>
S:        <org:fax>+1.7035555556</org:fax>
S:        <org:email>contact@organization.example</org:email>
S:        <org:url>https://organization.example</org:url>
S:        <org:contact type="admin">sh8013</org:contact>
S:        <org:contact type="billing">sh8013</org:contact>
S:        <org:contact type="custom" 
S:           typeName="legal">sh8013</org:contact>
S:        <org:crID>ClientX</org:crID>
S:        <org:crDate>2018-04-03T22:00:00.0Z</org:crDate>
S:        <org:upID>ClientX</org:upID>
S:        <org:upDate>2018-12-03T09:00:00.0Z</org:upDate>
S:      </org:infData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54322-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>Example &lt;info&gt; response for "Example Reseller Inc." organization object of reseller type managed by identifier "registrar1362":</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:infData
S:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:id>reseller1523</org:id>
S:        <org:roid>reseller1523-REP</org:roid>
S:        <org:role>
S:          <org:type>reseller</org:type>
S:          <org:status>ok</org:status>
S:          <org:status>linked</org:status>
S:        </org:role>
S:        <org:status>ok</org:status>
S:        <org:parentId>registrar1362</org:parentId>
S:        <org:postalInfo type="int">
S:          <org:name>Example Reseller Inc.</org:name>
S:          <org:addr>
S:            <org:street>123 Example Dr.</org:street>
S:            <org:street>Suite 100</org:street>
S:            <org:city>Dulles</org:city>
S:            <org:sp>VA</org:sp>
S:            <org:pc>20166-6503</org:pc>
S:            <org:cc>US</org:cc>
S:          </org:addr>
S:        </org:postalInfo>
S:        <org:fax>+1.7035555556</org:fax>
S:        <org:url>https://organization.example</org:url>
S:        <org:contact type="admin">sh8013</org:contact>
S:        <org:clID>1362</org:clID>
S:        <org:crID>ClientX</org:crID>
S:        <org:crDate>2018-04-03T22:00:00.0Z</org:crDate>
S:        <org:upID>ClientX</org:upID>
S:        <org:upDate>2018-12-03T09:00:00.0Z</org:upDate>
S:      </org:infData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54322-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>An EPP error response MUST be returned if an &lt;info&gt; command cannot be processed for any reason.</t> 
        </section>  
       <section title="EPP &lt;transfer&gt; Query Command"> 
          <t>The transfer semantics do not apply to organization objects. No
	  EPP &lt;transfer&gt; query command is defined in this document.</t> 
        </section> 
      </section>  
      <section title="EPP Transform Commands"> 
        <t>This document provides three commands to transform organization
	object information: &lt;create&gt; to create an instance of an
	organization object, &lt;delete&gt; to delete an instance of an
	organization object, and &lt;update&gt; to change information
	associated with an organization object. This document does not define
	a mapping for the EPP &lt;transfer&gt; and &lt;renew&gt; command.</t>  
        <t>Transform commands are typically processed and completed in real
	time. Server operators MAY receive and process transform commands but
	defer completing the requested action if human or third-party review
	is required before the requested action can be completed. In such
	situations, the server MUST return a 1001 response code to the client
	to note that the command has been received and processed but that the
	requested action is pending. The server MUST also manage the status of
	the object that is the subject of the command to reflect the
	initiation and completion of the requested action. Once the action has
	been completed, the client MUST be notified using a service message
	that the action has been completed and the status of the object
	has changed. Other notification methods MAY be used in addition to the
	required service message.</t>  
  
        <section title="EPP &lt;create&gt; Command"> 
          <t>The EPP &lt;create&gt; command provides a transform operation
	  that allows a client to create an organization object. In addition
	  to the standard EPP command elements, the &lt;create&gt; command
	  MUST contain an &lt;org:create&gt; element. This element or its
	  ancestor element MUST identify the organization namespace
	  "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The &lt;org:create&gt; element
	  contains the following child elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the desired
	      server-unique identifier for the organization to be created, as
	      defined in <xref target="org-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>One or more &lt;org:role&gt; elements that contain the role
	      type, role statuses, and optional role ID of the organization. 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:type&gt; element that contains the type of the
		  organization, as defined in <xref target="org-role"/>.
                  </t>  
                  <t>Zero or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the
		  role statuses. The possible values of the role statuses are defined in
		  <xref target="role-status-value"/>.
                  </t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:roleID&gt; element that contains a
		  third-party-assigned identifier, such as IANA ID for
		  registrars, as defined in <xref target="role-identifier"/>.
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the
	      operational status of the organization, as defined in <xref
	      target="org-state"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:parentId&gt; element that contains the
	      identifier of the parent object, as defined in <xref
	      target="parent-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>Zero to two &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; elements that contain
	      postal-address information. Two elements are provided so that
	      address information can be provided in both internationalized
	      and localized forms; a "type" attribute is used to identify the
	      two forms. If an internationalized form (type="int") is
	      provided, element content MUST be represented in a subset of
	      Unicode <xref target="UNICODE"/> in the range U+0020 - U+007E. If a localized form
	      (type="loc") is provided, element content MAY be represented in
	      unrestricted UTF-8. The &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; element contains
	      the following child elements: 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:name&gt; element that contains the name of the organization.</t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:addr&gt; element that contains
		  address information associated with the organization. An
		  &lt;org:addr&gt; element contains the following child
		  elements: 
                    <list style="symbols"> 
                      <t>One, two, or three &lt;org:street&gt; elements that contain the organization's street address.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:city&gt; element that contains the organization's city.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:sp&gt; element that contains the
		      organization's state or province.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:pc&gt; element that contains the organization's postal code.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:cc&gt; element that contains the alpha-2
		      organization's country code. The detailed format of this
		      element is described in Section 2.4.3 of <xref
		      target="RFC5733"/>.
                      </t> 
                    </list> 
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:voice&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's voice telephone number. The detailed format of
	      this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:fax&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's facsimile telephone number. The detailed format of this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:email&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's email address. The detailed format of this
	      element is described of <xref target="RFC5322"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:url&gt; element that contains the URL to
	      the website of the organization. The detailed format of this
	      element is described in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:contact&gt; elements that contain
	      identifiers for the contact objects associated with the
	      organization object.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;create&gt; command:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <create>
C:      <org:create
C:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
C:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
C:        <org:role>
C:          <org:type>reseller</org:type>
C:        </org:role>
C:        <org:parentId>1523res</org:parentId>
C:        <org:postalInfo type="int">
C:          <org:name>Example Organization Inc.</org:name>
C:          <org:addr>
C:            <org:street>123 Example Dr.</org:street>
C:            <org:street>Suite 100</org:street>
C:            <org:city>Dulles</org:city>
C:            <org:sp>VA</org:sp>
C:            <org:pc>20166-6503</org:pc>
C:            <org:cc>US</org:cc>
C:          </org:addr>
C:        </org:postalInfo>
C:        <org:voice x="1234">+1.7035555555</org:voice>
C:        <org:fax>+1.7035555556</org:fax>
C:        <org:email>contact@organization.example</org:email>
C:        <org:url>https://organization.example</org:url>
C:        <org:contact type="admin">sh8013</org:contact>
C:        <org:contact type="billing">sh8013</org:contact>
C:      </org:create>
C:    </create>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>When a &lt;create&gt; command has been processed successfully,
	  the EPP &lt;resData&gt; element MUST contain a child
	  &lt;org:creData&gt; element. This element or its ancestor element
	  MUST identify the organization namespace
	  "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The &lt;org:creData&gt;
	  element contains the following child elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique
	      identifier for the created organization, as defined in <xref
	      target="org-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An &lt;org:crDate&gt; element that contains the date and time
	      of organization-object creation.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;create&gt; response:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:creData
S:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
S:        <org:crDate>2018-04-03T22:00:00.0Z</org:crDate>
S:      </org:creData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>An EPP error response MUST be returned if a &lt;create&gt; command cannot be processed for any reason.</t> 
        </section>  
        <section title="EPP &lt;delete&gt; Command"> 
          <t>The EPP &lt;delete&gt; command provides a transform operation that allows a client to delete an organization object. In addition to the standard EPP command elements, the &lt;delete&gt; command MUST contain an &lt;org:delete&gt; element. This element or its ancestor element MUST identify the organization namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The &lt;org:delete&gt; element MUST contain the following child element:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique identifier of the organization object to be deleted, as defined in <xref target="org-identifier"/>.
              </t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>An organization object MUST NOT be deleted if it is associated with other known objects. An associated organization MUST NOT be deleted until associations with other known objects have been broken. A server MUST notify clients that object relationships exist by sending a 2305 error response code when a &lt;delete&gt; command is attempted and fails due to existing object relationships.</t>  
          <t>Example &lt;delete&gt; command:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <delete>
C:      <org:delete
C:       xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
C:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
C:      </org:delete>
C:    </delete>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>When a &lt;delete&gt; command has been processed successfully, a server MUST respond with an EPP response with no &lt;resData&gt; element.</t>  
          <t>Example &lt;delete&gt; response:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>An EPP error response MUST be returned if a &lt;delete&gt; command cannot be processed for any reason.</t> 
        </section>  
        <section title="EPP &lt;renew&gt; Command"> 
          <t>Renewal semantics do not apply to organization objects, so there is no mapping defined for the EPP &lt;renew&gt; command.</t> 
        </section>  
        <section title="EPP &lt;transfer&gt; Command"> 
          <t>Transfer semantics do not apply to organization objects, so there is no mapping defined for the EPP &lt;transfer&gt; command.</t> 
        </section>  
        <section title="EPP &lt;update&gt; Command" anchor="org-update"> 
          <t>The EPP &lt;update&gt; command provides a transform operation
	  that allows a client to modify the attributes of an organization
	  object. In addition to the standard EPP command elements, the
	  &lt;update&gt; command MUST contain an &lt;org:update&gt;
	  element. This element or its ancestor element MUST identify the
	  organization namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The
	  &lt;org:update&gt; element contains the following child
	  elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique
	      identifier of the organization object to be updated, as defined
	      in <xref target="org-identifier"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:add&gt; element that contains attribute values to be added to the object.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:rem&gt; element that contains attribute
	      values to be removed from the object.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:chg&gt; element that contains attribute values to be changed.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>At least one &lt;org:add&gt;, &lt;org:rem&gt;, or &lt;org:chg&gt;
	  element MUST be provided if the command is not being extended. All
	  of these elements MAY be omitted if an &lt;update&gt; extension is
	  present. The OPTIONAL &lt;org:add&gt; and &lt;org:rem&gt; elements
	  contain the following child elements:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:contact&gt; elements that contain the
	      identifiers for contact objects to be associated with or removed
	      from the organization object. Contact object identifiers MUST be
	      known to the server before the contact object can be associated with the organization object.</t>  
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:role&gt; elements that contain the role
	      type, role statuses, and optional role ID of the organization. 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:type&gt; element that contains the role type
		  of the organization, as defined in <xref
		  target="org-role"/>. The role type uniquely identifies the
		  role to update.
                  </t>  
                  <t>Zero or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the
		  role statuses. The values of the role status are defined in
		  <xref target="role-status-value"/>.
                  </t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:roleID&gt; element that contains a third-party-assigned identifier, such as IANA ID for registrars, as defined in <xref target="role-identifier"/>.
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>Zero or more &lt;org:status&gt; elements that contain the operational status of the organization.</t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:chg&gt; element contains the following child elements, where at least one child element MUST be present:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list style="symbols"> 
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:parentId&gt; element that contains the identifier of the parent object.</t>  
              <t>Zero to two &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; elements that contain
	      postal-address information. Two elements are provided so that
	      address information can be provided in both internationalized
	      and localized forms; a "type" attribute is used to identify the
	      two forms. If an internationalized form (type="int") is
	      provided, element content MUST be represented in a subset of
	      Unicode <xref target="UNICODE"/> in the range U+0020 - U+007E. If a localized form
	      (type="loc") is provided, element content MAY be represented in
	      unrestricted UTF-8. The change of the postal info is defined as
	      a replacement of that postal info element with the contents of
	      the sub-elements included in the &lt;update&gt; command. An empty
	      &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; element is supported to allow a type of
	      postal info to be removed. The &lt;org:postalInfo&gt; element
	      contains the following child elements: 
                <list style="symbols"> 
                  <t>An &lt;org:name&gt; element that contains the name of the organization.</t>  
                  <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:addr&gt; element that contains
		  address information associated with the organization. An
		  &lt;org:addr&gt; element contains the following child
		  elements: 
                    <list style="symbols"> 
                      <t>One, two, or three &lt;org:street&gt; elements that contain the organization's street address.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:city&gt; element that contains the organization's city.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:sp&gt; element that contains the organization's state or province.</t>  
                      <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:pc&gt; element that contains the organization's postal code.</t>  
                      <t>An &lt;org:cc&gt; element that contains the alpha-2
		      organization's country code. The detailed format of this
		      element is described in Section 2.4.3 of <xref
		      target="RFC5733"/>.
                      </t> 
                    </list> 
                  </t> 
                </list> 
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:voice&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's voice telephone number. The detailed format of
	      this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:fax&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's facsimile telephone number. The detailed format of this element is described in Section 2.5 of <xref
	      target="RFC5733"/>.</t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:email&gt; element that contains the
	      organization's email address. The detailed format of this
	      element is described in <xref target="RFC5322"/>.
              </t>  
              <t>An OPTIONAL &lt;org:url&gt; element that contains the URL to
	      the website of the organization. The detailed format of this
	      element is described in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
              </t> 
            </list> 
          </t>  
          <t>Example &lt;update&gt; command:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <update>
C:      <org:update
C:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
C:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
C:        <org:add>
C:          <org:contact type="tech">sh8013</org:contact>
C:          <org:role>
C:            <org:type>privacyproxy</org:type>
C:            <org:status>clientLinkProhibited</org:status>
C:          </org:role>
C:          <org:status>clientLinkProhibited</org:status>
C:        </org:add>
C:        <org:rem>
C:          <org:contact type="billing">sh8014</org:contact>
C:          <org:role>
C:            <org:type>reseller</org:type>
C:          </org:role> 
C:        </org:rem>
C:        <org:chg>
C:          <org:postalInfo type="int">
C:            <org:addr>
C:              <org:street>124 Example Dr.</org:street>
C:              <org:street>Suite 200</org:street>
C:              <org:city>Dulles</org:city>
C:              <org:sp>VA</org:sp>
C:              <org:pc>20166-6503</org:pc>
C:              <org:cc>US</org:cc>
C:            </org:addr>
C:          </org:postalInfo>
C:          <org:voice>+1.7034444444</org:voice>
C:          <org:fax/>
C:        </org:chg>
C:      </org:update>
C:    </update>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>When an &lt;update&gt; command has been processed successfully, a server MUST respond with an EPP response with no &lt;resData&gt; element.</t>  
          <t>Example &lt;update&gt; response:</t>  
          <figure> 
            <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
          </figure>  
          <t>An EPP error response MUST be returned if an &lt;update&gt; command cannot be processed for any reason.</t> 
        </section> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Offline Review of Requested Actions"> 
        <t>Commands are processed by a server in the order they are received
	from a client. Though an immediate response confirming receipt and
	processing of the command is produced by the server, a server operator
	MAY perform an offline review of requested transform commands before
	completing the requested action. In such situations, the response from
	the server MUST clearly note that the transform command has been
	received and processed, but the requested action is pending. The
	status in the response of the corresponding object MUST clearly
	reflect processing of the pending action. The server MUST notify the
	client when offline processing of the action has been completed.</t>  

        <t>Examples describing a &lt;create&gt; command that requires offline
	review are included here. Note the result code and message returned in
	response to the &lt;create&gt; command.</t>  
        <figure> 
          <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1001">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully; 
S:        action pending</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:creData
S:        xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:id>res1523</org:id>
S:        <org:crDate>2018-04-03T22:00:00.0Z</org:crDate>
S:      </org:creData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
        </figure>  
        <t>The status of the organization object after returning this response
	MUST include "pendingCreate". The server operator reviews the request
	offline and informs the client of the outcome of the review by queuing
	a service message for retrieval via the &lt;poll&gt; command; it MAY
	additionally use an out-of-band mechanism to inform the client of the
	outcome.</t>  

        <t>The service message MUST contain text that describes the
	notification in the child &lt;msg&gt; element of the response
	&lt;msgQ&gt; element. In addition, the EPP &lt;resData&gt; element
	MUST contain a child &lt;org:panData&gt; element. This element or its
	ancestor element MUST identify the organization namespace
	"urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0". The &lt;org:panData&gt; element
	contains the following child elements:</t>  
        <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>An &lt;org:id&gt; element that contains the server-unique
	    identifier of the organization object. The &lt;org:id&gt; element
	    contains a REQUIRED "paResult" attribute. A positive boolean value
	    indicates that the request has been approved and completed. A
	    negative boolean value indicates that the request has been denied
	    and the requested action has not been taken.</t>  

<!--[rfced] We're having difficulty parsing the following item in the list. Please
advise how we may clarify. What does "to process the command" refer to?

Original:
An <org:paTRID> element that contains the client transaction
identifier and server transaction identifier returned with the
original response to process the command.
--> 
            <t>An &lt;org:paTRID&gt; element that contains the client
	    transaction identifier and server transaction identifier returned
	    with the original response to process the command. The client
	    transaction identifier is OPTIONAL and will only be returned if
	    the client provided an identifier with the original &lt;create&gt;
	    command.</t>  

            <t>An &lt;org:paDate&gt; element that contains the date and time
	    describing when review of the requested action was completed.</t> 
          </list> 
        </t>  
        <t>Example "review completed" service message:</t>  
        <figure> 
          <artwork> <![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1301">
S:      <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully; 
S:        ack to dequeue</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <msgQ count="5" id="12345">
S:      <qDate>2018-04-04T22:01:00.0Z</qDate>
S:      <msg>Pending action completed successfully.</msg>
S:    </msgQ>
S:    <resData>
S:      <org:panData
S:       xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0">
S:        <org:id paResult="1">res1523</org:id>
S:        <org:paTRID>
S:          <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:          <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:        </org:paTRID>
S:        <org:paDate>2018-04-04T22:00:00.0Z</org:paDate>
S:      </org:panData>
S:    </resData>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>BCD-23456</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>65432-WXY</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>]]> </artwork> 
        </figure> 
      </section> 
    </section>  
    <section title="Formal Syntax"> 
      <t>An EPP object mapping is specified in XML Schema notation. The formal
      syntax presented here is a complete schema representation of the object
      mapping suitable for automated validation of EPP XML instances. The
      BEGIN and END tags are not part of the schema; they are used to note the
      beginning and ending of the schema for URI registration purposes.</t>  
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

   <schema targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0"
          xmlns:org="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0"
          xmlns:epp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0"
          xmlns:eppcom="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"
          xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
          elementFormDefault="qualified">

   <!--
   Import common element types.
   -->
    <import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"/>
    <import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0"/>

    <annotation>
      <documentation>
        Extensible Provisioning Protocol v1.0
        organization provisioning schema.
      </documentation>
    </annotation>

   <!--
   Child elements found in EPP commands.
   -->
    <element name="create" type="org:createType"/>
    <element name="delete" type="org:sIDType"/>
    <element name="update" type="org:updateType"/>
    <element name="check" type="org:mIDType"/>
    <element name="info" type="org:infoType"/>
    <element name="panData" type="org:panDataType"/>

   <!--
   Utility types.
   -->
    <simpleType name="statusType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <enumeration value="ok"/>
        <enumeration value="hold"/>
        <enumeration value="terminated"/>
        <enumeration value="clientDeleteProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="clientUpdateProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="clientLinkProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="linked"/>
        <enumeration value="pendingCreate"/>
        <enumeration value="pendingUpdate"/>
        <enumeration value="pendingDelete"/>
        <enumeration value="serverDeleteProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="serverUpdateProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="serverLinkProhibited"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <simpleType name="roleStatusType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <enumeration value="ok"/>
        <enumeration value="clientLinkProhibited"/>
        <enumeration value="linked"/>
        <enumeration value="serverLinkProhibited"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <complexType name="roleType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="type" type="token"/>
        <element name="status" type="org:roleStatusType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="3"/>
        <element name="roleID" type="token" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

    <complexType name="postalInfoType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="name"
          type="org:postalLineType"/>
        <element name="addr"
          type="org:addrType" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
      <attribute name="type"
        type="org:postalInfoEnumType"
        use="required"/>
    </complexType>

    <complexType name="contactType">
      <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:clIDType">
          <attribute name="type" type="org:contactAttrType"
            use="required"/>
          <attribute name="typeName" type="token"/>
        </extension>
      </simpleContent>
    </complexType>

    <simpleType name="contactAttrType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <enumeration value="admin"/>
        <enumeration value="billing"/>
        <enumeration value="tech"/>
        <enumeration value="abuse"/>
        <enumeration value="custom"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <complexType name="e164Type">
      <simpleContent>
        <extension base="org:e164StringType">
          <attribute name="x" type="token"/>
        </extension>
      </simpleContent>
    </complexType>

    <simpleType name="e164StringType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <pattern value="(\+[0-9]{1,3}\.[0-9]{1,14})?"/>
        <maxLength value="17"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <simpleType name="postalLineType">
      <restriction base="normalizedString">
        <minLength value="1"/>
        <maxLength value="255"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <simpleType name="optPostalLineType">
      <restriction base="normalizedString">
        <maxLength value="255"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <simpleType name="pcType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <maxLength value="16"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <simpleType name="ccType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <length value="2"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

    <complexType name="addrType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="street" type="org:optPostalLineType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="3"/>
        <element name="city" type="org:postalLineType"/>
        <element name="sp" type="org:optPostalLineType"
          minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="pc" type="org:pcType"
          minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="cc" type="org:ccType"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

    <simpleType name="postalInfoEnumType">
      <restriction base="token">
        <enumeration value="loc"/>
        <enumeration value="int"/>
      </restriction>
    </simpleType>

   <!--
   Child element of commands that require only an identifier.
   -->
    <complexType name="sIDType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Child element of commands that accept multiple identifiers.
   -->
    <complexType name="mIDType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Pending action notification response elements.
   -->
    <complexType name="panDataType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id" type="org:paCLIDType"/>
        <element name="paTRID" type="epp:trIDType"/>
        <element name="paDate" type="dateTime"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

    <complexType name="paCLIDType">
      <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:clIDType">
          <attribute name="paResult" type="boolean"
           use="required"/>
        </extension>
      </simpleContent>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Child elements of the <info> commands.
   -->
    <complexType name="infoType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id"
          type="eppcom:clIDType"/> 
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Child elements of the <create> command.
   -->
    <complexType name="createType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id"
          type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
        <element name="role"
          type="org:roleType" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="status"
          type="org:statusType" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="4"/>
        <element name="parentId"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="postalInfo"
          type="org:postalInfoType" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="2"/>
        <element name="voice"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="fax"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="email"
          type="eppcom:minTokenType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="url"
          type="anyURI" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="contact"
          type="org:contactType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/> 
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Child elements of the <update> command.
   -->
    <complexType name="updateType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id"
          type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
        <element name="add"
          type="org:addRemType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="rem"
          type="org:addRemType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="chg"
          type="org:chgType" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Data elements that can be added or removed.
   -->
    <complexType name="addRemType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="contact"
          type="org:contactType" minOccurs="0"
          maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="role" type="org:roleType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="status" type="org:statusType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="9"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Data elements that can be changed.
   -->
    <complexType name="chgType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="parentId"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="postalInfo"
          type="org:chgPostalInfoType"
          minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="2"/>
        <element name="voice"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="fax"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="email"
          type="eppcom:minTokenType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="url"
          type="anyURI" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

    <complexType name="chgPostalInfoType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="name"
          type="org:postalLineType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="addr"
          type="org:addrType" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
      <attribute name="type"
        type="org:postalInfoEnumType" use="required"/>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   Child response elements.
   -->
    <element name="chkData" type="org:chkDataType"/>
    <element name="creData" type="org:creDataType"/>
    <element name="infData" type="org:infDataType"/>

   <!--
   <check> response elements.
   -->
    <complexType name="chkDataType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="cd" type="org:checkType"
          maxOccurs="unbounded" />
      </sequence>
    </complexType>
   
    <complexType name="checkType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id" type="org:checkIDType"/>
        <element name="reason" type="eppcom:reasonType"
          minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

    <complexType name="checkIDType">
      <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:clIDType">
          <attribute name="avail" type="boolean"
            use="required"/>
        </extension>
      </simpleContent>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   <info> response elements.
   -->
    <complexType name="infDataType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id"
          type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
        <element name="roid"
          type="eppcom:roidType"/>
        <element name="role"
          type="org:roleType" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="status"
          type="org:statusType" maxOccurs="9"/>
        <element name="parentId"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="postalInfo"
          type="org:postalInfoType" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="2"/>
        <element name="voice"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="fax"
          type="org:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="email"
          type="eppcom:minTokenType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="url"
          type="anyURI" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="contact"
          type="org:contactType" minOccurs="0"
          maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="clID"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="crID"
          type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
        <element name="crDate"
          type="dateTime"/>
        <element name="upID"
          type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
        <element name="upDate"
          type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>
   <!--
   <create> response elements.
   -->
    <complexType name="creDataType">
      <sequence>
        <element name="id" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
        <element name="crDate" type="dateTime"/>
      </sequence>
    </complexType>

   <!--
   End of schema.
   -->
   </schema>
   END
]]></artwork>
      </figure> 
    </section>  
    <section title="Internationalization Considerations" anchor="Internationalization"> 
      <t>EPP is represented in XML, which provides native support for encoding
      information using the Unicode character set <xref target="UNICODE"/> and its more compact
      representations, including UTF-8. Conformant XML processors recognize
      both UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/> and UTF-16 <xref
      target="RFC2781"/>. Though XML includes provisions to identify and use
      other character encodings through use of an "encoding" attribute in an
      &lt;?xml?&gt; declaration, use of UTF-8 is RECOMMENDED.
      </t>  
      <t>As an extension of the EPP organization object mapping, the elements
      and element content described in this document MUST inherit the
      internationalization conventions used to represent higher-layer domain
      and core protocol structures present in an XML instance that includes
      this extension.</t> 
    </section>  
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="Iana"> 
      <section title="XML Namespace"> 
        <t>This document uses URNs to describe XML namespaces and XML schemas conforming to a registry mechanism described in <xref target="RFC3688"/>. IANA has assigned the following URI.
        </t>  
        <t>The organization namespace:</t>  
        <t> 
          <list> 
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:org-1.0</t>  
            <t>Registrant Contact: IESG</t>  
            <t>XML: None. Namespace URIs do not represent an XML specification.</t> 
          </list> 
        </t>  
        <t>The organization XML schema:</t>  
        <t> 
          <list> 
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:epp:org-1.0</t>  
            <t>Registrant Contact: IESG</t>  
            <t>XML: See the "Formal Syntax" section of RFC 8543 (this document).</t> 
          </list> 
        </t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="EPP Extension Registry"> 
        <t>The EPP extension described in this document has been
        registered by IANA in the "Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning Protocol
   (EPP)" registry described in
        <xref target="RFC7451"/>. The details of the registration are
        as follows:
        </t>  
        <t> 
          <list> 
            <t>Name of Extension: Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) Organization Mapping</t>  
            <t>Document status: Standards Track</t>  
            <t>Reference: RFC 8543</t>  
            <t>Registrant Name and Email Address: IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>  
            <t>TLDs: Any</t>  
            <t>IPR Disclosure: None</t>  
            <t>Status: Active</t>  
            <t>Notes: None</t> 
          </list> 
        </t> 
      </section>  
      <section title="Role Type Values Registry" anchor="role"> 
        <t>IANA has created a new category of protocol registry for values of
	the organization roles. The name of this registry is "EPP Organization
	Role Values". The registration policy for this registry is "Expert
	Review" <xref target="RFC8126"/>.
        </t>  
        <section title="Registration Template"> 
          <t>Value: The string value being registered.</t>  
          <t>Description: Brief description of the organization role values.</t>
	  <t>Registrant Name: For RFC specifications, state "IESG". For other
	  specifications, give the name of the responsible party.</t>  
          <t>Registrant Contact Information: An email address, postal address,
	  or some other information to be used to contact the registrant.</t>
        </section>  
        <section title="Initial Registry Contents"> 
          <t>The following are the initial registry contents:</t>  
          <t> 
            <list> 
              <t>Value: registrar</t>  
              <t>Description: The entity object instance represents the authority responsible for the registration in the registry.</t>  
              <t>Registrant: IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>  

            </list>  
            <list> 
              <t>Value: reseller</t>  
              <t>Description: The entity object instance represents a third party through which the registration was conducted (i.e., not the registry or registrar).</t>
	      <t>Registrant: IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>  
	      
            </list>  
            <list> 
              <t>Value: privacyproxy</t>  
              <t>Description: The entity object instance represents a third
	      party who could help to register a domain without exposing the
	      registrants' private information.</t>
	       <t>Registrant: IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>  
              
            </list>  
            <list> 
              <t>Value: dns-operator</t>  
              <t>Description: The entity object instance represents a
	      third-party DNS operator that maintains the name servers and
	      zone data on behalf of a registrant.</t>  
            <t>Registrant: IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>  
            </list> 
          </t> 
        </section> 
      </section> 
    </section>  

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security"> 
      <t>The organization object may have personally identifiable information,
      such as &lt;org:contact&gt;. This information is not a required element
      in this document that can be provided on a voluntary basis. If it is
      provided, both client and server MUST ensure that authorization
      information is stored and exchanged with high-grade encryption
      mechanisms to provide privacy services, which are specified in <xref
      target="RFC5733"/>. The security considerations described in <xref
      target="RFC5730"/> or those caused by the protocol layers used by EPP
      will apply to this specification as well.
      </t> 
    </section>  
  </middle>  
  <back> 
    <references title="Normative References"> 
	  &RFC2119;
	  &RFC3629;
      &RFC3688; 
	  &RFC3986;
	  &RFC5322;
	  &RFC5646;
      &RFC5730;
	  &RFC5733;	
	  &RFC8126;
	  &RFC8174;
  <reference anchor="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"
		 target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml/">
        <front>
          <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</title>
          <author initials="T" surname="Bray">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Paoli">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="C" surname="Sperberg-McQueen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E" surname="Maler">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="F" surname="Yergeau">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2008"/>
        </front>
         <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation" value="REC-xml-20081126"/>

      </reference>

 <reference anchor="W3C.REC-xmlschema-1-20041028"
                 target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-1-20041028">
        <front>
          <title>XML Schema Part 1: Structures Second Edition</title>
          <author initials="H" surname="Thompson">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D" surname="Beech">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M" surname="Maloney">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N" surname="Mendelsohn">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004"/>
        </front>
<seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation" value="REC-xmlschema-1-20041028"/>

</reference>

      <reference anchor="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"
                 target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028">
        <front>

          <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</title>
          <author initials="P" surname="Biron">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Malhotra">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004"/>
        </front>
<seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation" value="REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"/>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor="UNICODE"
                 target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/latest/">
        <front>
          <title>The Unicode Standard</title>
          <author>
		    <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>
		  <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>  


    <references title="Informative References">
	  &RFC2781;
	  &RFC7451; 
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="acknowledgment" numbered="no"> 
      <t>The authors would like to thank Rik Ribbers, Marc Groeneweg, Patrick
      Mevzek, Antoin Verschuren, and Scott Hollenbeck for their careful review
      and valuable comments.</t> 
    </section> 

  </back> 
</rfc>
