<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="8126" seriesNo="26" category="bcp" submissionType="IETF"
  consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="5226">


  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA Considerations Section in RFCs">
    Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="Michelle Cotton">
      <organization abbrev="PTI">
        PTI, an affiliate of ICANN
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90094-2536</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-424-254-5300</phone>
        <email>michelle.cotton@iana.org</email>
        <uri>https://www.iana.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='B.' surname="Leiba" fullname='Barry Leiba'>
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 646 827 0648</phone>
        <email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
        <uri>http://internetmessagingtechnology.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='T.' surname="Narten" fullname='Thomas Narten'>
      <organization>IBM Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3039 Cornwallis Ave., PO Box 12195 - BRQA/502</street>
          <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
          <region>NC</region>
          <code>27709-2195</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 919 254 7798</phone>
        <email>narten@us.ibm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2017"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>
      Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use constants
      to identify various protocol parameters. To ensure that the values
      in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote
      interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central
      record keeper. For IETF protocols, that role is filled by the Internet
      Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).
      </t>

      <t>
      To make assignments in a given registry prudently, guidance 
      describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as well
      as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed. This document
      defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines by
      specification authors, in order to assure that the provided guidance for the
      IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the
      operation of a registry.
      </t>

      <t>This is the third edition of this document; it obsoletes RFC 5226.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use
        constants to identify various protocol parameters. To ensure that the
        values in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote
        interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central
        record keeper. The Protocol field in the IP header <xref target="RFC0791"/> and
        MIME media types <xref target="RFC6838"/> are two examples of such
        coordinations.
      </t>
      <t>
        The IETF selects an IANA Functions Operator (IFO) for protocol
        parameters defined by the IETF.  In the contract between the IETF
        and the current IFO (ICANN), that entity is referred to as the
        IANA PROTOCOL PARAMETER SERVICES Operator, or IPPSO.  For
        consistency with past practice, the IFO or IPPSO is referred to in
        this document as "IANA" <xref target="RFC2860"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        In this document, we call the range of possible values for such a
        field a "namespace". The binding or association of a specific value with
        a particular purpose within a namespace is called an assignment (or,
        variously: an assigned number, assigned value, code point, protocol
        constant, or protocol parameter). The act of assignment is called a
        registration, and it takes place in the context of a registry.
        The terms "assignment" and "registration" are used interchangably
        throughout this document.
      </t>
      <t>
        To make assignments in a given namespace prudently, guidance 
        describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as
        well as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed. This
        document defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines
        by specification authors, in order to assure that the guidance for the
        IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the
        operation of a registry.
      </t>
      <t>
        Typically, this information is recorded in a dedicated section of
        the specification with the title "IANA Considerations".
      </t>

      <section anchor="keep-it-simple" title="Keep IANA Considerations for IANA">
        <t>
          The purpose of having a dedicated IANA Considerations section is to provide
          a single place to collect clear and concise information and instructions for IANA.
          Technical documentation should reside in
          other parts of the document; the IANA Considerations should refer to these
          other sections by reference only (as needed). 
          Using the IANA Considerations section
          as primary technical documentation both hides it from the target audience of
          the document and interferes with IANA's review of the actions they need to take.
        </t>
        <t>
          An ideal IANA Considerations section clearly enumerates and specifies each
          requested IANA action; includes all information IANA needs, such as the
          full names of all applicable registries; and includes clear references
          to elsewhere in the document for other information.
        </t>
        <t>
          The IANA actions are normally phrased as requests for IANA (such as, "IANA
          is asked to assign the value TBD1 from the Frobozz Registry..."); 
          the RFC Editor will change those sentences to reflect the actions taken
          ("IANA has assigned the value 83 from the Frobozz Registry...").
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="more-info" title="For Updated Information">
        <t>
          IANA maintains a web page that includes additional clarification
          information beyond what is provided here, such as minor updates and
          summary guidance. Document authors should check that page.
          Any significant updates to the best current practice will have to feed
          into updates to BCP 26 (this document), which is definitive.
              <list style="empty"><t>
              &lt;https://iana.org/help/protocol-registration&gt;
              </t></list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="checklist" title="A Quick Checklist Upfront">
        <t>
          It's useful to be familiar with this document as a whole. But when you return for quick reference, here are checklists for the most common things you'll need to do and references to help with the less common ones.
        </t>
        <t>
          In general...
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Put all the information that IANA will need to know into the
              "IANA Considerations" section of your document (see <xref target="keep-it-simple"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Try to keep that section only for information to IANA and to designated expert reviewers; put significant technical information in the appropriate technical sections of the document (see <xref target="keep-it-simple"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Note that the IESG has the authority to resolve issues with IANA
	      registrations. If you have any questions or problems, you should consult your document shepherd and/or 
              working group chair, who may ultimately involve an Area Director (see <xref target="overriding-procedures"/>).
            </t>
          </list>          
        </t>
        <t>
          If you are creating a new registry...
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Give the registry a descriptive name and provide a brief description of its use (see <xref target="what-to-put"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Identify any registry grouping that it should be part of (see <xref target="registry-structure"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Clearly specify what information is required in order to register new items (see <xref target="what-to-put"/>).  Be sure to specify data types, lengths, and valid ranges for fields.
            </t>
            <t>
              Specify the initial set of items for the registry, if applicable (see <xref target="what-to-put"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Make sure the change control policy for the registry is clear
	      to IANA, in case changes to the format or policies need to be
	      made later (see Sections <xref target="change-control"
	      format="counter" /> and <xref
	      target="assignee" format="counter" />). 
            </t>
            <t>
              Select a registration policy -- or a set of policies -- to use
	      for future registrations (see <xref target="well-known"/>, and
	      especially note Sections <xref target="using-well-known"
	      format="counter"/> and <xref target="multiple-policies" format="counter"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              If you're using a policy that requires a designated expert
	      (Expert Review or Specification Required), understand <xref
	      target="experts"/> and provide review guidance to the
	      designated expert (see <xref target="expert-reviews"/>). 
            </t>
            <t>
              If any items or ranges in your registry need to be reserved for special use or are otherwise unavailable for assignment, see <xref target="regstatus"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          If you are registering into an existing registry...
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Clearly identify the registry by its exact name and optionally by its URL (see <xref target="put-in-existing"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              If the registry has multiple ranges from which assignments can be made, make it clear which range is requested (see <xref target="put-in-existing"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Avoid using specific values for numeric or bit assignments, and let IANA pick a suitable value at registration time (see <xref target="put-in-existing"/>).  This will avoid registration conflicts among multiple documents.
            </t>
            <t>
              For "reference" fields, use the document that provides the best
	      and most current documentation for the item being
	      registered. Include section numbers to make it easier for
	      readers to locate the relevant documentation (see Sections <xref
	      target="put-in-existing" format="counter"/> and <xref
	      target="referring" format="counter"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Look up (in the registry's reference document) what information is required for the registry and accurately provide all the necessary information (see <xref target="put-in-existing"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Look up (in the registry's reference document) any special rules or processes there may be for the registry, such as posting to a particular mailing list for comment, and be sure to follow the process (see <xref target="put-in-existing"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              If the registration policy for the registry does not already dictate the change control policy, make sure it's clear to IANA what the change control policy is for the item, in case changes to the registration need to be made later (see <xref target="assignee"/>).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          If you're writing a "bis" document or otherwise making older documents obsolete, see <xref target="bis-docs"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          If you need to make an early registration, such as for supporting test implementations during document development, rather than waiting for your document to be finished and approved, see <xref target="RFC7120"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          If you need to change the format/contents or policies for an existing registry, see <xref target="updating-existing"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          If you need to update an existing registration, see <xref target="updating-registrations"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          If you need to close down a registry because it is no longer needed, see <xref target="closing-obsoleting"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="creating" title="Creating and Revising Registries">
      <t>
        Defining a registry involves describing the namespaces to be
        created, listing an initial set of assignments (if applicable), and
        documenting guidelines on how future assignments are to be made.
      </t>
      <t>
        When defining a registry, consider structuring the namespace in such a way
        that only top-level assignments need to be made with central coordination,
        and those assignments can delegate lower-level assignments so coordination
        for them can be distributed.
        This lessens the burden on IANA for dealing with assignments, and is particularly
        useful in situations where distributed coordinators have better knowledge of their
        portion of the namespace and are better suited to handling those assignments.
      </t>

      <section anchor="registry-structure" title="Organization of Registries">
        <t>
          All registries are anchored from the IANA "Protocol Registries" page:
              <list style="empty"><t>
              &lt;https://www.iana.org/protocols&gt;
              </t></list>
        </t>
        <t>
          That page lists registries in protocol category groups, placing
          related registries together and making it easier for users of the
          registries to find the necessary information.  Clicking on the
          title of one of the registries on the IANA Protocol Registries
          page will take the reader to the details page for that registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          Unfortunately, we have been inconsistent in how we refer to these entities.
          The group names, as they are referred to here, have been variously called
          "protocol category groups",
          "groups", "top-level registries", or just "registries".  The registries
          under them have been called "registries" or "sub-registries".
        </t>
        <t>
          Regardless of the terminology used, document authors should pay
          attention to the registry groupings, should request that related registries
          be grouped together to make related registries easier to find,
          and, when creating a new registry, should check
          whether that registry might best be included in an existing group.
          That grouping information should be clearly communicated to IANA in the
          registry creation request.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="what-to-put" title="Documentation Requirements for Registries">
        <t>
          Documents that create a new namespace (or modify the definition of
          an existing space) and that expect IANA to play a role in maintaining
          that space (serving as a repository for registered values) must
          provide clear instructions on details of the namespace, either in the
          IANA Considerations section or referenced from it.
        </t>
        <t>
          In particular, such instructions must include:

          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">

            <t hangText="The name of the registry">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            This name will appear on the IANA web page and
            will be referred to in future documents that need to allocate a
            value from the new space. The full name (and abbreviation, if
            appropriate) should be provided. It is highly desirable that the
            chosen name not be easily confused with the name of another
            registry.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            When creating a registry, the group that it is a part of
            must be identified using its full name, exactly as it appears
            in the Protocol Registries list.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Providing a URL to precisely identify the registry helps IANA
            understand the request. Such URLs can be removed from the RFC
            prior to final publication or left in the document for reference.
            If you include iana.org URLs, IANA will provide corrections, if
            necessary, during their review.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Required information for registrations">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            This tells registrants what information they have to include in their
            registration requests.  Some registries require only the requested value
            and a reference to a document where use of the value is defined.
            Other registries require a more detailed registration template that
            describes relevant security considerations, internationalization considerations,
            and other such information.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Applicable registration policy">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The policy that will apply to all future requests for registration.
            See <xref target="well-known"/>.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Size, format, and syntax of registry entries">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            What fields to record in the registry, any technical requirements on registry entries
            (valid ranges for integers, length limitations on strings, and such),
            and the exact format in which registry values should be displayed.
            For numeric assignments, one should specify whether
            values are to be recorded in decimal, in hexadecimal, or in some other
            format.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Strings are expected to be ASCII, and it should be clearly specified whether
            case matters, and whether, for example, strings should be shown in the registry
            in uppercase or lowercase.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Strings that represent protocol parameters will rarely, if ever,
            need to contain non-ASCII characters.  If non-ASCII characters
            are really necessary, instructions should make it very clear that they are
            allowed and that the non-ASCII characters should be represented as Unicode
            characters using the "(U+XXXX)" convention.  Anyone creating such a registry
            should think carefully about this and consider internationalization advice
            such as that in <xref target="RFC7564"/>, Section 10.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Initial assignments and reservations">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Any initial assignments or registrations to be
            included. In addition, any ranges that are to be reserved for
            "Private Use", "Reserved", "Unassigned", etc.&nbsp;(see <xref target="regstatus"/>)
            should be indicated.
            </t>

          </list>
        </t>

        <t><figure>
          <preamble>For example, a document might specify a new registry by
          including:</preamble>
          <artwork>
    ---------------------------------------------------------------

    X. IANA Considerations

    This document defines a new DHCP option, entitled "FooBar" (see
    Section y), and assigns a value of TBD1 from the DHCP Option space
    &lt;https://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters&gt;
    [RFC2132] [RFC2939]:
                                   Data
          Tag     Name            Length      Meaning
          ----    ----            ------      -------
          TBD1    FooBar          N           FooBar server

    The FooBar option also defines an 8-bit FooType field, for which
    IANA is to create and maintain a new registry entitled
    "FooType values" used by the FooBar option.  Initial values for the
    DHCP FooBar FooType registry are given below; future assignments
    are to be made through Expert Review [BCP26].  Assignments consist 
    of a DHCP FooBar FooType name and its associated value.

          Value    DHCP FooBar FooType Name   Definition
          ----     ------------------------   ----------
          0        Reserved
          1        Frobnitz                   RFCXXXX, Section y.1
          2        NitzFrob                   RFCXXXX, Section y.2
          3-254    Unassigned
          255      Reserved
    ---------------------------------------------------------------
          </artwork>
        </figure></t>

        <t>
          For examples of documents that establish registries, consult
          <xref target="RFC3575"/>,
          <xref target="RFC3968"/>, and
          <xref target="RFC4520"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Any time IANA includes names and contact information in the public registry,
          some individuals might prefer that their contact information not be made public.
          In such cases, arrangements can be made with IANA to keep the contact
          information private.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="change-control" title="Specifying Change Control for a Registry">

        <t>
          Registry definitions and registrations within registries often need to be
          changed after they are created.  The process of making such changes is complicated
          when it is unclear who is authorized to make the changes.  For registries created
          by RFCs in the IETF stream, change control for the registry lies by default with
          the IETF, via the IESG.  The same is true for value registrations made in IETF-stream
          RFCs.
        </t>
        <t>
          Because registries can be created and registrations can be made outside the
          IETF stream,
          it can sometimes be desirable to have change control outside the IETF and IESG,
          and clear specification of change control policies is always helpful.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is advised, therefore, that all registries that are created clearly specify a
          change control policy and a change controller.  It is also advised that registries
          that allow registrations from outside the IETF stream include, for each value,
          the designation of a change controller for that value.  If the definition or
          reference for a registered value ever needs to change, or if a registered value
          needs to be deprecated, it is critical that IANA know who is authorized to make
          the change. For example, the Media Types registry <xref target="RFC6838"/> includes a "Change
          Controller" in its registration template.
          See also <xref target="assignee"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="updating-existing" title="Revising Existing Registries">
        <t>
          Updating the registration process or making changes to the format
          of an already existing (previously created) registry (whether created
          explicitly or implicitly) follows a process similar to that used when
          creating a new registry. That is, a document is produced that makes
          reference to the existing namespace and then provides detailed guidance
          for handling assignments in the registry or detailed instructions
          about the changes required.
        </t>
        <t>
          If a change requires a new column in the registry, the instructions
          need to be clear about how to populate that column for the existing
          entries.  Other changes may require similar clarity.
        </t>
        <t>
          Such documents are normally processed with the same document status as
          the document that created the registry.
          Under some circumstances, such as with a straightforward change that is
          clearly needed (such as adding a "status" column), or when an earlier
          error needs to be corrected, the IESG may approve an update to a registry
          without requiring a new document.
        </t>
        <t>
          Example documents that updated the guidelines for assignments in                                                                                                                                        
          pre-existing registries include:
          <xref target="RFC6195"/>,
          <xref target="RFC3228"/>, and
          <xref target="RFC3575"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="existing" title="Registering New Values in an Existing Registry">
      <section anchor="put-in-existing" title="Documentation Requirements for Registrations">
        <t>
          Often, documents request an assignment in an existing
          registry (one created by a previously published document).
        </t>
        <t>
          Such documents should clearly identify the registry into which each
          value is to be registered.
          Use the exact registry name as listed on
          the IANA web page, and cite the RFC where the registry is defined.
          When referring to an existing registry, providing a URL to
          precisely identify the registry is helpful (see <xref target="what-to-put"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          There is no need to mention what the assignment policy is
          when making new assignments in existing registries,
          as that should be clear from the references.
          However, if multiple assignment policies might apply, as in registries
          with different ranges that have different policies, it is
          important to make it clear which range is being requested, so that
          IANA will know which policy applies and can assign a value in the correct range.
        </t>
        <t>
          Be sure to provide all the information required for a registration, and follow any
          special processes that are set out for the registry.  Registries sometimes require
          the completion of a registration template for registration or ask registrants to
          post their request to a particular mailing list for discussion prior to registration.
          Look up the registry's reference document: the required information and special
          processes should be documented there.
        </t>
        <t>
          Normally, numeric values to be used are chosen by IANA when the document
          is approved; drafts should not specify final values.
          Instead, placeholders such as "TBD1" and "TBD2" should
          be used consistently throughout the document, giving each item to be registered
          a different placeholder.  The IANA Considerations should ask the RFC Editor to
          replace the placeholder names with the IANA-assigned values.
          When drafts need to specify numeric values for testing or early implementations,
          they will either request early allocation (see <xref target="early-allocations"/>)
          or use values that have already been set aside for testing or experimentation
          (if the registry in question allows that without explicit assignment).
          It is important that drafts not choose their own values, lest IANA
          assign one of those values to another document in the meantime.
          A draft can request a specific value in the IANA Considerations section, and IANA
          will accommodate such requests when possible, but the proposed number
          might have been assigned to some other use by the time the draft is approved.
        </t>

        <t>
          Normally, text-string values to be used are specified in the document,
          as collisions are less likely with text strings.
          IANA will consult with the authors if there is, in fact, a collision,
          and a different value has to be used.
          When drafts need to specify string values for testing or early implementations,
          they sometimes use the expected final value.  But it is often useful to
          use a draft value instead, possibly including the draft version number.
          This allows the early implementations to be distinguished from those
          implementing the final version.  A document that intends to use "foobar" in
          the final version might use "foobar-testing-draft-05" for the -05 version
          of the draft, for example.
        </t>

        <t>
          For some registries, there is a long-standing policy prohibiting
          assignment of names or codes on a vanity or organization-name basis.
          For example, codes might always be assigned sequentially unless there is a
          strong reason for making an exception. Nothing in this document is
          intended to change those policies or prevent their future application.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          As an example, the following text could be used to request
          assignment of a DHCPv6 option number:
          <list>
            <t>
              IANA is asked to assign an option code value of TBD1 to the DNS
              Recursive Name Server option and an option code value of TBD2 to
              the Domain Search List option from the DHCP option code space
              defined in Section 24.3 of RFC 3315.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The IANA Considerations section should summarize all of the IANA
          actions, with pointers to the relevant sections elsewhere in the
          document as appropriate. Including section numbers is especially
          useful when the reference document is large; the section numbers
          will make it easier for those searching the reference document to
          find the relevant information.
        </t>

        <t>
          When multiple values are requested, it is
          generally helpful to include a summary table of the additions/changes.
          It is also helpful for
          this table to be in the same format as it appears or will appear on
          the IANA web site. For example:
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          <figure><artwork>
  Value     Description          Reference
  --------  -------------------  ---------
  TBD1      Foobar               this RFC, Section 3.2
  TBD2      Gumbo                this RFC, Section 3.3
  TBD3      Banana               this RFC, Section 3.4
          </artwork></figure>
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          Note: In cases where authors feel that including the full table of changes is
          too verbose or repetitive, authors should still include the table in the draft,
          but may include a note asking that the table be removed prior to
          publication of the final RFC.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="updating-registrations" title="Updating Existing Registrations">
        <t>
          Even after a number has been assigned, some types of registrations contain
          additional information that may need to be updated over time.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, MIME media types, character sets, and language tags typically
          include more information than just the registered value itself, and may
          need updates to items
          such as point-of-contact information, security issues, pointers
          to updates, and literature references.
        </t>
        <t>
          In such cases, the document defining the namespace must clearly state who
          is responsible for maintaining and updating a registration. Depending on
          the registry, it may be appropriate to specify one or more of:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Letting registrants and/or nominated change controllers update their
              own registrations, subject to the same constraints and review as with
              new registrations.
            </t>
            <t>
              Allowing attachment of comments to the registration. This can be
              useful in cases where others have significant objections to a
              registration, but the author does not agree to change the
              registration.
            </t>
            <t>
              Designating the IESG, a designated expert, or another entity as having
              the right to change the registrant associated with a registration and
              any requirements or conditions on doing so. This is mainly to get
              around the problem when a registrant cannot be reached in order to
              make necessary updates.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="overriding-procedures" title="Overriding Registration Procedures">
        <t>
          Experience has shown that the documented IANA considerations for individual
          protocols do not always adequately cover the reality of registry operation
          or are not sufficiently clear. In addition, documented IANA considerations
          are sometimes found to be too stringent to allow even working group
          documents (for which there is strong consensus) to perform a registration
          in advance of actual RFC publication.
        </t>
        <t>
          In order to allow assignments in such cases, the IESG is granted authority
          to override registration procedures and approve assignments on a
          case-by-case basis.
        </t>
        <t>
          The intention here is not to overrule properly documented procedures or to
          obviate the need for protocols to properly document their IANA
          considerations. Rather, it is to permit assignments in specific cases where
          it is obvious that the assignment should just be made, but updating the
          IANA process beforehand is too onerous.
        </t>
        <t>
          When the IESG is required to take action as described above,
          it is a strong indicator that the applicable registration procedures
          should be updated, possibly in parallel with the work that instigated it.
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA always has the discretion to ask the IESG for advice or intervention
          when they feel it is needed, such as
          in cases where policies or procedures are unclear to them,
          where they encounter issues or questions they are unable to resolve,
          or where registration requests or patterns of requests appear to be
          unusual or abusive.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="early-allocations" title="Early Allocations">
        <t>
          IANA normally takes its actions when a document is approved for
	  publication. There are times, though, when early allocation of a
	  value is important for the
          development of a technology, for example, when early implementations are
          created while the document is still under development.
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA has a mechanism for handling such early allocations in some cases.
          See <xref target="RFC7120" /> for details.
          It is usually not necessary to explicitly mark a registry as allowing early 
          allocation, because the general rules will apply.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="well-known" title="Choosing a Registration Policy and Well-Known Policies">
      <t>
        A registration policy is the policy that controls how new
        assignments in a registry are accepted.
        There are several issues to consider when defining the registration policy.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the registry's namespace is limited, assignments will need to
        be made carefully to prevent exhaustion.
      </t>
      <t>
        Even when the space is essentially unlimited, it is still often
        desirable to have at least a minimal review prior to assignment in order to:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
          prevent the hoarding of or unnecessary wasting of values. For
          example, if the space consists of text strings, it may be
          desirable to prevent entities from obtaining large sets of strings
          that correspond to desirable names (existing company names, for
          example).
          </t>
          <t>
          provide a sanity check that the request actually makes sense
          and is necessary. Experience has shown that some level of minimal
          review from a subject matter expert is useful to prevent
          assignments in cases where the request is malformed or not
          actually needed (for example, an existing assignment for an
          essentially equivalent service already exists).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Perhaps most importantly, unreviewed extensions can impact
        interoperability and security. See <xref target='RFC6709'/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        When the namespace is essentially unlimited and there are no
        potential interoperability or security issues, assigned numbers can
        usually be given out to anyone without any subjective review. In such
        cases, IANA can make assignments directly, provided that IANA is given
        detailed instructions on what types of requests it should grant, and
        it is able to do so without exercising subjective judgement.
      </t>
      <t>
        When this is not the case, some level of review is required.
        However, it's important to balance adequate review and ease of
        registration. In many cases, those making registrations will not be
        IETF participants; requests often come from other standards
        organizations, from organizations not directly involved in standards,
        from ad-hoc community work (from an open-source project, for example),
        and so on. Registration must not be unnecessarily difficult,
        unnecessarily costly (in terms of time and other resources), nor
        unnecessarily subject to denial.
      </t>
      <t>
        While it is sometimes necessary to restrict what gets registered
        (e.g., for limited resources such as bits in a byte, or for items for
        which unsupported values can be damaging to protocol operation), in
        many cases having what's in use represented in the registry is more
        important. Overly strict review criteria and excessive cost (in time
        and effort) discourage people from even attempting to make a
        registration. If a registry fails to reflect the protocol elements
        actually in use, it can adversely affect deployment of protocols on
        the Internet, and the registry itself is devalued.
      </t>
      <t>
        Therefore, it is important to think specifically about the registration
        policy, and not just pick one arbitrarily nor copy text from another
        document.  Working groups and other document developers should use
        care in selecting appropriate registration policies when their
        documents create registries.  They should select the least strict
        policy that suits a registry's needs, and look for specific
        justification for policies that require significant community
        involvement (those stricter than Expert Review or Specification
        Required, in terms of the well-known policies).
        The needs here will vary from registry to registry, and, indeed,
        over time, and this BCP will not be the last word on the subject.
      </t>
      <t>
        The following policies are defined for common usage.
        These cover a range of typical policies that have been used
        to describe the procedures for assigning new values in a namespace.
        It is not strictly required that documents use these terms; the
        actual requirement is that the instructions to IANA be clear and
        unambiguous.  However, use of these terms is strongly recommended
        because their meanings are widely understood.  Newly minted policies,
        including ones that combine the elements of procedures associated with
        these terms in novel ways,
        may be used if none of these policies are suitable; it will help the
        review process if an explanation is included as to why that is the case.
        The terms are fully explained in the following subsections.
      </t>
      <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Private Use</t>
              <t>Experimental Use</t>
              <t>Hierarchical Allocation</t>
              <t>First Come First Served</t>
              <t>Expert Review</t>
              <t>Specification Required</t>
              <t>RFC Required</t>
              <t>IETF Review</t>
              <t>Standards Action</t>
              <t>IESG Approval</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
      </t>
      <t>
        It should be noted that it often makes sense to partition a namespace
        into multiple categories, with assignments within each category
        handled differently.
        Many protocols now partition
        namespaces into two or more parts, with one range reserved
        for Private or Experimental Use while other ranges are reserved for
        globally unique assignments assigned following some review process.
        Dividing a namespace into ranges makes it possible to have different
        policies in place for different ranges and different use cases.
      </t>
      <t>
        Similarly, it will often be useful to specify multiple policies in parallel,
        with each policy being used under different circumstances.
        For more discussion of that topic, see <xref target="multiple-policies"/>.
      </t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
      <t>
        Examples of RFCs that specify multiple policies in parallel:
        <list>
          <t>LDAP <xref target="RFC4520"/></t>
          <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers <xref target="RFC5246"/>
             (as detailed in the subsections below)</t>
          <t>MPLS Pseudowire Types Registry <xref target="RFC4446"/></t>
        </list>
      </t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
      <section anchor="policy-private" title="Private Use">
        <t>
          Private Use is for private or local use only, with the type and
          purpose defined by the local site.  No attempt is made to
          prevent multiple sites from using the same value in
          different (and incompatible) ways.
          IANA does not record assignments from registries or ranges with this
          policy (and therefore there is no need for IANA to review them)
          and assignments are not generally useful for broad
          interoperability.  It is the responsibility of the sites
          making use of the Private Use range to ensure that no
          conflicts occur (within the intended scope of use).
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>Site-specific options in DHCP <xref target="RFC2939"/></t>
            <t>Fibre Channel Port Type Registry <xref target="RFC4044"/></t>
            <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 224-255 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-experimental" title="Experimental Use">
        <t>
          Experimental Use is similar to Private Use, but with the
          purpose being to facilitate experimentation.  See
          <xref target="RFC3692"/> for details.
          IANA does not record assignments from registries or ranges with this
          policy (and therefore there is no need for IANA to review them)
          and assignments are not generally useful for broad
          interoperability.
          Unless the registry explicitly allows it, it is not appropriate for
          documents to select explicit values from registries or ranges with
          this policy. Specific experiments will select a value to use during the experiment.
        </t>
        <t>
          When code points are set aside for Experimental Use, it's important to
          make clear any expected restrictions on experimental scope.  For example,
          say whether it's acceptable to run experiments using those code points
          over the open Internet or whether such experiments should be confined to
          more closed environments.  See <xref target="RFC6994"/> for an example of
          such considerations.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Example:
          <list>
            <t>Experimental Values in IPv4, IPv6, ICMPv4, ICMPv6,
               UDP, and TCP Headers <xref target="RFC4727"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-hierarchical" title="Hierarchical Allocation">
        <t>
          With Hierarchical Allocation,
          delegated administrators are given control over part of the
          namespace and can assign values in that part of the
          namespace.  IANA makes allocations in the higher levels of the
          namespace according to one of the other policies.
        </t>
        <t>
          Examples:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>DNS names - IANA manages the top-level domains (TLDs), and, as
              <xref target="RFC1591"/> says:
              <list style="empty">
                <t>
                  Under each TLD may be created a hierarchy of names.  Generally, under
                  the generic TLDs the structure is very flat.  That is, many
                  organizations are registered directly under the TLD, and any further
                  structure is up to the individual organizations.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <t>Object Identifiers - defined by ITU-T recommendation X.208. According to
              &lt;http://www.alvestrand.no/objectid/&gt;, some registries include
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>IANA, which hands out OIDs under the "Private Enterprises" branch,</t>
                <t>ANSI, which hands out OIDs under the "US Organizations" branch, and</t>
                <t>BSI, which hands out OIDs under the "UK Organizations" branch.</t>
              </list>
	    </t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
            <t>URN namespaces - IANA registers URN Namespace IDs (NIDs <xref target="RFC8141"/>),
              and the organization registering an NID is
              responsible for allocations of URNs within that namespace.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-fcfs" title="First Come First Served">
        <t>
          For the First Come First Served policy,
          assignments are made to anyone on a
          first come, first served basis.  There is no substantive
          review of the request, other than to ensure that it is
          well-formed and doesn't duplicate an existing assignment.
          However, requests must include a minimal amount of clerical
          information, such as a point of contact (including an email
          address, and sometimes a postal address)
          and a brief description of how the value will be
          used.  Additional information specific to the type of value
          requested may also need to be provided, as defined by the
          namespace.
          For numbers, IANA generally assigns the next in-sequence unallocated
          value, but other values may be requested and assigned if an extenuating
          circumstance exists.
          With names, specific text strings can
          usually be requested.
        </t>
        <t>
          When creating a new registry with First Come First Served
          as the registration policy, in addition to the contact person field or
          reference, the registry should contain a field for change controller.
          Having a change controller for each entry for these types of registrations makes
          authorization of future modifications more clear.
          See <xref target="change-control"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is important that changes to the registration of a First Come First Served
          code point retain compatibility with the current usage of that code point,
          so changes need to be made with care.
          The change controller should not, in most cases, be requesting incompatible changes
          nor repurposing a registered code point.
          See also Sections <xref target="reclaiming" format="counter"/> and
	  <xref target="assignee" format="counter"/>. 
        </t>
        <t>
          A working group
          or any other entity that is developing a protocol based on a First Come First Served
          code point has to be extremely careful that the protocol retains wire compatibility
          with current use of the code point.  Once that is no longer true, the new work
          needs to change to a different code point (and register that use at the
          appropriate time).
        </t>
        <t>
          It is also important to understand that First Come First Served really has
          no filtering.  Essentially, any well-formed request is accepted.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>SASL mechanism names <xref target="RFC4422"/></t>
            <t>LDAP Protocol Mechanisms and LDAP Syntax <xref target="RFC4520"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-expert" title="Expert Review">
        <t>
          For the Expert Review policy, review and approval by a
          designated expert (see <xref target="experts"/>) is required.
          While this does
          not necessarily require formal documentation, information needs
          to be provided with the request for the designated expert to
          evaluate.  The registry's definition needs to make clear to
          registrants what information is necessary.  The actual process
          for requesting registrations is administered by IANA
          (see <xref target="more-info"/> for details).
        </t>
        <t>
          (This policy was also called "Designated Expert" in earlier
          editions of this document.  The current term is "Expert Review".)
        </t>
        <t>
          The required documentation and review criteria, giving clear guidance
          to the designated expert, should be provided when defining the registry.
          It is particularly important to lay out what should be considered when
          performing an evaluation and reasons for rejecting a request.
          It is also a good idea to include, when possible, a sense of whether
          many registrations are expected over time, or if the registry is
          expected to be updated infrequently or in exceptional circumstances only.
        </t>
        <t>
          Thorough understanding of <xref target="experts"/> is important when deciding
          on an Expert Review policy and designing the guidance to the designated expert.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Good examples of guidance to designated experts:
          <list>
            <t>
              Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) <xref target="RFC3748"/>, Sections 6 and 7.2
            </t>
            <t>
              North-Bound Distribution of Link-State and TE Information Using BGP
              <xref target="RFC7752"/>, Section 5.1
            </t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
        <t>
          When creating a new registry with Expert Review
          as the registration policy, in addition to the contact person field or
          reference, the registry should contain a field for change controller.
          Having a change controller for each entry for these types of registrations makes
          authorization of future modifications more clear.
          See <xref target="change-control"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>EAP Method Types <xref target="RFC3748"/></t>
            <t>HTTP Digest AKA algorithm versions <xref target="RFC4169"/></t>
            <t>URI schemes <xref target="RFC4395"/></t>
            <t>GEOPRIV Location Types <xref target="RFC4589"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-specification" title="Specification Required">
        <t>
          For the Specification Required policy, review and approval
          by a designated expert (see <xref target="experts"/>) is required,
          and the values and their meanings must be
          documented in a permanent and readily available public
          specification, in sufficient detail so that interoperability
          between independent implementations is possible.
          This policy is the same as Expert Review, with the additional
          requirement of a formal public specification.  In addition to the
          normal review of such a request, the designated expert will review
          the public specification and evaluate whether it is sufficiently
          stable and permanent, and sufficiently clear and technically sound
          to allow interoperable implementations.
        </t>
        <t>
          The intention behind
          "permanent and readily available" is that a document can
          reasonably be expected to be findable and retrievable long
          after IANA assignment of the requested value.  Publication
          of an RFC is an ideal means of achieving this requirement,
          but Specification Required is intended to also cover the
          case of a document published outside of the RFC path, including
          informal documentation.
        </t>
        <t>
          For RFC publication, formal review by the designated expert is still
          requested, but the normal RFC review process is expected
          to provide the necessary review for interoperability.
          The designated expert's review is still important, but it's equally
          important to note that when there is IETF consensus, the expert can
          sometimes be "in the rough"
          (see also the last paragraph of <xref target="expert-lifecycle"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          As with Expert Review (<xref target="policy-expert"/>), clear guidance
          to the designated expert should be provided when defining the registry, and
          thorough understanding of <xref target="experts"/> is important.
        </t>
        <t>
          When specifying this policy, just use the term "Specification Required".
          Some specifications have chosen to refer to it as "Expert Review with
          Specification Required", and that only causes confusion.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>Diffserv-aware TE Bandwidth Constraints Model Identifiers <xref target="RFC4124"/></t>
            <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 64-223 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
            <t>ROHC Profile Identifiers <xref target="RFC5795"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-rfc" title="RFC Required">
        <t>
          With the RFC Required policy, the registration request, along with
          associated documentation, must be published in an RFC.
          The RFC need not be in the IETF stream, but may be in any RFC stream
          (currently an RFC may be in the IETF, IRTF, IAB, or 
          Independent Submission streams <xref target="RFC5742"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Unless otherwise specified, any type of RFC is sufficient
          (currently Standards Track, BCP, Informational, Experimental,
          or Historic).
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>DNSSEC DNS Security Algorithm Numbers <xref target="RFC6014"/></t>
            <t>Media Control Channel Framework registries <xref target="RFC6230"/></t>
            <t>DANE TLSA Certificate Usages <xref target="RFC6698"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-ietf" title="IETF Review">
        <t>
          (Formerly called "IETF Consensus" in the first edition of this document.)
          With the IETF Review policy,
          new values are assigned only through RFCs in the IETF Stream --
          those that have been shepherded through the IESG as AD-Sponsored or
          IETF working group documents <xref target="RFC2026"/> <xref target="RFC5378"/>,
          have gone through IETF Last Call, and have been approved by the IESG as having IETF consensus.
        </t>
        <t>
          The intent is that the document and proposed assignment will
          be reviewed by the IETF community (including appropriate IETF
          working groups, directorates, and other experts) and by the IESG,
          to ensure that the proposed assignment will not negatively
          affect interoperability or otherwise extend IETF protocols
          in an inappropriate or damaging manner.
        </t>
        <t>
          Unless otherwise specified, any type of RFC is sufficient
          (currently Standards Track, BCP, Informational, Experimental,
          or Historic).
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>IPSECKEY Algorithm Types <xref target="RFC4025"/></t>
            <t>Accounting-Auth-Method AVP values in DIAMETER <xref target="RFC4005"/></t>
            <t>TLS Extension Types <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-standards" title="Standards Action">
        <t>
          For the Standards Action policy,
          values are assigned only through Standards Track or Best Current Practice
          RFCs in the IETF Stream.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>BGP message types <xref target="RFC4271"/></t>
            <t>Mobile Node Identifier option types <xref target="RFC4283"/></t>
            <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 0-63 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
            <t>DCCP Packet Types <xref target="RFC4340"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-iesg" title="IESG Approval">
        <t>
          New assignments may be approved by the IESG.
          Although there is no requirement that the request be
          documented in an RFC, the IESG has the discretion to request
          documents or other supporting materials on a case-by-case
          basis.
        </t>
        <t>
          IESG Approval is not intended to be used often or as a
          "common case"; indeed, it has seldom been used in practice.
          Rather, it is
          intended to be available in conjunction with other policies
          as a fall-back mechanism in the case where one of the other
          allowable approval mechanisms cannot be employed in a timely
          fashion or for some other compelling reason.  IESG Approval
          is not intended to circumvent the public review processes
          implied by other policies that could have been employed for
          a particular assignment.  IESG Approval would be
          appropriate, however, in cases where expediency is desired
          and there is strong consensus (such as from a working group)
          for making the assignment.
        </t>
        <t>
          Before approving a request, the IESG might consider consulting the community,
          via a "call for comments" that provides as much information as is reasonably
          possible about the request.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          Examples:
          <list>
            <t>IPv4 Multicast address assignments <xref target="RFC5771"/></t>
            <t>IPv4 IGMP Type and Code values <xref target="RFC3228"/></t>
            <t>Mobile IPv6 Mobility Header Type and Option values <xref target="RFC6275"/></t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="using-well-known" title="Using the Well-Known Registration Policies">
        <t>
          Because the well-known policies benefit from both community
          experience and wide understanding, their use is encouraged, and
          the creation of new policies needs to be accompanied by
          reasonable justification.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is also acceptable to cite one or more well-known policies and
          include additional guidelines for what kind of considerations should
          be taken into account by the review process.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, for media-type registrations <xref target="RFC6838"/>,
          a number of different situations are covered that involve the use of
          IETF Review and Specification Required, while also including
          specific additional criteria the designated expert should follow.
          This is not meant to represent a registration procedure, but to show 
          an example of what can be done when special circumstances need to be
          covered.
        </t>
        <t>
          The well-known policies from "First Come First Served" to
          "Standards Action" specify a range of policies in increasing order
          of strictness (using the numbering from the full list in
          <xref target="well-known"/>):
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">
            <t hangText="4.">First Come First Served<vspace/>
              No review, minimal documentation.</t>
<!-- [rfced] We recommend separating this bullet into two items for
readability. 

Original:
   5/6. Expert Review / Specification Required
        Expert review with sufficient documentation for review.  /
        Significant stable public documentation sufficient for
	interoperability.

Suggested:
   5.   Expert Review 
        Expert review with sufficient documentation for review. 

   6.   Specification Required
        Significant stable public documentation sufficient for
	interoperability.

[Barry] Try this, and let me know what you think.
-->
            <t hangText="5 and 6">(of equal strictness).
              <list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">
                <t hangText="5.">Expert Review<vspace/>
                  Expert review with sufficient documentation for review.</t>
                <t hangText="6.">Specification Required<vspace/>
                  Significant stable public documentation sufficient for interoperability.</t>
              </list></t>
            <t hangText="7.">RFC Required<vspace/>
              Any RFC publication, IETF or a non-IETF Stream.</t>
            <t hangText="8.">IETF Review<vspace/>
              RFC publication, IETF Stream only, but need not be Standards Track.</t>
            <t hangText="9.">Standards Action<vspace/>
              RFC publication, IETF Stream, Standards Track or BCP only.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Examples of situations that might merit IETF
          Review or Standards Action include the following:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              When a resource is limited, such as bits in a byte (or in two
              bytes, or four), or numbers in a limited range. In these cases,
              allowing registrations that haven't been carefully reviewed and
              agreed to by community consensus could too quickly deplete the
              allowable values.
            </t>
            <t>
              When thorough community review is necessary to avoid extending
              or modifying the protocol in ways that could be damaging. One
              example is in defining new command codes, as opposed to options
              that use existing command codes: the former might require a strict
              policy, where a more relaxed policy could be adequate for the
              latter. Another example is in defining protocol elements that
              change the semantics of existing operations.
            </t>
            <t>
              When there are security implications with respect to the resource,
              and thorough review is needed to ensure that the new usage is sound.
              Examples of this include lists of acceptable hashing and cryptographic
              algorithms, and assignment of transport ports in the system range.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          When reviewing a document that asks IANA to create a new registry
          or change a registration policy to any policy more stringent than
          Expert Review or Specification Required, the IESG should ask for
          justification to ensure that more relaxed policies have been
          considered and that the more strict policy is the right one.
        </t>
        <t>
          Accordingly, document developers need to anticipate this and
          document their considerations for selecting the specified policy
          (ideally, in the document itself; failing that, in the shepherd
          writeup). Likewise, the document shepherd should ensure that the
          selected policies have been justified before sending the document to
          the IESG.
        </t>
        <t>
          When specifications are revised, registration policies should be
          reviewed in light of experience since the policies were set.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="multiple-policies" title="Using Multiple Policies in Combination">
        <t>
          In some situations, it is necessary to define multiple registration policies.
          For example, registrations through the normal IETF process might
          use one policy, while registrations from outside the process would have a
          different policy applied.
        </t>
        <t>
          Thus, a particular registry might want to use a policy such as
          "RFC Required" or "IETF Review" sometimes, with a designated expert
          checking a "Specification Required" policy at other times.
        </t>
        <t>
          The alternative to using a combination requires either that all
          requests come through RFCs or that requests in RFCs go through
          review by the designated expert, even though they already have
          IETF review and consensus.
        </t>
        <t>
          This can be documented in the IANA Considerations section when
          the registry is created, for example:
          <list style="empty">
            <t>
              IANA is asked to create the registry "Fruit Access Flags" under
              the "Fruit Parameters" group. New registrations will be
              permitted through either the IETF Review policy or the
              Specification Required policy [BCP26].  The latter should be
              used only for registrations requested by SDOs outside the IETF.
              Registrations requested in IETF documents will be subject to
              IETF review.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Such combinations will commonly use one of {Standards Action,
          IETF Review, RFC Required} in combination with one of
          {Specification Required, Expert Review}.
          Guidance should be provided about when each policy is appropriate,
          as in the example above.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="provisional" title="Provisional Registrations">
        <t>
          Some existing registries have policies that allow provisional
          registration: see URI Schemes <xref target="RFC7595"/> and
          Email Header Fields <xref target="RFC3864"/>. Registrations
          that are designated as provisional are usually defined as
          being more readily created, changed, reassigned, moved to
          another status, or removed entirely.  URI Schemes, for
          example, allow provisional registrations to be made with
          incomplete information.
        </t>
        <t>
          Allowing provisional registration ensures that the primary
          goal of maintaining a registry &mdash; avoiding collisions
          between incompatible semantics &mdash; is achieved without the
          side effect of "endorsing" the protocol mechanism the
          provisional value is used for.  Provisional registrations for
          codepoints that are ultimately standardized can be promoted to
          permanent status. The criteria that are defined for converting
          a provisional registration to permanent will likely be more
          strict than those that allowed the provisional registration.
        </t>
        <t>
          If your registry does not have a practical limit on
          codepoints, perhaps adding the option for provisional
          registrations might be right for that registry as well.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="experts" title="Designated Experts">
      <section anchor="experts-motivation" title="The Motivation for Designated Experts">
        <t>
          Discussion on a mailing list can provide valuable technical
          feedback, but opinions often vary and discussions may continue for some
          time without clear resolution.  In addition, IANA cannot participate
          in all of these mailing lists and cannot determine if or when such
          discussions reach consensus.  Therefore, IANA relies on a "designated
          expert" for advice regarding the specific question of whether an
          assignment should be made.  The designated expert is an individual
          who is responsible for carrying out an appropriate evaluation and
          returning a recommendation to IANA.
        </t>
        <t>
          It should be noted that a key motivation for having designated
          experts is for the IETF to provide IANA with a subject matter expert
          to whom the evaluation process can be delegated.  IANA forwards
          requests for an assignment to the expert for evaluation, and the
          expert (after performing the evaluation) informs IANA as to whether
          or not to make the assignment or registration.
          In most cases, the registrants do not work directly with the designated
          experts.
          The list of designated experts for a registry is listed in the registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          It will often be useful to use a designated expert only some of the time,
          as a supplement to other processes.  For more discussion of that topic,
          see <xref target="multiple-policies"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="experts-role" title="The Role of the Designated Expert">
        <t>
          The designated expert is responsible for coordinating
          the appropriate review of an assignment request.  The review may be
          wide or narrow, depending on the situation and the judgment of the
          designated expert.  This may involve consultation with a set of
          technology experts, discussion on a public mailing list, consultation
          with a working group (or its mailing list if the working group has
          disbanded), etc.  Ideally, the designated expert follows specific
          review criteria as documented with the protocol that creates or uses
          the namespace.  See the IANA Considerations sections of <xref target="RFC3748"/>
          and <xref target="RFC3575"/> for specific examples.
        </t>
        <t>
          Designated experts are expected to be able to defend their decisions
          to the IETF community, and the evaluation process is not intended to
          be secretive or bestow unquestioned power on the expert.  Experts are
          expected to apply applicable documented review or vetting procedures,
          or in the absence of documented criteria, follow generally accepted
          norms such as those in <xref target="expert-reviews"/>.
          Designated experts are generally not expected to be "gatekeepers",
          setting out to make registrations difficult to obtain,
          unless the guidance in the defining document specifies that they should
          act as such.  Absent stronger guidance, the experts should be evaluating
          registration requests for completeness, interoperability, and conflicts
          with existing protocols and options.
        </t>
        <t>
          It has proven useful to have multiple designated experts for some registries.
          Sometimes those experts work together in evaluating a
          request, while in other cases additional experts serve as backups,
          acting only when the primary expert is unavailable.
          In registries with a pool of experts, the pool
          often has a single chair responsible for defining how requests are
          to be assigned to and reviewed by experts.
          In other cases, IANA might assign requests to individual members in
          sequential or approximate random order.
          The document defining the registry can, if it's appropriate for the
          situation, specify how the group should work -- for example, it might
          be appropriate to specify rough consensus on a mailing list, within
          a related working group or among a pool of designated experts.
        </t>
        <t>
          In cases of disagreement among multiple experts, it is the
          responsibility of those experts to make a single clear recommendation
          to IANA.  It is not appropriate for IANA to resolve disputes among
          experts.  In extreme situations, such as deadlock, the designating body
          may need to step in to resolve the problem.
        </t>
        <t>
          If a designated expert has a conflict of interest for a particular review
          (is, for example, an author or significant proponent of a specification
          related to the registration under review), that expert should recuse himself.
          In the event that all the designated experts are conflicted, they should ask
          that a temporary expert be designated for the conflicted review.
          The responsible AD may then appoint someone or the AD may handle the review.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document defines the designated expert mechanism with respect
          to documents in the IETF stream only.  If other streams want to use
          registration policies that require designated experts, it is up to
          those streams (or those documents) to specify how those designated experts
          are appointed and managed.  What is described below, with management
          by the IESG, is only appropriate for the IETF stream.
        </t>

        <section anchor="expert-management" title="Managing Designated Experts in the IETF">
          <t>
            Designated experts for registries created by the IETF are appointed by the IESG,
            normally upon recommendation by the relevant Area Director.
            They may be appointed at the time a document creating or updating a namespace
            is approved by the IESG, or subsequently, when the first registration request
            is received.
            Because experts originally appointed may later
            become unavailable, the IESG will appoint replacements as necessary.
            The IESG may remove any designated expert that it appointed, at its discretion.
          </t>
          <t>
            The normal appeals process, as described in <xref target="RFC2026"/>, Section 6.5.1,
            applies to issues that arise with the designated expert team.
            For this purpose, the designated expert team takes the place of the working group
            in that description.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="expert-reviews" title="Designated Expert Reviews">
        <t>
          In the years since <xref target="RFC2434" /> was published and put to
          use, experience has led to the following observations:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              A designated expert must respond in a timely fashion, normally
              within a week for simple requests to a few weeks for more
              complex ones.  Unreasonable delays can cause significant
              problems for those needing assignments, such as when products
              need code points to ship.  This is not to say that all reviews
              can be completed under a firm deadline, but they must be
              started, and the requester and IANA should have some
              transparency into the process if an answer cannot be given
              quickly.
            </t>
            <t>
              If a designated expert does not respond to IANA's requests
              within a reasonable period of time, either with a response or
              with a reasonable explanation for the delay (some requests
              may be particularly complex), and if this is a recurring event,
              IANA must raise the issue with the IESG.  Because of the
              problems caused by delayed evaluations and assignments, the IESG
              should take appropriate actions to ensure that the expert
              understands and accepts his or her responsibilities, or appoint
              a new expert.
            </t>
            <t>
              The designated expert is not required to personally bear the
              burden of evaluating and deciding all requests, but acts as a
              shepherd for the request, enlisting the help of others as
              appropriate.  In the case that a request is denied, and
              rejecting the request is likely to be controversial, the expert
              should have the support of other subject matter experts.  That
              is, the expert must be able to defend a decision to the
              community as a whole.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          When a designated expert is used, the documentation should give
          clear guidance to the designated expert, laying out criteria for
          performing an evaluation and reasons for rejecting a request.
          In the case where there are no specific documented criteria, the
          presumption should be that a code point should be granted unless
          there is a compelling reason to the contrary (and see also
          <xref target="expert-lifecycle"/>).
          Reasons that have been used to deny requests have included these:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Scarcity of code points, where the finite remaining code points
              should be prudently managed, or where a request for a large
              number of code points is made and a single code point is the
              norm.
            </t>
            <t>
              Documentation is not of sufficient clarity to evaluate or ensure
              interoperability.
            </t>
            <t>
              The code point is needed for a protocol extension, but the
              extension is not consistent with the documented (or generally
              understood) architecture of the base protocol being extended
              and would be harmful to the protocol if widely deployed.  It is
              not the intent that "inconsistencies" refer to minor differences
              "of a personal preference nature".  Instead, they refer to
              significant differences such as inconsistencies with the
              underlying security model, implying a change to the semantics of
              an existing message type or operation, requiring unwarranted
              changes in deployed systems (compared with alternate ways of
              achieving a similar result), etc.
            </t>
            <t>
              The extension would cause problems with existing deployed
              systems.
            </t>
            <t>
              The extension would conflict with one under active development
              by the IETF, and having both would harm rather than foster
              interoperability.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Documents must not name the
          designated expert(s) in the document itself; instead, any suggested
          names should be relayed to the appropriate Area Director at the time
          the document is sent to the IESG for approval. This is usually done
          in the document shepherd writeup.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the request should also be reviewed on a specific public mailing
          list, its address should be specified.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="expert-lifecycle" title="Expert Reviews and the Document Lifecycle">
        <t>
          Review by the designated expert is necessarily done at a particular point in time
          and represents review of a particular version of the document.
          While reviews are generally done around the time of IETF Last Call,
          deciding when the review should take place is a question of good judgment.
          And while rereviews might be done when it's acknowledged that the documentation
          of the registered item has changed substantially, making sure that rereview
          happens requires attention and care.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is possible, through carelessness, accident, inattentiveness, or even
          willful disregard, that changes might be made after the designated expert's
          review and approval that would, if the document were rereviewed, cause the expert
          not to approve the registration.  It is up to the IESG, with the token held by
          the responsible Area Director, to be alert to such situations and to
          recognize that such changes need to be checked.
        </t>
        <t>
          For registrations made from documents on the Standards Track, there is often
          expert review required (by the registration policy) in addition to IETF consensus
          (for approval as a Standards Track RFC).  In such cases, the review by the
          designated expert needs to be timely, submitted before the IESG evaluates the
          document.  The IESG should generally not hold the document up
	  waiting for a late
          review.  It is also not intended for the expert review to override IETF consensus:
          the IESG should consider the review in its own evaluation, as it would do for other
          Last Call reviews.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="regstatus" title="Well-Known Registration Status Terminology">
      <t>
   The following labels describe the status of an assignment or range of
   assignments:
        <list style="empty"><t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
          <t hangText="Private Use:">
            Private use only (not assigned), as described in <xref target="policy-private"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Experimental:">
            Available for general experimental use as described in
            <xref target="RFC3692"/>.  IANA does not record specific
            assignments for any particular use.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Unassigned:">
            Not currently assigned, and available for assignment via documented procedures.
            While it's generally clear that any values that are not registered are unassigned
            and available for assignment, it is sometimes useful to explicitly specify that
            situation.
            Note that this is distinctly different from "Reserved".
          </t>
          <t hangText="Reserved:">
            Not assigned and not available for assignment.
            Reserved values are held for special uses,
            such as to extend the namespace when it becomes exhausted.
            "Reserved" is also sometimes used to designate values that had been assigned
            but are no longer in use, keeping them set aside as long as other unassigned
            values are available.
            Note that this is distinctly different from "Unassigned".
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Reserved values can be released for assignment by the change controller
            for the registry (this is often the IESG, for registries created by RFCs
            in the IETF stream).
          </t>
          <t hangText="Known Unregistered Use:">
            It's known that the assignment or range is in use without having been
            defined in accordance with reasonable practice.  Documentation for use
            of the assignment or range may be unavailable, inadequate, or conflicting.
            This is a warning against use, as well as an alert to network operators
            who might see these values in use on their networks.
          </t>
        </list></t></list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="referring" title="Documentation References in IANA Registries">
      <t>
        Usually, registries and registry entries include references to documentation (RFCs
        or other documents).  The purpose of these references is to provide pointers for
        implementors to find details necessary for implementation, NOT to simply note what
        document created the registry or entry.  Therefore:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            If a document registers an item that is defined and explained elsewhere, the
            registered reference should be to the document containing the definition,
            not to the document that is merely performing the registration.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the registered item is defined and explained in the current document,
            it is important to include sufficient information to enable implementors to
            understand the item and to create a proper implementation.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the registered item is explained primarily in a specific section of the
            reference document, it is useful to include a section reference.
            For example, "[RFC4637], Section 3.2", rather than just "[RFC4637]".
          </t>
          <t>
            For documentation of a new registry, the reference should provide information
            about the registry itself, not just a pointer to the creation of it.
            Useful information includes the purpose of the registry, a rationale for its
            creation, documentation of the process and policy for new registrations,
            guidelines for new registrants or designated experts, and other such
            related information.
            But note that, while it's important to include this information in the
            document, it needn't all be in the IANA Considerations
            section.  See <xref target="keep-it-simple"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bis-docs" title='What to Do in "bis" Documents'>
      <t>
        On occasion, an RFC is issued that obsoletes a previous edition of the
        same document. We sometimes call these "bis" documents, such as when
        RFC 4637 is to be obsoleted by draft-ietf-foo-rfc4637bis. When the original
        document created registries and/or registered entries, there is a
        question of how to handle the IANA Considerations section in the "bis"
        document.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the registrations specify the original document as a reference,
        those registrations should be updated to point to the current (not
        obsolete) documentation for those items. Usually, that will mean
        changing the reference to be the "bis" document.
      </t>
      <t>
        There will, though, be times when a document updates another,
        but does not make it obsolete, and
        the definitive reference is changed for some items but not for others.
        Be sure that the references always point to the correct,
        current documentation for each item.
      </t>
      <t>
        For example, suppose RFC 4637 registered the "BANANA" flag in the
        "Fruit Access Flags" registry, and the documentation for that flag is
        in Section 3.2.
        
        <figure>
          <preamble>The current registry might look, in part, like this:</preamble>
          <artwork>
   Name      Description          Reference
   --------  -------------------  ---------
   BANANA    Flag for bananas     [RFC4637], Section 3.2
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        If draft-ietf-foo-rfc4637bis obsoletes RFC 4637 and, because of some
        rearrangement, now documents the flag in Section 4.1.2, the IANA
        Considerations of the bis document might contain text such as this:
<figure><artwork>
   IANA is asked to change the registration information for the
   BANANA flag in the "Fruit Access Flags" registry to the 
   following:

   Name      Description          Reference
   --------  -------------------  ---------
   BANANA    Flag for bananas     [[this RFC]], Section 4.2.1
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        In many cases, if there are a number of registered references to the
        original RFC and the document organization has not changed the
        registered section numbering much, it may simply be reasonable to do
        this:
        <list style="empty"><t>
        Because this document obsoletes RFC 4637,
        IANA is asked to change all registration information that references
        [RFC4637] to instead reference [[this RFC]].
        </t></list>
      </t>
      <t>
        If information for registered items has been or is being moved to
        other documents, then the registration information should be changed
        to point to those other documents. In most cases, documentation
        references should not be left pointing to the obsoleted document
        for registries or registered items that are still in current use.
        For registries or registered items that are no longer in current
        use, it will usually make sense to leave the references pointing
        to the old document -- the last current reference for the obsolete
        items.  The main point is to make sure that the reference pointers
        are as useful and current as is reasonable, and authors should
        consider that as they write the IANA Considerations for the new
        document.  As always: do the right thing, and there is flexibility
        to allow for that.
      </t>
      <t>
        It is extremely important to be clear in your instructions regarding
        updating references, especially in cases where some references need to
        be updated and others do not.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="misc" title="Miscellaneous Issues">
      <section anchor="misc-no-actions" title="When There Are No IANA Actions">
        <t>
          Before an Internet-Draft can be published as an RFC, IANA needs to
          know what actions (if any) it needs to perform.  Experience has shown
          that it is not always immediately obvious whether a document has no
          IANA actions, without reviewing the document in some detail.  In
          order to make it clear to IANA that it has no actions to perform (and
          that the author has consciously made such a determination), such
          documents should, after the authors confirm that this is the case,
          include an IANA Considerations section that states:
          <list>
            <t>
              This document has no IANA actions.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA prefers that these "empty" IANA Considerations sections be left
          in the document for the record: it makes it clear later on that the
          document explicitly said that no IANA actions were needed (and that
          it wasn't just omitted).
          This is a change from the prior practice
          of requesting that such sections be removed by the RFC Editor, and authors
          are asked to accommodate this change.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="lacking-guidance" title="Namespaces Lacking Documented Guidance">
        <t>
          For all existing RFCs that either explicitly or implicitly rely on
          IANA to make assignments without specifying a precise assignment
          policy, IANA will work with the IESG to decide
          what policy is appropriate.  Changes to existing policies can always
          be initiated through the normal IETF consensus process, or through
          the IESG when appropriate.
        </t>
        <t>
          All future RFCs that either explicitly or implicitly rely on IANA to
          register or otherwise administer namespace assignments must provide
          guidelines for administration of the namespace.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="after-fact" title="After-the-Fact Registrations">
        <t>
          Occasionally, the IETF becomes aware that an unassigned value from a
          namespace is in use on the Internet or that an assigned value
          is being used for a different purpose than it was registered for.
          The IETF does not condone such misuse; procedures of the type
          described in this document need to be applied to such cases,
          and it might not always be possible to formally assign the desired value.
          In the absence of specifications to the contrary, values may only be
          reassigned for a different purpose with the consent of the original
          assignee (when possible) and with due consideration of the impact of
          such a reassignment.  In cases of likely controversy, consultation
          with the IESG is advised.
        </t>
        <t>
          This is part of the reason for the advice in <xref target="put-in-existing"/>
          about using placeholder values, such as "TBD1", during document development:
          problems are often caused by the open use of unregistered values after results
          from well-meant, early implementations,
          where the implementations retained the use of developmental code points that never
          proceeded to a final IANA assignment.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="reclaiming" title="Reclaiming Assigned Values">
        <t>
          Reclaiming previously assigned values for reuse is tricky, because
          doing so can lead to interoperability problems with deployed systems
          still using the assigned values.  Moreover, it can be extremely
          difficult to determine the extent of deployment of systems making use
          of a particular value.  However, in cases where the namespace is
          running out of unassigned values and additional ones are needed, it
          may be desirable to attempt to reclaim unused values.  When
          reclaiming unused values, the following (at a minimum) should be
          considered:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Attempts should be made to contact the original party to which a
              value is assigned, to determine if the value was ever used, and
              if so, the extent of deployment.  (In some cases, products were
              never shipped or have long ceased being used.  In other cases,
              it may be known that a value was never actually used at all.)
            </t>
            <t>
              Reassignments should not normally be made without the
              concurrence of the original requester.  Reclamation under such
              conditions should only take place where there is strong evidence
              that a value is not widely used, and the need to reclaim the
              value outweighs the cost of a hostile reclamation.
              IESG Approval is needed in this case.
            </t>
            <t>
              It may be appropriate to write up the proposed action and
              solicit comments from relevant user communities.  In some cases,
              it may be appropriate to write an RFC that goes through a formal
              IETF process (including IETF Last Call) as was done when DHCP
              reclaimed some of its "Private Use" options <xref target="RFC3942"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              It may be useful to differentiate between revocation, release, and
              transfer. Revocation occurs when IANA removes an assignment, release
              occurs when the assignee initiates that removal, and transfer occurs
              when either revocation or release is coupled with immediate
              reassignment. It may be useful to specify procedures for each of these
              or to explicitly prohibit combinations that are not desired.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="assignee" title="Contact Person vs Assignee or Owner">
        <t>
          Many registries include designation of a technical or administrative contact
          associated with each entry.  Often, this is recorded as contact information for
          an individual.  It is unclear, though, what role the individual has with respect
          to the registration: is this item registered on behalf of the individual,
          the company the individual worked for, or perhaps another organization the
          individual was acting for?
        </t>
        <t>
          This matters because some time later, when the individual has changed jobs or roles,
          and perhaps can no longer be contacted, someone might want to update the registration.
          IANA has no way to know what company, organization, or individual should be allowed
          to take the registration over.  For registrations rooted in RFCs, the stream owner
          (such as the IESG or the IAB) can make an overriding decision.  But in other cases,
          there is no recourse.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registries can include, in addition to a "Contact" field, an "Assignee"
          or "Owner" field (also referred to as "Change Controller") that can be
          used to address this situation,
          giving IANA clear guidance as to the actual owner of the registration.
          This is strongly advised, especially for registries that do not require
          RFCs to manage their information (e.g., registries with policies such as
          First Come First Served (<xref target="policy-fcfs"/>),
          Expert Review (<xref target="policy-expert"/>), and
          Specification Required (<xref target="policy-specification"/>)).
          Alternatively, organizations can put an organizational role into the "Contact"
          field in order to make their ownership clear.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="closing-obsoleting" title="Closing or Obsoleting a Registry/Registrations">
        <t>
          Sometimes there is a request to "close" a registry to further registrations.
          When a registry is closed, no further registrations will be accepted.
          The information in the registry will still be valid and registrations
          already in the registry can still be updated.
        </t>

        <t>
          A closed registry can also be marked as "obsolete", as an indication that
          the information in the registry is no longer in current use.
        </t>

        <t>
          Specific entries in a registry can be marked as "obsolete" (no longer in
          use) or "deprecated" (use is not recommended).
        </t>

        <t>
          Such changes to registries and registered values are subject to normal
          change controls (see <xref target="change-control"/>).
          Any closure, obsolescence, or deprecation serves to annotate the registry involved;
          the information in the registry remains there for informational and historic purposes.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="appeals" title="Appeals">
      <t>
        Appeals of protocol parameter registration decisions can be made using the
        normal IETF appeals process as described in <xref target="RFC2026"/>, Section 6.5.
        That is, an initial appeal should be directed to the IESG,
        followed (if necessary) by an appeal to the IAB.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mailing-lists" title="Mailing Lists">
      <t>
<!-- [rfce] Please note that we lowercased "Best Current Practices" because
we believe it refers to generally good practice, as opposed to the status of
various documents.  Please let us know if this is incorrect. 

Original:
   All IETF mailing lists associated with evaluating or discussing
   assignment requests as described in this document are subject to
   whatever rules of conduct and methods of list management are
   currently defined by Best Current Practices or by IESG decision.
-->
        All IETF mailing lists associated with evaluating or discussing
        assignment requests as described in this document are subject to
        whatever rules of conduct and methods of list management are
        currently defined by best current practices or by IESG decision.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Information that creates or updates a registration needs to be
        authenticated and authorized.  IANA updates registries according to
        instructions in published RFCs and from the IESG.  It may also accept
        clarifications from document authors, relevant working group chairs, designated
        experts, and mail list participants.
      </t>
      <t>
        Information concerning possible security vulnerabilities of a
        protocol may change over time.  Likewise, security vulnerabilities
        related to how an assigned number is used may change as well.
        As new vulnerabilities are discovered,
        information about such vulnerabilities may need to be attached to
        existing registrations so that users are not misled as to the true
        security issues surrounding the use of a registered number.
      </t>
      <t>
        Security needs to be considered as part of the selection of a registration policy.
        For some protocols, registration of certain parameters will have security implications,
        and registration policies for the relevant registries must ensure that requests get
        appropriate review with those security implications in mind.
      </t>
      <t>
        An analysis of security issues is generally required for all
        protocols that make use of parameters (data types, operation codes,
        keywords, etc.) documented in IETF protocols or registered by IANA. Such
        security considerations are usually included in the protocol document
        <xref target="BCP72"/>.  It is the responsibility of the IANA considerations
        associated with a particular registry to specify whether value-specific
        security considerations must be provided when assigning new values and
	the process for reviewing such claims.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
Sitewide, IANA has replaced references to RFC 5226 with references to this document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="changes" title="Changes Relative to Earlier Editions of BCP 26">

      <section title="2016: Changes in This Document Relative to RFC 5226">
        <t>Significant additions:
          <list style="symbols">

            <t>Removed RFC 2119 key words, boilerplate, and reference, preferring plain English -- this is not a protocol specification.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="keep-it-simple"/>, Keep IANA Considerations for IANA</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="more-info"/>, For Updated Information</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="registry-structure"/>, Organization of Registries</t>

            <t>Added best practice for selecting an appropriate policy into  <xref target="well-known"/>.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="multiple-policies"/>, Using Multiple Policies in Combination</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="change-control"/>, Specifying Change Control for a Registry</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="early-allocations"/>, Early Allocations</t>

            <t>Moved each well-known policy into a separate subsection of <xref target="well-known"/>.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="expert-lifecycle"/>, Expert Reviews and the Document Lifecycle</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="referring"/>, Documentation References in IANA Registries</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="bis-docs"/>, What to Do in "bis" Documents</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="assignee"/>, Contact Person vs Assignee or Owner</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="closing-obsoleting"/>, Closing or
	    Obsoleting a Registry/Registrations</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Clarifications and such:
          <list style="symbols">

            <t>Some reorganization -- moved text around for clarity and easier reading.</t>

            <t>Made clarifications about identification of IANA registries and use of URLs for them.</t>

            <t>Clarified the distinction between "Unassigned" and "Reserved".</t>

            <t>Made some clarifications in "Expert Review" about instructions to the designated expert.</t>

            <t>Made some clarifications in "Specification Required" about how to declare this policy.</t>

            <t>Assorted minor clarifications and editorial changes throughout.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="2008: Changes in RFC 5226 Relative to RFC 2434">
      <t>
   Changes include:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
        Major reordering of text to expand descriptions and to better
        group topics such as "updating registries" vs.&nbsp;"creating new
        registries", in order to make it easier for authors to find the
        text most applicable to their needs.
          </t>
          <t>
        Numerous editorial changes to improve readability.
          </t>
          <t>
        Changed the term "IETF Consensus" to "IETF Review" and added
        more clarifications.  History has shown that people see the
        words "IETF Consensus" (without consulting the actual
        definition) and are quick to make incorrect assumptions about
        what the term means in the context of IANA Considerations.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added "RFC Required" to list of defined policies.
          </t>
          <t>
        Much more explicit directions and examples of "what to put in
        RFCs".
          </t>
          <t>
        "Specification Required" now implies use of a designated expert
        to evaluate specs for sufficient clarity.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section describing provisional registrations.
          </t>
          <t>
        Significantly changed the wording in the "Designated Experts" section.
        Main purpose is to make clear that Expert Reviewers are accountable to the
        community, and to provide some guidance for review criteria in
        the default case.
          </t>
          <t>
        Changed wording to remove any special appeals path.  The normal
        RFC 2026 appeals path is used.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section about reclaiming unused values.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section on after-the-fact registrations.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section indicating that mailing lists used to evaluate
        possible assignments (such as by a designated expert) are subject
        to normal IETF rules.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2026" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!--      <?rfc include="reference.BCP.72" ?> -->

<reference  anchor='BCP72' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp72'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Korver' fullname='B. Korver'><organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract><t>All RFCs are required to have a Security Considerations section. Historically, such sections have been relatively weak.  This document provides guidelines to RFC authors on how to write a good Security Considerations section.   This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='72'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3552'/>
</reference>


      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0791" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1591" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2434" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2860" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2939" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3228" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3575" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3692" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3748" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3864" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3942" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3968" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4005" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4025" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4044" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4124" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4169" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4283" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4340" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4395" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4422" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4446" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4520" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4589" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4727" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5378" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5742" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5771" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5795" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6014" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6195" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6230" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6275" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6698" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6709" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6838" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6994" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7120" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7564" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7595" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7752" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8141" ?>

    </references>

<section title="Acknowledgments for This Document (2017)" numbered="no">
        <t>
          Thomas Narten and Harald Tveit Alvestrand edited the two earlier
          editions of this document (RFCs 2434 and 5226), and Thomas continues
          his role in this third edition.  Much of the text from RFC 5226
          remains in this edition.
        </t>
        <t>
          Thank you to Amanda Baber and Pearl Liang for their multiple reviews and 
          suggestions for making this document as thorough as possible.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document has benefited from thorough review and comments by
          many people, including
          Benoit Claise,
          Alissa Cooper,
          Adrian Farrel,
          Stephen Farrell,
          Tony Hansen,
          John Klensin,
          Kathleen Moriarty,
          Mark Nottingham,
          Pete Resnick,
          and Joe Touch.
        </t>
        <t>
          Special thanks to Mark Nottingham for reorganizing some of the text
          for better organization and readability, to Tony Hansen for acting
          as document shepherd, and to Brian Haberman and Terry Manderson for
          acting as sponsoring ADs.
        </t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments from the second edition (2008)" numbered="no">
        <t>
   The original acknowledgments section in RFC 5226 was:
        </t>
        <t>
   This document has benefited from specific feedback from Jari Arkko,
   Marcelo Bagnulo Braun, Brian Carpenter, Michelle Cotton, Spencer
   Dawkins, Barbara Denny, Miguel Garcia, Paul Hoffman, Russ Housley,
   John Klensin, Allison Mankin, Blake Ramsdell, Mark Townsley, Magnus
   Westerlund, and Bert Wijnen.
        </t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments from the first edition (1998)" numbered="no">
        <t>
   The original acknowledgments section in RFC 2434 was:
        </t>
        <t>
   Jon Postel and Joyce Reynolds provided a detailed explanation on what
   IANA needs in order to manage assignments efficiently, and patiently
   provided comments on multiple versions of this document.  Brian
   Carpenter provided helpful comments on earlier versions of the
   document.  One paragraph in the Security Considerations section was
   borrowed from RFC 4288.
        </t>
</section>

  </back>
</rfc>
