<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3311 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4028 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4028.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4320 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4320.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4321 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4321.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc number="8498" category="info" consensus="yes" 
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902" 
 updates="5502" 
 submissionType="IETF" 
 xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="P-Served-User Parameter for CDIV in SIP">A P-Served-User Header Field
    Parameter for an Originating Call Diversion (CDIV) Session Case in the Session Initiation Protocol
    (SIP)</title>

    <author fullname="Marianne Mohali" initials="M.M." surname="Mohali">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Orange Gardens, 44 avenue de la Republique</street>
          <city>Chatillon</city>
          <region/>
          <code>92326</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>marianne.mohali@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2019"/>

    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SIP, RFC5502, P-, 3GPP, IMS, Served-User, orig-cdiv</keyword>

    <abstract>
<t>
The P-Served-User header field was defined based on a
requirement from the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) IMS (IP Multimedia Subsystem)
in order to convey the identity of the served user, his/her registration 
state, and the session case that applies to that particular communication 
session and application invocation. A session case is metadata that 
captures the status of the session of a served user regardless of whether or not the served 
user is registered or the session originates or terminates
with the served user.
This document updates RFC 5502 by defining a new P-Served-User header 
field parameter, "orig-cdiv".  
The parameter conveys the session case used by a proxy when handling 
an originating session after Call Diversion (CDIV) services have been 
invoked for the served user.
This document also fixes the ABNF in RFC 5502 and provides more guidance
for using the P-Served-User header field in IP networks.
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="General">
        <t>
The P-Served-User header field <xref target="RFC5502"/> was defined
based on a requirement from the 3rd Generation Partnership 
Project (3GPP) IMS (IP Multimedia Subsystem) in order to convey the 
identity of the served user, his/her registration state, and the session
case between a Serving Call Session Control Function (S-CSCF) and an 
Application Server (AS) on the IMS Service Control (ISC) interface. A 
session case is metadata that captures the status of the session of a
served user regardless of whether or not the served user is
registered or the session originates or terminates with the served user. For more 
information on session cases and the IMS, a detailed description can be 
found in <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/>.  
</t>
<t>
<xref target="RFC5502"/> defines the originating and terminating 
session cases for a registered or unregistered user. This document extends the 
P-Served-User header field to include the session case for a forwarded leg when 
both a CDIV service has been invoked and an originating service of the diverting
user has to be triggered.
</t>
<t>
		The sessioncase-param parameter of the P-Served-User header field is 
		extended with the "orig-cdiv" parameter for this originating-after-CDIV session case. 
		</t>
		<t>
		The following section defines usage of the "orig-cdiv" parameter of 
		the P-Served-User header field, Section 3 discusses the applicability and 
		scope of this new header field parameter, and <xref target="sect.prox"/> 
		specifies the proxy behavior for handling the new header field parameter. 
		<xref target="sect.proc"/> clarifies some of the <xref target="RFC5502"/> 
		procedures, <xref target="sect.syn"/> describes the extended syntax 
		and corrects the syntax of <xref target="RFC5502"/>, <xref
		target="sect.cf"/> gives some call flow examples, <xref target="sect.iana"/> 
		registers the P&nbhy;Served-User header field parameters with IANA, and <xref target="sect.secu"/> 
		discusses the security properties of the environment where this new 
		header field parameter is intended to be used.
		</t>
      </section>
	  
      <section title="Basic Use Case">
        <t>
		In the 3GPP IMS (IP Multimedia Subsystem), the S-CSCF (Serving CSCF) 
		is a SIP proxy that serves as a registrar and handles originating and 
		terminating session states for users assigned to it.
        This means that any call that is originated by a specific user or any
        call that is terminated to that specific user will pass through the
        S-CSCF that is assigned to that user.
		</t>
		<t>
		At the moment that an S-CSCF is assigned to a specific user, the 
		user profile is downloaded from the Home Subscriber Server (HSS) to 
		that S-CSCF; see <xref target="TS.3GPP.29.228"/>. The user profile 
		contains the list of actions to be taken by the S-CSCF for the served 
		user depending on the session direction (originating or terminating)
		and the user state (registered or not) in the IMS network. With this 
		user profile, the S-CSCF determines the current case and applies the
		corresponding actions such as forwarding the request to an AS.
		The AS then goes through a similar process of determining who is the 
		current served user, what is his/her "registration state", and what 
		is the "session case" of the session. <xref target="RFC5502"/> defines 
		all those parameters and in particular the originating and terminating
		session cases.
		</t>
		<t>
		In basic call scenarios, there is no particular issue for the S-CSCF and 
		AS to know which scenario needs to be realized, but in case of CDIV services
		for which the session is re-targeted, the session cases defined in 
		<xref target="RFC5502"/> pose some limitations as described in the following section.
		</t>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section title="Problem Statement">
		<t>
		To illustrate the problem statement, let's imagine Alice trying to call Bob 
		and Bob having a CDIV service activated towards Carol's address.
		In the case of a CDIV service, the received request is first
		treated as a terminating session case (at Bob's side), and the terminating filter 
		criteria configured in the S-CSCF is performed. A filter criteria is 
		information in the user profile that determines whether an initial 
		request is sent to a particular AS. When the AS receives 
		the call initiation request, the AS is able to determine the served user (Bob)
		and the session case (here "term") from the received P-Served-User header 
		field content and is able to execute terminating services. When the CDIV
		service is executed (as a terminating service of Bob), the AS changes 
		the target (Request-URI) of the session (toward Carol's address) and a new call 
		leg is created. The served user becomes the diverting user.
		This new call leg could be considered as an originating call leg from 
		the diverting user (Bob), but this is not the case. Indeed, the originating 
		user remains the same (Alice), and some of the diverting user's originating 
		services should not be triggered as if it was an originating call. For
		instance, the originating user identity (Alice) should not be restricted 
		because the diverting user (Bob) has a privacy service for his own 
		identity. The privacy of the diverting user should apply to information 
		related to this user only (e.g., in the History-Info header field). In the 
		same manner, some specific services will need to be triggered on the 
		outgoing leg after a CDIV.
		Without a dedicated session case for originating-after-CDIV, the S-CSCF
		cannot trigger an originating service for the diverting user, nor can 
		an AS execute the procedures for this particular session case.  
		</t>
		<t>
		For this use case, this document creates a new parameter ("orig-cdiv") for 
		the originating-after-CDIV session case to be embedded in the 
		P-Served-User header field.
		</t>
      </section>
    </section>


	<section title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>
	
	<section title="Applicability">
		<t>
		The use of the P-Served-User header field extensions is only applicable 
		inside a Trust Domain <xref target="RFC3324"/> for the P-Served-User header 
		field. Nodes in such a Trust Domain explicitly trust each other to convey
		the served user and to be responsible for withholding that information 
		outside of the Trust Domain. The means by which the network determines 
		the served user and the policies that are executed for a specific served
		user is outside the	scope of this document.
		</t>
    </section>
	
    <section anchor="sect.prox" title="Proxy Behavior and Parameter Handling">
		<t>
		The following section illustrates how this header field parameter can 
		be	used in a 3GPP network.
		</t>
		<t>
		For a terminating call, the following steps will be followed:
		<list style="numbers">
			<t>
			The S-CSCF receives the initial INVITE request for a terminating 
			call and determines that the session case is for a terminating 
			user as described in <xref target="RFC5502"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
			The S-CSCF determines who is the served user by looking at the 
			Request-URI and saves the current Request-URI.
			</t>
			<t>
			The S-CSCF analyzes the filter criteria. It then sends the request 
			to the AS of the served user as an INVITE that includes the 
			P-Served-User header field with the "sescase" parameter set to 
			"term" and the "regstate" set to the corresponding value in order 
			to trigger execution of terminating services.
			</t>
			<t>
			Based on some criteria, the AS concludes that the request has to
			be diverted to another target user or application. The AS replaces 
			the received Request-URI with the new diverted-to
			address and stores the successive Request-URI(s) values by adding one 
			or two History-Info header field entry(ies) <xref target="RFC7044"/> 
			in the outgoing INVITE. In the History-Info header field, the 
			served user address is tagged by using the mp-param header field 
			parameter added in the newly created entry that contains the diverted-to 
			address. The AS forwards the INVITE request back to the S-CSCF.
			</t>
			<t>
			When receiving back the INVITE request, the S-CSCF can see that the 
			topmost Route header field contains its own hostname, but the 
			Request-URI does not match the saved Request-URI. In this case, the 
			S-CSCF updates the P-Served-User header field content by replacing 
			the "sescase" parameter with the "orig-cdiv" parameter. The 
			P-Served-User header field value remains unchanged.
			</t>
			<t>
			The S-CSCF forwards the INVITE request to an AS that hosts the 
			served user's (diverting user's) originating services, which need to be
			executed on the forwarded leg after a CDIV service.
			</t>
			<t>
			When the AS receives the INVITE request, it determines that the 
			session case is for the "orig-cdiv" session case and performs the 
			originating services to be executed after retargeting for the 
			diverting user (i.e., served user).
			</t>
        </list>
		</t>
    </section>
	
	<section anchor="sect.proc" title="Clarification of RFC 5502 Procedures">
		<t>
		This document provides the following guidance for the handling of 
		the P-Served-User header field that is missing in <xref target="RFC5502"/>:
		<list hangIndent="0" style="symbols">
            <t>
			The P-Served-User header field MUST NOT be repeated within a request for a 
			particular session at a particular time for the reason that 
			session cases are mutually exclusive. This document updates <xref target="RFC5502"/> 
			to clearly state that the P-Served-User header field MUST NOT contain 
			multiple values either comma-separated or header-separated. This 
			document also updates the syntax of the header from <xref target="RFC5502"/> 
			to reflect this uniqueness of parameter values.
			</t>
            <t>
			<xref target="RFC5502"/> does not clearly state what to do with 
			the received P-Served-User header field when a call is diverted to 
			another destination. This document highlights that there are several 
			ways of handling the P-Served-User header field: the S-CSCF could 
			store the previous "regstate" value and decide that the same value
			applies, the "regstate" may no longer be relevant after a 
			diverting service so the S-CSCF removes it, or the "regstate" could 
			be combined with the "orig-cdiv" session case to provide different 
			services depending on whether the served user is registered or 
			unregistered. These choices are implementation dependent.
			</t>
        </list>
		</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.syn" title="Syntax">
      <section title="General">      
		<t>
		<xref target="RFC5502"/> defines the P-Served-User header field with 
		the sessioncase-param parameter "sescase", which is specified as having
		"orig" and "term" as predefined values. This document defines
		an additional parameter, "orig-cdiv", for the
		sessioncase-param. 
		</t>
		<t>
		Because this document extends the existing sessioncase-param
		parameter, and because errors have been identified in
		the syntax, this document corrects and extends the
		P-Served-User header field.
		</t>
		<t>
		The extension of the sessioncase-param parameter to add the 
		"orig-cdiv" session case is done in a way that fits the parameter format
		introduced in Release 11 of the 3GPP <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229"/> 
		and maintains backward compatibility.
		</t>
        <t>  
		"EQUAL", "HCOLON", "SEMI", "name-addr", "addr-spec", and
		"generic-param" are defined in <xref target="RFC3261"/>.
		</t>
		<t>
If the "addr-spec" contains a comma, question mark, or semicolon, the
"name-addr" form MUST be used. The "name-addr" form requires the use of angle
brackets (&lt; and &gt;).
		</t>
      </section>

      <section title="ABNF">
        <t>
		The Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) <xref target="RFC5234"/>
        syntax of the P&nbhy;Served-User header field is described in <xref
        target="RFC5502"/>.
		</t>
		<t>
		This document updates <xref target="RFC5502"/> to correct the
		P-Served-User header field ABNF syntax and extend it as the
		following: 
		</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
P-Served-User            = "P-Served-User" HCOLON PServedUser-value
                           *(SEMI served-user-param)
served-user-param        = sessioncase-param
                           / registration-state-param
                           / generic-param
PServedUser-value        = name-addr / addr-spec
sessioncase-param        = "sescase" EQUAL ("orig"/"term")/ orig-cdiv
registration-state-param = "regstate" EQUAL ("unreg" / "reg")
orig-cdiv                = "orig-cdiv"
 ]]> 
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
Examples of possible P-Served-User header fields:
        </t>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
P-Served-User: <sip:user@example.com>; orig-cdiv; regstate=reg
or
P-Served-User: <sip:user@example.com>; orig-cdiv
or
P-Served-User: <sip:user@example.com>; sescase=term; regstate=unreg
 ]]> 
</artwork>
</figure>
		<t>
		This document allows choosing between "addr-spec" and "name-addr" when
		constructing the header field value. As specified in RFC 8217,
		the "addr-spec" form MUST NOT be used if its value would contain
		a comma, semicolon, or question mark <xref target="RFC8217"/>.
		</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect.cf" title="Call Flow Examples">
<section title="Call Diversion Case">
<t>
The following call flow shows a session establishment when Alice
calls Bob, who has a CDIV service that diverts to Carol
when Bob is busy.
</t>
<figure>
<artwork align="center" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[     
                  proxy           server            UA         
Alice    Bob's...S-CSCF-B..........AS-B.............Bob            Carol
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   INVITE F1    |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   INVITE F2    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F3    |                |                |
  |                |<---------------|  INVITE F4     |                |
  |                |-------------------------------->|                |
  |                |                486   F5         |                |  
  |                |<--------------------------------|                | 
  |                |    486   F6    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F7    |                |                | 
  |                |<---------------|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F8    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F9    |                |                |
  |                |<---------------|      INVITE F10                 |
  |                |------------------------------------------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |    180   F11   |
  |                |                |    180   F12   |<---------------|
  |                |    180   F13   |<---------------|                |
  |    180   F14   |<---------------|                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |                |

[Alice calls Bob]

   F1 INVITE Alice -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>

   F2 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> AS-B
   INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg

   F3 INVITE AS-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg

   F4 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> Bob
   INVITE sip:bob@192.0.2.4 SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg
 
[Bob is busy. His CDIV when busy is invoked towards Carol]

   F5-F6 486 BUSY Bob -> S-CSCF-B  -> AS-B
   486 BUSY
    From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>;tag=es43sd

[Alice's call is diverted to Carol]

   F7 INVITE AS-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg

[The forwarded leg to Carol is identified as an originating call after
CDIV, which should not trigger all of Bob's originating services]
  
   F8 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> AS-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; orig-cdiv; regstate=reg

   F9 INVITE AS-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; orig-cdiv; regstate=reg

   F10 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> Carol
   INVITE sip:carol@192.0.2.7 SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>

             Figure 1. P-Served-User During CDIV Service
]]>
                        </artwork>
                </figure>
        </section>
	<section title="Call Diversion and Privacy">
		<t>
		The following call flow shows a CDIV use case for which 
		Alice has no identity restriction service and Bob has an unconditional
		CDIV service towards Carol and an identity presentation 
		restriction service.
                </t>
<figure>
<artwork align="center" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   
                  proxy           server            UA         
Alice    Bob's...S-CSCF-B..........AS-B.............Bob            Carol  
  |                |                |                |                |
  |   INVITE F1    |                |                |                |
  |--------------->|   INVITE F2    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F3    |                |                | 
  |                |<---------------|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F4    |                |                |
  |                |--------------->|                |                |
  |                |   INVITE F5    |                |                |
  |                |<---------------|      INVITE F6 |                |
  |                |------------------------------------------------->|
  |                |                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |    180   F7    |
  |                |                |    180   F8    |<---------------|
  |                |    180   F9    |<---------------|                |
  |    180   F10   |<---------------|                |                |
  |<---------------|                |                |                |
  |                |                |                |                |

[Alice calls Bob]

   F1 INVITE Alice -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        Supported: histinfo

   F2 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> AS-B
   INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Bob <sip:bob@example.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg

[Bob's unconditional CDIV to Carol is triggered]

   F3 INVITE AS-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Carol <sip:carol@domainc.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; term; regstate=reg
        History-Info:
                <sip:bob@example.com>;index=1, 
                <sip:carol@domainc.com;cause=302>;index=1.1;mp=1

[Alice's call is diverted to Carol]

   F4 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> AS-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Carol <sip:carol@domainc.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; orig-cdiv; regstate=reg
        History-Info:
                <sip:bob@example.com>;index=1, 
                <sip:carol@domainc.com;cause=302>;index=1.1;mp=1

   F5 INVITE AS-B -> S-CSCF-B
   INVITE sip:carol@domainc.com SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Carol <sip:carol@domainc.com>
        P-Served-User: <sip:bob@example.com>; orig-cdiv; regstate=reg
        History-Info:
                <sip:bob@example.com?privacy=history>;index=1, 
                <sip:carol@domainc.com;cause=302>;index=1.1;mp=1

[Forwarded leg to Carol is identified as an originating call after
CDIV that allows Bob's privacy service to be applied to his 
identity within the History-Info header field]
  
   F6 INVITE S-CSCF-B -> Carol
   INVITE sip:carol@192.0.2.7 SIP/2.0
        From: Alice <sip:alice@domaina.com>;tag=1928301774
        To: Carol <sip:carol@domainc.com>
        History-Info:
                <sip:bob@example.com?privacy=history>;index=1, 
                <sip:carol@domainc.com;cause=302>;index=1.1;mp=1
                <sip:carol@192.0.2.7>;index=1.1.1;rc=1.1
    
            Figure 2. P-Served-User When Privacy Requested
]]>
                  </artwork>
                      </figure>
             </section>
    </section>
        <section anchor="sect.iana" title="IANA Considerations">
                <t>
                The syntax of the P-Served-User header field <xref
        target="RFC5502"/> is updated in Section 4 of this document. 
               </t>
                <t>
                IANA has updated the existing row for the 
                P-Served-User header field in the "Header Fields" subregistry 
                within the "Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Parameters" registry:
                </t>
                <figure>
                        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   Header Name        Compact Form          Reference
  -------------       ------------     ------------------
  P-Served-User          none          [RFC5502][RFC8498]
]]>
                        </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                IANA has added new rows for the P-Served-User 
                header field parameters in the "Header Field Parameters and Parameter
                Values" subregistry within the "Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) 
                Parameters" registry (as per the registry created by <xref
                target="RFC3968"/>):
                </t>
                <figure>
                       <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 Header Field   Parameter Name    Predefined Values    Reference
--------------  ----------------  -----------------  -------------
P-Served-User     sescase              Yes             [RFC5502]
P-Served-User     regstate             Yes             [RFC5502]
P-Served-User     orig-cdiv            No              [RFC8498] 
]]>
</artwork>
                </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sect.secu" title="Security Considerations">
                <t>
                The security considerations in <xref target="RFC5502"/> apply.
                </t>
                <t>
                As the "orig-cdiv" parameter of the P-Served-User header field can be 
                used to trigger applications when a call is diverted, it is important
                to ensure that the parameter has not been added to the SIP message by
                an unauthorized SIP entity. Thus, the P-Served-User header field is to 
                be used in a trusted environment, and proxies MUST NOT insert the header
                unless they have sufficient knowledge that the route set
                includes another trusted proxy.
                </t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3324"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8217"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3968"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7044"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5502"?>
	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">
		<reference anchor="TS.3GPP.24.229">
			<front>
			<title>IP multimedia call control protocol based on Session
			Initiation Protocol (SIP) and Session Description Protocol
			(SDP);Stage 3</title>
			<author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
			</author>
			<date month="December" year="2018"/>
			</front>
			<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="24.229 11.28.0"/>
			<format target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/24229.htm"
                type="HTML"/>
		</reference>
		
		<reference anchor="TS.3GPP.29.228">
			<front>
			<title>IP Multimedia (IM) Subsystem Cx and Dx interfaces; Signalling
			flows and message contents</title>
			<author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
			</author>
			<date month="September" year="2018"/>
			</front>
			<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.228 15.1.0"/>
			<format target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29228.htm"
                type="HTML"/>
		</reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
		<t>
		The author wishes to thank the 3GPP community for providing guidance,
		input, and comments on the document. Thanks to Dale Worley, Jean Mahoney, 
		and Ben Campbell for their careful review of the document. Thanks to 
		Paul Kyzivat and Adam Roach. A special thanks to Christer Holmberg.
		</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
