<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2475 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.2475.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2914 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.2914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3168 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.3168.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4594 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.4594.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3439 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.3439.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3662 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.3662.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3754 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.3754.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5053 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.5053.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6297 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.6297.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6817 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.6817.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6973 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.6973.xml">
<!ENTITY DS-INTERCON SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8100.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8085 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8085.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8087 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8087.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8325 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8325.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8436 SYSTEM "./reference.RFC.8436.xml">

<!ENTITY LE-DSCP "000001">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" number="8622" ipr="pre5378Trust200902"
     updates="4594, 8325" obsoletes="3662" submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">

 <front>

   <title abbrev="Lower-Effort PHB">A Lower-Effort Per-Hop Behavior (LE PHB) for Differentiated Services</title>

   <author fullname="Roland Bless" initials="R." surname="Bless">
     <organization abbrev="KIT">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
	 <street>Institute of Telematics (TM)</street>
         <street>Kaiserstr. 12</street>
         <city>Karlsruhe</city>
         <code>76131</code>
         <country>Germany</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+49 721 608 46413</phone>
       <email>roland.bless@kit.edu</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date month="June" year="2019" />

   <keyword>Lower Effort, Per-Hop Behavior, Scavenger Service</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>This document specifies properties and characteristics of a
     Lower-Effort Per-Hop Behavior (LE PHB). The primary objective
     of this LE PHB is to protect Best-Effort (BE) traffic (packets
     forwarded with the default PHB) from LE traffic in congestion
     situations, i.e., when resources become scarce, BE traffic has
     precedence over LE traffic and may preempt it.
     Alternatively, packets forwarded by the LE PHB can be
     associated with a scavenger service class, i.e., they
     scavenge otherwise-unused resources only. There are numerous uses
     for this PHB, e.g., for background traffic of
     low precedence, such as bulk data transfers with low priority in
     time, non-time-critical backups, larger software updates, web search
     engines while gathering information from web servers and so on.
     This document recommends a standard Differentiated Services Code Point
     (DSCP) value for the LE PHB.</t>

     <t>This specification obsoletes RFC 3662 and
     updates the DSCP recommended in RFCs 4594 and 8325 to use the DSCP
     assigned in this specification.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec:intro">
     
     <t>This document defines a Differentiated Services (DS) per-hop
     behavior <xref target="RFC2474"/> called "Lower-Effort
     Per-Hop Behavior" (LE PHB), which is intended for traffic of sufficiently
     low urgency that all other traffic takes precedence over the LE
     traffic in consumption of network link bandwidth.  Low&nbhy;urgency
     traffic has a low priority for timely forwarding; note, however, that
     this does not necessarily imply that it is generally of minor importance.
     From this viewpoint, it can be considered as a network equivalent to a
     background priority for processes in an operating system.  There
     may or may not be memory (buffer) resources allocated for this
     type of traffic.
     </t>

     <t>Some networks carry packets that ought to consume network
     resources only when no other traffic is demanding them.
     From this point of view, packets forwarded by the 
     LE PHB scavenge otherwise-unused resources only; this led to the name
     "scavenger service" in early Internet2 deployments
     (see <xref target="app-history"/>). Other commonly used names for
     LE PHB types of services are "Lower than best effort" <xref
     target="Carlberg-LBE-2001"/> or "Less than best effort"
     <xref target="Chown-LBE-2003"/>. In summary, with the
     above-mentioned feature, the LE PHB has two important properties:
     it should scavenge residual capacity, and it must be preemptable
     by the default PHB (or other elevated PHBs) in case they
     need more resources.
     
     Consequently, the effect of this type of traffic on all other
     network traffic is strictly limited (the "no&nbsp;harm" property).  This
     is distinct from "Best&nbhy;Effort" (BE) traffic, since the network
     makes no commitment to deliver LE packets.  In contrast, BE
     traffic receives an implied "good faith" commitment of at least
     some available network resources.  This document proposes an LE
     DS PHB for handling this "optional" traffic in a DS node.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL&nbsp;NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD&nbsp;NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
      "NOT&nbsp;RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
      are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when,
      and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Applicability" anchor="sec:applicability">
       <t>An LE PHB is applicable for many applications that otherwise use BE
       delivery. More specifically, it is suitable for traffic and services
       that can tolerate strongly varying throughput for their data flows,
       especially periods of very low throughput or even
       starvation (i.e., long interruptions due to significant or
       even complete packet loss).
       Therefore, an application sending an LE&nbhy;marked flow needs to
       be able to tolerate short or (even very) long interruptions due
       to the presence of severe congestion conditions during the
       transmission of the flow. Thus, there ought to be an expectation
       that packets of the LE PHB could be excessively delayed or
       dropped when any other traffic is present. Whether or not
       a lack of progress is considered to be a failure is
       application dependent (e.g., if a transport connection fails due
       to timing out, the application may try several times to reestablish
       the transport connection in order to resume the application session
       before finally giving up). The LE PHB is suitable for sending
       traffic of low urgency across a DS domain or DS region.</t>

       <t>Just like BE traffic, LE traffic SHOULD be
       congestion controlled (i.e., use a congestion controlled
       transport or implement an appropriate congestion control method
       <xref target="RFC2914"/> <xref target="RFC8085"/>). Since LE
       traffic could be starved completely for a longer period of
       time, transport protocols or applications (and their related
       congestion control mechanisms) SHOULD be able to detect and
       react to such a starvation situation. An appropriate reaction
       would be to resume the transfer instead of aborting it, i.e.,
       an LE-optimized transport ought to use appropriate retry strategies
       (e.g., exponential back-off with an upper bound) as well as
       corresponding retry and timeout limits in order to avoid the
       loss of the connection due to the above&nbhy;mentioned starvation
       periods. While it is desirable to achieve a quick resumption of the
       transfer as soon as resources become available again, it may be
       difficult to achieve this in practice. In the case of a lack of a
       transport protocol and congestion control that are adapted to LE,
       applications can also use existing common transport
       protocols and implement session resumption by trying to
       reestablish failed connections.
       Congestion control is not only useful for letting the
       flows within the LE Behavior Aggregate (BA) adapt to the available
       bandwidth, which may be highly fluctuating; it is also essential
       if LE traffic is mapped to the default PHB in DS domains that
       do not support LE. In this case, the use of background transport
       protocols, e.g., similar to Low Extra Delay Background Transport
       (LEDBAT) <xref target="RFC6817"/>, is expedient.
       </t>

       <t>The use of the LE PHB might assist a network operator in moving
       certain kinds of traffic or users to off-peak times.
       Furthermore, packets can be designated for
       the LE PHB when the goal is to protect all other packet traffic
       from competition with the LE aggregate while not completely
       banning LE traffic from the network. An LE PHB SHOULD&nbsp;NOT be
       used for a customer's "normal Internet" traffic and
       packets SHOULD NOT be "downgraded" to the LE PHB instead of being
       dropped, particularly when the packets are unauthorized traffic.       
       The LE PHB is expected to have applicability in
       networks that have at least some unused capacity during certain
       periods.</t>
       
       <t>The LE PHB allows networks to protect themselves from
       selected types of traffic as a complement to giving
       preferential treatment to other selected traffic aggregates.
       LE ought not be used for the general case of downgraded traffic,
       but it could be used by design, e.g., to protect an internal network
       from untrusted external traffic sources. In this case, there is
       no way for attackers to preempt internal (non&nbhy;LE) traffic by
       flooding. Another use case in this regard is the forwarding of
       multicast traffic from untrusted sources. Multicast forwarding
       is currently enabled within domains only for specific sources
       within a domain -- not for sources from anywhere in the
       Internet. One major problem is that multicast routing creates
       traffic sources at (mostly) unpredictable branching points within
       a domain, potentially leading to congestion and packet loss.
       In the case where multicast traffic packets from untrusted sources are
       forwarded as LE traffic, they will not harm traffic from non-LE BAs.
       A further related use case is mentioned in <xref target="RFC3754"/>:
       preliminary forwarding of non&nbhy;admitted multicast traffic.
       </t>

       <t> There is no intrinsic reason to limit the applicability of
       the LE PHB to any particular application or type of traffic.
       It is intended as an additional traffic engineering tool for
       network administrators.  For instance, it can be used to fill
       protection capacity of transmission links that is otherwise
       unused.  Some network providers keep link utilization below 50%
       to ensure that all traffic is forwarded without loss after
       rerouting caused by a link failure (cf. Section 6 of <xref target="RFC3439"/>).
       LE&nbhy;marked traffic can utilize the normally unused capacity and
       will be preempted automatically in the case of link failure when 100%
       of the link capacity is required for all other traffic.
       Ideally, applications mark their packets as LE traffic, because they
       know the urgency of flows. Since LE traffic may be starved for
       longer periods of time, it is probably less suitable for real-time
       and interactive applications.
       </t>

       <t>Example uses for the LE PHB:
       <list style="symbols">
         <t>For traffic caused by World Wide Web search engines while
         they gather information from web servers.</t>

         <t>For software updates or dissemination of new releases of
         operating systems.</t>

         <t>For reporting errors or telemetry data from operating systems
         or applications.</t>
         
         <t>For backup traffic, non-time-critical synchronization, or
         mirroring traffic.</t>
         
         <t>For content distribution transfers between caches.</t>

         <t>For preloading or prefetching objects from web sites.</t>
         
         <t>For network news and other "bulk mail" of the Internet.</t>
         
         <t>For "downgraded" traffic from some other PHB when this does
         not violate the operational objectives of the other PHB. 
         </t>

         <t>For multicast traffic from untrusted (e.g., non-local) sources.</t>
       </list>
       </t>
     </section>


   <section title="PHB Description" anchor="sec:phb_description">
     <t>The LE PHB is defined in relation to the default PHB (BE).
     A packet forwarded with the LE PHB SHOULD have
     lower precedence than packets forwarded with the default PHB,
     i.e., in the case of congestion, LE&nbhy;marked traffic SHOULD be
     dropped prior to dropping any default PHB traffic. Ideally, LE
     packets would be forwarded only when no packet with any other PHB
     is awaiting transmission. This means that in the case of link
     resource contention LE traffic can be starved completely, which
     may not always be desired by the network operator's policy.
     A scheduler used to implement the LE PHB may reflect this policy
     accordingly.
     </t>

     <t>A straightforward implementation could be a
     simple priority scheduler serving the default PHB queue with
     higher priority than the LE PHB queue.  Alternative
     implementations may use scheduling algorithms that assign a very
     small weight to the LE class. This, however, could sometimes cause
     better service for LE packets compared to BE packets in cases
     when the BE share is fully utilized and the LE share is not.</t>

     <t>If a dedicated LE queue is not available, an active queue management
     mechanism within a common BE/LE queue could also be used. This could
     drop all arriving LE packets as soon as certain queue length or sojourn
     time thresholds are exceeded.</t>

     <t>Since congestion control is also useful within the LE traffic class,
     Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) <xref target="RFC3168"/>
     SHOULD be used for LE packets, too. More specifically, an LE
     implementation SHOULD also apply Congestion Experienced (CE) marking
     for ECT-marked packets ("ECT" stands for ECN-Capable Transport), and
     transport protocols used for LE SHOULD support and employ ECN.
     For more information on the
     benefits of using ECN, see <xref target="RFC8087"/>.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Traffic-Conditioning Actions" anchor="sec:traffic_conditioning">
     <t>If possible, packets SHOULD be pre-marked in DS-aware end
     systems by applications due to their specific knowledge about the
     particular precedence of packets. There is no incentive for DS
     domains to distrust this initial marking, because letting LE
     traffic enter a DS domain causes no harm. Thus, any policing, such as
     limiting the rate of LE traffic, is not necessary at the DS
     boundary.</t>

     <t>As for most other PHBs, an initial classification and marking
     can also be performed at the first DS boundary node according to
     the DS domain's own policies (e.g., as a protection measure against
     untrusted sources). However, non-LE traffic (e.g., BE
     traffic) SHOULD NOT be re&nbhy;marked to LE.
     Re&nbhy;marking traffic from another PHB results in that traffic
     being "downgraded". This changes the way the network treats this
     traffic, and it is important not to violate the operational
     objectives of the original PHB. See
     Sections&nbsp;<xref target="sec:applicability" format="counter"/> and
     <xref target="sec:phb_remark" format="counter"/> for notes related to
     downgrading.
     </t>
 
   </section>

   <section anchor="phb_dscp" title="Recommended DSCP">
     <t>The RECOMMENDED codepoint for the LE PHB is '&LE-DSCP;'.</t>

     <t>Earlier specifications (e.g., <xref target="RFC4594"/>) recommended the use of
     Class Selector 1 (CS1) as the codepoint (as mentioned in <xref
     target="RFC3662" />). This is problematic, since it may cause a priority
     inversion in Diffserv domains that treat CS1 as originally proposed in
     <xref target="RFC2474" />, resulting in forwarding LE packets with
     higher precedence than BE packets. Existing implementations
     SHOULD transition to use the unambiguous LE codepoint '&LE-DSCP;'
     whenever possible.</t>

     <t>This particular codepoint was chosen due to measurements
     on the currently observable Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP)
     re&nbhy;marking behavior in the Internet
     <xref target="IETF99-Secchi" />.

     Since some network domains set the former IP Precedence bits to
     zero, it is possible that some other standardized DSCPs get mapped
     to the LE PHB DSCP if it were taken from the DSCP Standards Action
     Pool 1 (xxxxx0) <xref target="RFC2474"/> <xref target="RFC8436"/>.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Deployment Considerations" anchor="sec:deployment">
     <t>In order to enable LE support, DS nodes typically only need
     <list style="symbols">
       <t>A BA classifier (see <xref target="RFC2475"/>)
       that classifies packets according to the LE DSCP</t>
       <t>A dedicated LE queue</t>
       <t>A suitable scheduling discipline, e.g., simple priority queueing</t>
     </list>
     Alternatively, implementations could use active queue management
     mechanisms instead of a dedicated LE queue, e.g., dropping all arriving
     LE packets when certain queue length or sojourn time thresholds are
     exceeded.
     </t>
     
     <t>Internet-wide deployment of the LE PHB is eased by the
     following properties:
     <list style="symbols">
       <t>No harm to other traffic: since the LE PHB has the
       lowest forwarding priority, it does not consume resources from other
       PHBs. Deployment across different provider domains with LE support
       causes no trust issues or attack vectors to existing (non&nbhy;LE)
       traffic. Thus, providers can trust LE markings from end&nbsp;systems,
       i.e., there is no need to police or re&nbhy;mark incoming LE traffic.
       </t>
       
       <t>No PHB parameters or configuration of traffic profiles:
       the LE PHB itself possesses no parameters that need to be
       set or configured. Similarly, since LE traffic requires no
       admission or policing, it is not necessary to configure traffic
       profiles.</t>

       <t>No traffic-conditioning mechanisms: the LE PHB requires
       no traffic meters, droppers, or shapers. See also
       <xref target="sec:traffic_conditioning"/> for further discussion.</t>
     </list>
     </t>

     <t>Operators of DS domains that cannot or do not want to
     implement the LE PHB (e.g., because there is no separate LE queue
     available in the corresponding nodes) SHOULD NOT drop packets
     marked with the LE DSCP. They SHOULD map packets with this DSCP
     to the default PHB and SHOULD preserve the LE DSCP marking.  DS
     domain operators that do not implement the LE PHB should be
     aware that they violate the "no harm" property of LE.  See also
     <xref target="sec:phb_remark"/> for further discussion of
     forwarding LE traffic with the default PHB instead of the LE PHB.
     </t>

   </section>
   
   <section title="Re&nbhy;marking to Other DSCPs/PHBs" anchor="sec:phb_remark">
     <t>"DSCP bleaching", i.e., setting the DSCP to '000000' (default
     PHB) is NOT RECOMMENDED for this PHB. This may cause effects that
     are in contrast to the original intent to protect BE traffic
     from LE traffic (the "no harm" property). In the case that a DS domain
     does not support the LE PHB, its nodes SHOULD treat LE&nbhy;marked
     packets with the default PHB instead (by mapping the LE DSCP to the
     default PHB), but they SHOULD do so without re&nbhy;marking to DSCP
     '000000'.  This is because DS domains that are traversed later may
     then still have the opportunity to treat such packets according to
     the LE PHB.</t>

     <t>Operators of DS domains that forward LE traffic
     within the BE aggregate need to be aware of the implications,
     i.e., induced congestion situations and QoS degradation
     of the original BE traffic. In this case, the LE
     property of not harming other traffic is no longer fulfilled.
     To limit the impact in such cases, traffic policing of the
     LE aggregate MAY be used.</t>
     
     <t>In the case that LE&nbhy;marked packets are effectively carried with
     the default PHB (i.e., forwarded as BE traffic), they get a
     better forwarding treatment than expected. For some applications
     and services, it is favorable if the transmission is
     finished earlier than expected. However, in some cases, it may be
     against the original intention of the LE PHB user to strictly
     send the traffic only if otherwise-unused resources are
     available. In the case that LE traffic is mapped to the default
     PHB, LE traffic may compete with BE traffic for the
     same resources and thus adversely affect the original BE
     aggregate. Applications that want to ensure the lower
     precedence compared to BE traffic even in such cases
     SHOULD additionally use a corresponding lower-than-BE transport
     protocol <xref target="RFC6297"/>, e.g., LEDBAT <xref target="RFC6817"/>.
     </t>
     
     <t>A DS domain that still uses DSCP CS1 for marking LE traffic
     (including Low-Priority Data as defined in <xref
     target="RFC4594"/> or the old definition in <xref
     target="RFC3662"/>) SHOULD re&nbhy;mark traffic to the LE DSCP '&LE-DSCP;'
     at the egress to the next DS domain. This increases the
     probability that the DSCP is preserved end to end, whereas a
     CS1&nbhy;marked packet may be re&nbhy;marked by the default DSCP if the
     next domain is applying Diffserv-Interconnection <xref
     target="RFC8100"/>.</t>
   </section>
   
   <section anchor="sec:multicast" title="Multicast Considerations">
     <t>Basically, the multicast considerations in <xref
     target="RFC3754"/> apply.  However, using the LE PHB for multicast
     requires paying special attention to how packets get replicated
     inside routers. Due to multicast packet
     replication, resource contention may actually occur even before a
     packet is forwarded to its output port. In the worst case, these
     forwarding resources are missing for higher-priority multicast
     or even unicast packets.</t>

     <t>Several forward error correction coding schemes, such as
     fountain codes (e.g., <xref target="RFC5053"/>), allow reliable
     data delivery even in environments with a potentially high amount
     of packet loss in transmission. When used, for example, over
     satellite links or other broadcast media, this means that
     receivers that lose 80% of packets in transmission simply need
     five&nbsp;times longer to receive the complete data than those receivers
     experiencing no loss (without any receiver feedback required).</t>

     <t>Superficially viewed, it may sound very attractive to use IP
     multicast with the LE PHB to build this type of opportunistic
     reliable distribution in IP networks, but it can only be usefully
     deployed with routers that do not experience
     forwarding/replication resource starvation when a large amount of
     packets (virtually) need to be replicated to links where the LE
     queue is full.
     </t>

     <t>Thus, a packet replication mechanism for LE&nbhy;marked packets
     should consider the situation at the respective output links: it
     is a waste of internal forwarding resources if a packet is
     replicated to output links that have no resources left for LE
     forwarding. In those
     cases, a packet would have been replicated just to be dropped
     immediately after finding a filled LE queue at the respective
     output port.  Such behavior could be avoided -- for example, by using
     a conditional internal packet replication: a packet would then
     only be replicated in cases where the output link is not fully
     used. This conditional replication, however, is probably not
     widely implemented.
     </t>
     
     <t>While the resource contention problem caused by multicast
     packet replication is also true for other Diffserv PHBs, LE
     forwarding is special, because often it is assumed that LE
     packets only get forwarded in the case of available resources at the
     output ports. The previously mentioned redundancy data traffic
     could suitably use the varying available residual bandwidth being
     utilized by the LE PHB, but only if the specific requirements
     stated above for conditional replication in the internal
     implementation of the network devices are considered.</t>
   </section>
   
   
   <section anchor="sec:changes_to_4594" title="The Updates to RFC 4594">
     <t><xref target="RFC4594"/> recommended the use of CS1
     as the codepoint in its Section&nbsp;4.10, whereas CS1 was defined in
     <xref target="RFC2474" /> to have a higher precedence than CS0,
     i.e., the default PHB. Consequently, Diffserv domains implementing
     CS1 according to <xref target="RFC2474" /> will cause a priority inversion
     for LE packets that contradicts the original purpose of LE.
     Therefore, every occurrence of the CS1 DSCP is replaced by the
     LE&nbsp;DSCP.</t>

     <t>Changes:
     <list style="symbols">
     
     <t>This update to RFC 4594 removes the following entry from its
     Figure&nbsp;3:
<!-- Figure is DNE -->
     <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
|---------------+---------+-------------+--------------------------|
| Low-Priority  |  CS1    |   001000    | Any flow that has no BW  |
|     Data      |         |             | assurance                |
 ------------------------------------------------------------------
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     and replaces it with the following entry:
     <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
|---------------+---------+-------------+--------------------------|
| Low-Priority  |   LE    |   &LE-DSCP;    | Any flow that has no BW  |
|     Data      |         |             | assurance                |
 ------------------------------------------------------------------
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     </t>
<!-- First "Notes for Figure 3:" is DNE. -->     
     <t>This update to RFC 4594 extends the Notes text below Figure 3
     that currently states "Notes for Figure 3: Default Forwarding
     (DF) and Class Selector 0 (CS0) provide equivalent behavior and
     use the same DS codepoint, '000000'." to state "Notes for Figure&nbsp;3:
     Default Forwarding (DF) and Class Selector 0 (CS0) provide
     equivalent behavior and use the same DSCP, '000000'.  The
     prior recommendation to use the CS1 DSCP for Low-Priority Data
     has been replaced by the current recommendation to use the
     LE DSCP, '000001'."
     </t>
     
     <t>This update to RFC 4594 removes the following entry from its
     Figure&nbsp;4:
<!-- Figure is DNE.  Have to leave the " RFC3662 " as is. -->
     <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
|---------------+------+-------------------+---------+--------+----|
| Low-Priority  | CS1  | Not applicable    | RFC3662 |  Rate  | Yes|
|     Data      |      |                   |         |        |    |
 ------------------------------------------------------------------
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     and replaces it with the following entry:
    <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
|---------------+------+-------------------+----------+--------+----|
| Low-Priority  | LE   | Not applicable    | RFC 8622 |  Rate  | Yes|
|     Data      |      |                   |          |        |    |
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     </t>

     <t>Section 2.3 of <xref target="RFC4594"/> specifies the following:
<!-- Text in this paragraph is DNE. -->
      "In network segments that use IP precedence marking, only one of
      the two service classes can be supported, High-Throughput Data or
      Low&nbhy;Priority Data.  We RECOMMEND that the DSCP value(s) of the
      unsupported service class be changed to 000xx1 on ingress and
      changed back to original value(s) on egress of the network segment
      that uses precedence marking.  For example, if Low-Priority Data
      is mapped to Standard service class, then 000001 DSCP marking MAY
      be used to distinguish it from Standard marked packets on egress."
      This document removes this recommendation, because by using the
      LE DSCP defined herein, such re&nbhy;marking is not necessary.
      So, even if Low-Priority Data is unsupported (i.e., mapped to the
      default PHB), the LE DSCP should be kept across the domain as
      RECOMMENDED in <xref target="sec:phb_remark"/>.
      That removed text is replaced by the following:
      "In network segments that use
      IP Precedence marking, the Low-Priority Data service class
      receives the same Diffserv QoS as the Standard service class when
      the LE DSCP is used for Low-Priority Data traffic.  This is
      acceptable behavior for the Low-Priority Data service class,
      although it is not the preferred behavior."</t>
     
     <t>This document removes the following line in Section&nbsp;4.10 of
     RFC&nbsp;4594: "The RECOMMENDED DSCP marking is CS1
     (Class Selector&nbsp;1)." and replaces it with the following text:
     "The&nbsp;RECOMMENDED DSCP marking is LE (Lower Effort), which replaces
     the prior recommendation for CS1 (Class Selector 1) marking."</t>
     </list>
     </t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="sec:changes_to_8325" title="The Updates to RFC 8325">
<!-- First bit of quoted text is DNE. -->
     <t>Section 4.2.10 of RFC 8325 <xref target="RFC8325" /> specifies
     that "<xref target="RFC3662"/> and <xref target="RFC4594"/> both
     recommend Low-Priority Data be marked CS1 DSCP." This is updated to
     "<xref target="RFC3662"/> recommends that Low-Priority Data be marked CS1
     DSCP. <xref target="RFC4594"/>, as updated by RFC 8622,
     recommends that Low&nbhy;Priority Data be marked LE DSCP."</t>
     
<!-- Quoted text is DNE.  "[LE-PHB]" (as listed in RFC 8325) is an
     early draft version of this document. -->
     <t>This document removes the following paragraph in
     Section&nbsp;4.2.10 of <xref target="RFC8325"/>, because this document
     makes the anticipated change: "Note: This marking recommendation may
     change in the future, as [LE-PHB] defines a Lower Effort (LE) PHB for
     Low-Priority Data traffic and recommends an additional DSCP for
     this traffic."</t>

<!-- First bit of quoted text is DNE. -->
     <t>Section 4.2.10 of RFC 8325 <xref target="RFC8325" /> specifies that
     "therefore, it is RECOMMENDED to map Low-Priority Data traffic
     marked CS1 DSCP to UP&nbsp;1", which is updated to "therefore, it is
     RECOMMENDED to map Low&nbhy;Priority Data traffic marked with LE DSCP
     or legacy CS1 DSCP to UP&nbsp;1".</t>
     
     <t>This update to RFC 8325 replaces the following entry from its
     Figure&nbsp;1:
<!-- Figure is DNE. -->
     <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
+---------------+------+----------+------------+--------------------+
| Low-Priority  | CS1  | RFC 3662 |     1      | AC_BK (Background) |
|     Data      |      |          |            |                    |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     with the following entries:
     <figure>
       <artwork align="center">
+---------------+------+----------+------------+--------------------+
| Low-Priority  | LE   | RFC 8622 |     1      | AC_BK (Background) |
|     Data      |      |          |            |                    |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Low-Priority  | CS1  | RFC 3662 |     1      | AC_BK (Background) |
| Data (legacy) |      |          |            |                    |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
       </artwork>
     </figure>
     </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>
       This document assigns the Differentiated Services Field Codepoint (DSCP)
       '&LE-DSCP;' from the "Differentiated Services Field Codepoints (DSCP)"
       registry
       (https://www.iana.org/assignments/dscp-registry/) ("DSCP Pool 3 Codepoints",
       Codepoint Space xxxx01, Standards Action) 
       <xref target="RFC8126"/> to the LE PHB.
       This document uses a DSCP from Pool 3 in order to avoid
       problems for other PHB&nbhy;marked flows, where they could
       become accidentally re&nbhy;marked as LE PHB, e.g., due to partial DSCP
       bleaching. See <xref target="RFC8436"/> regarding reclassifying
       Pool&nbsp;3 for Standards Action.</t>

    <t>
       IANA has updated this registry as follows:
       <list style="symbols">
       <t>Name: LE</t>
       <t>Value (Binary): &LE-DSCP;</t>
       <t>Value (Decimal): 1</t>
       <t>Reference: RFC 8622</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>There are no specific security exposures for this PHB.  Since
     it defines a new class that is of low forwarding priority, re&nbhy;marking
     other traffic as LE traffic may lead to QoS degradation
     of such traffic. Thus, any attacker that is able to
     modify the DSCP of a packet to LE may carry out a downgrade
     attack. See the general security considerations in <xref
     target="RFC2474"/> and <xref target="RFC2475"/>.</t>

     <t>With respect to privacy, an attacker could use the information
     from the DSCP to infer that the transferred (probably even
     encrypted) content is considered of low priority or low urgency
     by a user if the DSCP was set per the user's request. On the
     one hand, this disclosed information is useful only if
     correlation with metadata (such as the user's IP address) and/or
     other flows reveal a user's identity. On the other hand, it might
     help an observer (e.g., a state-level actor) who is interested in
     learning about the user's behavior from observed traffic: LE&nbhy;marked
     background traffic (such as software downloads, operating system
     updates, or telemetry data) may be less interesting for
     surveillance than general web traffic. Therefore, the LE marking
     may help the observer to focus on potentially more interesting
     traffic (however, the user may exploit this particular assumption
     and deliberately hide interesting traffic in the LE aggregate).
     Apart from such considerations, the impact of disclosed information
     by the LE DSCP is likely negligible in most cases, given the numerous
     traffic analysis possibilities and general privacy threats
     (e.g., see <xref target="RFC6973"/>).
     </t>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <back>

   <references title="Normative References">

     &RFC2119;
     &RFC2474;
     &RFC2475;
     &RFC8174;

   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">

<!-- "LBE-CARLBERG" in orig., aka carlberg-lbe-2001 -->
<reference anchor="Carlberg-LBE-2001" target="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=844193.844208">
    <front>
        <title>Lower than best effort: a design and implementation</title>
        <author initials="K" surname="Carlberg" fullname="Ken Carlberg">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="P" surname="Gevros" fullname="Panos Gevros">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="J" surname="Crowcroft" fullname="Jon Crowcroft">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <date month="April" year="2001"/>
    </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review,"
 value="Volume 31 Issue 2 supplement"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/844193.844208"/>
</reference>

<!-- "LESSBE-CHOWN" in orig., aka chown-lbe-2003 -->
<reference anchor="Chown-LBE-2003" target="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F3-540-36480-3_10">
    <front>
        <title>Less than Best Effort: Application Scenarios and Experimental Results</title>
        <author initials="T" surname="Chown" fullname="T. Chown">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="T" surname="Ferrari" fullname="T. Ferrari">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="S" surname="Leinen" fullname="S. Leinen">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="R" surname="Sabatino" fullname="R. Sabatino">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="N" surname="Simar" fullname="N. Simar">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <author initials="S" surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
            <organization></organization>
        </author>
        <date month="February" year="2003"/>
    </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the Second International Workshop on
 Quality of Service in Multiservice IP Networks (QoS-IP 2003),"
 value="Lecture Notes in Computer Science"/>
  <seriesInfo name="vol 2601," value="Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg"/>
  <seriesInfo name="Pages" value="131-144"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/3-540-36480-3_10"/>
</reference>

     &RFC2914;
     &RFC3168;
     &RFC3439;
     &RFC3662;
     &RFC3754;
     &RFC4594;
     &RFC5053;
     &RFC6297;
     &RFC6817;
     &RFC6973;
     &RFC8085;
     &RFC8087;
     &RFC8126;
     &RFC8325;

<reference anchor="IETF99-Secchi"
 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/meeting/99/materials/slides-99-tsvwg-sessb-31measurements-concerning-the-dscp-for-a-le-phb-00">
<front>
<title>Measurements concerning the DSCP for a LE PHB</title>
<author initials="R" surname="Secchi" fullname="R. Secchi">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="A" surname="Venne" fullname="A. Venne">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="A" surname="Custura" fullname="A. Custura">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="July" year="2017"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Presentation held at the 99th IETF Meeting," value="TSVWG, Prague"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-bless-diffserv-lbe-phb (Expired) -->
<reference anchor='Diffserv-LBE-PHB'>
<front>
<title>A Lower Than Best-Effort Per-Hop Behavior</title>
<author initials='R' surname='Bless' fullname='Roland Bless'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Wehrle' fullname='Klaus Wehrle'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='September' year='1999' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-bless-diffserv-lbe-phb-00' />
</reference>

&DS-INTERCON; <!-- RFC 8100 -->

&RFC8436;

   </references>

   <section anchor="app-history" title="History of the LE PHB">
     <t>A first draft version of this PHB was suggested by Roland Bless and
     Klaus Wehrle in September 1999 <xref target="Diffserv-LBE-PHB"/>, named
     "A Lower Than Best-Effort Per-Hop Behavior". 
     After some discussion in the Diffserv Working Group, Brian Carpenter and
     Kathie Nichols proposed a "bulk handling" per-domain behavior and believed
     a PHB was not necessary. Eventually, "Lower Effort" was
     specified as per&nbhy;domain behavior and finally became <xref
     target="RFC3662" />.
     More detailed information about its history can be found in
     Section&nbsp;10 of <xref target="RFC3662" />. 
     </t>

     <t>There are several other names in use for this type of PHB or associated
     service classes. Well known is the QBone Scavenger Service (QBSS) that
     was proposed in March 2001 within the Internet2 QoS Working
     Group. Alternative names are
     "Lower than best effort" <xref target="Carlberg-LBE-2001"/> or
     "Less than best effort" <xref target="Chown-LBE-2003"/>.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="app-Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
     <t>Since text is partially borrowed from earlier Internet-Drafts
     and RFCs, the coauthors of previous specifications are acknowledged
     here:
     Kathie Nichols and Klaus Wehrle. David Black, Olivier Bonaventure,
     Spencer Dawkins, Toerless Eckert, Gorry Fairhurst, Ruediger Geib,
     and Kyle Rose provided helpful comments and (partially also text)
     suggestions.
     </t>
   </section>

 </back>

</rfc>
