<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2309 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2309.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2481 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2481.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3168 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3168.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3649 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3649.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3742 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3742.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3758 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3758.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4340 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4340.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4774 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4774.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5562 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5562.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5670 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5670.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5681 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5681.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5696 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5696.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6040 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6040.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6679 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6679.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6789 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6789.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<rfc number="8087" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Benefits of ECN">The Benefits of Using Explicit Congestion
    Notification (ECN)</title>

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G." surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>School of Engineering, Fraser Noble Building</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <code>AB24 3UE</code>

          <city>Aberdeen</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael Welzl" initials="M." surname="Welzl">
      <organization>University of Oslo</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box 1080 Blindern</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <code>N-0316</code>

          <city>Oslo</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+47 22 85 24 20</phone>

        <email>michawe@ifi.uio.no</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2017" />

<!-- [rfced] Steve Baillarge asked the following in early December 2016:

   Hi
   Sorry to come so late with a comment. 
   Is it too late to add one more benefit to the draft?

   I suspect ECN brings potential and significant savings in CPU cycles and 
   memory usage , especially on the "server side" terminating a large number
   of TCP connections. Has anyone done any analysis to confirm or contradict
   this assumption? 

   Regards
   Steve Baillargeon
   Ericsson

Please let us know if any updates are needed.
-->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <keyword>ecn</keyword>
    <keyword>aqm</keyword>
    <keyword>sctp</keyword>
    <keyword>tcp</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The goal of this document is to describe the potential benefits of
      applications using a transport that enables Explicit Congestion
      Notification (ECN). The document outlines the principal gains in terms
      of increased throughput, reduced delay, and other benefits when ECN is
      used over a network path that includes equipment that supports
      Congestion Experienced (CE) marking. It also discusses challenges for
      successful deployment of ECN. It does not propose new algorithms to use
      ECN nor does it describe the details of implementation of ECN in
      endpoint devices (Internet hosts), routers, or other network devices.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--    <section title="Definitions" anchor='sec-def'>
         <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
         "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
         document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
         target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
         
         <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
         <t hangText="Wha'ever:">
         <vspace />
         Wha'ever is short for Whatever.</t>
         </list></t>
         
         </section>
         -->

    <section anchor="sec-intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Internet transports (such as TCP and Stream Control Transmission
      Protocol (SCTP)) are implemented in
      endpoints (Internet hosts) and are designed to detect and react to
      network congestion. Congestion may be detected by loss of an IP packet
      or, if Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) <xref
      target="RFC3168"></xref> is enabled, by the reception of a packet with a
      Congestion Experienced (CE) marking in the IP header. Both of these are
      treated by transports as indications of congestion. ECN may also be
      enabled by other transports: UDP applications that provide congestion
      control may enable ECN when they are able to correctly process the ECN
      signals <xref target="RFC8085"></xref> (e.g., ECN with RTP <xref
      target="RFC6679"></xref>).</t>

      <t>Active Queue Management (AQM) <xref target="RFC7567"></xref> is a
      class of techniques that can be used by network devices (a router,
      middlebox, or other device that forwards packets through the network) to
      manage the size of queues in network buffers.</t>

      <t>A network device that does not support AQM typically uses a drop-tail
      policy to drop excess IP packets when its queue becomes full. The
      discard of packets is treated by transport protocols as a signal that
      indicates congestion on the end-to-end network path. End-to-end
      transports, such as TCP, can cause a low level of loss while seeking to
      share capacity with other flows. Although losses are not always due to
      congestion (loss may be due to link corruption, receiver overrun, etc.),
      endpoints have to conservatively presume that all loss is potentially
      due to congestion and reduce their rate. Observed loss therefore results
      in a congestion control reaction by the transport to reduce the maximum
      rate permitted by the sending endpoint.</t>

      <t>ECN makes it possible for the network to signal the presence of
      incipient congestion without incurring packet loss; it lets the network
      deliver some packets to an application that would otherwise have been
      dropped if the application or transport did not support ECN. This packet-loss reduction is the most obvious benefit of ECN, but it is often
      relatively modest. However, enabling ECN can also result in a number of
      beneficial side effects, some of which may be much more significant than
      the immediate packet-loss reduction from receiving a CE marking instead of
      dropping packets. Several benefits reduce latency (e.g., reduced
      head-of-line blocking).</t>

      <t>The use of ECN is indicated in the ECN field <xref
      target="RFC3168"></xref>, which is carried in the packet header of all IPv4 and
      IPv6 packets. This field may be set to one of the four values shown in Figure
      1. The Not&nbhy;ECT codepoint '00' indicates a packet that is not using ECN.
      The ECT(0) codepoint '01' and the ECT(1) codepoint '10' both indicate
      that the transport protocol using the IP layer supports the use of ECN.
      The CE codepoint '11' is set by an ECN-capable network device to
      indicate congestion to the transport endpoint.</t>

      <figure anchor="table_1" title="The ECN Field in the IP Packet
	Header (based on [RFC3168])">
          <artwork><![CDATA[+-----+-----+---------+
| ECN FIELD |  Name   |
+-----+-----+---------+
|  0  |  0  | Not-ECT | 
|  0  |  1  | ECT(1)  |
|  1  |  0  | ECT(0)  |
|  1  |  1  | CE      |
+-----+-----+---------+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
<t>When an application uses a transport that enables use of ECN <xref
      target="RFC3168"></xref>, the transport layer sets the ECT(0) or ECT(1)
      codepoint in the IP header of packets that it sends. This indicates to
      network devices that they may mark, rather than drop, the ECN-capable IP
      packets. An ECN-capable network device can then signal incipient
      congestion (network queuing) at a point before a transport experiences
      congestion loss or high queuing delay. The marking is generally
      performed as the result of various AQM algorithms <xref
      target="RFC7567"></xref> where the exact combination of AQM/ECN
      algorithms does not need to be known by the transport endpoints.</t>

      <t>The focus of the document is on usage of ECN by transport- and
      application-layer flows, not its implementation in endpoint hosts,
      routers, and other network devices.</t>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>The following terms are used:</t>

        <t>AQM: Active Queue Management.</t>

        <t>CE: Congestion Experienced; a codepoint value '11' marked in the
        ECN field of the IP packet header.</t>

        <t>ECN-capable IP Packet: A packet where the ECN field is set to a
        non-zero ECN value (i.e., with ECT(0), ECT(1), or the CE
        codepoint).</t>

        <t>ECN-capable network device: An ECN-capable network device may
        forward, drop, or queue an ECN-capable packet and may choose to
        CE mark this packet when there is incipient congestion.</t>

        <t>ECN-capable transport/application: A transport that sends
        ECN-capable IP Packets, monitors reception of the ECN field, and
        generates appropriate feedback to control the rate of the sending
        endpoint to provide end-to-end congestion control.</t>

        <t>ECN field: A 2-bit field specified for use with explicit congestion
        signaling in the IPv4 and IPv6 packet headers.</t>

        <t>Endpoint: An Internet host that terminates a transport protocol
        connection across an Internet path.</t>

        <t>Incipient Congestion: The detection of congestion when it is
        starting, perhaps by a network device noting that the arrival rate
        exceeds the forwarding rate.</t>

        <t>Network device: A router, middlebox, or other device that forwards
        IP packets through the network.</t>

        <t>non-ECN-capable: A network device or endpoint that does not
        interpret the ECN field. Such a device is not permitted to change the
        ECN codepoint.</t>

        <t>not-ECN-capable IP Packet: An IP packet with the ECN field set to a
        value of zero ('00'). A not-ECN-capable packet may be forwarded,
        dropped, or queued by a network device.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Benefit of Using ECN to Avoid Congestion Loss">
      <t>An ECN-capable network device is expected to CE mark an ECN-capable
      IP packet as a CE when an AQM method detects incipient congestion rather than
      drop the packet <xref target="RFC7567"></xref>. An application can
      benefit from this marking in several ways, which are detailed in the
      rest of this section.</t>

      <section anchor="throughput" title="Improved Throughput">
        <t>ECN seeks to avoid the inefficiency of dropping data that has
        already made it across at least part of the network path.</t>

        <t>ECN can improve the throughput of an application, although this
        increase in throughput is often not the most significant gain. When an
        application uses a lightly to moderately loaded network path, the number
        of packets that are dropped due to congestion is small. Using an
        example from Table 1 of <xref target="RFC3649"></xref>, for a standard
        TCP sender with an RTT of 0.1 seconds, a packet size
        of 1500 bytes, and an average throughput of 1 Mbps, the average packet-drop ratio would be 0.02 (i.e., 1 in 50 packets). This translates into
        an approximate 2% throughput gain if ECN is enabled. (Note that in
        heavy congestion, packet loss may be unavoidable with or without
        ECN.)</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-hol" title="Reduced Head-of-Line Blocking">
        <t>Many Internet transports provide in-order delivery of received data
        segments to the applications they support. For these applications, use
        of ECN can reduce the delay that can result when these applications
        experience packet loss.</t>

        <t>Packet loss may occur for various reasons. One cause arises when an
        AQM scheme drops a packet as a signal of incipient congestion.
        Whatever the cause of loss, a missing packet needs to trigger a
        congestion control response. A reliable transport also triggers
        retransmission to recover the lost data. For a transport providing
        in-order delivery, this requires that the transport receiver stall
        (or wait) for all data that was sent ahead of a lost segment to be
        correctly received before it can forward any later data to the
        application. A loss therefore creates a delay of at least one RTT
        after a loss event before data can be delivered to an application. We
        call this head-of-line blocking. This is the usual requirement
        for TCP and SCTP. Partially Reliable SCTP (PR&nbhy;SCTP) <xref target="RFC3758"></xref>, UDP <xref
        target="RFC0768"></xref> <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>, and the
        Datagram Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP) <xref
	target="RFC4340"></xref> provide a transport that does not
        provide reordering.</t>

        <t>By enabling ECN, a transport continues to receive in-order data
        when there is incipient congestion and can pass this data to the
        receiving application. Use of ECN avoids the additional reordering
        delay in a reliable transport. The sender still needs to make an
        appropriate congestion response to reduce the maximum transmission
        rate for future traffic, which usually will require a reduction in the
        sending rate <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reduced Probability of RTO Expiry">
        <t>Some patterns of packet loss can result in a Retransmission Timeout
	(RTO), 
        which causes a sudden and significant change in the allowed
        rate at which a transport/application can forward packets. Because ECN
        provides an alternative to drop for network devices to signal
        incipient congestion, this can reduce the probability of loss and
        hence reduce the likelihood of RTO expiry.</t>

        <t>Internet transports/applications generally use an RTO timer as a
        last resort to detect and recover loss <xref
        target="RFC8085"></xref> <xref target="RFC5681"></xref>.
        Specifically, an RTO timer detects loss of a packet that is not
        followed by other packets, such as at the end of a burst of data
        segments or when an application becomes idle (either because the
        application has no further data to send or the network prevents
        sending further data, e.g., flow or congestion control at the
        transport layer). This loss of the last segment (or last few segments)
        of a traffic burst is also known as a "tail loss". Standard transport
        recovery methods, such as Fast Recovery <xref
        target="RFC5681"></xref>, are often unable to recover from a tail
        loss. This is because the endpoint receiver is unaware that the lost
        segments were actually sent and therefore generates no feedback <xref
        target="Fla13"></xref>. Retransmission of these segments 
        relies on expiry of a transport retransmission timer. This timer is
        also used to detect a lack of forwarding along a path. Expiry of the
        RTO results in the consequent loss of state about the
        network path being used. This typically includes resetting path
        estimates such as the RTT, reinitializing the congestion window, and
        possibly making updates to other transport state. This can reduce the
        performance of the transport until it again adapts to the path.</t>

        <t>An ECN-capable network device cannot eliminate the possibility of
        tail loss because a drop may occur due to a traffic burst exceeding
        the instantaneous available capacity of a network buffer or as a
        result of the AQM algorithm (e.g., overload protection mechanisms <xref
        target="RFC7567"></xref>). However, an ECN-capable network device that
        observes incipient congestion may be expected to buffer the IP packets
        of an ECN-capable flow and set a CE mark in one or more packet(s)
        rather than triggering packet drop. Setting a CE mark signals
        incipient congestion without forcing the transport/application to
        enter retransmission timeout. This reduces application-level latency
        and can improve the throughput for applications that send intermittent
        bursts of data.</t>

        <t>The benefit of avoiding retransmission loss is expected to be
        significant when ECN is used on TCP SYN/ACK packets <xref
        target="RFC5562"></xref> where the RTO interval may be large because
        TCP cannot base the timeout period on prior RTT measurements from the
        same connection.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applications That Do Not Retransmit Lost Packets">
        <t>A transport that enables ECN can receive timely congestion signals
        without the need to retransmit packets each time it receives a
        congestion signal.</t>

        <t>Some latency-critical applications do not retransmit lost packets,
        yet they may be able to adjust their sending rate following detection of
        incipient congestion. Examples of such applications include UDP-based
        services that carry Voice over IP (VoIP), interactive video, or
        real-time data. The performance of many such applications degrades
        rapidly with increasing packet loss, and the transport/application may
        therefore employ mechanisms (e.g., packet forward error correction,
        data duplication, or media codec error concealment) to mitigate the
        immediate effect of congestion loss on the application. Some
        mechanisms consume additional network capacity, some require
        additional processing, and some contribute additional path latency when
        congestion is experienced. By decoupling congestion control from loss,
        ECN can allow transports that support these applications to reduce
        their rate before the application experiences loss from congestion.
        This can reduce the negative impact of triggering loss-hiding
        mechanisms with a direct positive impact on the quality experienced by
        the users of these applications.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-visibility"
               title="Making Incipient Congestion Visible">
        <t>A characteristic of using ECN is that it exposes the presence of
        congestion on a network path to the transport and network layers, thus
        allowing information to be collected about the presence of incipient
        congestion.</t>

        <t>Recording the presence of CE-marked packets can provide information
        about the current congestion level experienced on a network path. A
        network flow that only experiences CE marking and no loss implies that
        the sending endpoint is experiencing only congestion. A network flow
        may also experience loss (e.g., due to queue overflow, AQM methods
        that protect other flows, link corruption, or loss in middleboxes).
        When a mixture of CE marking and packet loss is experienced,
        transports and measurements need to assume there is congestion <xref
        target="RFC7567"></xref>. Therefore, an absence of CE marks does not
        indicate a path has not experienced congestion.</t>

        <t>The reception of CE-marked packets can be used to monitor the level
        of congestion by a transport/application or a network operator. For
        example, ECN measurements are used by Congestion Exposure (ConEx)
        <xref target="RFC6789"></xref>. In contrast, metering packet loss is
        harder.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Acc-feedback"
               title="Opportunities for New Transport Mechanisms">
        <t>ECN can enable design and deployment of new algorithms in network
        devices and Internet transports. Internet transports need to regard
        both loss and CE marking as an indication of congestion. 

However,
        while the amount of feedback provided by drop ought naturally be
        minimized, this is not the case for ECN. In contrast, an ECN-capable
        network device could provide richer (more frequent and fine-grained)
        indication of its congestion state to the transport.</t>

        <t>For any ECN-capable transport (ECT), the receiving endpoint needs to
        provide feedback to the transport sender to indicate that CE marks
        have been received. <xref target="RFC3168"> </xref> provides one method
        that signals once each round-trip time (RTT) that CE-marked packets have
        been received.</t>

        <t>A receiving endpoint may provide more detailed feedback to the
        congestion controller at the sender (e.g., describing the set of
        received ECN codepoints or indicating each received CE-marked
        packet). Precise feedback about the number of CE marks encountered is
        supported by RTP when used over UDP <xref
        target="RFC6679"></xref> and has been proposed for SCTP <xref
        target="ST14"></xref> and TCP <xref target="ECN-FEEDBACK"></xref>.</t>

        <t>More detailed feedback is expected to enable evolution of transport
        protocols allowing the congestion control mechanism to make a more
        appropriate decision on how to react to congestion. Designers of
        transport protocols need to consider not only how network devices
        CE-mark packets but also how the control loop in the
        application/transport reacts to reception of these CE-marked
        packets.</t>

        <t>Benefit has been noted when packets are CE marked early using an
        instantaneous queue, and if the receiving endpoint provides feedback
        about the number of packet marks encountered, an improved sender
        behavior has been shown to be possible, e.g, Data Center TCP (DCTCP)
        <xref target="AL10"></xref>. DCTCP is targeted at controlled
        environments such as a data center. This is a work in progress, and it is
        currently unknown whether or how such behavior could be safely
        introduced into the Internet. Any update to an Internet transport
        protocol requires careful consideration of the robustness of the
        behavior when working with endpoints or network devices that were not
        designed for the new congestion reaction.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Support for ECN">
<t>For an application to use ECN requires that the endpoints
enable ECN within the transport being used. It also requires 
that all network devices along the path at least forward IP 
packets that set a non-zero ECN codepoint.</t>

      <t>ECN can be deployed both in the general Internet and in controlled
      environments:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>ECN can be incrementally deployed in the general Internet. The
          IETF has provided guidance on configuration and usage in <xref
          target="RFC7567"></xref>.</t>

          <t>ECN may be deployed within a controlled environment, for example,
          within a data center or within a well-managed private network. This
          use of ECN may be tuned to the specific use case. An example is
          DCTCP <xref target="AL10"></xref> <xref
          target="DCTCP"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Early experience of using ECN across the general Internet encountered
      a number of operational difficulties when the network path either failed
      to transfer ECN-capable packets or inappropriately changed the ECN
      codepoints <xref target="BA11"></xref>. A recent survey reported a
      growing support for network paths to pass ECN codepoints <xref
      target="TR15"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The remainder of this section identifies what is needed for network
      devices to effectively support ECN.</t>

      <section anchor="Codepoint" title="The ECN Field ">
        <t>The current IPv4 and IPv6 specifications assign usage of 2 bits in
        the IP header to carry the ECN codepoint. This 2-bit field was
        reserved in <xref target="RFC2474"></xref> and assigned in <xref
        target="RFC3168"></xref>.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC4774"></xref> discusses some of the issues in
        defining alternate semantics for the ECN field and specifies
        requirements for a safe coexistence in an Internet that could include
        routers that do not understand the defined alternate semantics.</t>

        <t>Some network devices were configured to use a routing hash that
        included the set of 8 bits forming the now deprecated Type of Service
        (TOS) field <xref target="RFC1349"></xref>. The present use of this
        field assigns 2 of these bits to carry the ECN field. This is
        incompatible with use in a routing hash because it could lead to IP
        packets that carry a CE mark being routed over a different path to
        those packets that carried an ECT mark. The resultant reordering would
        impact the performance of transport protocols (such as TCP or SCTP)
        and UDP-based applications that are sensitive to reordering. A network
        device that conforms to this older specification needs to be updated
        to the current specifications <xref target="RFC2474"> </xref> to
        support ECN. Configuration of network devices must note that the ECN
        field may be updated by any ECN-capable network device along a
        path.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Forwarding" title="Forwarding ECN-Capable IP Packets">
        <t>Not all network devices along a path need to be ECN-capable (i.e.,
        perform CE marking). However, all network devices need to be
        configured not to drop packets solely because the ECT(0) or ECT(1)
        codepoints are used.</t>

        <t>Any network device that does not perform CE marking of an
        ECN-capable packet can be expected to drop these packets under
        congestion. Applications that experience congestion at these network
        devices do not see any benefit from enabling ECN. However, they may
        see benefit if the congestion were to occur within a network device
        that did support ECN.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Enabling" title="Enabling ECN in Network Devices">
        <t>Network devices should use an AQM algorithm that CE-marks
        ECN-capable traffic when making decisions about the response to
        congestion <xref target="RFC7567"></xref>. An ECN method should set a
        CE mark on ECN-capable packets in the presence of incipient
        congestion. A CE-marked packet will be interpreted as an indication of
        incipient congestion by the transport endpoints.</t>

        <t>There is an opportunity to design an AQM method for an ECN-capable
        network device that differs from an AQM method designed to drop
        packets. <xref target="RFC7567"></xref> states that the network device
        should allow this behavior to be configurable.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC3168"></xref> describes a method in which a
        network device sets the CE mark at the time that the network device
        would otherwise have dropped the packet. While it has often been
        assumed that network devices should CE-mark packets at the same level
        of congestion at which they would otherwise have dropped them, <xref
        target="RFC7567"></xref> recommends that network devices allow
        independent configuration of the settings for AQM dropping and ECN
        marking. Such separate configuration of the drop and mark policies is
        supported in some network devices.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Non-ECN" title="Coexistence of ECN and Non-ECN Flows">
        <t>Network devices need to be able to forward all IP flows and provide
        appropriate treatment for both ECN and non-ECN traffic.</t>

        <t>The design considerations for an AQM scheme supporting ECN needs to
        consider the impact of queueing during incipient congestion. For
        example, a simple AQM scheme could choose to queue ECN-capable and
        non-ECN-capable flows in the same queue with an ECN scheme that
        CE-marks packets during incipient congestion. The CE-marked packets
        that remain in the queue during congestion can continue to contribute
        to queueing delay. In contrast, non-ECN-capable packets would normally
        be dropped by an AQM scheme under incipient congestion. This
        difference in queueing is one motivation for consideration of more
        advanced AQM schemes and may provide an incentive for enabling flow
        isolation using scheduling <xref target="RFC7567"></xref>. The IETF is
        defining methods to evaluate the suitability of AQM schemes for
        deployment in the general Internet <xref
        target="RFC7928"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Bleaching"
               title="Bleaching and Middlebox Requirements to Deploy ECN">
        <t>Network devices should not be configured to change the ECN
        codepoint in the packets that they forward, except to set the
        CE codepoint to signal incipient congestion.</t>

        <t>Cases have been noted where an endpoint sends a packet with a
        non-zero ECN mark, but the packet is received by the remote endpoint
        with a zero ECN codepoint <xref target="TR15"></xref>. This could be a
        result of a policy that erases or "bleaches" the ECN codepoint values
        at a network edge (resetting the codepoint to zero). Bleaching may
        occur for various reasons (including normalizing packets to hide which
        equipment supports ECN). This policy prevents use of ECN by
        applications.</t>

        <t>When ECN-capable IP packets, marked as ECT(0) or ECT(1), are
        re-marked to non-ECN-capable (i.e., the ECN field is set to the zero
        codepoint), this could result in the packets being dropped by
        ECN-capable network devices further along the path. This eliminates
        the advantage of using of ECN.</t>

        <t>A network device must not change a packet with a CE mark to a zero
        codepoint; if the network device decides not to forward the packet
        with the CE mark, it has to instead drop the packet and not bleach the
        marking. This is because a CE-marked packet has already received ECN
        treatment in the network, and re-marking it would then hide the
        congestion signal from the receiving endpoint. This eliminates the
        benefits of ECN. It can also slow down the response to congestion
        compared to using AQM because the transport will only react if it
        later discovers congestion by some other mechanism.</t>

        <t>Prior to <xref target="RFC2474"/>, a previous usage assigned the bits now forming
        the ECN field as a part of the now deprecated TOS
        field <xref target="RFC1349"></xref>. A network device that conforms
        to this older specification was allowed to re-mark or erase the ECN
        codepoints, and such equipment needs to be updated to the current
        specifications in order to support ECN.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Tunnels"
               title="Tunneling ECN and the Use of ECN by Lower-Layer Networks">
        <t>Some networks may use ECN internally or tunnel ECN (e.g., for
        traffic engineering or security). These methods need to ensure that
        the ECN field of the tunnel packets is handled correctly at the
        ingress and egress of the tunnel. Guidance on the correct use of ECN
        is provided in <xref target="RFC6040"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Further guidance on the encapsulation and use of ECN by non-IP network
        devices is provided in <xref
        target="ECN-ENCAP"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mechanisms" title="Using ECN across the Internet">
      <t>A receiving endpoint needs to report the loss it experiences when it
      uses loss-based congestion control. So also, when ECN is enabled, a
      receiving endpoint must correctly report the presence of CE marks by
      providing a mechanism to feed this congestion information back to the
      sending endpoint <xref target="RFC3168"></xref> <xref
      target="RFC8085"></xref>, thus enabling the sender to react to
      experienced congestion. This mechanism needs to be designed to operate
      robustly across a wide range of Internet path characteristics. 
      This section describes partial deployment, that is, how ECN-enabled endpoints can
      continue to work effectively over a path that experiences misbehaving
      network devices or when an endpoint does not correctly provide feedback
      of ECN information.</t>

      <section title="Partial Deployment">
        <t>Use of ECN is negotiated between the endpoints prior to using the
        mechanism.</t>

        <t>ECN has been designed to allow incremental partial deployment <xref
        target="RFC3168"></xref>. Any network device can choose to use either
        ECN or some other loss-based policy to manage its traffic. Similarly,
        transport/application negotiation allows sending and receiving
        endpoints to choose whether ECN will be used to manage congestion for
        a particular network flow.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Verification"
               title="Detecting Whether a Path Really Supports ECN">
        <t>Internet transports and applications need to be robust to the
        variety and sometimes varying path characteristics that are
        encountered in the general Internet. They need to monitor correct
        forwarding of ECN over the entire path and duration of a session.</t>

        <t>To be robust, applications and transports need to be designed with
        the expectation of heterogeneous forwarding (e.g., where some IP
        packets are CE marked by one network device and some by another, 
        possibly using a different AQM algorithm, or when a combination of
        CE marking and loss-based congestion indications are used). Note that <xref
        target="RFC7928"></xref> describes methodologies for evaluating
        AQM schemes.</t>

        <t>A transport/application also needs to be robust to path changes. A
        change in the set of network devices along a path could impact the
        ability to effectively signal or use ECN across the path, e.g., when a
        path changes to use a middlebox that bleaches ECN codepoints (see
        <xref target="Bleaching"></xref>).</t>

        <t>A sending endpoint can check that any CE marks applied to packets
        received over the path are indeed delivered to the remote receiving
        endpoint and that appropriate feedback is provided. (This could be
        done by a sender setting a known CE codepoint for specific packets in
        a network flow and then checking whether the remote endpoint correctly
        reports these marks <xref target="ECN-FALLBACK"></xref> <xref
        target="TR15"></xref>.) If a sender detects persistent misuse of ECN,
        it needs to fall back to using loss-based recovery and congestion
        control. Guidance on a suitable transport reaction is provided in <xref
        target="ECN-FALLBACK"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Cheating"
               title="Detecting ECN-Receiver Feedback Cheating">
        <t>Appropriate feedback requires that the endpoint receiver not
        try to conceal reception of CE-marked packets in the ECN feedback
        information provided to the sending endpoint <xref
        target="RFC7567"></xref>. Designers of applications/transports are
        therefore encouraged to include mechanisms that can detect this
        misbehavior. If a sending endpoint detects that a receiver is not
        correctly providing this feedback, it needs to fall back to using
        loss-based recovery instead of ECN.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Summary: Enabling ECN in Network Devices and Hosts">
      <t>This section summarizes the benefits of deploying and using ECN
      within the Internet. It also provides a list of prerequisites to achieve
      ECN deployment.</t>

      <t>Application developers should, where possible, use transports that
      enable ECN. Applications that directly use UDP need to provide support
      to implement the functions required for ECN <xref
      target="RFC8085"></xref>. Once enabled, an application that uses
      a transport that supports ECN will experience the benefits of ECN as
      network deployment starts to enable ECN. The application does not need
      to be rewritten to gain these benefits. Figure 2 summarizes the key
      benefits.</t>

      <figure anchor="table_2" title="Summary of Key Benefits">
        <artwork><![CDATA[+---------+-----------------------------------------------------+
| Section | Benefit                                             |
+---------+-----------------------------------------------------+
|   2.1   | Improved Throughput                                 |
|   2.2   | Reduced Head-of-Line Blocking                       |
|   2.3   | Reduced Probability of RTO Expiry                   |
|   2.4   | Applications that do not Retransmit Lost Packets    |
|   2.5   | Making Incipient Congestion Visible                 |
|   2.6   | Opportunities for New Transport Mechanisms          |
+---------+-----------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Network operators and people configuring network devices should
      enable ECN <xref target="RFC7567"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Prerequisites for network devices (including IP routers) to enable
      use of ECN include:<list style="symbols">
          <t>A network device that updates the ECN field in IP packets must
          use IETF-specified methods (see <xref
          target="Codepoint"></xref>).</t>

          <t>A network device may support alternate ECN semantics (see <xref
          target="Codepoint"></xref>).</t>

          <t>A network device must not choose a different network path solely
          because a packet carries a CE-codepoint set in the ECN Field;
          CE-marked packets need to follow the same path as packets with an
          ECT(0) or ECT(1) codepoint (see <xref
          target="Codepoint"></xref>). Network devices need to be configured
          not to drop packets solely because the ECT(0) or ECT(1) codepoints
          are used (see <xref target="Forwarding"></xref>).</t>

          <t>An ECN-capable network device should correctly update the ECN
          codepoint of ECN-capable packets in the presence of incipient
          congestion (see <xref target="Enabling"></xref>).</t>

          <t>Network devices need to be able to forward both ECN-capable and
          not-ECN-capable flows (see <xref target="Non-ECN"></xref>).</t>

	  <t>A network device must not change a packet with a CE mark to a
	  not-ECN-capable codepoint ('00'); if the network device decides not
	  to forward the packet with the CE mark, it has to instead drop the 
	  packet and not bleach the marking (see <xref target="Bleaching"></xref>).</t>

        </list></t>

      <t>Prerequisites for network endpoints to enable use of ECN include the following:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>An application should use an Internet transport that can set and
          receive ECN marks (see <xref target="mechanisms"></xref>).</t>

          <t>An ECN-capable transport/application must return feedback
          indicating congestion to the sending endpoint and perform an
          appropriate congestion response (see <xref
          target="mechanisms"></xref>).</t>

          <t>An ECN-capable transport/application should detect paths where
          there is persistent misuse of ECN and fall back to not
          sending ECT(0) or ECT(1) (see <xref
          target="Verification"></xref>).</t>

          <t>Designers of applications/transports are encouraged to include
          mechanisms that can detect and react appropriately to misbehaving
          receivers that fail to report CE-marked packets (see <xref
          target="Cheating"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces no new security considerations. Each RFC
      listed in this document discusses the security considerations of the
      specification it contains.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

<reference  anchor='RFC3168' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3168'>
<front>
<title>The Addition of Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) to IP</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Ramakrishnan' fullname='K. Ramakrishnan'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Floyd' fullname='S. Floyd'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Black' fullname='D. Black'><organization /></author>
<date year='2001' month='September' />
<abstract><t>This memo specifies the incorporation of ECN (Explicit Congestion Notification) to TCP and IP, including ECN's use of two bits in the IP header.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3168'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3168'/>
</reference>


<reference  anchor='RFC7567' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7567'>
<front>
<title>IETF Recommendations Regarding Active Queue Management</title>
<author initials='F.' surname='Baker' fullname='F. Baker' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Fairhurst' fullname='G. Fairhurst' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2015' month='July' />
<abstract><t>This memo presents recommendations to the Internet community concerning measures to improve and preserve Internet performance.  It presents a strong recommendation for testing, standardization, and widespread deployment of active queue management (AQM) in network devices to improve the performance of today's Internet.  It also urges a concerted effort of research, measurement, and ultimate deployment of AQM mechanisms to protect the Internet from flows that are not sufficiently responsive to congestion notification.</t><t>Based on 15 years of experience and new research, this document replaces the recommendations of RFC 2309.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='197'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7567'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7567'/>
</reference>


<reference  anchor='RFC2474' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2474'>
<front>
<title>Definition of the Differentiated Services Field (DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Nichols' fullname='K. Nichols'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Blake' fullname='S. Blake'><organization /></author>
<author initials='F.' surname='Baker' fullname='F. Baker'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Black' fullname='D. Black'><organization /></author>
<date year='1998' month='December' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2474'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2474'/>
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis-19: RFC 8085-->

<reference anchor='RFC8085' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8085">
<front>
<title>UDP Usage Guidelines</title>

<author initials='L' surname='Eggert' fullname='Lars Eggert'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Fairhurst' fullname='Gorry Fairhurst'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Shepherd' fullname='Greg Shepherd'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='145' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8085' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8085"/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='RFC6040' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6040'>
<front>
<title>Tunnelling of Explicit Congestion Notification</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Briscoe' fullname='B. Briscoe'><organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6040'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6040'/>
</reference>


    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<reference  anchor='RFC0768' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc768'>
<front>
<title>User Datagram Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
<date year='1980' month='August' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='6'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='768'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0768'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='RFC1349' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1349'>
<front>
<title>Type of Service in the Internet Protocol Suite</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Almquist' fullname='P. Almquist'><organization /></author>
<date year='1992' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1349'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC1349'/>
</reference>

      &RFC3649;

      &RFC3758;

      &RFC4340;

      &RFC4774;

      &RFC5562;

      &RFC5681;

      &RFC6679;

      &RFC6789;

<!-- draft-ietf-tcpm-accurate-ecn-02: I-D Exists-->

<reference anchor='ECN-FEEDBACK'>
<front>
<title>More Accurate ECN Feedback in TCP</title>

<author initials='B' surname='Briscoe' fullname='Bob Briscoe'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Kuehlewind' fullname='Mirja Kuehlewind'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Scheffenegger' fullname='Richard Scheffenegger'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2016' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-tcpm-accurate-ecn-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-tcpm-accurate-ecn-02.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-bensley-tcpm-dctcp-05: I-D Expired-->

<reference anchor='DCTCP'>
<front>
<title>Microsoft's Datacenter TCP (DCTCP): TCP Congestion Control for Datacenters</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Bensley' fullname='Stephen Bensley'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Eggert' fullname='Lars Eggert'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Balasubramanian' fullname='Praveen Balasubramanian'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Judd' fullname='Glenn Judd'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' year='2015' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-bensley-tcpm-dctcp-05' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-bensley-tcpm-dctcp-05.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-aqm-eval-guidelines: Now RFC 7928-->
<reference  anchor='RFC7928' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7928'>
<front>
<title>Characterization Guidelines for Active Queue Management (AQM)</title>
<author initials='N.' surname='Kuhn' fullname='N. Kuhn' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Natarajan' fullname='P. Natarajan' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Khademi' fullname='N. Khademi' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Ros' fullname='D. Ros'><organization /></author>
<date year='2016' month='July' />
<abstract><t>Unmanaged large buffers in today's networks have given rise to a slew of performance issues.  These performance issues can be addressed by some form of Active Queue Management (AQM) mechanism, optionally in combination with a packet-scheduling scheme such as fair queuing. This document describes various criteria for performing characterizations of AQM schemes that can be used in lab testing during development, prior to deployment.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7928'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7928'/>
</reference>


<!--draft-kuehlewind-tcpm-ecn-fallback-01: I-D Expired -->
<reference anchor='ECN-FALLBACK'>
<front>
<title>A Mechanism for ECN Path Probing and Fallback</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Kuehlewind' fullname='Mirja Kuehlewind'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Trammell' fullname='Brian Trammell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-kuehlewind-tcpm-ecn-fallback-01' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-kuehlewind-tcpm-ecn-fallback-01.txt' />
</reference>


<!--draft-ietf-tsvwg-ecn-encap-guidelines-07: I-D Exists-->

<reference anchor='ECN-ENCAP'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Adding Congestion Notification to Protocols that Encapsulate IP</title>

<author initials='B' surname='Briscoe' fullname='Bob Briscoe'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Kaippallimalil' fullname='John Kaippallimalil'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Thaler' fullname='Patricia Thaler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' year='2016' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-tsvwg-ecn-encap-guidelines-07' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-tsvwg-ecn-encap-guidelines-07.txt' />
</reference>


      <reference anchor="BA11">
        <front>
          <title>Measuring the State of ECN Readiness in Servers, Clients, and
          Routers</title>

          <author fullname="Steven Bauer" initials="Steven" surname="Bauer">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Robert Beverly" initials="Robert"
                  surname="Beverly">
          </author>

          <author fullname="Arthur Berger" initials="Arthur" surname="Berger">
            </author>

          <date month="November" year="2011" />
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 2011 ACM SIGCOMM Conference on
			  ICM,"
		    value="pages 171-180"/>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2068816.2068833"/>
    </reference>

      <reference anchor="AL10" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Data Center TCP (DCTCP)</title>

          <author fullname="M. Alizadeh" initials="M." surname="Alizadeh"></author>

          <author fullname="A. Greenberg" initials="A." surname="Greenberg"></author>

          <author fullname="D. A. Maltz" initials="D. A." surname="Maltz"></author>

          <author fullname="J. Padhye" initials="J." surname="Padhye"></author>

          <author fullname="P. Patel" initials="P." surname="Patel"></author>

          <author fullname="B. Prabhakar" initials="B." surname="Prabhakar"></author>

          <author fullname="S. Sengupta" initials="S." surname="Sengupta"></author>

          <author fullname="M. Sridharan" initials="M." surname="Sridharan"></author>

          <date month="October" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review,"
		    value="Volume 40, Issue 4, pages 63-74" />
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/1851182.1851192"/>
      </reference>

      <!--       <reference anchor="KH13" target="">
        <front>
          <title>The New AQM Kids on the Block: Much Ado About
          Nothing?</title>

          <author fullname="N. Perkins" initials="N." surname="Khademi"></author>

          <author fullname="D. Ros" initials="D." surname="Ros"></author>

          <author fullname="M. Welzl" initials="M." surname="Welzl"></author>

          <date month="October" year="2013" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="University of Oslo Department of Informatics technical report"
                    value="434" />
      </reference>
-->

      <reference anchor="Fla13" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Reducing web latency: the virtue of gentle
          aggression</title>

          <author fullname="Tobias Flach" initials="Tobias" surname="Flach"></author>

          <author fullname="Nandita Dukkipati" initials="Nandita"
                  surname="Dukkipati"></author>

          <author fullname="Andreas Terzis" initials="Andreas"
                  surname="Terzis"></author>

          <author fullname="Barath Raghavan" initials="Barath"
                  surname="Raghavan"></author>

          <author fullname="Neal Cardwell" initials="Neal" surname="Cardwell"></author>

          <author fullname="Yuchung Cheng" initials="Yuchung" surname="Cheng"></author>

          <author fullname="Ankur Jain" initials="Ankur" surname="Jain"></author>

          <author fullname="Shuai Hao" initials="Shuai" surname="Hao"></author>

          <author fullname="Ethan Katz-Bassett" initials="Ethan"
                  surname="Katz-Bassett">
          </author>

          <author fullname="Ramesh Govindan" initials="Ramesh"
                  surname="Govindan">
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2013" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review,"
		    value="Volume 43, Issue 4, pages 159-170" />
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2534169.2486014"/>
      </reference>

<!-- draft-stewart-tsvwg-sctpecn-05: I-D Expired -->

<reference anchor='ST14'>
<front>
<title>ECN for Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP)</title>
<author initials='R' surname='Stewart' fullname='Randall Stewart'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Tuexen' fullname='Michael Tuexen'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='X' surname='Dong' fullname='Xuesong Dong'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='January' year='2014' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-stewart-tsvwg-sctpecn-05' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-stewart-tsvwg-sctpecn-05.txt' />
</reference>

      <reference anchor="TR15">
        <front>
	  <title>Enabling Internet-Wide Deployment of Explicit Congestion Notification</title>

          <author fullname="B. Trammel" initials="Brian" surname="Tranmmel">
            <organization>Tr</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Kuehlewind" initials="Mirja"
                  surname="Kuehlewind">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Boppart" initials=" Damiano" surname="Boppart">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="I. Learmonth" initials="Iain" surname="Learmonth">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Fairhurst" initials="Gorry"
                  surname=" Fairhurst">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015" />
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="Lecture Notes in Computer Science," value="Volume
	  8995, pp 193-205"/>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-319-15509-8_15"/>
      </reference>

      <!--	  <reference anchor="rtcweb-usecases" target="">
             <front>
             <title>Web Real-Time Communication Use-cases and Requirements</title>
             <author initials="C." surname="Holmberg" fullname="C. Holmberg"></author>
             <author initials="S." surname="Hakansson" fullname="S. Hakansson"></author>
             <author initials="G." surname="Eriksson" fullname="G. Eriksson"></author>
             <date month="December" year="2012"/>
             </front>
             <seriesInfo name="Internet-draft" value="draft-ietf-rtcweb-use-cases-and-requirements-10.txt"/>
             </reference>
             
             <reference anchor="transport-multiplex" target="">
             <front>
             <title>Multiple RTP Sessions on a Single Lower-Layer Transport</title>
             <author initials="M." surname="Westerlund" fullname="M. Westerlund"></author>
             <author initials="C." surname="Perkins" fullname="C. Perkins"></author>
             <date month="October" year="2012"/>
             </front>
             <seriesInfo name="Internet-draft" value="draft-westerlund-avtcore-transport-multiplexing-04.txt"/>
             </reference>
             
             <reference anchor="rtcweb-rtp-usage" target="">
             <front>
             <title>Web Real-Time Communication (WebRTC): Media Transport and Use of RTP</title>
             <author initials="C." surname="Perkins" fullname="C. Perkins"></author>
             <author initials="M." surname="Westerlund" fullname="M. Westerlund"></author>
             <author initials="J." surname="Ott" fullname="J. Ott"></author>
             <date month="October" year="2012"/>
             </front>
             <seriesInfo name="Internet-draft" value="draft-ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage-05.txt"/>
             </reference>
             -->
    </references>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>The authors were partly funded by the European Community under its
Seventh Framework Programme through the Reducing Internet Transport
Latency (RITE) project (ICT-317700). The views expressed are solely
those of the authors.</t>
<t>The authors would like to thank the following people for their
comments on prior draft  versions of this document: Bob Briscoe, David
Collier-Brown, Colin Perkins, Richard Scheffenegger, Dave Taht, Wes
Eddy, Fred Baker, Mikael Abrahamsson, Mirja Kuehlewind, John Leslie, and
other members of the TSVWG and AQM working groups.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
