<?xml version='1.0' encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='1'?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>

<rfc number="8261" category="std" submissionType="IETF"
     ipr="trust200902">

<front>
<title abbrev='SCTP over DTLS'>
Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Encapsulation of SCTP Packets
</title>

<author initials='M.' surname='Tuexen' fullname='Michael Tuexen'>
  <organization abbrev='Muenster Univ. of Appl. Sciences'>
                Muenster University of Applied Sciences</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Stegerwaldstrasse 39</street>
      <city>48565 Steinfurt</city>
      <country>Germany</country>
    </postal>
    <email>tuexen@fh-muenster.de</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='R. R.' surname='Stewart' fullname='Randall R. Stewart'>
  <organization>Netflix, Inc.</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street></street>
      <city>Chapin</city>
      <region>SC</region>
      <code>29036</code>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </postal>
    <email>randall@lakerest.net</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='R.' surname='Jesup' fullname='Randell Jesup'>
  <organization>WorldGate Communications</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>3800 Horizon Blvd, Suite #103</street>
      <city>Trevose</city>
      <region>PA</region>
      <code>19053-4947</code>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+1-215-354-5166</phone>
    <email>randell-ietf@jesup.org</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='S.' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
  <organization>Ericsson</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
      <city>Jorvas</city>
      <code> 02420 </code>
      <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>Salvatore.Loreto@ericsson.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date month="November" year="2017"/>

<abstract>
<t>The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) is a transport protocol
originally defined to run on top of the network protocols IPv4 or IPv6.
This document specifies how SCTP can be used on top of the Datagram
Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol.
Using the encapsulation method described in this document, SCTP is unaware
of the protocols being used below DTLS; hence, explicit IP addresses cannot
be used in the SCTP control chunks. As a consequence, the SCTP associations
carried over DTLS can only be single-homed.
</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>
<section title='Overview'>
<t>The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) as defined in
<xref target='RFC4960'/> is a transport protocol running on top of the network
protocols IPv4 <xref target='RFC0791'/> or IPv6 <xref target='RFC8200'/>.

This document specifies how SCTP is used on top of the Datagram
Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol.
DTLS 1.0 is defined in <xref target='RFC4347'/>, and the latest version when
this RFC was published, DTLS 1.2, is defined in <xref target='RFC6347'/>.
This encapsulation is used, for example, within the WebRTC protocol suite
(see <xref target='RTC-OVERVIEW'/> for an overview)
for transporting non-SRTP data between browsers.
The architecture of this stack is described in
<xref target='DATA-CHAN'/>.</t>


<figure title='Basic Stack Diagram'
        anchor='fig-stack'>
<artwork align='center'>
+----------+
|   SCTP   |
+----------+
|   DTLS   |
+----------+
| ICE/UDP  |
+----------+
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>This encapsulation of SCTP over DTLS over UDP or ICE/UDP
(see <xref target='RFC5245'/>) can provide a NAT traversal
solution in addition to confidentiality, source authentication, and
integrity-protected transfers.
Please note that using ICE does not necessarily imply that a different packet
format is used on the wire.</t>
<t>Please note that the procedures defined in <xref target='RFC6951'/>
for dealing with the UDP port numbers do not apply here.
When using the encapsulation defined in this document, SCTP is unaware
about the protocols used below DTLS.</t>
</section>

<section title='Conventions'>

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

</section>

<section title='Encapsulation and Decapsulation Procedure'>
<t>When an SCTP packet is provided to the DTLS layer, the complete
SCTP packet, consisting of the SCTP common header and a number of SCTP chunks,
is handled as the payload of the application-layer protocol of DTLS.
When the DTLS layer has processed a DTLS record containing a message of
the application-layer protocol, the payload is passed to the SCTP layer.
The SCTP layer expects an SCTP common header followed by a number of
SCTP chunks.</t>
</section>

<section title='General Considerations'>
<t>An implementation of SCTP over DTLS MUST implement and use a path
maximum transmission unit (MTU) discovery method that functions without
ICMP to provide SCTP/DTLS with an MTU estimate.
An implementation of "Packetization Layer Path MTU Discovery"
<xref target='RFC4821'/> either in SCTP or DTLS is RECOMMENDED.</t>


<t>The path MTU discovery is performed by SCTP when SCTP over DTLS is used
for data channels (see Section 5 of
<xref target='DATA-CHAN'/>).</t>
</section>

<section title='DTLS Considerations'>
<t>The DTLS implementation MUST support DTLS 1.0 <xref target='RFC4347'/>
and SHOULD support the most recently published version of DTLS,
which was DTLS 1.2 <xref target='RFC6347'/> when this RFC was published.
In the absence of a revision to this document, the latter requirement applies
to all future versions of DTLS when they are published as RFCs.
This document will only be revised if a revision to DTLS or SCTP makes a
revision to the encapsulation necessary.</t>


<t>SCTP performs segmentation and reassembly based on the path MTU.
Therefore, the DTLS layer MUST NOT use any compression algorithm.</t>
<t>The DTLS MUST support sending messages larger than the current
path MTU. This might result in sending IP-level fragmented messages.</t>
<t>If path MTU discovery is performed by the DTLS layer, the method described
in <xref target='RFC4821'/> MUST be used. For probe packets, the extension
defined in <xref target='RFC6520'/> MUST be used.</t>
<t>If path MTU discovery is performed by the SCTP layer and IPv4 is
used as the network-layer protocol, the DTLS implementation SHOULD allow
the DTLS user to enforce that the corresponding IPv4 packet is sent with
the Don't Fragment (DF) bit set.
If controlling the DF bit is not possible (for example, due to implementation
restrictions), a safe value for the path MTU has to be used by the SCTP stack.
It is RECOMMENDED that the safe value not exceed 1200 bytes.
Please note that <xref target='RFC1122'/> only requires that end hosts
be able to reassemble fragmented IP packets up to 576 bytes in length.</t>
<t>The DTLS implementation SHOULD allow the DTLS user to set the
Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) used for IP packets being sent
(see <xref target='RFC2474'/>).
This requires the DTLS implementation to pass the value through and
the lower layer to allow setting this value. If the lower layer
does not support setting the DSCP, then the DTLS user will end up with the
default value used by the protocol stack.
Please note that only a single DSCP value can be used for all packets belonging
to the same SCTP association.</t>

<t>Using Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) in SCTP requires the DTLS
layer to pass the ECN bits through and its lower layer to expose access to
them for sent and received packets (see <xref target='RFC3168'/>).
The implementations of DTLS and its lower layer have to provide this support.
If this is not possible (for example, due to implementation restrictions),
ECN can't be used by SCTP.</t>
</section>

<section title='SCTP Considerations'>
<t>This section describes the usage of the base protocol and the applicability
of various SCTP extensions.</t>

<section title='Base Protocol'>
<t>This document uses SCTP <xref target='RFC4960'/> with the following
restrictions, which are required to reflect that the lower layer
is DTLS instead of IPv4 and IPv6 and that SCTP does not deal with the IP
addresses or the transport protocol used below DTLS:
<list style='symbols'>
<t>A DTLS connection MUST be established before an SCTP association can be
   set up.</t>
<t>Multiple SCTP associations MAY be multiplexed over a single DTLS connection.
   The SCTP port numbers are used for multiplexing and demultiplexing the SCTP
   associations carried over a single DTLS connection.</t>
<t>All SCTP associations are single-homed, because DTLS does not expose
   any address management to its upper layer.
   Therefore, it is RECOMMENDED to set the SCTP parameter path.max.retrans to
   association.max.retrans.</t>
<t>The INIT and INIT-ACK chunk MUST NOT contain any IPv4 Address or IPv6 Address
   parameters. The INIT chunk MUST NOT contain the Supported Address Types
   parameter.</t>
<t>The implementation MUST NOT rely on processing ICMP or ICMPv6 packets,
   since the SCTP layer most likely is unable to access the SCTP common header
   in the plain text of the packet, which triggered the sending of the ICMP or
   ICMPv6 packet.
   This applies in particular to path MTU discovery when performed by SCTP.</t>
<t>If the SCTP layer is notified about a path change by its lower layers,
   SCTP SHOULD retest the path MTU and reset the congestion state to the
   initial state. The window-based congestion control method specified in
   <xref target='RFC4960'/> resets the congestion window and slow-start
   threshold to their initial values.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title='Padding Extension'>
<t>When the SCTP layer performs path MTU discovery as specified in
<xref target='RFC4821'/>, the padding extension defined in
<xref target='RFC4820'/> MUST be supported and used for probe packets
(HEARTBEAT chunks bundled with PADDING chunks <xref target='RFC4820'/>).</t>
</section>

<section title='Dynamic Address Reconfiguration Extension'>
<t>If the dynamic address reconfiguration extension defined in
<xref target='RFC5061'/> is used, ASCONF chunks MUST use wildcard
addresses only.</t>
</section>

<section title='SCTP Authentication Extension'>
<t>The SCTP authentication extension defined in <xref target='RFC4895'/>
can be used with DTLS encapsulation, but does not provide any additional
benefit.</t>
</section>

<section title='Partial Reliability Extension'>
<t>Partial reliability as defined in <xref target='RFC3758'/> can be used
in combination with DTLS encapsulation. It is also possible to use
additional Partially Reliable Stream Control Transmission Protocol (PR-SCTP) policies, for example, the ones defined in
<xref target='RFC7496'/>.</t>
</section>

<section title='Stream Reset Extension'>
<t>The SCTP stream reset extension defined in <xref target='RFC6525'/> can
be used with DTLS encapsulation.
It is used to reset SCTP streams and add SCTP streams during the lifetime of
the SCTP association.</t>
</section>

<section title='Interleaving of Large User Messages'>
<t>SCTP as defined in <xref target='RFC4960'/> does not support the
interleaving of large user messages that need to be fragmented and
reassembled by the SCTP layer. The protocol extension defined in
<xref target='RFC8260'/> overcomes this limitation
and can be used with DTLS encapsulation.</t>
</section>


</section>

<section title='IANA Considerations'>
<t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
</section>

<section title='Security Considerations'>
<t>Security considerations for DTLS are specified in <xref target='RFC4347'/>
and for SCTP in <xref target='RFC4960'/>, <xref target='RFC3758'/>,
and <xref target='RFC6525'/>.
The combination of SCTP and DTLS introduces no new security considerations.</t>
<t>SCTP should not process the IP addresses used for the underlying
communication since DTLS provides no guarantees about them.</t>
<t>It should be noted that the inability to process ICMP or ICMPv6 messages
does not add any security issue. When SCTP is carried over a connection-less
lower layer like IPv4, IPv6, or UDP, processing of these messages is required
to protect other nodes not supporting SCTP. Since DTLS provides a
connection-oriented lower layer, this kind of protection is not necessary.</t>
</section>


</middle>

<back>

<references title='Normative References'>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.1122' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4347' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4820' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4821' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4960' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6347' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6520' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174' ?>
</references>
<references title='Informative References'>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.0791' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2474' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.3168' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.3758' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4895' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5061' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5245' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6525' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6951' ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.8200' ?>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview: I-D Exists -->
<reference anchor='RTC-OVERVIEW'>
<front>
<title>Overview: Real Time Protocols for Browser-based Applications</title>

<author initials='H' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='Harald Alvestrand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This document gives an overview and context of a protocol suite intended for use with real-time applications that can be deployed in browsers - "real time communication on the Web".  It intends to serve as a starting and coordination point to make sure all the parts that are needed to achieve this goal are findable, and that the parts that belong in the Internet protocol suite are fully specified and on the right publication track.  This document is an Applicability Statement - it does not itself specify any protocol, but specifies which other specifications WebRTC compliant implementations are supposed to follow.  This document is a work item of the RTCWEB working group.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview-18' />

</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-data-channel in queue in MISSREF -->
<reference anchor='DATA-CHAN'>
<front>
<title>WebRTC Data Channels</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Jesup' fullname='Randell Jesup'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Tuexen' fullname='Michael Tuexen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' day='4' year='2015' />

<abstract><t>The WebRTC framework specifies protocol support for direct interactive rich communication using audio, video, and data between two peers' web-browsers.  This document specifies the non-media data transport aspects of the WebRTC framework.  It provides an architectural overview of how the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) is used in the WebRTC context as a generic transport service allowing WEB-browsers to exchange generic data from peer to peer.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-rtcweb-data-channel-13'/>

</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-tsvwg-sctp-prpolicies = 7496 -->
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7496"?>

<!-- draft-ietf-tsvwg-sctp-ndata in AUTH48 (should be published together per the note from the author)
-->
<reference anchor='RFC8260'>
<front>
<title>Stream Schedulers and User Message Interleaving for the Stream Control Transmission Protocol</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Stewart' fullname='Randall Stewart'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Tuexen' fullname='Michael Tuexen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Seggelmann' fullname='Robin Seggelmann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2017' />

</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8260'/>
</reference>

</references>

<section title='Acknowledgments' numbered='no'>
<t>The authors wish to thank
David Black,
Benoit Claise,
Spencer Dawkins,
Francis Dupont,
Gorry Fairhurst,
Stephen Farrell,
Christer Holmberg,
Barry Leiba,
Eric Rescorla,
Tom Taylor,
Joe Touch,
and Magnus Westerlund
for their invaluable comments.</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
