<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" number="8545" ipr="trust200902" updates="4656, 5357"
  submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
   <title abbrev="OWAMP/TWAMP Well-Known Ports">Well-Known Port Assignments
 for the One-Way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP) and the Two-Way Active
 Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)</title>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." role="editor" surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <code>07748</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>
        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>
        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Greg Mirsky" initials="G." role="editor"
            surname="Mirsky">
      <organization>ZTE Corp.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2019"/>

<keyword>OWAMP, TWAMP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo explains the motivation and describes the reassignment of
      well-known ports for the One-Way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP)
      and the Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP) for control and
      measurement.  It also clarifies the meaning and composition of these
      Standards Track protocol names for the industry.</t>

      <t>This memo updates RFCs 4656 and 5357, in terms of the UDP
      well-known port assignments, and it clarifies the complete OWAMP and
      TWAMP protocol composition for the industry.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The IETF IP Performance Metrics (IPPM) Working Group first developed
      the One-Way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP), as specified in <xref
      target="RFC4656"/>. Further protocol development to support testing
      resulted in the Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP), as
      specified in <xref target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

      <t>Both OWAMP and TWAMP require the implementation of a control and mode
      negotiation protocol (OWAMP-Control and TWAMP-Control) that employs the
      reliable transport services of TCP (including security configuration and
      key derivation). The control protocols arrange for the configuration and
      management of test sessions using the associated test protocol
      (OWAMP-Test or TWAMP-Test) on UDP transport.</t>

      <t>The IETF recognizes the value of assigning a well&nbhy;known UDP port
      to the OWAMP-Test and TWAMP-Test protocols and also recognizes that this
      goal can be easily arranged through port reassignments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL&nbsp;NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD&nbsp;NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
      "NOT&nbsp;RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
      are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when,
      and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope">
      <t>The scope of this memo is twofold: (1) to reallocate the
      well&nbhy;known ports for the UDP test protocols that compose necessary
      parts of their respective Standards Track protocols (OWAMP and TWAMP)
      and (2)&nbsp;to clarify the meaning and composition of these
      Standards Track protocol names for the industry.</t>

      <t>This memo updates <xref target="RFC4656"/> and <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>, in terms of the UDP well&nbhy;known port
      assignments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions and Background" anchor="defs-and-bgrnd">
      <t>This section defines key terms and clarifies the required composition
      of the OWAMP and TWAMP Standards Track protocols.</t>

      <t>"OWAMP-Control" is the protocol defined in Section&nbsp;3 of <xref
      target="RFC4656"/>.</t>

      <t>"OWAMP-Test" is the protocol defined in Section&nbsp;4 of <xref
      target="RFC4656"/>.</t>

<!-- Quoted text is DNE. -->
      <t>OWAMP is described in this direct quote from Section 1.1 of <xref
      target="RFC4656"> </xref>: "OWAMP actually consists of two inter-related
      protocols: OWAMP&nbhy;Control and OWAMP-Test." A similar sentence
      appears in Section&nbsp;2 of <xref target="RFC4656"/>. For avoidance of
      doubt, the implementation of both OWAMP&nbhy;Control and OWAMP&nbhy;Test
      is REQUIRED for Standards Track OWAMP as specified in <xref
      target="RFC4656"/> (applying the consensus of many dictionary
      definitions of "consist").</t>

      <t>"TWAMP-Control" is the protocol defined in Section&nbsp;3 of <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

      <t>"TWAMP-Test" is the protocol defined in Section&nbsp;4 of <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

<!-- Quoted text is DNE. -->
      <t>TWAMP is described in this direct quote from Section 1.1 of <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>: "Similar to OWAMP <xref target="RFC4656"/>, TWAMP
      consists of two inter&nbhy;related protocols: TWAMP-Control and
      TWAMP-Test." For avoidance of doubt, the implementation of both
      TWAMP-Control and TWAMP-Test is REQUIRED for Standards Track TWAMP as
      specified in <xref target="RFC5357"/> (applying the consensus of many
      dictionary definitions of "consist").</t>

      <t>"TWAMP Light" is an idea described in Appendix&nbsp;I 
      ("TWAMP Light (Informative)") of <xref target="RFC5357"/>; TWAMP Light
      includes an unspecified control protocol combined with the
      TWAMP&nbhy;Test protocol.  In <xref target="RFC5357"/>, the
      TWAMP Light idea was relegated to Appendix&nbsp;I because TWAMP Light
      failed to meet the requirements for IETF protocols (there are no
      specifications for negotiating this form of operation and no
      specifications for mandatory-to-implement security features), as
      described in <xref target="App-A"/> of this memo.  See also <xref
      target="LarsAD"/> and <xref target="TimDISCUSS"/>.</t>

      <t>Since the idea of TWAMP Light clearly includes the TWAMP-Test
      component of TWAMP, it is considered reasonable for future systems to
      use the TWAMP-Test well-known UDP port (whose reallocated assignment is
      specified in this document). Clearly, the TWAMP Light idea envisions many
      components and communication capabilities beyond TWAMP-Test
      (implementing the security requirements, for example); otherwise,
      Appendix&nbsp;I of <xref target="RFC5357"/> would be one sentence long
      (equating TWAMP Light with TWAMP-Test only).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="New Well-Known Ports">
      <t>Originally, both TCP and UDP well-known ports were assigned to the
      control protocols that are essential components of Standards Track OWAMP
      and TWAMP.</t>

      <t>Since OWAMP-Control and TWAMP-Control require TCP transport, they
      cannot make use of the UDP ports that were originally assigned.
      However, test sessions using OWAMP&nbhy;Test or TWAMP&nbhy;Test operate
      on UDP transport.</t>

      <t>Per this memo, IANA has reassigned the UDP well-known port from
      the control protocol to the test protocol (see <xref target="IANA"/>
      ("IANA Considerations")). The use of this UDP port is OPTIONAL in
      Standards Track OWAMP and TWAMP. It may simplify some operations to have
      a well-known port available for the test protocols or for future
      specifications involving TWAMP-Test to use this port as a default
      port. For example, <xref target="TR-390"/> is a specification for
      testing at the customer edge of IP&nbsp;networks, and conforming
      implementations will benefit from reallocation of the well&nbhy;known UDP
      port to the test protocol.</t>

      <section anchor="twamp-control" title="Impact on TWAMP-Control Protocol">
        <t>Section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC5357"/> describes the detailed
        process of negotiating the Receiver Port number, on which the TWAMP
        Session&nbhy;Reflector will send and receive TWAMP-Test packets; see
        the quoted text below. The Control-Client, acting on behalf of the
        Session-Sender, proposes the Receiver Port number from the Dynamic
        Ports range <xref target="RFC6335"/>:
<!-- Quoted text is DNE. -->
<list>
        <t>The Receiver Port is the desired UDP port to which TWAMP-Test
        packets will be sent by the Session-Sender (the port where the
        Session-Reflector is asked to receive test packets). The Receiver
        Port is also the UDP port from which TWAMP-Test packets will be
        sent by the Session-Reflector (the Session-Reflector will use the
        same UDP port to send and receive packets).</t>
</list>
</t>

        <t>It is possible that the proposed Receiver Port may not be
        available, e.g., the port is in use by another test session or another
        application. In this case, we update the last paragraph of
        Section&nbsp;3.5 of <xref target="RFC5357"/> per Erratum ID&nbsp;1587
        (see &lt;https://www.rfc&nbhy;editor.org/errata/eid1587&gt;) as follows:

<list>
        <t>... the Server at the Session-Reflector MAY suggest an
        alternate and available port for this session in the Port field.
        The Control&nbhy;Client either accepts the alternate port or composes
        a new Session-Request message with suitable parameters. Otherwise,
        the Server uses the Accept field to convey other forms of session
        rejection or failure to the Control-Client and MUST NOT suggest an
        alternate port; in this case, the Port field MUST be set to zero.
</t>
</list>
</t>

        <t>A Control-Client that supports the use of the allocated TWAMP-Test
        Receiver Port (<xref target="IANA"/>) MAY request to use that port
        number in the Request-TW-Session command. If the Server does not
        support the allocated TWAMP-Test Receiver Port, then it sends an
        alternate port number in the Accept-Session message with
        Accept field = 0. Thus, the deployment of the allocated
        TWAMP Receiver Port number is backward compatible with existing
        TWAMP&nbhy;Control solutions that are based on
        <xref target="RFC5357"/>. Of course, using a UDP port number
        chosen from the Dynamic Ports range <xref target="RFC6335"/> will help
        avoid the situation where the Control-Client or Server finds that the
        proposed port is already in&nbsp;use.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact on OWAMP-Control Protocol">
        <t>As described above, an OWAMP-Control client that supports the use of
        the allocated OWAMP-Test Receiver Port (<xref target="IANA"/>) MAY
        request to use that port number in the Request-Session command. If the
        Server does not support the allocated OWAMP-Test Receiver Port (or
        does not have the port available), then it sends an alternate port
        number in the Accept-Session message with Accept field = 0. Further
        exchanges proceed as already specified.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="twamp-test"
               title="Impact on OWAMP-Test/TWAMP-Test Protocols">
        <t>OWAMP&nbhy;Test/TWAMP&nbhy;Test may be used to measure IP performance metrics in
        an Equal-Cost Multipath (ECMP) environment. Though algorithms to
        balance IP flows among available paths have not been standardized, the
        most common is the five-tuple that uses destination IP address, source
        IP address, protocol type, destination port number, and source port
        number. When attempting to monitor different paths in an ECMP network,
        it is sufficient to vary only one of five parameters, e.g., the source
        port number. Thus, there will be no negative impact on the ability to
        arrange concurrent OWAMP/TWAMP test sessions between the same test
        points to monitor different paths in the ECMP network when using the
        reallocated UDP port number as the Receiver Port, as using the port
        is optional.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations that apply to any active measurement of
      live paths are relevant here as well (see <xref target="RFC4656"/> and
      <xref target="RFC5357"/>).</t>

      <t>When considering the privacy of those involved in measurement or
      those whose traffic is measured, the sensitive information available to
      potential observers is greatly reduced when using active techniques
      that are within this scope of work. Passive observations of user
      traffic for measurement purposes raise many privacy issues. We refer the
      reader to the security and privacy considerations described in the
      Large-Scale Measurement of Broadband Performance (LMAP) framework <xref
      target="RFC7594"/>, which covers both active and passive techniques.</t>

      <t>The registered UDP port as the Receiver Port for
      OWAMP&nbhy;Test/TWAMP&nbhy;Test could become a target of denial of
      service (DoS) or could be used to aid man-in-the-middle (MITM)
      attacks. To improve protection against DoS, the following methods are
      recommended: <list style="symbols">
         <t>filtering access to the OWAMP/TWAMP Receiver Port via an
          access&nbsp;list.</t>

          <t>using a non-globally routable IP address for the OWAMP/TWAMP
          Session-Reflector address.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>A MITM attacker may try to modify the contents of the
      OWAMP&nbhy;Test/TWAMP&nbhy;Test packets in order to alter the measurement
      results. However, an implementation can use authenticated mode to detect
      modification of data. In addition, an implementation can use encrypted
      mode to prevent eavesdropping and undetected modification of the
      OWAMP&nbhy;Test/TWAMP&nbhy;Test packets.</t>

      <t>There is also the risk of a network under test giving special
      treatment to flows involving the well-known UDP port, with or without
      knowing source and destination addresses of measurement systems, and thus
      biasing the results through preferential or detrimental processing.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has reallocated two UDP port numbers from the
      System Ports range of the "Service Name and Transport Protocol Port
      Number Registry" <xref target="RFC6335"/>. Specifically, 
      IANA has reallocated UDP ports 861 and 862 as shown below,
      leaving the TCP port assignments as is. IANA has also updated the
      Assignee and Contact for these ports (both UDP and TCP) to be
      the IESG and the IETF Chair, respectively.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------------+--------+-----------+------------------+-----------+
| Service       | Port   | Transport | Description      | Reference |
| Name          | Number | Protocol  |                  |           |
+---------------+--------+-----------+------------------+-----------+
| owamp-control | 861    | tcp       | OWAMP-Control    | RFC 4656  |
| owamp-test    | 861    | udp       | OWAMP-Test       | RFC 8545  |
|               |        |           |    Receiver Port |           |
|               |        |           |                  |           |
| twamp-control | 862    | tcp       | TWAMP-Control    | RFC 5357  |
| twamp-test    | 862    | udp       | TWAMP-Test       | RFC 8545  |
|               |        |           |    Receiver Port |           |
+---------------+--------+-----------+------------------+-----------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4656'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5357'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6335'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7594'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

    <reference anchor="LarsAD" target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/ippm/LzcTPYhPhWhbb5-ncR046XKpnzo">
      <front>
        <title>Subject: [ippm] AD review: draft-ietf-ippm-twamp-06.txt</title>
          <author initials="L" surname="Eggert" fullname="Lars Eggert"/>
          <date month="April" year="2008"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name="message to the" value="ippm mailing list"/>
      </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-ippm-twamp (precursor to RFC 5357) -->
<reference anchor='IPPM-TWAMP-06'>
<front>
<title>A Two-way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)</title>
<author initials='K' surname='Hedayat' fullname='Kaynam Hedayat'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Krzanowski' fullname='Roman M. Krzanowski'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='K' surname='Yum' fullname='Kiho Yum'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='A' surname='Morton' fullname='Al Morton'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Babiarz' fullname='Jozef Babiarz'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' year='2007' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ippm-twamp-06' />
</reference>

      <reference anchor="TimDISCUSS" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc5357/history">
        <front>
          <title>Tim Polk&apos;s Ballot discuss</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date day="16 " month="July" year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TR-390" target="https://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-390.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>TR-390: Performance Measurement from IP Edge to Customer
          Equipment using TWAMP Light</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Broadband Forum</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2017"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name="Issue:" value="1"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Background on TWAMP Light" anchor="App-A">

      <t>This informative appendix provides the background on the decision to
      move the TWAMP Light idea to an informative appendix in <xref
      target="RFC5357"/>.</t>

      <t>As also noted in <xref target="defs-and-bgrnd"/>, the TWAMP Light
      idea was relegated to Appendix&nbsp;I of <xref target="RFC5357"/>
      because it failed to meet the requirements for
      IETF protocols (there are no specifications for negotiating this form of
      operation and no specifications for mandatory-to-implement security
      features), as described in the references cited below:

    <list style="symbols">
          <t>Lars Eggert's Area Director review <xref target="LarsAD"/>, where
          he pointed out that having two variants of TWAMP
(TWAMP Light and Complete TWAMP) requires a protocol mechanism to negotiate
which variant will be used. Note that "Complete TWAMP" is called "Standards
Track TWAMP" in this document. See Lars's "Section 5.2, paragraph 0"
comment on <xref target="LarsAD"/>, which refers to a section in
<xref target="IPPM-TWAMP-06"/>.

<!-- Quoted text is DNE. -->
 The working group consensus was to place the TWAMP Light
          description in Appendix&nbsp;I and to refer to that appendix only as
          an "incremental path to adopting TWAMP, by implementing the
          TWAMP&nbhy;Test protocol first."</t>

          <t>Tim Polk's "Ballot discuss" of 2008-07-16 <xref
          target="TimDISCUSS"/>, which points out that TWAMP Light was
          an incomplete specification because the key required for
          authenticated and encrypted modes depended on the TWAMP-Control
          Session key. Additional requirement statements were added
          in Appendix&nbsp;I to address Tim's Ballot discuss (see the last
          three paragraphs of Appendix&nbsp;I in <xref target="RFC5357"/>).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Since the idea of TWAMP Light clearly includes the TWAMP&nbhy;Test
      protocol and other undefined facilities, Appendix&nbsp;I of <xref
      target="RFC5357"/> simply describes ideas for how TWAMP&nbhy;Test might
      be used outside of the context of Standards Track TWAMP.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors thank the IPPM Working Group for their rapid review;
      thanks also to Muthu Arul Mozhi Perumal and Luay Jalil for their
      participation and suggestions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contrib" title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>Richard Foote and Luis M.&nbsp;Contreras made notable contributions on
      this topic.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
