<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
 <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY RFC2205 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC3209 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC3473 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3473.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC3471 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3471.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC5420 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5420.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC6003 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6003.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC3945 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3945.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC5920 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5920.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC8330 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8330.xml">
 ]>
 <rfc number="8625" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">

	 <?rfc compact="yes"?>
	 <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	 <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	 <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	 <?rfc strict="yes"?>
	 <?rfc toc="yes"?>


	 <front>
	   <title abbrev="Availability Extension to RSVP-TE">Ethernet Traffic Parameters with Availability Information</title>

	 <author fullname="Hao Long" initials="H." surname="Long">
	 <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>
	 <address><postal><street>No.1899, Xiyuan Avenue, Hi-tech Western District</street>
	 <street>Chengdu 611731</street>
	 <street>China</street>
	 </postal>
	 <phone>+86-18615778750</phone>
	 <email>longhao@huawei.com</email>
	 </address>
	 </author>

	 <author fullname="Min Ye" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Ye">
	 <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>
	 <address><postal><street>No.1899, Xiyuan Avenue, Hi-tech Western District</street>
	 <street>Chengdu 611731</street>
	 <street>China</street>
	 </postal>
	 <email>amy.yemin@huawei.com</email>
	 </address>
	 </author>

	 <author fullname="Greg Mirsky" initials="G." role="editor" surname="Mirsky">
	 <organization>ZTE</organization>
	 <address><email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
	 </address>
	 </author>

	 <author fullname="Alessandro D'Alessandro" initials="A." surname="D'Alessandro">
	 <organization>Telecom Italia S.p.A</organization>
	 <address><email>alessandro.dalessandro@telecomitalia.it</email>
	 </address>
	 </author>

	 <author fullname="Himanshu Shah" initials="H." surname="Shah">
	 <organization abbrev="Ciena">Ciena Corp.</organization>
	 <address><postal><street>3939 North First Street</street>
	 <street>San Jose, CA 95134</street>
	 <street>United States of America</street>
	 </postal>
	 <email>hshah@ciena.com</email>
	 </address>
	 </author>

	 <date month="August" year="2019"/>
	 

<abstract><t>
    A packet-switching network may contain links with variable
    bandwidths (e.g., copper and radio). The bandwidth of such links is
    sensitive to the external environment (e.g., climate). Availability is
    typically used to describe these links when doing network
    planning. This document introduces an optional Bandwidth
    Availability TLV in 
    RSVP-TE signaling. This extension can be used to set up a
    GMPLS Label Switched
    Path (LSP) in conjunction with the Ethernet SENDER_TSPEC object.</t>

	 </abstract>

	 </front>

	 <middle>
	 <section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
    The RSVP-TE specification <xref target="RFC3209"/> and GMPLS extensions <xref target="RFC3473"/>
    specify the signaling message, including the bandwidth request for
    setting up an LSP in a packet-switching network.</t>

	 <t>
    Some data communication technologies allow a seamless change of
    the maximum physical bandwidth through a set of known discrete values.
    The parameter availability <xref target="G.827"/> <xref target="F.1703"/> <xref target="P.530"/> is often used
    to describe the link capacity during network planning. The
    availability is based on a time scale, which is a proportion of the
    operating time that the requested bandwidth is ensured. A more
    detailed example of bandwidth availability can be found in
    <xref target="section-a"/>. 
   Assigning different bandwidth availability classes to 
   different types of services over links with variable discrete bandwidth provides for a 
   more efficient planning of link capacity.
   To set up an LSP across
    these links, bandwidth availability information is required for the
    nodes to verify bandwidth satisfaction and make a bandwidth
    reservation. The bandwidth availability information should be
    inherited from the bandwidth availability requirements of the
    services expected to be carried on the LSP. For example, voice
    service usually needs 99.999% bandwidth availability, while
    non-real-time services may adequately perform at 99.99% or 99.9%
    bandwidth availability. Since different service types may need
    different availability guarantees, multiple &lt;availability, bandwidth&gt; pairs may be required when signaling.</t>

	 <t>
    If the bandwidth availability requirement is not specified in the
    signaling message, the bandwidth will likely be reserved as the
    highest bandwidth availability. Suppose, for example, the bandwidth
    with 99.999% availability of a link is 100 Mbps, and the bandwidth with
    99.99% availability is 200 Mbps. When a video application makes a
    request for 120 Mbps without a bandwidth availability requirement, the
    system will consider the request as 120 Mbps with 99.999% bandwidth
    availability, while the available bandwidth with 99.999% bandwidth
    availability is only 100 Mbps. Therefore, the LSP path cannot be set
    up. However, the video application doesn't need 99.999%
    bandwidth availability; 99.99% bandwidth availability is enough. In
    this case, the LSP could be set up if the bandwidth availability is also
    specified in the signaling message.</t>



	 <t>
    To fulfill an LSP setup by signaling in these scenarios, this document
    specifies a Bandwidth Availability TLV. The Bandwidth Availability
    TLV can be applicable to any kind of physical link with variable
    discrete bandwidth, such as microwave or DSL. Multiple Bandwidth
    Availability TLVs, together with multiple Ethernet Bandwidth Profile TLVs,
    can be carried by the Ethernet SENDER_TSPEC object <xref target="RFC6003"/>. Since
    the Ethernet FLOWSPEC object has the same format as the Ethernet
    SENDER_TSPEC object <xref target="RFC6003"/>, the Bandwidth Availability TLV can
    also be carried by the Ethernet FLOWSPEC object.</t>

	 <section title="Conventions Used in This Document"
		  anchor="section-1.1">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

	<t>
   The following acronyms are used in this document:</t>

	<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="9"><t hangText="RSVP-TE">
	Resource Reservation Protocol - Traffic Engineering
	</t>

	<t hangText="LSP">
	Label Switched Path
	</t>

<t hangText="SNR">
	Signal-to-Noise Ratio
</t>

	<t hangText="TLV">
	Type-Length-Value
	</t>

	<t hangText="LSA">
	Link State Advertisement
	</t>


	<t hangText="QAM">
        Quadrature Amplitude Modulation
	</t>

	<t hangText="QPSK">
	Quadrature Phase Shift Keying
	</t>


	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Overview" anchor="section-2"><t>
   A tunnel in a packet-switching network may span one or more links in
   a network. To set up an LSP, a node may collect
   link information that is advertised in a routing message (e.g.,
   an OSPF TE LSA message) by network nodes to obtain network topology
   information, and it can then calculate an LSP route based on the network
   topology. The calculated LSP route is signaled using a PATH/RESV
   message to set up the LSP.</t>

	<t>
   If a network contains one or more links with variable discrete bandwidths,
   a &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; requirement list should be specified for an LSP
   at setup.
   Each &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; pair
   in the list means the listed bandwidth with specified availability
   is required. The list can be derived from the results of service
   planning for the LSP.</t>

	<t>
   A node that has link(s) with variable discrete bandwidth attached
   should contain a &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; information list in its
   OSPF TE LSA messages. The list provides the mapping between the link
   nominal bandwidth and its availability level. This information can
   then be used for path calculation by the node(s). The routing
   extension for availability can be found in <xref target="RFC8330"/>.</t>

	<t>
   When a node initiates a PATH/RESV signaling to set up an LSP, the
   PATH message should carry the &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; requirement
   list as a bandwidth request.  Intermediate node(s) will allocate the
   bandwidth resources for each availability requirement from the
   remaining bandwidth with the corresponding availability. An error
   message may be returned if any &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; request
   cannot be satisfied.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Extension to RSVP-TE Signaling" anchor="section-3"><section title="Bandwidth Availability TLV" anchor="section-3.1"><t>
   A Bandwidth Availability TLV is defined as a TLV of the Ethernet
   SENDER_TSPEC object <xref target="RFC6003"/> in this document. The Ethernet
   SENDER_TSPEC object MAY include more than one Bandwidth Availability
   TLV. The Bandwidth Availability TLV has the following format:</t>

	<figure title="Bandwidth Availability TLV" anchor="ref-bandwidth-availability-tlv"><artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |               Type            |              Length           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Index      |                 Reserved                      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Availability                          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>
   Type (2 octets): 4</t>

	<t>
   Length (2 octets): 0x0C. Indicates the length in bytes of the
   whole TLV, including the Type and Length fields. In this case, the
   length
   is 12 bytes.</t>

	<t>
   Index (1 octet):  When the Bandwidth Availability TLV is included, the Ethernet
   Bandwidth Profile TLV MUST also be included. If there are multiple
   bandwidth requirements present (in multiple Ethernet Bandwidth
   Profile TLVs) and they have different availability requirements,
   multiple Bandwidth Availability TLVs MUST be carried. 
   In such a 
   case, the Bandwidth Availability TLV has a one-to-one 
   correspondence with the Ethernet Bandwidth Profile TLV as both have
   the same value in the Index field. 
   If all the bandwidth requirements
   in the Ethernet Bandwidth Profile TLV have the same availability
   requirement, one Bandwidth Availability TLV SHOULD be carried. In
   this case, the Index field is set to 0.</t>

	<t>
   Reserved (3 octets): These bits SHOULD be set to zero when sent
   and MUST be ignored when received.</t>



	<t>
   Availability (4 octets): A 32-bit floating-point number in binary
   interchange format <xref target="IEEE754"/> describes the decimal value of the
   availability requirement for this bandwidth request. 
   The value MUST be less than 1 and is usually expressed as one of the
   following values: 0.99, 0.999, 0.9999, or 0.99999.
The IEEE floating-point number is used
   here to align with <xref target="RFC8330"/>. 





When representing values
   higher than 0.999999, the floating-point number starts to
   introduce errors to intended precision. 


However, in
   reality, 0.99999 is normally considered the highest
   availability value (which results in 5 minutes of outage in a year) in a telecom
   network. Therefore, the use of a floating-point number for
   availability is acceptable.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Signaling Process" anchor="section-3.2"><t>
   The source node initiates a PATH message, which may carry a number of
   bandwidth requests, including one or more Ethernet Bandwidth Profile
   TLVs and one or more Bandwidth Availability TLVs. Each Ethernet
   Bandwidth Profile TLV corresponds to an availability parameter in
   the associated Bandwidth Availability TLV.</t>


	<t>
When the intermediate and destination nodes receive the PATH message,
the nodes compare the requested bandwidth under each availability level
in the SENDER_TSPEC objects, with the remaining link bandwidth resources
under a corresponding availability level on a local link, to check if they can
meet the bandwidth requirements.   
</t>



	<t><list style="symbols"><t>When all &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt;
	requirement requests can
        be satisfied (that is, the requested bandwidth under each availability
        parameter is smaller than or equal to the remaining bandwidth
        under the corresponding availability parameter on its local
        link), the node SHOULD reserve the bandwidth resources from each
        remaining sub-bandwidth portion on its local link to set up
        this LSP. Optionally, a higher availability bandwidth can be
        allocated to a lower availability request when the lower
        availability bandwidth cannot satisfy the request.</t>

	<t>When at least one &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; requirement
        request cannot be satisfied, the node SHOULD generate a PathErr
        message with the error code "Admission Control Error" and the
        error value "Requested Bandwidth Unavailable" (see <xref target="RFC2205"/>).</t>

	</list>
	</t>


	<t>
   When two LSPs request bandwidth with the same availability requirement, the
   contention MUST be resolved by comparing the node IDs, where the LSP with
   the higher node ID is assigned the reservation.  This is consistent with
   the general contention resolution mechanism provided in Section 4.2 of
   <xref target="RFC3471"/>.</t>




	<t>
   When a node does not support the Bandwidth Availability TLV, the node
   should send a PathErr message with error code "Unknown Attributes TLV", as
   specified in <xref target="RFC5420"/>. An LSP could also be set up in this
   case if there's enough bandwidth (note that the availability level of the reserved
   bandwidth is unknown). When a node receives Bandwidth Availability TLVs
   with a mix of zero and non-zero indexes, the message MUST be ignored and
   MUST NOT be propagated. 


   When a node receives Bandwidth Availability TLVs (non-zero index) with no
   matching index value among the Ethernet Bandwidth Profile TLVs, the message
   MUST be
   ignored and MUST NOT be propagated. When a node receives several
   &lt;bandwidth, availability&gt; pairs, but there are extra Ethernet Bandwidth
   Profile TLVs that do not match the index of any Bandwidth Availability TLV,
   the extra
   Ethernet Bandwidth Profile TLVs MUST be ignored and MUST NOT be
   propagated.  
</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="section-4"><t> This
	document defines a Bandwidth Availability TLV in RSVP-TE signaling
	used in GMPLS networks. <xref target="RFC3945"/> notes that
	authentication in GMPLS systems may use the authentication mechanisms
	of the component protocols. <xref target="RFC5920"/> provides an
	overview of security vulnerabilities and protection mechanisms for the
	GMPLS control plane. In particular, Section 7.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5920"/>
	discusses the control-plane protection with RSVP-TE by using general
	RSVP security tools, limiting the impact of an attack on control-plane
	resources, and using authentication for RSVP messages. Moreover, the GMPLS
	network is often considered to be a closed network such that
	insertion, modification, or inspection of packets by an outside party
	is not possible.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-5">

<t>
	IANA maintains a registry of GMPLS parameters called the "Generalized
	Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Signaling Parameters" registry.
   This registry includes the "Ethernet Sender TSpec
   TLVs/Ethernet Flowspec TLVs" subregistry that contains the TLV type values for TLVs
   carried in the Ethernet SENDER_TSPEC object. This subregistry has been
   updated to include the Bandwidth Availability TLV:
</t>


   <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Type             Description                 Reference 
   ----             ----------------------      --------- 
    4               Bandwidth Availability      RFC 8625     

]]></artwork>
	</figure>


	</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">


	&RFC2119;

	&RFC2205;
	&RFC3209;
	&RFC3473;
	&RFC3471;
	&RFC5420;
	&RFC6003;
	&RFC8174;
	
      <reference anchor="IEEE754">
        <front>
          <title>
            IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="754"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2008.4610935"/>
      </reference>

	

	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">

	&RFC3945;
	&RFC5920;
	<reference anchor="G.827" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-G.827/en">
<front>
	<title>Availability performance parameters and objectives for end-to-end international constant bit-rate digital paths</title>
	<author>
	<organization>ITU-T</organization>
	</author>

	<date month="September" year="2003"/>
	</front>
<seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="G.827"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="F.1703" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/R-REC-F.1703/en">
<front>
	<title>Availability objectives for real digital fixed wireless links used in 27 500 km hypothetical reference paths and connections</title>
	<author>
	<organization>ITU-R</organization>
	</author>
	<date month="January" year="2005"/>
	</front>
<seriesInfo name="ITU-R Recommendation" value="F.1703-0"/>
	</reference>


	<reference anchor="P.530" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/R-REC-P.530/en">
<front>
	<title>Propagation data and prediction methods required for the design of terrestrial line-of-sight systems</title>
	<author>
	<organization>ITU-R</organization>
	</author>
	<date month="December" year="2017"/>
	</front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-R Recommendation" value="P.530-17" />
	</reference>


	<reference anchor="EN-302-217"><front>
	<title>Fixed Radio Systems; Characteristics and requirements for
	point-to-point equipment and antennas; Part 1: Overview and
	system-independent common characteristics</title>
	<author>
	<organization>ETSI</organization>
	</author>

	<date month="May" year="2017"/>
	</front>
        <seriesInfo name='ETSI EN' value='302 217-1, Version 3.1.1' />
	</reference>

	&RFC8330;
	</references>
	<section title="Bandwidth Availability Example" anchor="section-a"><t>
   In mobile backhaul networks, microwave links are very popular for
   providing connections of last hops. 
   To maintain link connectivity in heavy rain conditions, the microwave link
   may lower the modulation level since moving to a lower modulation
   level provides for a lower SNR requirement.
   This is called "adaptive modulation" technology <xref target="EN-302-217"/>. However,
   a lower modulation level also means a lower link bandwidth. When a link
   bandwidth is reduced because of modulation downshifting, high-priority
   traffic can be maintained, while lower-priority traffic is
   dropped. Similarly, copper links may change their link bandwidth due
   to external interference.</t>

	<t>
   Presume that a link has three discrete bandwidth levels:</t>


<t>
<list style="symbols">
	<t>
   The link bandwidth under modulation level 1 (e.g., QPSK) is 100
   Mbps.</t>

	<t>
   The link bandwidth under modulation level 2 (e.g., 16QAM) is 200
   Mbps.</t>

	<t>
   The link bandwidth under modulation level 3 (e.g., 256QAM) is 400
   Mbps.</t>
</list>
</t>
	<t>
   On a sunny day, modulation level 3 can be used to achieve a 400
   Mbps link bandwidth.</t>


	<t>
   Light rain with a X mm/h rate triggers the system to change the
   modulation level from level 3 to level 2, with the bandwidth changing
   from 400 Mbps to 200 Mbps. The probability of X mm/h rain in the
   local area is 52 minutes in a year. Then the dropped 200 Mbps
   bandwidth has 99.99% availability.</t>

	<t>
   Heavy rain with a Y(Y&gt;X) mm/h rate triggers the system to change the
   modulation level from level 2 to level 1, with the bandwidth changing
   from 200 Mbps to 100 Mbps. The probability of Y mm/h rain in the
   local area is 26 minutes in a year. Then the dropped 100 Mbps
   bandwidth has 99.995% availability.</t>


	<t>
   For the 100 Mbps bandwidth of modulation level 1, only extreme
   weather conditions can cause the whole system to be unavailable,
   which only happens for 5 minutes in a year. So the 100 Mbps
   bandwidth of the modulation level 1 owns the availability of
   99.999%.</t>

	<t>
   There are discrete buckets per availability level. Under the worst
   weather conditions, there's only 100 Mbps capacity, which is
   99.999% available.  It's treated effectively as "always available"
   since better availability is not possible. If the weather is bad but not
   the worst possible conditions, modulation level 2 can be used, which gets an
   additional 100 Mbps bandwidth (i.e., 200 Mbps total). Therefore, 100 Mbps
   is in the 99.999% bucket, and 100 Mbps is in the 99.995% bucket.
   In clear weather, modulation level 3 can be used to get 400 Mbps
   total, but that's only 200 Mbps more than at modulation level 2, so the
   99.99% bucket has that "extra" 200 Mbps, and the other two buckets
   still have 100 Mbps each.</t>

	<t>
   Therefore, the maximum bandwidth is 400 Mbps. The sub-bandwidth and its
   availability according to the weather conditions are shown as follows:</t>



	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Sub-bandwidth (Mbps)   Availability                       
   ------------------     ------------          

   200                    99.99%                 

   100                    99.995%                

   100                    99.999% 
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	</section>

	<section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no" anchor="acknowledgments"><t>
   The authors would like to thank Deborah Brungard, Khuzema Pithewan,
   Lou Berger, Yuji Tochio, Dieter Beller, and Autumn Liu for their
   comments on and contributions to the document.</t>

	</section>

	</back>

	</rfc>
	
