<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4944 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4944.xml'>
]>


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc iprnotified='no' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>

<rfc number="8137" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902">

<front>
  <title>IEEE 802.15.4 Information Element for IETF</title>
        
  <author initials='T.' surname='Kivinen' fullname='Tero Kivinen'>
    <organization>INSIDE Secure</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Lonnrotinkatu 11</street>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <code>FI-00120</code>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </postal>
      <email>kivinen@iki.fi</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Pat Kinney" initials="P." surname="Kinney">
    <organization>Kinney Consulting LLC</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
	<street/>
	<city/>
	<region/>
	<code/>
	<country/>
      </postal>
      <email>pat.kinney@kinneyconsultingllc.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <date year='2017' month="May" />
  <area>Internet</area>

  <abstract>
    <t>IEEE Std 802.15.4 defines Information Elements (IEs) that can
    be used to extend 802.15.4 in an interoperable manner. The IEEE
    802.15 Assigned Numbers Authority (ANA) manages the registry of
    the Information Elements. This document formulates a request for
    ANA to allocate a number from that registry for IETF and
    describes how the IE is formatted to provide subtypes.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section title='Introduction'>
    <t>IEEE Std 802.15.4 <xref target="IEEE-802-15-4" /> is a
    standard, referred to by RFC 4944 <xref target="RFC4944" /> and other documents,
    that enables very low-cost and low-power communications. The
    standard defines numerous optional Physical Layers
    (PHYs) operating in many different frequency bands with a simple
    and effective Medium Access Control (MAC).</t>

    <t>IEEE Std 802.15.4 defines Information Elements (IEs) that can
    be used to extend 802.15.4 in an interoperable manner. An
    IE provides a flexible, extensible, and
    easily implementable method of encapsulating information. The
    general format of an IE as defined in Section 7.4 of IEEE Std
    802.15.4-2015 <xref target="IEEE-802-15-4" /> consists of an
    identification (ID) field, a length field, and a content field.
    Multiple IEs may be concatenated, and elements with unknown ID
    values in a list of IEs can be skipped since their length is
    known. IEs provide a flexible container for information that
    allows the addition of new IE definitions in future versions of the
    standard in a backwards-compatible manner.</t>

    <t>There are two different IE types, Header IE and Payload IE. A
    Header IE is part of the MAC header; it is
    never encrypted, but it may be authenticated. Most of the Header IE
    processing is done by the MAC, and IETF protocols should not have
    any direct effect on that processing. A Payload IE is part of the
    MAC payload and may be encrypted and authenticated.</t>

    <t>IETF protocols will need to insert information in the 802.15.4
    frames; the 802.15.4 standard enables that by including one or more payload
    IEs in the frame that will contain the information. For this
    purpose, the IETF requests a dedicated Payload IE from the IEEE
    802.15 Assigned Numbers Authority (ANA) <xref
    target='IEEE-802-15-ANA' />. The current 802.15 ANA database can
    be found at <xref target='IEEE-802-15-ANA-DB' />.</t>

    <t>The 802.15.4 operations manual <xref target='IEEE-802-15-OPS'
    /> describes how a Standards Development Organization (SDO) may request
    an allocation of one IE. To make this request the SDO has to
    provide (i) the reason for the request, (ii) a description of the
    protocol format that shows an appropriate subtype capability, and
    (iii) an agreement that only one IE number will be allocated for
    use by the SDO.</t>

    <t>This document provides the information needed for the
    request.</t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
      appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Working Groups Benefiting from the IETF 802.15.4 IE" anchor="users">
    <t>There are several IETF working groups such as 6TiSCH, 6lo, and
    CoRE that could benefit from the IETF IE. The 6TiSCH
    Working Group has already expressed the need for the IE; this
    allocation is expected to satisfy that need.</t>
  </section>

  <section title='IETF IE Subtype Format' anchor='ietf-ie'>

    <t>The maximum length of the Payload IE content is 2047 octets,
    and the 802.15.4 frame contains a list of payload IEs. A single frame
    can have multiple payload IEs, terminated with the payload IE
    terminator, which may then be followed by the payload.</t>

    <t>Since the 802.15.4 standard defines a list of payload IEs along with
    their structures, there is no need for this document to specify the
    internal nesting structure of the IETF IE. The Payload IE
    format of 802.15.4 standard contains the Length field. The length of
    the subtype content can be calculated from the 802.15.4
    Payload IE Length field of the IETF IE.</t>

    <t>The format of the IETF IE is as follows:</t>
    
    <figure anchor="ietf-ie-figure" title="IETF IE Subtype Format" ><artwork><![CDATA[
                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Subtype ID    |                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               |
~                       subtype content                         ~
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>Subtype ID is the IANA-allocated number specifying the
      subtype of the IETF IE. Value 0 is reserved for future
      extensibility, i.e., in case a longer subtype ID field is
      needed.</t>

      <t>Subtype content is the actual content of the Information
      Element, and its length can be calculated from the Length field
      of the IETF IE. </t>
    </list></t>

    <t>One IEEE 802.15.4 frame MAY contain multiple IETF IEs with the
    same or different subtypes.</t>
    
  </section>

  <section title="Request to Allocate an IETF IE">

<t>   Per the IETF's request, the IEEE 802.15 Working Group has allocated an ID
   (5) for a Payload IE for IETF use.  The IETF understands that this is the
   only ID it will be issued.</t>

  </section>

  <section title='Security Considerations'>

    <t>This document creates an IANA registry for IETF IE subtype IDs
    (see <xref target='iana'/>). The security of the protocols using
    the IEs MUST be described in the documents requesting allocations
    from this registry.</t>

    <t>The IEEE Std 802.15.4-2015 <xref target="IEEE-802-15-4" />
    contains methods in which security of the IE can be enforced when a
    frame is received, but this is only per IE type. Therefore, all
    IETF IEs will have the same security-level requirements regardless of
    the subtype ID used. This can cause issues if different security
    processing would be needed and any of those IEs would need to be
    processed in the MAC level. Since all IETF protocols should
    operate at a higher level than the MAC level, the higher-layer
    processing for these IEs SHOULD perform separate security policy
    checking based on the IETF IE subtype ID in addition to the
    checks done by the MAC.</t>

  </section>
  
  <section title='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>

    <t>

The "IEEE Std 802.15.4 IETF IE Subtype IDs" registry has been created
    as follows: </t>

    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Value     Subtype ID
0         Reserved
1-200     Unassigned
201-255   Experimental Use
]]></artwork></figure>

    <t>
Any change or addition to this registry requires Expert
    Review <xref target="RFC5226"/>.</t>

    <t>Note that there are vendor-specific IEs already defined in
    IEEE 802.15.4 (see <xref target="vendor" />); because of this,
    there is no need to reserve any subtype IDs for the
    vendor-specific uses.</t>

  </section>

</middle>
<back>

  <references title="Normative References">
    &rfc2119;



<reference  anchor='RFC8174' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174'>
<front>
<title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<date year='2017' month='May' />
<abstract><t>RFC 2119 specifies common key words that may be used in protocol  specifications.  This document aims to reduce the ambiguity by clarifying that only UPPERCASE usage of the key words have the  defined special meanings.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8174'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8174'/>
</reference>


  </references>

  <references title='Informative References'>
    
    &rfc4944;

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226"?>

    <reference anchor='IEEE-802-15-4'>
      <front>
        <title>IEEE Standard for Low-Rate Wireless Personal Area
        Networks (WPANs)</title>
	<author></author>
        <date year='2015'/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="Standard 802.15.4" />
    </reference>

    <reference anchor='IEEE-802-15-ANA'
	       target="http://www.ieee802.org/15/ANA.html">
      <front>
        <title>IEEE 802.15 Assigned Numbers Authority</title>
	<author></author>
        <date />
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor='IEEE-802-15-ANA-DB'
	       target='https://mentor.ieee.org/802.15/documents?is_dcn=257&amp;is_group=0000'>
      <front>
        <title>IEEE 802.15 ANA database</title>
	<author></author>
        <date />
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor='IEEE-802-15-OPS'
	       target='https://mentor.ieee.org/802.15/documents?is_dcn=235&amp;is_group=0000'>
      <front>
        <title>IEEE 802.15 Operations Manual</title>
	<author></author>
        <date />
      </front>
    </reference>

  </references>

  <section title="Vendor Specific IE in IEEE 802.15.4" anchor='vendor'>

    <t>IEEE 802.15.4 already has several numbers for different Vendor
    Specific IE types. There is one for the Vendor Specific Header IE
    for Header IEs. There is one incorrectly named Vendor Specific
    Nested IE for Payload IEs, and there is another one with exactly
    the same name, but under the MLME Nested IE long format. All of
    the Vendor Specific IEs start with a 3-octet vendor OUI to
    identify the organization.</t>
    
  </section>

<!-- [rfced] Terminology:

Should IEEE precede instances of 802.15.4?  For example:

Originals:
   IEEE Std 802.15.4 defines Information Elements (IEs) that can be used
   to extend 802.15.4 in an interoperable manner.

   The current
   802.15 ANA database can be found at [IEEE-802-15-ANA-DB].

   The 802.15.4 operations manual [IEEE-802-15-OPS] describes how a
   standardization organization (SDO) may request an allocation of one
   IE. 
-->

</back>

</rfc>
