<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../Tools/rfcbootstrap/rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<rfc number="8615" ipr="trust200902" category="std" obsoletes="5785"
     updates="7230, 7595" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Well-Known URIs">Well-Known Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs)</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
        <uri>https://www.mnot.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2019"/>

    <area>General</area>
    
<keyword>link</keyword>
<keyword>link relation</keyword>
<keyword>link relation type</keyword>
<keyword>link relation registry</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This memo defines a path prefix for "well-known locations", "/.well&nbhy;known/", in selected Uniform
Resource Identifier (URI) schemes.</t>

<t>In doing so, it obsoletes RFC 5785 and updates the URI schemes defined in RFC 7230 to reserve that
space. It also updates RFC 7595 to track URI schemes that support well-known URIs in their
registry.</t>



    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>Some applications on the Web require the discovery of information about an origin <xref target="RFC6454"/>
(sometimes called "site-wide metadata") before making a request. For example, the Robots Exclusion
Protocol (http://www.robotstxt.org) specifies a way for automated processes to obtain permission
to access resources; likewise, the Platform for Privacy Preferences <xref target="P3P"/>
tells user agents how to discover privacy policy before interacting with an origin server.</t>

<t>While there are several ways to access per-resource metadata (e.g., HTTP header fields, 
PROPFIND in Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV) <xref target="RFC4918"/>), the perceived overhead (either in terms of client-perceived latency and/or
deployment difficulties) associated with them often precludes their use in these scenarios.</t>

<t>At the same time, it has become more popular to use HTTP as a substrate for non-Web protocols. Sometimes, such protocols need a way to locate one or more resources on a given host.</t>

<t>When this happens, one solution is to designate a "well-known location" for data or services related
to the origin overall, so that it can be easily located. However, this approach has the drawback of
risking collisions, both with other such designated "well-known locations" and with resources that
the origin has created (or wishes to create). Furthermore, defining well-known locations usurps
the origin's control over its own URI space <xref target="RFC7320"/>.</t>

<t>To address these uses, this memo reserves a path prefix in HTTP, HTTPS,
WebSocket (WS), and Secure WebSocket (WSS) URIs for these
"well-known locations", "/.well-known/". Future specifications that need to define a resource for
such metadata can register their use to avoid collisions and minimise impingement upon origins' URI
space.</t>

<t>Well-known URIs can also be used with other URI schemes, but only when those schemes'
definitions explicitly allow it.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

</section>
<section anchor="well-known" title="Well-Known URIs">

<t>A well-known URI is a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/> whose path component begins with the characters
"/.well-known/", provided that the scheme is explicitly defined to support well-known URIs.</t>

<t>For example, if an application registers the name 'example', the corresponding well-known URI on
'http://www.example.com/' would be 'http://www.example.com/.well-known/example'.</t>

<t>This specification updates the "http" <xref target="RFC7230"/> and "https" <xref target="RFC7230"/> schemes to support
well-known URIs. Other existing schemes can use the appropriate process for updating their
definitions; for example, <xref target="RFC8307"/> does so for the "ws" and "wss" schemes. The "Uniform Resource
Identifier (URI) Schemes" registry tracks which schemes support well-known URIs; see
<xref target="register-scheme"/>.</t>

<t>Applications that wish to mint new well-known URIs MUST register them, following the procedures in
<xref target="register"/>, subject to the following requirements.</t>

<t>Registered names MUST conform to the "segment-nz" production in <xref target="RFC3986"/>. This means they cannot
contain the "/" character.</t>

<t>Registered names for a specific application SHOULD be correspondingly precise; "squatting" on
generic terms is not encouraged. For example, if the Example application wants a well-known
location for metadata, an appropriate registered name might be "example-metadata" or even
"example.com-metadata", not "metadata".</t>

<t>At a minimum, a registration will reference a specification that defines the format and associated
media type(s) to be obtained by dereferencing the well-known URI, along with the URI scheme(s) that
the well-known URI can be used with. If no URI schemes are explicitly specified, "http" and "https"
are assumed.</t>

<t>Typically, applications will use the default port for the given scheme; if an alternative port is
used, it MUST be explicitly specified by the application in question.</t>

<t>Registrations MAY also contain additional information, such as the syntax of additional path
components, query strings, and/or fragment identifiers to be appended to the well-known URI, or
protocol-specific details (e.g., HTTP <xref target="RFC7231"/> method handling).</t>

<t>Note that this specification defines neither how to determine the hostname to use to find the
well-known URI for a particular application, nor the scope of the metadata discovered by
dereferencing the well-known URI; both should be defined by the application itself.</t>

<t>Also, this specification does not define a format or media type for the resource located at
"/.well-known/", and clients should not expect a resource to exist at that location.</t>

<t>Well-known URIs are rooted in the top of the path's hierarchy; they are not well-known by
definition in other parts of the path. For example, "/.well-known/example" is a well-known URI,
whereas "/foo/.well-known/example" is not.</t>

<t>See also <xref target="sec"/> for Security Considerations regarding well-known locations.</t>

<section anchor="procedure" title="Registering Well-Known URIs">

<t>The "Well-Known URIs" registry is located at &lt;https://www.iana.org/assignments/well-known-uris/&gt;.
Registration requests can be made by following the instructions located there or by sending an
email to the &lt;wellknown-uri-review@ietf.org&gt; mailing list.</t>

<t>Registration requests consist of at least the following information:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='URI suffix:'>
  The name requested for the well-known URI, relative to "/.well-known/"; e.g., "example".</t>
  <t hangText='Change controller:'>
  For Standards Track RFCs, state "IETF". For others, give the name of the responsible party. Other
details (e.g., email address, home page URI) may also be included.</t>
  <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
  Reference to the document that specifies the field, preferably including a URI that can be used
to retrieve a copy of the document. An indication of the relevant sections may also be included,
but is not required.</t>
  <t hangText='Status:'>
  One of "permanent" or "provisional". See guidance below.</t>
  <t hangText='Related information:'>
  Optionally, citations to additional documents containing further relevant information.</t>
</list></t>

<t>General requirements for registered values are described in <xref target="well-known"/>.</t>

<t>Values defined by Standards Track RFCs and other open standards (in the sense of <xref target="RFC2026"/>, Section 7.1.1) have a status of "permanent". Other values can also be registered as permanent, if the experts find that they are in use, in consultation with the community. Other values should be registered as "provisional".</t>

<t>Provisional entries can be removed by the experts if -- in consultation with the community -- the
experts find that they are not in use. The experts can change a provisional entry's status to
permanent; in doing so, the experts should consider how widely used a value is
and consult the
community beforehand.</t>

<t>Note that "consult the community" above refers to those responsible for the
URI scheme(s) in question. Generally, this would take place on the mailing
list(s) of the appropriate Working Group(s) (possibly concluded), or on
&lt;art@ietf.org&gt; if no such list exists.</t>

<t>Well-known URIs can be registered by third parties (including the expert(s)), if the expert(s)
determine that an unregistered well-known URI is widely deployed and not likely to be registered
in a timely manner otherwise. Such registrations still are subject to the requirements defined,
including the need to reference a specification.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="sec" title="Security Considerations">

<t>Applications minting new well-known URIs, as well as administrators deploying them, will need to
consider several security-related issues, including (but not limited to) exposure of sensitive
data, denial-of-service attacks (in addition to normal load issues), server and client
authentication, vulnerability to DNS rebinding attacks, and attacks where limited access to a
server grants the ability to affect how well-known URIs are served.</t>

<t><xref target="RFC3552"/> contains some examples of potential security considerations that may be relevant to
application protocols and administrators deploying them.</t>

<section anchor="protecting-well-known-resources" title="Protecting Well-Known Resources">

<t>Because well-known locations effectively represent the entire origin, server operators should
appropriately control the ability to write to them. This is especially true when more than one
entity is co-located on the same origin. Even for origins that are controlled by and represent a
single entity, due care should be taken to assure that write access to well-known locations is not
granted unwittingly, either externally through server configuration or locally through
implementation permissions (e.g., on a filesystem).</t>

</section>
<section anchor="interaction-with-web-browsing" title="Interaction with Web Browsing">

<t>Applications using well-known URIs for "http" or "https" URLs need to be aware that well-known
resources will be accessible to Web browsers, and therefore are able to be manipulated by content
obtained from other parts of that origin. If an attacker is able to inject content (e.g., through a
Cross-Site Scripting vulnerability), they will be able to make potentially arbitrary requests to
the well-known resource.</t>

<t>HTTP and HTTPS also use origins as a security boundary for many other mechanisms, including (but
not limited to) cookies <xref target="RFC6265"/>, Web Storage <xref target="WEBSTORAGE"/>, and
various capabilities.</t>

<t>An application that defines well-known locations should not assume that it
has sole access to these
mechanisms or that it is the only application using the origin. Depending on the nature of the application, mitigations can include:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Encrypting sensitive information</t>
  <t>Allowing flexibility in the use of identifiers (e.g., cookie names) to avoid collisions with other applications</t>
  <t>Using the 'HttpOnly' flag on cookies to assure that cookies are not exposed to browser scripting languages <xref target="RFC6265"/></t>
  <t>Using the 'Path' parameter on cookies to assure that they are not available to other parts of the origin <xref target="RFC6265"/></t>
  <t>Using X-Content-Type-Options: nosniff <xref target="FETCH"/> to assure that content under attacker control can't be coaxed into a form that is interpreted as active content by a Web browser</t>
</list></t>

<t>Other good practices include:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Using an application-specific media type in the Content-Type header field, and requiring clients to fail if it is not used</t>
  <t>Using Content-Security-Policy <xref target="CSP"/> to constrain the capabilities of active content (such as HTML <xref target="HTML5"/>), thereby mitigating Cross-Site Scripting attacks</t>
  <t>Using Referrer-Policy <xref target="REFERRER-POLICY"/> to prevent sensitive data in URLs from being leaked in the Referer request header field</t>
  <t>Avoiding use of compression on any sensitive information (e.g., authentication tokens, passwords), as the scripting environment offered by Web browsers allows an attacker to repeatedly probe the compression space; if the attacker has access to the path of the communication, they can use this capability to recover that information.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="scoping-applications" title="Scoping Applications">

<t>This memo does not specify the scope of applicability for the information obtained from a
well-known URI, and does not specify how to discover a well-known URI for a particular application.</t>

<t>Individual applications using this mechanism must define both aspects; if this is not specified,
security issues can arise from implementation deviations and confusion about boundaries between
applications.</t>

<t>Applying metadata discovered in a well-known URI to resources other than
those co-located on the same origin risks administrative as well as security
issues.
   For example, allowing
   "https://example.com/.well-known/example" to apply policy to
   "https://department.example.com", "https://www.example.com", or even
   "https://www.example.com:8000" assumes a relationship between hosts
   where there might be none, thereby giving control to a potential 
   attacker.
</t>

<t>Likewise, specifying that a well-known URI on a particular hostname is to be used to bootstrap a
protocol can cause a large number of undesired requests. For example, if a well-known HTTPS URI is
used to find policy about a separate service such as email, it can result in a flood of requests
to Web servers, even if they don't implement the well-known URI. Such undesired requests can
resemble a denial-of-service attack.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="hidden-capabilities" title="Hidden Capabilities">

<t>
   Applications using well-known locations should consider that some
   server administrators might be unaware of their existence (especially
   on operating systems that hide directories whose names begin with
   ".").
 This means that if an attacker has write access to the .well&nbhy;known directory, they would
be able to control its contents, possibly without the administrator realising it.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<section anchor="register" title="The Well-Known URI Registry">

<t>This specification updates the registration procedures for the "Well-Known
URI" registry, first defined in <xref target="RFC5785"/>; see <xref
target="procedure"/>.</t> 

<t>Well-known URIs are registered on the advice of one or more experts, with a
Specification Required (using terminology from <xref target="RFC8126"/>).</t> 

<t>The experts' primary considerations in evaluating registration requests
are:</t> 

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Conformance to the requirements in <xref target="well-known"/></t>
  <t>The availability and stability of the specifying document</t>
  <t>The considerations outlined in <xref target="sec"/></t>
</list></t>

<t>
IANA will direct the senders of any incoming registry requests to
this document and, if defined, the processes established by the
expert(s); typically, this will mean referring them to the registry
Web page.
</t>

<t>Per this document, IANA has:

<list style="symbols">
  <t>Updated the registration procedure to Specification Required.</t>
  <t>Added a "Status" column to the registry and marked all of the existing
  registrations as "permanent".</t> 
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="register-scheme" title="The Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes Registry">

<t>This specification adds a field to the registration template of the
"Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes" registry, with the name
"Well-Known URI Support" and a default value of "-".</t> 

<t>If a URI scheme explicitly has been specified to use well-known URIs as per
<xref target="well-known"/>, the value changes to a reference to that
specification. Initial values not equal to "-" are given in 
<xref target="tab-initial"/>.</t> 

<texttable title="Rows in URI Scheme Registry with Nonempty New Column" anchor="tab-initial">
      <ttcol align='left'>URI Scheme</ttcol>
      <ttcol align='left'>Well-Known URI Support</ttcol>
      <c>coap</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC7252"/></c>
      <c>coap+tcp</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8323"/></c>
      <c>coap+ws</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8323"/></c>
      <c>coaps</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC7252"/></c>
      <c>coaps+tcp</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8323"/></c>
      <c>coaps+ws</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8323"/></c>
      <c>http</c>
      <c>[RFC8615]</c>
      <c>https</c>
      <c>[RFC8615]</c>
      <c>ws</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8307"></xref></c>
      <c>wss</c>
      <c><xref target="RFC8307"></xref></c>
</texttable>

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference  anchor="RFC6454" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6454'>
<front>
<title>The Web Origin Concept</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Barth' fullname='A. Barth'><organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='December' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the concept of an &quot;origin&quot;, which is often used as the scope of authority or privilege by user agents.  Typically, user agents isolate content retrieved from different origins to prevent malicious web site operators from interfering with the operation of benign web sites.  In addition to outlining the principles that underlie the concept of origin, this document details how to determine the origin of a URI and how to serialize an origin into a string.  It also defines an HTTP header field, named &quot;Origin&quot;, that indicates which origins are associated with an HTTP request.   [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6454'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6454'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC2119" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC8174" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174'>
<front>
<title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<date year='2017' month='May' />
<abstract><t>RFC 2119 specifies common key words that may be used in protocol  specifications.  This document aims to reduce the ambiguity by clarifying that only UPPERCASE usage of the key words have the  defined special meanings.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8174'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8174'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC3986" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986'>
<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='T. Berners-Lee'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'><organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='L. Masinter'><organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<abstract><t>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.  The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='66'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3986'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC7230" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7230'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='J. Reschke' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract><t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless application-level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document provides an overview of HTTP architecture and its associated terminology, defines the &quot;http&quot; and &quot;https&quot; Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes, defines the HTTP/1.1 message syntax and parsing requirements, and describes related security concerns for implementations.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7230'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7230'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC8126" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8126'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Cotton' fullname='M. Cotton'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
<date year='2017' month='June' />
<abstract><t>Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use constants to identify various protocol parameters.  To ensure that the values in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central record keeper.  For IETF protocols, that role is filled by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t><t>To make assignments in a given registry prudently, guidance describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as well as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed.  This document defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines by specification authors, in order to assure that the provided guidance for the IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the operation of a registry.</t><t>This is the third edition of this document; it obsoletes RFC 5226.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='26'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8126'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8126'/>
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

<reference anchor="HTML5" target="https://html.spec.whatwg.org">
  <front>
    <title>HTML - Living Standard</title>
    <author>
      <organization>WHATWG</organization>
    </author>
    <date />
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="FETCH" target="https://fetch.spec.whatwg.org">
  <front>
    <title>Fetch - Living Standard</title>
    <author>
      <organization>WHATWG</organization>
    </author>
    <date />
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="P3P"
           target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-P3P-20020416'>
<front>
<title>The Platform for Privacy Preferences 1.0 (P3P1.0) Specification</title>

<author initials='M.' surname='Marchiori' fullname='Massimo Marchiori'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='16' year='2002' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation' value='REC-P3P-20020416' />
<format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-P3P-20020416' />
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC4918" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4918'>
<front>
<title>HTTP Extensions for Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV)</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Dusseault' fullname='L. Dusseault' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2007' month='June' />
<abstract><t>Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV) consists of a set of methods, headers, and content-types ancillary to HTTP/1.1 for the management of resource properties, creation and management of resource collections, URL namespace manipulation, and resource locking (collision avoidance).</t><t>RFC 2518 was published in February 1999, and this specification obsoletes RFC 2518 with minor revisions mostly due to interoperability experience.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4918'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC4918'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC7320" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7320'>
<front>
<title>URI Design and Ownership</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='July' />
<abstract><t>Section 1.1.1 of RFC 3986 defines URI syntax as &quot;a federated and extensible naming system wherein each scheme's specification may further restrict the syntax and semantics of identifiers using that scheme.&quot;  In other words, the structure of a URI is defined by its scheme.  While it is common for schemes to further delegate their substructure to the URI's owner, publishing independent standards that mandate particular forms of URI substructure is inappropriate, because that essentially usurps ownership.  This document further describes this problematic practice and provides some acceptable alternatives for use in standards.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='190'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7320'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7320'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC8307" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8307'>
<front>
<title>Well-Known URIs for the WebSocket Protocol</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Bormann' fullname='C. Bormann'><organization /></author>
<date year='2018' month='January' />
<abstract><t>RFC 5785 defines a path prefix, &quot;/.well-known/&quot;, that can be used by well-known URIs.  It was specifically defined for the &quot;http&quot; and &quot;https&quot; URI schemes.  The present memo formally updates RFC 6455, which defines the URI schemes defined for the WebSocket Protocol, to extend the use of these well-known URIs to those URI schemes.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8307'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8307'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC7231" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7231'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='J. Reschke' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract><t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless \%application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document defines the semantics of HTTP/1.1 messages, as expressed by request methods, request header fields, response status codes, and response header fields, along with the payload of messages (metadata and body content) and mechanisms for content negotiation.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7231'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7231'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC2026" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2026'>
<front>
<title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1996' month='October' />
<abstract><t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community for the standardization of protocols and procedures.  It defines the stages in the standardization process, the requirements for moving a document between stages and the types of documents used during this process. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='9'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2026'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2026'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC3552" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3552'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Korver' fullname='B. Korver'><organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract><t>All RFCs are required to have a Security Considerations section. Historically, such sections have been relatively weak.  This document provides guidelines to RFC authors on how to write a good Security Considerations section.   This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='72'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3552'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3552'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC6265" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6265'>
<front>
<title>HTTP State Management Mechanism</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Barth' fullname='A. Barth'><organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='April' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the HTTP Cookie and Set-Cookie header fields. These header fields can be used by HTTP servers to store state (called cookies) at HTTP user agents, letting the servers maintain a stateful session over the mostly stateless HTTP protocol.  Although cookies have many historical infelicities that degrade their security and privacy, the Cookie and Set-Cookie header fields are widely used on the Internet.  This document obsoletes RFC 2965.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6265'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6265'/>
</reference>



<reference anchor="WEBSTORAGE"
           target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2016/REC-webstorage-20160419'>
<front>
<title>Web Storage (Second Edition)</title>

<author initials='I.' surname='Hickson' fullname='Ian Hickson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='19' year='2016' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation' value='REC-webstorage-20160419' />
<format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2016/REC-webstorage-20160419' />
</reference>



<reference anchor="CSP"
           target='https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/WD-CSP3-20160913'>
<front>
<title>Content Security Policy Level 3</title>

<author initials='M.' surname='West' fullname='Mike West'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='13' year='2016' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium WD' value='WD-CSP3-20160913' />
<format type='HTML' target='https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/WD-CSP3-20160913' />
</reference>



<reference anchor="REFERRER-POLICY"
           target='https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/CR-referrer-policy-20170126'>
<front>
<title>Referrer Policy</title>

<author initials='J.' surname='Eisinger' fullname='Jochen Eisinger'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E.' surname='Stark' fullname='Emily Stark'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' day='26' year='2017' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium CR' value='CR-referrer-policy-20170126' />
<format type='HTML' target='https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/CR-referrer-policy-20170126' />
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC5785" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5785'>
<front>
<title>Defining Well-Known Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs)</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'><organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Hammer-Lahav' fullname='E. Hammer-Lahav'><organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='April' />
<abstract><t>This memo defines a path prefix for &quot;well-known locations&quot;, &quot;/.well-known/&quot;, in selected Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes.   [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5785'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5785'/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7252"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8323"?>

    </references>


<section anchor="frequently-asked-questions" title="Frequently Asked Questions">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="Aren't well-known locations bad for the Web?"><vspace/>
  They are, but for various reasons -- both technical and social -- they are sometimes necessary.
This memo defines a "sandbox" for them, to reduce the risks of collision and to minimise the impact
upon preexisting URIs on sites.</t>
  <t hangText='Why "/.well-known?"'><vspace/>
  It's short, descriptive, and according to search indices, not widely used.</t>
  <t hangText="What impact does this have on existing mechanisms, such as P3P and robots.txt?"><vspace/>
  None, until they choose to use this mechanism.</t>
 <t hangText="Why aren't per-directory well-known locations defined?"><vspace/>
  Allowing every URI path segment to have a well-known location (e.g., "/images/.well-known/") would
increase the risks of colliding with a preexisting URI on a site, and generally these solutions
are found not to scale well because they're too "chatty".</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="changes-from-rfc5785" title="Changes from RFC 5785">

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Allowed non-Web well-known locations</t>
  <t>Adjusted IANA instructions</t>
  <t>Updated references</t>
  <t>Made various other clarifications</t>
  <t>Tracked supporting schemes in the "Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes" registry</t>
</list></t>

</section>

  </back>

</rfc>

