<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc number="8668" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"  ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Advertising L2 Bundle Attributes in IS-IS">Advertising Layer 2 Bundle Member Link
    Attributes in IS-IS</title> 

    <author fullname="Les Ginsberg" initials="L" surname="Ginsberg" role="editor"> 
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <region></region>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>ginsberg@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ahmed Bashandy" initials="A" surname="Bashandy">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <code>95134</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
<email>abashandy.ietf@gmail.com
</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C" surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>cf@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohan Nanduri" initials="M" surname="Nanduri">
      <organization>eBay</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>mnanduri@ebay.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ebben Aries" initials="E" surname="Aries">
      <organization>Arrcus Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2077 Gateway Place, Suite #400</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <code>95119
	  </code>
<region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America
	  </country>
        </postal>

        <email>exa@arrcus.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date  month="September" year="2019"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>There are deployments where the Layer 3 interface on which IS-IS
      operates is a Layer 2 interface bundle. Existing IS-IS advertisements
      only support advertising link attributes of the Layer 3 interface. If
      entities external to IS-IS wish to control traffic flows on the
      individual physical links that comprise the Layer 2 interface bundle
      link attribute information about the bundle members is required.</t>

      <t>This document introduces the ability for IS-IS to advertise the link
      attributes of Layer 2 (L2) Bundle Members.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>There are deployments where the Layer 3 interface on which an IS-IS
      adjacency is established is a Layer 2 interface bundle, for instance, a
      Link Aggregation Group (LAG) <xref target="IEEE802.1AX"/>. This reduces the number of
      adjacencies that need to be maintained by the routing protocol in cases
      where there are parallel links between the neighbors. Entities external
      to IS-IS such as Path Computation Elements (PCEs) <xref target="RFC4655"/> may wish to
      control traffic flows on individual members of the underlying Layer 2
      bundle. In order to do so, link attribute information about individual
      bundle members is required. The protocol extensions defined in this
      document provide the means to advertise this information.</t>

      <t>This document introduces a new TLV to advertise link attribute
      information for each of the L2 Bundle Members that comprise the Layer 3
      interface on which IS-IS operates.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8667"/> introduces a new link attribute, adjacency segment
      identifier (Adj-SID), which can be used as an instruction to forwarding
      to send traffic over a specific link. This document introduces
      additional sub-TLVs to advertise Adj-SIDs for L2 Bundle Members.</t>

      <t>Note that the new advertisements defined in this document are
      intended to be provided to external (to IS-IS) entities. The following
      items are intentionally not defined and/or are outside the scope of this
      document:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>What link attributes will be advertised. This is determined by
          the needs of the external entities.</t>

          <t>A minimum or default set of link attributes.</t>

          <t>How these attributes are configured.</t>

          <t>How the advertisements are used.</t>

          <t>What impact the use of these advertisements may have on traffic
          flow in the network.</t>

          <t>How the advertisements are passed to external entities.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
         <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>


    </section>

    <section title="L2 Bundle Member Attributes TLV" anchor="BUNDLE">
      <t>A new TLV is introduced to advertise L2 Bundle Member attributes.
      Although much of the information is identical to and uses the same
      sub-TLVs included in Extended IS-Neighbor advertisements (TLVs 22 and
      222), a new TLV is used so that changes to the advertisement of the L2
      Bundle Member link attributes do not trigger unnecessary action by the
      <xref target="ISO10589"/> Decision Process.</t>

      <t>Advertisement of this information implies that the identified link is
      a member of the L2 Bundle associated with the identified Parent L3
      Neighbor and that the member link is operationally up. Therefore,
      advertisements MUST be withdrawn if the link becomes operationally down
      or it is no longer a member of the identified L2 Bundle.</t>

      <t>This new TLV utilizes the sub-TLV space defined for TLVs 22, 23, 141,
      222, and 223.</t>

      <t>The following new TLV is introduced:</t>


      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    L2 Bundle Member Attributes                                                            
     Type: 25
     Length: Number of octets to follow                                                                                 
                                                                                                                       
    Parent L3 Neighbor Descriptor                                                                                      
     L3 Neighbor System ID + pseudonode ID (7 octets)                                                                  
     Flags: 1-octet field of the following flags:                                                                          
                                                                                                                       
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7                                                                                              
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                                                             
        |P|             |                                                                                             
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                                                             
                                                                                                                       
        where:                                                                                                         
                                                                                                                       
        P-flag: When set to 1, one of the sub-TLVs described                                                            
        in Section 3.1 immediately follows the flags field.                                                            
        If the P-flag is set to 0, then none of the sub-TLVs                                                           
        described in Section 3.1 are present.                                                                          
                                                                                                                       
        Other bits: MUST be zero when originated and ignored when                                                      
        received.                                                                                                     
                                                                                                                       
    One or more L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptors (as defined below).

     Length of L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptor (1 octet)                                                               
     NOTE: This includes all fields described below.                                                                
                                                                                                                       
     Number of L2 Bundle Member Descriptors (1 octet)                                                                 
     L2 Bundle Member Link Local Identifiers                                                                          
     (4 * Number of L2 Bundle Member Descriptors octets)                                                                     
     
     NOTE: An L2 Bundle Member Descriptor is a Link Local                                                           
     Identifier as defined in [RFC4202].
                                                                                            
     Sub-TLV(s)
     A sub-TLV may define an attribute common to all of                                                               
     the bundle members listed, or it may define an                                                             
     attribute unique to each bundle member.  Use of these                                                             
     two classes of sub-TLVs is described in the following                                                            
     sections.  
]]></artwork>
        </figure>NOTE: Only one Parent L3 Neighbor Descriptor is present in a                                          
      given TLV. Multiple L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptors may be present in a                                          
      single TLV.</t>


      <section title="Parallel L3 Adjacencies">
        <t>When there exist multiple L3 adjacencies to the same neighbor,
        additional information is required to uniquely identify the L3
        Neighbor. One and only one of the following three sub-TLVs is used to
        uniquely identify the L3 adjacency:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>IPv4 Interface Address (sub-TLV 6 defined in <xref target="RFC5305"/>)</t>

            <t>IPv6 Interface Address (sub-TLV 12 defined in <xref target="RFC6119"/>)</t>

            <t>Link Local/Remote Identifiers (sub-TLV 4 defined in
            <xref target="RFC5307"/>)</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When the P-flag is set in the flags field in the Parent L3 Neighbor
        Descriptor, one and only one of the above sub-TLVs MUST be present. The
        chosen sub-TLV MUST immediately follow the flags field described in
        <xref target="BUNDLE" />.</t>

        <t>These sub-TLVs MAY be omitted if no parallel adjacencies to the
        neighbor exist.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Shared Attribute Sub-TLVs">
        <t>These sub-TLVs advertise a single copy of an attribute (e.g., link
        bandwidth). The attribute applies to all of the L2 Bundle Members in
        the set advertised under the preceding&nbsp;L2 Bundle Member
        Attribute Descriptor. No more than one copy of a given sub-TLV in this
        category may appear in the set of sub-TLVs under the preceding L2
        Bundle Member Attribute Descriptor. If multiple copies of a given
        sub-TLV are present, all copies MUST be ignored.</t>

        <t>The set of L2 Bundle Member Descriptors that may be advertised
        under a single L2 Bundle Member Attribute Descriptor is therefore
        limited to bundle members that share the set of attributes advertised
        in the shared attribute sub-TLVs.</t>

        <t>All existing sub-TLVs defined in the IANA registry for sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23,
        141, 222, and 223 are in the category of shared attribute
        sub-TLVs unless otherwise specified in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Advertising L2 Bundle Member Adj-SIDs">
      <t><xref target="RFC8667"/> defines sub-TLVs to advertise Adj-SIDs for L3 adjacencies.
      However, these sub-TLVs only support the advertisement of a single Adj-SID.
      As it is expected that each L2 Bundle Member will have unique Adj-SIDs
      in many deployments, it is desirable to define a new sub-TLV that allows
      more efficient encoding of a set of Adj-SIDs in a single sub-TLV. Two
      new sub-TLVs are therefore introduced to support advertising Adj-SIDs
      for L2 Bundle Members. The format of the new sub-TLVs is similar to that
      used for L3 adjacencies, but it is optimized to allow advertisement of a
      set of Adj-SIDs (one per L2 Bundle Member) in a single sub-TLV.</t>

      <t>The two new sub-TLVs defined in the following sections do not fall
      into the category of shared attribute sub-TLVs.</t>

      <section title="L2 Bundle Member Adjacency Segment Identifier Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV is used to advertise Adj-SIDs for L2 Bundle Members
        associated with a parent L3 adjacency that is point-to-point. The
        following format is defined for this sub-TLV:</t>
    
 <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[     Type: 41 (1 octet)

     Length: variable (1 octet)
  
     Flags: 1-octet field of the following flags:

          0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
         +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
         |F|*|V|L|S|P|   |
         +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

         where:

         F-Flag: Address-Family flag.  If unset, then the Adj-SID refers
         to an L2 Bundle Member with outgoing IPv4 encapsulation.  If 
         set, then the Adj-SID refers to an L2 Bundle Member with 
         outgoing IPv6 encapsulation.

         V-Flag: Value flag.  If set, then the Adj-SID carries a value.
         By default, the flag is SET.

         L-Flag: Local Flag.  If set, then the value/index carried by
         the Adj-SID has local significance.  By default, the flag is
         SET.

         S-Flag.  Set Flag.  When set, the S-Flag indicates that the
         Adj-SID refers to a set of L2 Bundle Members (and therefore
         MAY be assigned to other L2 Bundle Members as well).

         P-Flag.  Persistent flag.  When set, the P-Flag indicates that
         the Adj-SID is persistently allocated, i.e., the Adj-SID value
         remains consistent across router restart and/or interface flap.

         Other bits: MUST be zero when originated and ignored when
         received.
     
         NOTE: The flags are deliberately kept congruent to the flags 
         in the L3 ADJ-SID defined in [RFC8667].
         * indicates a flag used in the L3 Adj-SID sub-TLV, but one that 
         is NOT used in this sub-TLV.  These bits SHOULD be sent as 0 
         and MUST be ignored on receipt.

     Weight: 1 octet.  The value represents the weight of the Adj-SID
     for the purpose of load balancing.  The use of the weight is
     defined in [RFC8402].

     NOTE: Flags and weight are shared by all L2 Bundle Members
     listed in the L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptor.

     L2 Bundle Member Adj-SID Descriptors: There MUST be one descriptor
     for each of the L2 Bundle Members advertised under the preceding
     L2 Bundle Member Attribute Descriptor.  Each descriptor consists 
     of one of the following fields:

       SID/Index/Label: according to the V and L flags, it contains
       either:

         *  A 3-octet local label where the 20 rightmost bits are used
            for encoding the label value.  In this case, the V and L 
            flags MUST be set.

         *  A 4-octet index defining the offset in the SID/Label space
            advertised by this router.  See [RFC8667].
            In this case, V and L flags MUST be unset.
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
</t>

   </section>

      <section title="L2 Bundle Member LAN Adjacency Segment Identifier Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV is used to advertise Adj-SIDs for L2 Bundle Members
        associated with a parent L3 adjacency that is a LAN adjacency. In LAN
        subnetworks, the Designated Intermediate System (DIS) is elected and
        originates the Pseudonode-LSP (PN-LSP) including all neighbors of the
        DIS. When Segment Routing is used, each router in the LAN MAY
        advertise the Adj-SID of each of its neighbors on the LAN. Similarly,
        for each L2 Bundle Member, a router MAY advertise an Adj-SID to each
        neighbor on the LAN.</t>

        <t>The following format is defined for this sub-TLV:</t>


        <t><figure>
         <artwork><![CDATA[     Type: 42 (1 octet)

     Length: variable (1 octet)

     Neighbor System ID: 6 octets
 
     Flags: 1-octet field of the following flags:

          0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
         +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
         |F|*|V|L|S|P|   |
         +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

         where:

         F-Flag: Address-Family flag.  If unset, then the Adj-SID refers
         to an L2 Bundle Member with outgoing IPv4 encapsulation.  If 
         set, then the Adj-SID refers to an L2 Bundle Member with 
         outgoing IPv6 encapsulation.

         V-Flag: Value flag.  If set, then the Adj-SID carries a value.
         By default, the flag is SET.

         L-Flag: Local Flag.  If set, then the value/index carried by
         the Adj-SID has local significance.  By default, the flag is
         SET.

         S-Flag.  Set Flag.  When set, the S-Flag indicates that the
         Adj-SID refers to a set of L2 Bundle Members (and therefore
         MAY be assigned to other L2 Bundle Members as well).

         P-Flag.  Persistent flag.  When set, the P-Flag indicates that
         the Adj-SID is persistently allocated, i.e., the Adj-SID value
         remains consistent across router restart and/or interface flap.

         Other bits: MUST be zero when originated and ignored when
         received.

         NOTE: The flags are deliberately kept congruent to the flags 
         in the L3 LAN_ADJ-SID defined in [RFC8667].
         * indicates a flag used in the L3 Adj-SID sub-TLV, but one that 
         is NOT used in this sub-TLV.  These bits SHOULD be sent as 0 
         and MUST be ignored on receipt.

     Weight: 1 octet.  The value represents the weight of the Adj-SID
     for the purpose of load balancing.  The use of the weight is
     defined in [RFC8402].

     NOTE: Flags and weight are shared by all L2 Bundle Members
     listed in the L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptor.

     L2 Bundle Member LAN Adj-SID Descriptors.  There MUST be one
     descriptor for each of the L2 Bundle Members advertised 
     under the preceding L2 Bundle Member Attribute Descriptor.
     Each descriptor consists of one of the following fields:

       SID/Index/Label: According to the V and L flags, it contains
       either:

         *  A 3-octet local label where the 20 rightmost bits are used
            for encoding the label value.  In this case, the V and L 
            flags MUST be set.

         *  A 4-octet index defining the offset in the SID/Label space
           advertised by this router.  See [RFC8667].
           In this case, V and L flags MUST be unset.
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document adds the following new TLV to the IS-IS "TLV Codepoints
      Registry".</t>

      <t>Value: 25</t>

      <t>Name: L2 Bundle Member Attributes</t>

      <t>The name of the IANA registry for sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223
      has been changed to include sub-TLV 25. An additional column has been added to the registry to
      indicate which sub-TLVs may appear in the new L2 Bundle Member
      Attributes TLV. The column for TLV 25 has one of the following three
      values:</t>



<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="y   ">sub-TLV may appear in TLV 25 but MUST
NOT be shared by multiple L2 Bundle Members
</t>
<t  hangText="y(s)">sub-TLV may appear in TLV 25 and MAY
be shared by multiple L2 Bundle Members
</t>
<t hangText="n   ">sub-TLV MUST NOT appear in TLV 25
</t>
</list>
</t>
      <t>The following table indicates the appropriate settings for all
      currently defined sub-TLVs with regard to their use in the new L2 Bundle
      Member Attributes TLV.</t>


      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    3 Administrative group (color) y(s)
    4 Link Local/Remote Identifiers y(s)
    6 IPv4 interface address y(s)
    8 IPv4 neighbor address y(s)
    9 Maximum link bandwidth y(s)
    10 Maximum reservable link bandwidth y(s)
    11 Unreserved bandwidth y(s)
    12 IPv6 Interface Address y(s)
    13 IPv6 Neighbor Address y(s)
    14 Extended Administrative Group y(s)
    18 TE Default metric y(s)
    19 Link-attributes y(s)
    20 Link Protection Type y(s)
    21 Interface Switching Capability Descriptor y(s)
    22 Bandwidth Constraints y(s)
    23 Unconstrained TE LSP Count (sub-)TLV y(s)
    24 remote AS number n
    25 IPv4 remote ASBR Identifier n
    26 IPv6 remote ASBR Identifier n
    27 Interface Adjustment Capability Descriptor (IACD) y(s)
    28 MTU n
    29 SPB-Metric y(s)
    30 SPB-A-OALG y(s)
    33 Unidirectional Link Delay y
    34 Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay y
    35 Unidirectional Delay Variation y
    36 Unidirectional Link Loss y
    37 Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth y
    38 Unidirectional Available Bandwidth y
    39 Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth y
    40 RTM Capability n

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>This document adds the following new sub-TLVs to the above registry.</t>

      <t>Value: 41</t>

      <t>Name: L2 Bundle Member Adj-SID</t>

      <t>This sub-TLV is allowed in the following TLVs:</t>
      
      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 22 23 25 141 222 223
 n  n  y   n   n   n
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Value: 42</t>

      <t>Name: L2 Bundle Member LAN Adj-SID</t>

      <t>This sub-TLV is allowed in the following TLVs:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 22 23 25 141 222 223
 n  n  y   n   n   n
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The IS-IS protocol has supported the advertisement of link attribute
      information, including link identifiers, for many years. The
      advertisements defined in this document are identical to existing
      advertisements defined in <xref target="RFC4202"/>, <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8667"/>, but are associated with L2 links that are part of a bundle interface
      on which the IS-IS protocol operates. There are therefore no new
      security issues introduced by the extensions in this document.</t>

      <t>As always, if the protocol is used in an environment where
      unauthorized access to the physical links on which IS-IS Protocol Data
      Units (PDUs) are sent occurs, then attacks are possible. The use of
      authentication as defined in <xref target="RFC5304"/> and <xref
      target="RFC5310"/> is recommended to prevent such attacks.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="ISO10589">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Telecommunications and information
	  exchange between systems -- Intermediate System to Intermediate
	  System intra-domain routeing information exchange protocol for use
	  in conjunction with the protocol for providing the
	  connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="ISO">International Organization for
            Standardization</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2002"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:2002, Second Edition"/>
      </reference>


      
      <reference anchor="IEEE802.1AX" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7055197">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Link
          Aggregation</title>
          <author>
            <organization abbrev="IEEE">IEEE</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1AX"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2014.7055197"/>
      </reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-isis-segment-routing-extensions-25: Companion document -->

<reference  anchor='RFC8667' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8667'>
<front>
<title>IS-IS Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi' role='editor'><organization/></author>
<author initials='L' surname='Ginsburg' fullname='Les Ginsburg' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'><organization /></author>
<author initials='A' surname='Bashandy' fullname='Ahmed Bashandy'><organization /></author>
<author initials='H' surname='Gredler' fullname='Hannes Gredler'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'><organization /></author>
<date year='2019' month='September'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8667'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8667'/>
</reference>


      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4202'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5304'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5305'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5307'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6119'?>
      
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8570'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4655'?>

 <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8402'?>
<!-- draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-11: Now  RFC 8402-->


    </references>

    <section title="Example Encoding">
      <t/>

      <t>Below is an example encoding of L2 Bundle advertisements in a case
      where we have two parallel adjacencies to the same neighbor whose
      system-id is 1234.1234.1234.00. The two L2 bundles have the following
      sets of attributes:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[L3 Adjacency #1
L3 IPv4 local link address: 192.0.2.1
Four bundle members with the following attributes:

--------------------------------------------------
Num | Link Local ID | Bandwidth | Adj-SID/Weight |
--------------------------------------------------
1   | 0x11111111    | 1G        | 0x11111/1      |
--------------------------------------------------
2   | 0x11112222    | 1G        | 0x11112/1      |
--------------------------------------------------
3   | 0x11113333    | 10G       | 0x11113/1      |
--------------------------------------------------
4   | 0x11114444    | 10G       | 0x11114/1      |
--------------------------------------------------

L3 Adjacency #2
L3 IPv4 local link address: 192.0.2.2
Three bundle members with the following attributes:

--------------------------------------------------
Num | Link Local ID | Bandwidth | Adj-SID/Weight |
--------------------------------------------------
1   | 0x22221111    | 10G       | 22221/1        |
--------------------------------------------------
2   | 0x22222222    | 10G       | 22222/1        |
--------------------------------------------------
3   | 0x22223333    | 10G       | 22223/1        |
--------------------------------------------------
]]></artwork>
        </figure>This requires two TLVs, one for each L3 adjacency.</t>

      <t>TLV for Adjacency #1:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

 0                   1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(25)     |Len: 64        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Parent L3 Neighbor Descriptor
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Neighbor System-ID octets 1-4: 1234.1234                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| System-ID octets 5-6: 1234    | P-node: 00    |1|0|0|0|0|0|0|0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  

IPv4 Interface Address Sub-TLV
 0                   1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(6)      | Length(4)     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| IPv4 address:192.0.2.1                                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  

L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptors
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Len:9+6+10 = 25| # Desc: 2     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #1: 0x11111111            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #2: 0x11112222            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


Maximum Link Bandwidth Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(9)       | Length(4)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Bandwidth Value: 1G/8                                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

L2 Bundle Member Adjacency Segment Identifier Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(41)     | Length(8)     |0|0|1|1|0|0|0|0| Weight: 1     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #1: 0x11111         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #2: 0x11112         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptors
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Len:9+6+10 = 25| # Desc: 2     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #3: 0x11113333            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #4: 0x11114444            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


Maximum Link Bandwidth Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(9)       | Length(4)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Bandwidth Value: 10G/8                                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

L2 Bundle Member Adjacency Segment Identifier Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(41)     | Length(8)     |0|0|1|1|0|0|0|0| Weight: 1     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #3: 0x11113         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #4: 0x11114         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+



]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>TLV for Adjacency #2</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(25)     | Len: 46       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Parent L3 Neighbor Descriptor
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Neighbor System-ID octets 1-4: 1234.1234                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| System-ID octets 5-6: 1234    | P-node: 00    |1|0|0|0|0|0|0|0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  

IPv4 Interface Address Sub-TLV
 0                   1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(6)      | Length(4)     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| IPv4 address: 192.0.2.2                                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  

L2 Bundle Attribute Descriptors
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Len:13+6+13=32 | # Desc: 3     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #1: 0x22221111            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #2: 0x22222222            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Link Local Identifier Bundle Member #3: 0x22223333            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


Maximum Link Bandwidth Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(9)       | Length(4)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  
| Bandwidth Value: 10G/8                                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

L2 Bundle Member Adjacency Segment Identifier Sub-TLV
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type(41)     | Length(11)    |0|0|1|1|0|0|0|0| Weight: 1     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #1: 0x22221         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #2: 0x22222         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Local Label Bundle Member #3: 0x22223         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Jon Mitchell for his careful
      review.</t>
    </section>


    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The following people gave a substantial contribution to the content
      of this document and should be considered coauthors:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Stefano Previdi
Huawei Technologies
Italy

Email: stefano@previdi.net]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
