<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>


<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" updates="6811" number="8481"
     submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<front>
  <title abbrev="Origin Validation Clarification">
Clarifications to BGP Origin Validation Based on 
Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)
</title> 

  <author fullname="Randy Bush" initials="R." surname="Bush">
    <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>5147 Crystal Springs</street>
        <city>Bainbridge Island</city>
        <region>Washington</region>
        <code>98110</code>
        <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
      <email>randy@psg.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <date month="September" year="2018"/>

<keyword>Security, Routing</keyword>


  <abstract>

    <t>Deployment of BGP origin validation based on Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)
    is hampered by, among other things, vendor
    misimplementations in two critical areas: which routes are
    validated and whether policy is applied when not specified by
    configuration.  This document is meant to clarify possible
    misunderstandings causing those misimplementations; it thus
    updates RFC 6811 by clarifying that all prefixes should have their
    validation state set and that policy must not be applied without
    operator configuration.</t>

    </abstract>


  </front>

<middle>

  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

    <t>Deployment of RPKI-based BGP origin validation is hampered by,
    among other things, vendor misimplementations in two critical areas:
    which routes are validated and whether policy is applied when not
    specified by configuration.  This document is meant to clarify
    possible misunderstandings causing those misimplementations.</t>

    <t>When a route is distributed into BGP, the origin validation state
    is set to NotFound, Valid, or Invalid per <xref target="RFC6811"/>.
    Operational testing has shown that the specifications of that RFC
    were not sufficient to avoid divergent implementations.  This
    document attempts to clarify two areas which seem to cause
    confusion.</t>

    <t>The implementation issues seem not to be about how to validate,
    i.e., how to decide if a route is NotFound, Valid, or Invalid.  The
    issues seem to be which routes should be evaluated and have their
    evaluation state set, and whether to apply policy without operator
    configuration.</t>

    </section>

  <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>


  <section anchor="reading" title="Suggested Reading">

    <t>It is assumed that the reader understands BGP <xref
    target="RFC4271"/>, the RPKI <xref target="RFC6480"/>, Route Origin
    Authorizations (ROAs) <xref target="RFC6482"/>, and RPKI-based
    Prefix Validation <xref target="RFC6811"/>.</t>

    </section>

  <section anchor="all" title="Evaluate ALL Prefixes">

    <t>Significant Clarification: A router MUST evaluate and set the
    validation state of all routes in BGP coming from any source (e.g., eBGP,
    iBGP, or redistribution from static or connected routes), unless
    specifically configured otherwise by the operator.  Otherwise, the
    operator does not have the ability to drop Invalid routes coming
    from every potential source and is therefore liable to complaints
    from neighbors about propagation of Invalid routes. For this
    reason, <xref target="RFC6811"/> says:

<list>
    <t>When a BGP speaker receives an UPDATE from a neighbor, it
    SHOULD perform a lookup as described above for each of the Routes
    in the UPDATE message.  The lookup SHOULD also be applied to routes
    that are redistributed into BGP from another source, such as
    another protocol or a locally defined static route.</t>
</list>
</t>
    <t><xref target="RFC6811"/> goes on to say, "An implementation MAY
    provide configuration options to control which routes the lookup is
    applied to."</t>

    <t>When redistributing into BGP from any source (e.g., IGP, iBGP, or from
    static or connected routes), there is no AS_PATH in the input to allow
    RPKI validation of the originating Autonomous System (AS). In such cases,
    the router MUST use the AS of the router's BGP configuration.  If that is
    ambiguous because of confederation, AS migration, or other multi-AS
    configuration, then the router configuration MUST provide a means of
    specifying the AS to be used on the redistribution, either per redistribution or
    globally.</t>

    </section>
   
  <section anchor="setstate" title="Set State, Don't Act">

    <t>Significant Clarification: Once routes are evaluated and have
    their state set, the operator should be in complete control of any
    policy applied based on the evaluation state.  Absent specific
    operator configuration, policy MUST NOT be applied.</t>

    <t>Automatic origin validation policy actions such as those
    described in "BGP Prefix Origin Validation
    State Extended Community" <xref target="RFC8097"/> MUST NOT be carried out or otherwise
    applied unless specifically configured by the operator.</t>
    
    </section>

  <section anchor="seccons" title="Security Considerations">

    <t>This document does not create security considerations beyond
    those of <xref target="RFC6811"/>.</t>
    
    </section>
  
  <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    
    </section>

  
  </middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6480"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6482"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6811"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8097"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
    </references>
  <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">

    <t>Many thanks to John Scudder, who had the patience to give
    constructive review multiple times, and Keyur Patel, who noted
    that the AS might have to be specified.  George Michaelson, Jay
    Borkenhagen, John Heasley, and Matthias Waehlisch kindly helped
    clean up loose wording.</t>
    
    </section>


  </back>

</rfc>
