<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" number="8202" ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="6822">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Multi-Instance">IS-IS Multi-Instance</title>

    <author fullname="Les Ginsberg" initials="L" surname="Ginsberg">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>821 Alder Drive</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <code>95035</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ginsberg@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S" surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Del Serafico 200</street>

          <city>Rome</city>

          <code>0144</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sprevidi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wim Henderickx" initials="W" surname="Henderickx">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wim.henderickx@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2017"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>



    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a mechanism that allows a single router to
      share one or more circuits among multiple Intermediate System to
      Intermediate System (IS-IS) routing protocol instances.</t>

      <t>Multiple instances allow the isolation of resources associated with
      each instance. Routers will form instance-specific adjacencies. Each
      instance can support multiple topologies. Each topology has a unique
      Link State Database (LSDB). Each Protocol Data Unit (PDU) will contain a
      new Type-Length-Value (TLV) identifying the instance and the topology
      (or topologies) to which the PDU belongs.</t>

      <t>This document obsoletes RFC 6822.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>An existing limitation of the protocol defined by <xref target="ISO10589" /> is that
      only one instance of the protocol can operate on a given circuit. This
      document defines an extension to IS-IS to remove this restriction. The
      extension is referred to as "Multi-Instance IS-IS" (MI-IS-IS).</t>

      <t>Routers that support this extension are referred to as
      "Multi-Instance-capable routers" (MI-RTR).</t>

      <t>The use of multiple instances enhances the ability to isolate the
      resources associated with a given instance both within a router and
      across the network. Instance-specific prioritization for processing PDUs
      and performing routing calculations within a router may be specified.
      Instance-specific flooding parameters may also be defined so as to allow
      different instances to consume network-wide resources at different
      rates.</t>

      <t>Another existing protocol limitation is that a given instance
      supports a single Update Process operating on a single Link State
      Database (LSDB). This document defines an extension to IS-IS to allow
      non-zero instances of the protocol to support multiple Update Processes.
      Each Update Process is associated with a topology and a unique topology-specific LSDB. Non-zero instances of the protocol are only supported by
      MI-RTRs. Legacy routers support the standard or zero instance of the
      protocol. The behavior of the standard instance is not changed in any
      way by the extensions defined in this document.</t>

      <t>MI-IS-IS might be used to support topology-specific routing. Two
      methods of supporting such a use are defined in this document: one
      supports the use of <xref target="RFC5120" /> within a reserved instance-specific
      topology and the other is an alternative to <xref target="RFC5120" /> that supports
      topology-specific flooding of link state information.</t>

      <t>MI-IS-IS might also be used to support the advertisement of information
      on behalf of applications <xref target="RFC6823" />. The advertisement of information
      not directly related to the operation of the IS-IS protocol can
      therefore be done in a manner that minimizes its impact on the operation
      of routing.</t>

      <t>The above are examples of how MI-IS-IS might be used. The
      specification of uses of MI-IS-IS is outside the scope of this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Elements of Procedure">
      <t>An Instance Identifier (IID) is introduced to uniquely identify an
      IS-IS instance. The protocol extension includes a new TLV (IID-TLV) in
      each IS-IS PDU originated by an MI-RTR except as noted in this document.
      The IID-TLV identifies the unique instance as well as the
      instance-specific topology/topologies to which the PDU applies. Each
      IS-IS PDU is associated with only one IS-IS instance.</t>

      <t>MI-RTRs form instance-specific adjacencies. The IID-TLV included in
      IS-IS Hellos (IIHs) includes the IID and the set of Instance-specific
      Topology Identifiers (ITIDs) that the sending IS supports. When multiple
      instances share the same circuit, each instance will have a separate set
      of adjacencies.</t>

      <t>MI-RTRs support the exchange of topology-specific Link State PDUs for
      the IID/ITID pairs that each neighbor supports. A unique IS-IS Update
      Process (see <xref target="ISO10589" />) operates for each IID/ITID pair. This MAY also
      imply IID/ITID-specific routing calculations and IID/ITID-specific
      routing and forwarding tables. However, this aspect is outside the scope
      of this specification.</t>


      <t>The mechanisms used to implement support of the separation of IS-IS
      instances and topology-specific Update Processes within a router are
      outside the scope of this specification.</t>

      <section title="Instance Identifier TLV">
        <t>A new TLV is defined in order to convey the IID and ITIDs
        supported. The IID-TLV associates a PDU with an IS-IS instance using a
        unique 16-bit number. The IID-TLV is carried in all IS-IS PDUs that
        are associated with a non-zero instance; this includes IIHs, Sequence
        Number PDUs (SNPs), and Link State PDUs (LSPs) .</t>

        <t>Multiple instances of IS-IS may coexist on the same circuit and on
        the same physical router. IIDs MUST be unique within the same routing
        domain.</t>

        <t>IID #0 is reserved for the standard instance supported by legacy
        systems. IS-IS PDUs associated with the standard instance MUST NOT
        include an IID-TLV except where noted in this document.</t>

        <t>The IID-TLV MAY include one or more ITIDs. An ITID is a 16-bit
        identifier where all values (0 - 65535) are valid.</t>

        <t>The following format is used for the IID-TLV:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[  Type:   7 
  Length: 2 - 254 
  Value:  
                                         No. of octets
              +-------------------------+
              | IID (0 - 65535)         |     2
              +-------------------------+
              | Supported ITID          |     2
              +-------------------------+
              :                         :
              +-------------------------+
              | Supported ITID          |     2
              +-------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure><t><list style="empty">
  <t>When the IID = 0, the list of supported ITIDs MUST NOT be present.</t>

  <t>An IID-TLV with IID = 0 MUST NOT appear in an SNP or LSP. When 
  the TLV appears (with a non-zero IID) in an SNP or LSP, exactly 
  one ITID MUST be present, indicating the instance-specific topology
  with which the PDU is associated. If no ITIDs or multiple ITIDs are
  present or the IID is zero, then the PDU MUST be ignored.</t>

  <t>When the IID is non-zero and the TLV appears in an IIH, the set 
  of ITIDs supported on the circuit over which the IIH is sent is 
  included. There MUST be at least one ITID present. </t>

  <t>ITID #0 is reserved for a specific use case as described later
  in this document. ITID #0 MUST NOT be supported in combination
  with any non-zero ITID. If multiple ITIDs are advertised in
  an IIH and one of the ITIDs is #0, then the PDU MUST be ignored.</t>

  <t>Multiple IID-TLVs MAY appear in IIHs. If multiple IID-TLVs are
  present and the IID value in all IID-TLVs is not the same, then
  the PDU MUST be ignored.</t>
      </list></t>

        <t>A single IID-TLV will support advertisement of up to 126 ITIDs. If
        multiple IID-TLVs are present in an IIH PDU, the supported set of
        ITIDs is the union of all ITIDs present in all IID-TLVs.</t>

        <t>When an LSP purge is initiated, the IID-TLV MUST be retained, but
        the remainder of the body of the LSP SHOULD be removed. The purge
        procedure is described in <xref target="RFC6233" /> and <xref target="RFC6232" />.</t>

        <t>It is recommended that (when present) the IID-TLV(s) be the first
        TLV(s) in the PDU. This allows determination of the association of a PDU
        with a particular instance more quickly.</t>

        <t>A PDU without an IID-TLV belongs to the standard instance.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Instance Membership">
        <t>Each MI-RTR is configured to be participating in one or more
        instances of IS-IS. For each non-zero instance in which it
        participates, an MI-RTR marks IS-IS PDUs (IIHs, LSPs, or SNPs)
        generated that pertain to that instance by including the IID-TLV with
        the appropriate instance identifier.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of Authentication">
        <t>When authentication is in use, the IID, if present, is first used
        to select the authentication configuration that is applicable. The
        authentication check is then performed as normal. When multiple ITIDs
        are supported, ITID-specific authentication MAY be used in SNPs and
        LSPs.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Adjacency Establishment">
        <t>In order to establish adjacencies, IS-IS routers exchange IIH PDUs.
        Two types of adjacencies exist in IS-IS: point-to-point and broadcast.
        The following subsections describe the additional rules an MI-RTR MUST
        follow when establishing adjacencies for non-zero instances.</t>

        <section title="Point-to-Point Adjacencies">
          <t>MI-RTRs include the IID-TLV in the point-to-point Hello PDUs
          associated with non-zero instances that they originate. Upon
          reception of an IIH, an MI-RTR inspects the received IID-TLV, and if
          the IID matches any of the IIDs that the router supports on that
          circuit, normal adjacency establishment procedures are used to
          establish an instance-specific adjacency. Note that the absence of
          the IID-TLV implies IID #0. For instances other than IID #0, an
          adjacency SHOULD NOT be established unless there is at least one
          ITID in common.</t>

          <t>This extension allows an MI-RTR to establish multiple adjacencies
          to the same physical neighbor over a point-to-point circuit.
          However, as the instances are logically independent, the normal
          expectation of at most one neighbor on a given point-to-point
          circuit still applies.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-Access Adjacencies">
          <t>Multi-Access (broadcast) circuits behave differently than
          point-to-point in that PDUs sent by one router are visible to all
          routers and all routers must agree on the election of a Designated
          Intermediate System (DIS) independent of the set of ITIDs
          supported.</t>

          <t>MI-RTRs will establish adjacencies and elect a DIS per IS-IS
          instance. Each MI-RTR will form adjacencies only with routers that
          advertise support for the instances that the local router has been
          configured to support on that circuit. Since an MI-RTR is not
          required to support all possible instances on a LAN, it's possible
          to elect a different DIS for different instances.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Update Process Operation">
        <t>For non-zero instances, a unique Update Process exists for each
        supported ITID.</t>

        <section title="Update Process Operation on Point-to-Point Circuits">
          <t>On Point-to-Point circuits -- including Point-to-Point Operation
          over LAN <xref target="RFC5309" /> -- the ITID-specific Update Process only operates
          on that circuit for those ITIDs that are supported by both ISs
          operating on the circuit.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Update Process Operation on Broadcast Circuits">
          <t>On broadcast circuits, a single DIS is elected for each supported
          IID independent of the set of ITIDs advertised in LAN IIHs. This
          requires that the DIS generate pseudo-node LSPs for all supported
          ITIDs and that the Update Process for all supported ITIDs operate on
          the broadcast circuit. Among MI-RTRs operating on a broadcast
          circuit, if the set of supported ITIDs for a given non-zero IID is
          inconsistent, connectivity for the topology (or topologies)
          associated with the ITIDs not supported by some MI-RTRs can be
          compromised.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Interoperability Considerations">
        <t><xref target="ISO10589" /> requires that any TLV that is not understood be silently
        ignored without compromising the processing of the whole IS-IS PDU
        (IIH, LSP, SNP).</t>

        <t>To a router not implementing this extension, all IS-IS PDUs
        received will appear to be associated with the standard instance,
        regardless of whether an IID-TLV is present in those PDUs. This can
        cause interoperability issues unless the mechanisms and procedures
        discussed below are followed.</t>

        <section title="Interoperability Issues on Broadcast Circuits">
          <t>In order for routers to correctly interoperate with routers not
          implementing this extension and in order not to cause disruption, a
          specific and dedicated Media Access Control (MAC) address is used
          for multicasting IS-IS PDUs with any non-zero IID. Each level will
          use a specific Layer 2 multicast address. Such an address allows
          MI-RTRs to exchange IS-IS PDUs with non-zero IIDs without these PDUs
          being processed by legacy routers; therefore, no disruption is
          caused.</t>

          <t>When sending SNPs, LSPs, and LAN IIHs for the standard instance
          (IID #0), an MI-RTR will use either the AllL1IS or the AllL2IS MAC-layer
          addresses (as defined in <xref target="ISO10589" />) as the destination address.
          When sending SNPs, LSPs, and LAN IIHs for any non-zero IID, an MI-RTR
          MUST use one of two new dedicated Layer 2 multicast addresses
          (AllL1MI-ISs or AllL2MI-ISs) as the destination address. These
          addresses are specified in <xref target="IANA" />.</t>

          <t>MI-RTRs MUST discard IS-IS PDUs received if either of the
          following is true:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>The destination multicast address is AllL1IS, AllL2IS, or
              AllIS and the PDU contains an IID-TLV.</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>The destination multicast address is AllL1MI-ISs or
              AllL2MI-ISs and the PDU contains an IID-TLV with a zero value
              for the IID or has no IID-TLV.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>NOTE: If the multicast addresses AllL1IS, AllL2IS, and/or AllIS
          are improperly used to send IS-IS PDUs for non-zero IIDs, legacy
          systems will interpret these PDUs as being associated with IID #0.
          This will cause inconsistencies in the LSDB in those routers, may
          incorrectly maintain adjacencies, and may lead to inconsistent DIS
          election.</t>

          <section title="Special Considerations when Operating in Point-to-Point Mode">
            <t>When operating in point-to-point mode on a broadcast circuit
            <xref target="RFC5309" />, an MI-RTR will use AllL1IS, AllL2IS, or AllIS MAC-layer
            addresses when sending SNPs, LSPs, and point-to-point IIHs
            associated with the standard instance. When sending SNPs, LSPs,
            and point-to-point IIHs for a non-zero IID, an MI-RTR MUST use one
            of the two new multicast addresses (AllL1MI-ISs or AllL2MI-IS) as
            the destination address. When sending point-to-point IIHs for a
            non-zero IID, either address is permitted.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Interoperability Using Point-to-Point Circuits">

          <t>In order for an MI-RTR to interoperate over a point-to-point
          circuit with a router that does NOT support this extension, the
          MI-RTR MUST NOT send IS-IS PDUs for instances other than IID #0 over
          the point-to-point circuit as these PDUs may affect the state of IID
          #0 in the neighbor.</t>

          <t>The presence or absence of the IID-TLV in an IIH indicates that
          the neighbor does or does not support this extension, respectively.
          Therefore, all IIHs sent on a point-to-point circuit by an MI-RTR
          MUST include an IID-TLV. This includes IIHs associated with IID #0.
          Once it is determined that the neighbor does not support this
          extension, an MI-RTR MUST NOT send PDUs (including IIHs) for
          instances other than IID #0.</t>

          <t>Until an IIH is received from a neighbor, an MI-RTR MAY send IIHs
          for a non-zero instance. However, once an IIH with no IID-TLV has
          been received (indicating that the neighbor is not an MI-RTR),
          the MI-RTR MUST NOT send IIHs for a non-zero instance. The temporary
          relaxation of the restriction on sending IIHs for non-zero instances
          allows a non-zero instance adjacency to be established on an
          interface on which an MI-RTR does NOT support the standard
          instance.</t>

          <t>Point-to-point adjacency setup MUST be done through the use of
          the three-way handshaking procedure as defined in <xref target="RFC5303" /> in order
          to prevent a non-MI-capable neighbor from bringing up an adjacency
          prematurely based on reception of an IIH with an IID-TLV for a
          non-zero instance.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Usage Guidelines">
      <t>As discussed above, MI-IS-IS extends IS-IS to support multiple
      instances on a given circuit. Each instance is uniquely identified by
      the IID and forms instance-specific adjacencies. Each instance supports
      one or more topologies as represented by the ITIDs. All topologies
      associated with a given instance share the instance-specific
      adjacencies. The set of topologies supported by a given IID MAY differ
      from circuit to circuit. Each topology has its own set of LSPs and runs
      a topology-specific Update Process. Flooding of topology-specific LSPs
      is only performed on circuits on which both the local router and the
      neighbor(s) support a given topology (i.e., advertise the same ITID in
      the set of supported ITIDs sent in the IID-TLV included in IIHs).</t>

      <t>The following subsections provide some guidelines for usage of
      instances and topologies within each instance. While this represents
      examples based on the intent of the authors, implementors are not
      constrained by the examples.</t>

      <section title="One-to-One Mapping between Topologies and Instances">
        <t>When the set of information to be flooded in LSPs is intended to be
        flooded to all MI-RTRs supporting a given IID, a single topology MAY
        be used. The information contained in the single LSDB MAY still
        contain information associated with multiple applications as the
        GENINFO TLV for each application has an application-specific ID that
        identifies the application to which the TLV applies <xref target="RFC6823" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Many-to-One Mapping between Topologies and Instances">
        <t>When the set of information to be flooded in LSPs includes subsets
        that are of interest to a subset of the MI-RTRs supporting a given
        IID, support of multiple ITIDs allows each subset to be flooded only
        to those MI-RTRs that are interested in that subset. In the simplest
        case, a one-to-one mapping between a given application and an ITID
        allows the information associated with that application to be flooded
        only to MI-RTRs that support that application -- but a many-to-one
        mapping between applications and a given ITID is also possible. When
        the set of application-specific information is large, the use of
        multiple ITIDs provides significantly greater efficiencies, as MI-RTRs
        only need to maintain the LSDB for applications of interest and that
        information only needs to be flooded over a topology defined by the
        MI-RTRs who support a given ITID.</t>

        <t>The use of multiple ITIDs also allows the dedication of a full LSP
        set (256 LSPs at each level) for the use of a given (set of)
        applications, thereby minimizing the possibility of exceeding the
        carrying capacity of an LSP set. Such a possibility might arise if
        information for all applications were to be included in a single LSP
        set.</t>

        <t>Note that the topology associated with each ITID MUST be fully
        connected in order for ITID-specific LSPs to be successfully flooded
        to all MI-RTRs that support that ITID.</t>

        <t>When multiple ITIDs are supported by an instance, ITID #0 MUST NOT
        be supported.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Considerations for the Number of Instances">
        <t>The support of multiple topologies within the context of a single
        instance provides better scalability in support of multiple
        applications both in terms of the number of adjacencies that are
        required and in the flooding of topology-specific LSDB. In many cases,
        the use of a single non-zero instance would be sufficient and optimal.
        However, in cases where the set of topologies desired in support of a
        set of applications is largely disjoint from the set of topologies
        desired in support of a second set of applications, it could make
        sense to use multiple instances.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Relationship to M-ISIS">
      <t><xref target="RFC5120" /> defines support for multi-topology routing. In that
      document, 12-bit Multi-Topology Identifiers (MTIDs) are defined to
      identify the topologies that an IS-IS instance (a "standard instance" as
      defined by this document) supports. There is no relationship between the
      MTIDs defined in <xref target="RFC5120" /> and the ITIDs defined in this
      document.</t>

      <t>An MI-RTR MAY use the extensions defined in this document to support
      multiple topologies in the context of an instance with a non-zero IID.
      Each MI topology is associated with a unique LSDB identified by an ITID.
      An ITID-specific IS-IS Update Process operates on each topology. This
      differs from <xref target="RFC5120" />, where a single LSDB and single IS-IS Update
      Process are used in support of all topologies. In such cases, if an MI-RTR
      uses the extensions in support of the BFD-Enabled TLV <xref target="RFC6213" />, the
      ITID MUST be used in place of the MTID; in which case, all 16 bits of the
      identifier field are useable.</t>

      <t>An MI-RTR MAY support <xref target="RFC5120" /> multi-topology within a non-zero
      instance when ITID #0 is supported. When ITID #0 is supported it MUST be
      the only ITID supported by that instance. In such cases, if an MI-RTR
      uses the extensions in support of the BFD Enabled TLV <xref target="RFC6213" /> the
      <xref target="RFC5120" /> MTID MUST be used as specified in <xref target="RFC6213" />.</t>

      <t>An MI-RTR MUST NOT support <xref target="RFC5120" /> multi-topology within a non-zero
      instance when any non-zero ITID is supported. The following TLVs MUST
      NOT be sent in an LSP associated with a non-zero instance that supports
      a non-zero ITID, and such an LSP MUST be ignored when received:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 TLV 222 - MT IS Neighbors
 TLV 235 - MT IP Reachability
 TLV 237 - MT IPv6 Reachability

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Graceful Restart Interactions">
      <t><xref target="RFC5306" /> defines protocol extensions in support of graceful restart
      of a routing instance. The extensions defined there apply to MI-RTRs
      with the notable addition that as there are topology-specific LSP
      databases all of the topology-specific LSP databases must be
      synchronized following restart in order for database synchronization to
      be complete. This involves the use of additional T2 timers. See
      <xref target="RFC5306" /> for further details.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has registered an IS-IS TLV, 
      reflected in the "IS-IS TLV Codepoints Registry":</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value  Name                   IIH  LSP  SNP  Purge 
 ----   ---------------------  ---  ---  ---  ----- 
  7     Instance Identifier     y    y    y     y 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t>Per <xref target="RFC6822" />, IANA has registered two EUI-48 multicast addresses
      from the IANA-managed EUI address space as specified in <xref target="RFC7042" />. The
      addresses are as follows:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   01-00-5E-90-00-02 AllL1MI-ISs 
   01-00-5E-90-00-03 AllL2MI-ISs 
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>All references to <xref target="RFC6822"/> in the "IS-IS TLV Codepoints Registry" and the "IANA 
Multicast 48-bit MAC Addresses" registry have been replaced by references to this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security concerns for IS-IS are addressed in <xref target="ISO10589"/>, <xref target="RFC5304"/>,
      and <xref target="RFC5310"/>.</t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5304'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5120'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5303'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5306'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6213'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6232'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6233'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6822"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6823"?>

    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

   

      <reference anchor="ISO10589">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Telecommunications and
              information exchange between systems -- Intermediate
              System to Intermediate System intra-domain routeing
              information exchange protocol for use in conjunction with
              the protocol for providing the connectionless-mode network
              service (ISO 8473)</title>

          <author> <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization></author>

          <date month="November" year="2002"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC 10589:2002," value="Second Edition"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5309'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7042'?>


<reference anchor="Err4519" quote-title="false"> 
<front> 
<title>Erratum ID 4519</title>
<author><organization>RFC Errata</organization></author> 
<date></date>
</front> 
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6822"/>
</reference>
  

<reference anchor="Err4520" quote-title="false"> 
<front> 
<title>Erratum ID 4520</title>
<author><organization>RFC Errata</organization></author> 
<date></date>
</front> 
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6822"/>
</reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes to RFC 6822">
      <t>RFC 6822 prohibited the use of Multi-Topology (MT) support as described in RFC 5120
      in a non-zero instance. However, deployment experience since the writing
      of RFC 6822 has revealed a desire to be able to support the style of
      MT in RFC 5120 using multiple non-zero instances as an alternative means of
      controlling leaking of information between L1 areas while also
      supporting incongruent topologies for different address families. The
      rules have therefore been relaxed to allow use of MT per RFC 5120 in a
      non-zero instance so long as ITID #0 is the only instance topology
      (ITID) supported by the instance.  Note that this change is not backwards
      compatible with implementations strictly following RFC 6822. As of this
      writing, all known implementations are compatible with this change.</t>

      <t>A suggestion has been added to place the IID-TLV as the first TLV in
      a PDU to speed recognition of the correct instance when parsing a
      received PDU.</t>

      <t>Clarification that when operating in point-to-point mode on a
      broadcast circuit the IID-TLV is only included in point-to-point IIHs associated
      with non-zero instances has been added. This addresses Errata ID
      4519 <xref target="Err4519"/>.</t>

      <t>Clarification of the appropriate MAC multicast addresses to use when
      sending PDUs on a broadcast interface for both standard instance and
      non-zero instances has been provided. This addresses Errata ID
      4520 <xref target="Err4520"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors greatly acknowledge Mike Shand, Abhay Roy, and Dave Ward for their contributions as coauthors of RFC 6822. In addition, we note that RFC 6822 acknowledged contributions made by Dino Farinacci and Tony Li.</t>

<t>The authors of this document would also like to thank Paul Wells.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
