<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8028" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" updates="4861">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Router Selection in a Multi-Prefix Network">
    First-Hop Router Selection by Hosts in a Multi-Prefix Network</title>
    
    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F.J." surname="Baker">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <code>93117</code>
          <region>California</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>FredBaker.IETF@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Brian Carpenter" initials="B. E." surname="Carpenter">
      <organization abbrev="Univ. of Auckland"/>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>

          <street>University of Auckland</street>

          <street>PB 92019</street>

          <city>Auckland</city>

          <region/>

          <code>1142</code>

          <country>New Zealand</country>
        </postal>

        <email>brian.e.carpenter@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2016"/>

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>IPv6 Maintenance</workgroup>


<keyword>example</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes expected IPv6 host behavior in a scenario that
      has more than one prefix, each allocated by an upstream network that is
      assumed to implement BCP 38 ingress filtering, when the host has multiple routers
      to choose from. It also applies to other scenarios such as the usage of
      stateful firewalls that effectively act as address-based filters. Host
      behavior in choosing a first-hop router may interact with source address
      selection in a given implementation.  However, the selection of the source
      address for a packet is done before the first-hop router for that packet
      is chosen. Given that the network or host
      is, or appears to be, multihomed with multiple provider-allocated
      addresses, that the host has elected to use a source address in a given
      prefix, and that some but not all neighboring routers are advertising
      that prefix in their Router Advertisement Prefix Information Options,
      this document specifies to which router a host should present its
      transmission. It updates RFC 4861.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and Applicability">
      <t>This document describes the expected behavior of an <xref target="RFC2460">IPv6</xref>
      host in a network that has more than one prefix, each allocated by an upstream network
      that is assumed to implement <xref target="RFC2827">BCP 38</xref> ingress filtering, and in which the host
      is presented with a choice of routers. It expects that the network will
      implement some form of egress routing, so that packets sent to a host
      outside the local network from a given ISP's prefix will go to that ISP.
      If the packet is sent to the wrong egress, it is liable to be discarded
      by the BCP 38 filter. However, the mechanics of egress routing once the
      packet leaves the host are out of scope. The question here is how the
      host interacts with that network.</t>

      <t>Various aspects of this issue, and possible solution approaches, are
      discussed in <xref target="RFC7157">"IPv6 Multihoming
      without Network Address Translation"</xref>.</t>

      <t>BCP 38 filtering by ISPs is not the only scenario where such behavior
      is valuable. Implementations that combine existing recommendations, such
      as <xref target="RFC6092"/> and <xref target="RFC7084"/> can also result in
      such filtering. Another case is when the connections to the upstream
      networks include stateful firewalls, such that return packets in a
      stream will be discarded if they do not return via the firewall that
      created the state for the outgoing packets. A similar cause of such discards
      is unicast reverse path forwarding (uRPF) <xref target="RFC3704"/>.</t>

      <t>In this document, the term "filter" is used for simplicity to cover
      all such cases. In any case, one cannot assume that the host is aware
      whether an ingress filter, a stateful firewall, or any other type of
      filter is in place. Therefore, the only known consistent solution is to
      implement the features defined in this document.</t>

      <t>Note that, apart from ensuring that a message with a given source
      address is given to a first-hop router that appears to know about the
      prefix in question, this specification is consistent with <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
      Nevertheless, implementers of Sections 6.2.3, 6.3.4, 6.3.6, and 8.1 of RFC 4861
      should extend their implementations accordingly.
      This specification is fully consistent with <xref target="RFC6724"/> and
      depends on support for its
      Rule 5.5 (see <xref target="sas"/>). Hosts that do not support these features may fail to
      communicate in the presence of filters as described above.</t>

      <section anchor="model" title="Host Model">

        <t>It could be argued that the proposal in this document, which is to
        send messages using a source address in a given prefix to the router
        that advertised the prefix in its Router Advertisement (RA), is a form of
        the Strong End System (ES, e.g., Host) model, discussed in Section
        3.3.4.2 of <xref target="RFC1122"/>. In short, <xref target="RFC1122"/> identifies two basic models. First, the "strong host"
model describes the host as a set of hosts in one chassis, each of which uses
a
single address on a single interface and always both sends and receives on
that interface. Alternatively, the "weak host" model treats the host as one
system with
zero or more addresses on every interface and is capable of using any
interface for
any communication. As noted there, neither
        model is completely satisfactory. For example, a host with a
        link-local-only interface and a default route pointing to that
        interface will necessarily send packets using that
        interface but with a source address derived from some other interface,
        and will therefore be a de facto weak host. If the router
        upstream from such a host implements <xref target="RFC2827">BCP 38
        Ingress Filtering</xref>, such as by implementing uRPF on each
        interface, the router might prevent communication by weak hosts.</t>

        <figure anchor="MIF" title="Hypothetical MIF Interconnection">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+-----------------+
|                 |
|     MIF Router  +---/--- Other interfaces
|                 |
+---+---------+---+
    |         | Two interfaces with subnets
    |         | from a common prefix
  --+-+--   --+-+--
      |         |
   +--+---------+--+
   |   MIF Host    |
   +---------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The proposal also differs slightly from 
        the language in  <xref target="RFC1122"/> for the Strong Host model. The proposal is that the packet
        will go to a router that advertised a given prefix but that does not
        specify what interface that might happen on. Hence, if the router is a
        multi-interface (MIF) router and it is using a common prefix spanning two or
        more LANs shared by the host (as in <xref target="MIF"/>), the host
        might use either of those LANs, according to this proposal. The Strong Host
        model is not stated in those terms, but in terms of the interface
        used. A strong host would treat such an MIF router as two separate routers when obeying
        the rules from RFC 1122 as they apply in the Strong case: <list style="format (%C)">
            <t>A host MUST silently discard an incoming datagram whose
            destination address does not correspond to the physical interface
            through which it is received.</t>

            <t>A host MUST restrict itself to sending (non-source-routed) IP datagrams only through the physical interface that
            corresponds to the IP source address of the datagrams.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>However, when comparing the presumptive route lookup mechanisms in each
        model, this proposal is indeed most similar to the Strong Host model,
        as is any source/destination routing paradigm. <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Strong:">route (src IP addr, dest IP addr, TOS) -&gt;
            gateway</t>

            <t hangText="Weak:">route (dest IP addr, TOS) -&gt; gateway,
            interface</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In the hypothetical MIF model suggested in <xref target="MIF"/>,
        the address fails to identify a single interface, but it does identify
        a single gateway.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Sending Context Expected by the Host">
      <section anchor="host_expects" title="Expectations the Host Has of the Network">
        <t>A host receives prefixes in a <xref target="RFC4861">Router
        Advertisement</xref>, which goes on to identify whether they are
        usable by <xref target="RFC4862">Stateless Address Autoconfiguration (SLAAC)</xref>  with any type
        of interface identifier <xref target="RFC4941"/>
        <xref target="RFC7217"/>. When no prefixes are usable for SLAAC, the
        Router Advertisement would normally signal the availability of
        <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref> and the host would use it to configure
        its addresses. In the latter case (or if both SLAAC and DHCPv6 are
        used on the same link for some reason), the configured addresses generally match one of the prefixes advertised in
        a Router Advertisement that are supposed to be on-link for that
        link.</t>

        <t>The simplest multihomed network implementation in which a host
        makes choices among routers might be a LAN with one or more hosts on
        it and two or more routers, one for each upstream network, or a host
        that is served by disjoint networks on separate interfaces. In such a
        network, especially the latter, there is not necessarily a routing
        protocol, and the two routers may not even know that the other is a
        router as opposed to a host, or may be configured to ignore its
        presence. One might expect that the routers may or may not receive
        each other's RAs and form an address in the other router's prefix
        (which is not per <xref target="RFC4862"/>, but is implemented by some
        stub router implementations). However, all hosts in such a network
        might be expected to create an address in each prefix so
        advertised.</t>

        <figure anchor="simple" title="Two Simple Networks">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+---------+   +---------+    +---------+    +---------+
|   ISP   |   |   ISP   |    |   ISP   |    |   ISP   |
+----+----+   +----+----+    +----+----+    +----+----+
     |             |              |              |
     |             |              |              |
+----+----+   +----+----+    +----+----+    +----+----+
|  Router |   |  Router |    |  Router |    |  Router |
+----+----+   +----+----+    +----+----+    +----+----+
     |             |              |              |
     +------+------+              |  +--------+  |
            |                     +--+  Host  +--+
       +----+----+                   +--------+
       |  Host   |
       +---------+
     Common LAN Case            Disjoint LAN Case
  (Multihomed Network)          (Multihomed Host)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>If there is no routing protocol among those routers, there is no
        mechanism by which packets can be deterministically forwarded between
        the routers (as described in <xref target="RFC3704">BCP 84</xref>) in
        order to avoid filters. Even if there was routing, it would result in
        an indirect route, rather than a direct route originating with the
        host; this is not "wrong", but can be inefficient. Therefore, the host
        would do well to select the appropriate router itself.</t>

        <t>Since the host derives fundamental default routing information from
        the Router Advertisement, this implies that, in any network with hosts
        using multiple prefixes, each prefix SHOULD be advertised via a Prefix
        Information Option (PIO) <xref target="RFC4861"/> by one of the
        attached routers, even if addresses are being assigned using DHCPv6. A
        router that advertises a prefix indicates that it is able to
        appropriately route packets with source addresses within that prefix,
        regardless of the setting of the L and A flags in the PIO.</t>

        <t>In some circumstances, both L and A might be zero. If SLAAC is not
        wanted (A=0) and there is no reason to announce an on-link prefix
        (L=0), a PIO SHOULD be sent to inform hosts that they should use  the
        router in question as the first hop for packets with source addresses
        in the PIO prefix. An example case is the MIF router in <xref target="MIF"/>,
        which could send PIOs with A=L=0 for the common prefix.
        Although this does not
        violate the existing standard <xref target="RFC4861"/>,
        such a PIO has not previously been common, and it is possible that existing host
        implementations simply ignore such a PIO or that existing router
        implementations are not capable of sending such a PIO. Newer
        implementations that support this mechanism should be updated
        accordingly:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>A host SHOULD NOT ignore a PIO simply because both L and
          A flags are cleared (extending Section 6.3.4 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>).</t>
          <t>A router SHOULD be able to send such a PIO
          (extending Section 6.2.3 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>).</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Expectations of Multihomed Networks">

        <t>Networking equipment needs to support source/destination routing for at least 
        some of the routes in the Forwarding Information Base (FIB), such as default egress routes differentiated 
        by source prefix. Installation of source/destination routes in the FIB might 
        be accomplished using static routes, Software-Defined Networking (SDN) technologies, or dynamic routing 
        protocols.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="network_expects" title="Reasonable Expectations of the Host">
      <section title="Interpreting Router Advertisements">
        <t>As described in <xref target="RFC4191"/> and <xref target="RFC4861"/>,
        a Router Advertisement may contain zero or more
        Prefix Information Options (PIOs) or zero or more Route Information
        Options (RIOs). In their original intent, these indicate general
        information to a host: "the router whose address is found in the
        source address field of this packet is one of your default routers",
        "you might create an address in this prefix", or "this router would be
        a good place to send traffic directed to a given destination prefix".
        In a multi-prefix network with multiple exits, the host's characterization
        of each default router SHOULD include the prefixes it
        has announced (extending Section 6.3.4 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>).
        In other words, the PIO is reinterpreted to also imply that
        the advertising router would be a reasonable first hop for any packet
        using a source address in any advertised prefix, regardless of Default Router Preference.</t>

        <?rfc needLines="12"?>

        <figure anchor="BobAlice" title="PIOs, RIOs, and Default Routes">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                                            +---------+  |
                                ( ISP A ) - +  Bob-A  +--+  +-----+
+-------+                      /            +---------+  +--+     |
|       |                     /                          |  |     |
| Alice +--/--( The Internet )                              | Bob |
|       |                     \                          |  |     |
+-------+                      \            +---------+  +--+     |
                                ( ISP B ) - +  Bob-B  +--+  +-----+
                                            +---------+  |
]]></artwork>
        </figure>


        <t>The implications bear consideration. Imagine, <xref target="BobAlice"/>, that hosts Alice and Bob are in communication.
        Bob's network consists of at least Bob (the computer), two routers
        (Bob-A and Bob-B), and the links between them; it may be much larger, for
        example, a campus or corporate network.
        Bob's network is therefore multihomed, and Bob's first-hop routers are Bob-A (to
        the upstream ISP A advertising prefix PA) and Bob-B (to the upstream network B
        and advertising prefix PB). We assume that Bob is not applying Rule 5.5 
        of <xref target="RFC6724"/>. If Bob is responding to a message from
        Alice, his choice of source address is forced to be the address Alice
        used as a destination (which we may presume to have been in prefix
        PA). Hence, Bob either created or was assigned an address in PA, and can only
        reasonably send traffic using it to Bob-A as a first-hop router.        
        If there are several routers in Bob's network advertising the prefix PA
        (referred to as "Bob-Ax" routers), then Bob should choose its first-hop
        router only from among those routers.  From among the multiple Bob-Ax
        routers, Bob should choose the first-hop router based on the criteria
        specified in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC4191"/>.  If none of the
        Bob-Ax routers has advertised an RA with a non-zero Router Lifetime or
        an RIO with a non-zero Route Lifetime that includes Alice, but router Bob-B
        has, it is irrelevant. Bob is using the address allocated in PA and
        courts a BCP 38 discard if he doesn't send the packet to Bob-A.</t>

        <t>In the special case that Bob is initiating the conversation, an RIO
        might, however, influence source address choice. Bob could presumably
        use any address allocated to him, in this case, his address in PA or
        PB. If Bob-B has advertised an RIO for Alice's prefix and Bob-A has
        not, Bob MAY take that fact into account in address selection --
        choosing an address that would allow him to make use of the RIO.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Default Router Selection">
        <t>Default Router Selection (Section 6.3.6 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>)
        is extended as follows: A host SHOULD
        select default routers for each prefix it is assigned an address in.
        Routers that have advertised the prefix in their Router Advertisement
        message SHOULD be preferred over routers that do not advertise the
        prefix, regardless of Default Router Preference. Note that this
        document does not change the way in which default router
        preferences are communicated <xref target="RFC4191"/>.</t>
        
        <t>If no router has advertised the prefix in an RA, normal
        routing metrics will apply. An example is a host connected to the Internet via
        one router, and at the same time connected by a VPN to a private
        domain that is also connected to the global Internet.</t>

        <t>As a result of this, when a host sends a packet using a source
        address in one of those prefixes and has no history directing it
        otherwise, it SHOULD send it to the indicated default router. In the
        "simplest" network described in <xref target="host_expects"/>, that
        would get it to the only router that is directly capable of getting it
        to the right ISP. This will also apply in more complex networks, even
        when more than one physical or virtual interface is involved.</t>

        <t>In more complex cases, wherein routers advertise RAs for multiple
        prefixes whether or not they have direct or isolated upstream
        connectivity, the host is dependent on the routing system already. If
        the host gives the packet to a router advertising its source prefix,
        it should be able to depend on the router to do the right thing.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sas" title="Source Address Selection">
        <t>There is an interaction with <xref target="RFC6724">Default Address
        Selection</xref>. A host following the recommendation in the previous
        section will store information about which next hops advertised which
        prefixes. Rule 5.5 of RFC 6724 states that the source address used to
        send to a given destination address should, if possible, be chosen from
        a prefix known to be advertised by the next-hop router for that
        destination. Therefore, this selection rule SHOULD be implemented in a
        host following the recommendation in the previous section.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Redirects">
        <t>There is potential for adverse interaction with any off-link
        Redirect (Redirect for a destination that is not on-link) message sent
        by a router in accordance with Section 8 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
        Hosts SHOULD apply off-link redirects only for the specific pair of
        source and destination addresses concerned, so the host's Destination
        Cache might need to contain appropriate source-specific entries.
        This extends the validity check specified in Section 8.1 of
        <xref target="RFC4861"/>.</t>
      </section>


      <section title="History">
        <t>Some modern hosts maintain history, in terms of what has previously
        worked or not worked for a given address or prefix and in some cases
        the effective window and Maximum Segment Size (MSS) values for TCP or other protocols. This
        might include a next-hop address for use when a packet is sent to the
        indicated address.</t>

        <t>When such a host makes a successful exchange with a remote
        destination using a particular address pair, and the host has
        previously received a PIO that matches the source address, then the
        host SHOULD include the prefix in such history, whatever the setting
        of the L and A flags in the PIO. On subsequent attempts to communicate
        with that destination, if it has an address in that prefix at that
        time, a host MAY use an address in the remembered prefix for the
        session.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Residual Issues">
      <t>Consider a network where routers on a link run a routing protocol and
      are configured with the same information. Thus, on each link, all routers
      advertise all prefixes on that link. The assumption that packets will be
      forwarded to the appropriate egress by the local routing system might
      cause at least one extra hop in the local network (from the host to the
      wrong router, and from there to another router on the same link).</t>

      <t>In a slightly more complex situation such as the disjoint LAN case of
      <xref target="simple"/>, for example, a home
      plus corporate home-office configuration, the two upstream routers might
      be on different LANs and therefore different subnets (e.g., the host is
      itself multihomed). In that case, there is no way for the "wrong"
      router to detect the existence of the "right" router, or to route to
      it.</t>

      <t>In such a case, it is particularly important that hosts take the
      responsibility to memorize and select the best first hop as described in
      <xref target="network_expects"/>.</t>
    </section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t> This document does not request any registry actions.</t>
</section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document is intended to avoid connectivity issues in the presence of BCP 38
      ingress filters or stateful firewalls combined with multihoming. 
      It does not, in itself, create any new security or privacy exposures.
      However, since the solution is designed to ensure that routing occurs correctly
      in situations where it previously failed, this might result in unexpected
      exposure of networks that were previously unreachable.</t>

      <t>There might be a small privacy improvement: with the current
      practice, a multihomed host that sends packets with the wrong address to
      an upstream router or network discloses the prefix of one upstream to
      the other upstream network. This practice reduces the probability of
      that occurrence.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2460"?>
            
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4191" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6724" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1122" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2827" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3704" ?>


      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4941" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7217" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6092" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7084" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7157" ?>


    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>Comments were received from Jinmei Tatuya and Ole Troan, who have
      suggested important text, plus Mikael Abrahamsson, Steven Barth,
      Carlos Bernardos Cano, Chris Bowers, Zhen Cao, Juliusz
      Chroboczek, Toerless Eckert, David Farmer, Bob Hinden, Ben Laurie, Dusan Mudric,
      Tadahisa Okimoto, Pierre Pfister, Behcet Sarikaya, Mark Smith,       
      and James Woodyatt.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
