<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="8161"
     submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="NDP Benchmarking">Benchmarking the Neighbor Discovery
    Protocol</title>

    <author fullname="Bill Cerveny" initials="W.J." surname="Cerveny">
      <organization>Arbor Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2727 South State Street</street>

          <city>Ann Arbor</city>

          <region>MI</region>

          <code>48104</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wcerveny@arbor.net</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ron Bonica" initials="R." surname="Bonica">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2251 Corporate Park Drive</street>

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>20170</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rbonica@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Reji Thomas" initials="R." surname="Thomas">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Elnath-Exora Business Park Survey</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>KA</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rejithomas@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2017"/>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>Scaling</keyword>

    <keyword>NDP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides benchmarking procedures for the Neighbor
      Discovery Protocol (NDP). It also proposes metrics by which an NDP
      implementation's scaling capabilities can be measured.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>When an IPv6 node forwards a packet, it executes the following
      procedure:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Identifies the outbound interface and IPv6 next hop.</t>

          <t>Queries a local Neighbor Cache (NC) to determine the IPv6 next
          hop's link-layer address.</t>

          <t>Encapsulates the packet in a link-layer header. The link-layer
          header includes the IPv6 next hop's link-layer address.</t>

          <t>Forwards the packet to the IPv6 next hop.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>IPv6 nodes use the <xref target="RFC4861">Neighbor Discovery Protocol
      (NDP) </xref> to maintain the NC. <xref target="RFC6583"> Operational
      experience</xref> shows that when an implementation cannot maintain a
      sufficiently complete NC, its ability to forward packets is
      impaired.</t>

      <t>NDP, like any other protocol, consumes processing, memory, and
      bandwidth resources. Its ability to maintain a sufficiently complete NC
      depends upon the availability of the above-mentioned resources.</t>

      <t>This document provides benchmarking procedures for NDP. Benchmarking
      procedures include a Baseline Test and an NDP Scaling Test. In both
      tests, the Device Under Test (DUT) is an IPv6 router. Two physical links
      (A and B) connect the DUT to a Tester. The Tester sends traffic through
      Link A to the DUT. The DUT forwards that traffic, through Link B, back
      to the Tester.</t>

      <t>The above-mentioned traffic stream contains one or more interleaved
      flows. An IPv6 Destination Address uniquely identifies each flow. Or,
      said another way, every packet within a flow has the same IPv6
      Destination Address.</t>

      <t>In the Baseline Test, the traffic stream contains exactly one flow.
      Because every packet in the stream has the same IPv6 Destination
      Address, the DUT can forward the entire stream using exactly one NC
      entry. NDP is exercised minimally, and no packet loss should be
      observed.</t>

      <t>The NDP Scaling Test is identical to the Baseline Test, except that
      the traffic stream contains many flows. In order to forward the stream
      without loss, the DUT must maintain one NC entry for each flow. If the
      DUT cannot maintain one NC entry for each flow, packet loss will be
      observed and attributed to NDP scaling limitations.</t>

      <t>This document proposes an NDP scaling metric, called
      NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS. NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS is the maximum number of neighbors
      to which an IPv6 node can send traffic during periods of high NDP
      activity.</t>

      <t>The procedures described herein reveal how many IPv6 neighbors an NDP
      implementation can discover. They also provide a rough estimate of the
      time required to discover those neighbors. However, that estimate does
      not reflect the maximum rate at which the implementation can discover
      neighbors. Maximum rate discovery is a topic for further
      exploration.</t>

      <t>The test procedures described herein assume that NDP does not compete
      with other applications for resources on the DUT. When NDP competes for
      resources, its scaling characteristics may differ from those reported by
      the benchmarks described and may vary over time.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Setup" title="Test Setup" toc="default">
      <figure align="center" anchor="setup" suppress-title="false"
              title="Test Setup">
        <artwork align="center" name="Test Setup"><![CDATA[+---------------+             +-----------+
|               |             |           |
|               |   Link A    |   Device  | 
|               |------------>|   Under   |
|    Tester     |             |   Test    |
|               |<------------|   (DUT)   |
|               |   Link B    |           |
+---------------+             +-----------+
               ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The DUT is an IPv6 router. Two links (A and B) connect the DUT to the
      Tester. Link A capabilities must be identical to Link B capabilities.
      For example, if the interface to Link A is a 10 Gigabit Ethernet port,
      the interface to Link B must also be a 10 Gigabit Ethernet port.</t>

      <section title="Device Under Test (DUT)">
        <section title="Interfaces">
          <t>DUT interfaces are numbered as follows:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Link A - 2001:2:0:0::2/64</t>

              <t>Link B - 2001:2:0:1::1/64</t>
            </list>Both DUT interfaces should be configured with a 1500-byte
          MTU. However, if they cannot support a 1500-byte MTU, they may be
          configured with a 1280-byte MTU.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Neighbor Discovery Protocol (NDP)">
          <t>NDP is enabled on both DUT interfaces. Therefore, the DUT emits
          both solicited and unsolicited Router Advertisement (RA) messages.
          The DUT emits an RA message at least once every 600 seconds and no
          more frequently than once every 200 seconds.</t>

          <t>When the DUT sends an RA message, it includes the following
          information:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Router Lifetime - 1800 seconds</t>

              <t>Reachable Time - 0 seconds</t>

              <t>Retrans Time - 0 seconds</t>

              <t>Source Link-Layer Address - link-layer address of DUT
              interface</t>

              <t>M-bit is clear (0)</t>

              <t>O-bit is clear (0)</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The above-mentioned values are chosen because they are the
          default values specified in RFC 4861.</t>

          <t>NDP manages the NC. Each NC entry represents an on-link neighbor
          and is identified by the neighbor's on-link unicast IP address. As
          per RFC 4861, each NC entry needs to be refreshed periodically. NDP
          refreshes NC entries by exchanging Neighbor Solicitation (NS) and
          Neighbor Advertisement (NA) messages.</t>

          <t>No static NC entries are configured on the DUT.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Routing">
          <t>The DUT maintains a direct route to 2001:2:0:0/64 through Link A.
          It also maintains a direct route to 2001:2:0:1/64 through Link B. No
          static routes or dynamic routing protocols are configured on the
          DUT.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Tester">
        <section anchor="tface" title="Interfaces">
          <t>Interfaces are numbered as follows:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Link A - 2001:2:0:0::1/64</t>

              <t>Link B - Multiple addresses are configured on Link B. These
              addresses are drawn sequentially from the 2001:2:0:1::/64
              address block. The first address is 2001:2:0:1::2/64. Subsequent
              addresses are 2001:2:0:1::3/64, 2001:2:0:1::4/64,
              2001:2:0:1::5/64, etc. The number of configured addresses should
              be the expected value of NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS times 1.1.</t>
            </list>Both Tester interfaces should be configured with a
          1500-byte MTU. However, if they cannot support a 1500-byte MTU, they
          may be configured with a 1280-byte MTU.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Neighbor Discovery Protocol (NDP)">
          <t>NDP is enabled on both Tester interfaces. Therefore, upon
          initiation, the Tester sends Router Solicitation (RS) messages and
          waits for Router Advertisement (RA) messages. The Tester also
          exchanges Neighbor Solicitation (NS) and Neighbor Advertisement (NA)
          messages with the DUT.</t>

          <t>No static NC entries are configured on the Tester.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Routing">
          <t>The Tester maintains a direct route to 2001:2:0:0/64 through Link
          A. It also maintains a direct route to 2001:2:0:1/64 through Link B.
          No static routes or dynamic routing protocols are configured on the
          Tester.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="stream" title="Test Traffic">
          <t>The Tester sends a stream of test traffic through Link A to the
          DUT. The test traffic stream contains one or more interleaved flows.
          Flows are numbered 1 through N, sequentially.</t>

          <t>Within each flow, each packet contains an IPv6 header, and each
          IPv6 header contains the following information:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Version - 6</t>

              <t>Traffic Class - 0</t>

              <t>Flow Label - 0</t>

              <t>Payload Length - 0</t>

              <t>Next Header - IPv6-NoNxt (59)</t>

              <t>Hop Limit - 255</t>

              <t>Source Address - 2001:2:0:0::1</t>

              <t>Destination Address - The first 64 bits of the Destination
              Address are 2001:2:0:1::.&nbsp;&nbsp;The next 64 are uniquely
              associated with the flow. Every packet in the first flow carries
              the Destination Address 2001:2:0:1::2. Every subsequent flow has
              an IP address one greater than the last (i.e., 2001:2:0:1::3,
              2001:2:0:1::4, etc.).</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>In order to avoid link congestion, test traffic is offered at a
          rate not to exceed 50% of available link bandwidth. In order to
          avoid burstiness and buffer occupancy, every packet in the stream is
          exactly 40 bytes long (i.e., the length of an IPv6 header with no
          IPv6 payload). Furthermore, the gap between packets is
          identical.</t>

          <t>During the course of a test, the number of flows that the test
          stream contains may increase. When this occurs, the rate at which
          test traffic is offered remains constant. For example, assume that a
          test stream is offered at a rate of 1,000 packets per second. This
          stream contains two flows, each contributing 500 packets per second
          to the 1,000 packet per second aggregate. When a third stream is
          added to the flow, all three streams must contribute 333 packets per
          second in order to maintain the 1,000 packet per second limit. (As
          in this example, rounding error is acceptable.)</t>

          <t>The DUT attempts to forward every packet in the test stream
          through Link B to the Tester. It does this because:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Every packet in the test stream has a Destination Address
              drawn from the 2001:2:0:1::/64 address block.</t>

              <t>The DUT has a direct route to 2001:2:0:1/64 through Link
              B.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Counters">
          <t>On the Tester, two counters are configured for each flow. One
          counter, configured on Link A, increments when the Tester sends a
          packet belonging to the flow. The other counter, configured on Link
          B, increments when the Tester receives a packet from the flow. In
          order for a packet to be associated with a flow, the following
          conditions must all be true:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>The IPv6 Destination Address must be that of the flow.</t>

              <t>The IPv6 Next Header must be IPv6-NoNxt (59).</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The following counters also are configured on both Tester
          Interfaces:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>RS packets sent</t>

              <t>RA packets received</t>

              <t>NS packets sent</t>

              <t>NS packets received</t>

              <t>NA packets sent</t>

              <t>NA packets received</t>

              <t>Total packets sent</t>

              <t>Total packets received</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tests" title="Tests">
      <section title="Baseline Test">
        <t>The purpose of the Baseline Test is to ensure that the DUT can
        forward every packet in the test stream, without loss, when NDP is
        minimally exercised and not operating near its scaling limit.</t>

        <section title="Procedure">
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>On the DUT, clear the NC.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, clear all counters.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, set a timer to expire in 60 seconds.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, start the test stream with exactly one flow
              (i.e., IPv6 Destination Address equals 2001:2:0:1::2).</t>

              <t>Wait for either the timer to expire or the packets-received
              counter associated with the flow to increment.</t>

              <t>If the timer expires, stop the test stream and end the
              test.</t>

              <t>If the packets-received counter increments, pause the traffic
              stream, log the initial counter values, clear the counters,
              reset the timer to expire in 1800 seconds, and restart the
              traffic stream.</t>

              <t>When the timer expires, stop the test stream, wait sufficient
              time for any queued packets to exit, log the final counter
              values, and end the test.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Baseline Test Procedure Flow Chart" toc="default">
          <figure align="center" anchor="baseline-procedure"
                  suppress-title="false"
                  title="Baseline Test Procedure Flow Chart">
            <artwork align="center" name="Baseline Test Procedure Flow Chart"><![CDATA[
                +--------------------------+
                | On the DUT, clear the NC |
                +-------------|------------+
                              |
           +------------------v------------------+
           |  On the Tester, clear all counters  |
           +------------------|------------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |        On the Tester, set a        |
           |        timer to expire in          |
           |        60 seconds                  |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |On the Tester, start the test stream|
           |with exactly one flow (i.e., IPv6   |
           |Destination Address equals          |
           |2001:2:0:0:1::2)                    |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |Wait for either the timer to expire |
           |or packets-received counter         |
           |associated with the flow to         |
           |increment                           |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
                      /-------v-------\
                     /                 \  Yes  +--------------+
                     |Did timer expire?|-------| End the test |
                     \                 /       +--------------+
                      \-------|-------/        
                              | No
                              |
                    /---------v--------\
                   /                    \  No  +--------------+
                   |Did packets-received|------| End the test |
                   |counter increment?  |      +--------------+
                   \                    /      
                    \---------|--------/
                              | Yes
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |Pause traffic stream, log initial   |
           |counter values, clear the counters, |
           |reset the timer to expire in 1800   |
           |seconds, and restart traffic stream |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |When timer expires, stop the test   |
           |stream, wait sufficient time for    |
           |any queued packets to exit, log the |
           |final counter values                |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
                         +----v---+
                         |End test|
                         +--------+
                   ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Results">
          <t>The log contains initial and final values for the following
          counters:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>packets-sent</t>

              <t>packets-received</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The initial values of packets-sent and packets-received may be
          equal to one another. If these values are identical, none of the
          initial packets belonging to the flow were lost. However, if the
          initial value of packets-sent is greater than the initial value of
          packets-received, initial packets were lost. This loss of initial
          packets is acceptable.</t>

          <t>The final values of packets-sent and packets-received should be
          equal to one another. If they are not, an error has occurred.
          Because this error is likely to affect Scaling Test results, the
          error must be corrected before the Scaling Test is executed.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
 <section title="Scaling Test">
        <t>The purpose of the Scaling Test is to discover the number of                                                                                                                                                                                               
        neighbors to which an IPv6 node can send traffic during periods of                                                                                                                                                                                            
        high NDP activity. We call this number NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS.</t>

        <section title="Procedure">
          <t>Execute the following procedure:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>On the DUT, clear the NC.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, clear all counters.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, set a timer to expire in 60 seconds.</t>

              <t>On the Tester, start the test stream with exactly one flow                                                                                                                                                                                           
              (i.e., IPv6 Destination Address equals 2001:2:0:1::2).</t>

              <t>Wait for either the timer to expire or the packets-received                                                                                                                                                                                          
              counter associated with the flow to increment.</t>

              <t>If the timer expires, stop the test stream and end the                                                                                                                                                                                               
              test.</t>

              <t>If the packets-received counter increments, execute the                                                                                                                                                                                              
              following procedure N times, starting at 2 and ending                                                                                                                                                                                                   
          at the expected value of NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS times 1.1.                                                                                                                                                                                                       
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      
          <list>
              <t>Pause the test stream.</t>

              <t>Log the time and the value of N minus one.</t>

              <t>Clear the packets-sent and packets-received counters                                                                                                                                                                                                 
              associated with the previous flow (i.e., N minus one).</t>

              <t>Reset the timer to expire in 60 seconds.</t>

              <t>Add the next flow to the test stream (i.e., IPv6 Destination                                                                                                                                                                                         
              Address is a function of N).</t>

              <t>Restart the test stream.</t>

              <t>Wait for either the timer to expire or the packets-received                                                                                                                                                                                          
              counter associated with the new flow to increment.</t>
            </list></t>
</list>                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               
After the procedure described above has been executed N                                                                                                                                                                                                               
          times, clear the timer and reset it to expire in 1800 seconds. When                                                                                                                                                                                         
          the timer expires, stop the stream, log all counters, and end the                                                                                                                                                                                           
          test (after waiting sufficient time for any queued packets to                                                                                                                                                                                               
          exit).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Scaling Test Procedure Flow Chart" toc="default">

          <figure align="center" anchor="scaling-test-procedure"
                  suppress-title="false"
                  title="Scaling Test Procedure Flow Chart">
            <artwork align="center" name="Scaling Test Procedure Flow Chart"><![CDATA[
                +--------------------------+
                | On the DUT, clear the NC |
                +-------------|------------+
                              |
           +------------------v------------------+
           |  On the Tester, clear all counters  |
           +------------------|------------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |        On the Tester, set a        |
           |        timer to expire in          |
           |        60 seconds                  |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |On the Tester, start the test stream|
           |with exactly one flow (i.e., IPv6   |
           |Destination Address equals          |
           |2001:2:0:0:1::2)                    |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
           +------------------v-----------------+
           |Wait for either the timer to expire |
           |or packets-received counter         |
           |associated with the flow to         |
           |increment                           |
           +------------------|-----------------+
                              |
                      /-------v-------\
                     /                 \  Yes  +--------------+
                     |Did timer expire?|-------|   End test   |
                     \                 /       |   and return |
                      \-------|-------/        +--------------+
                              | No
                              |
                    /---------v--------\
                   /                    \  No  +--------------+
                   |Did packets-received|------|   End test   |
                   |counter increment?  |      |   and return |
                   \                    /      +--------------+
                    \---------|--------/
                              |  Yes
                              |
                       +------v------+
                       |     N=2     |
                       +------|------+
                              |
               /--------------v-------------\
              /              Is              \ No +----------+
              |      N < NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS   |----| End test |
       -------|         times 1.1            |    +----------+
       |      \                              /
       |       \--------------|-------------/
       |                      |    Yes
       |          +-----------v----------+
       |          |Pause the test stream |
       |          +-----------|----------+
       |                      |
       |           +----------v----------+
       |           |Log the time and the |
       |           |value of N minus one |
       |           +----------|----------+
       |                      |
       |          +-----------v-----------+
       |          |Clear the packets-sent |
       |          |and packets-received   |
       |          |counters associated    |
       |          |with the previous flow |
       |          |(i.e., N minus one)    |
       |          +-----------|-----------+
       |                      |
       |           +----------v----------+
       |           |Reset the timer to   |
       |           |expire in 60 seconds |
       |           +----------|----------+
       |                      |
       |       +--------------v---------------+
       |       |Add the next flow to the test |
       |       |stream (i.e., IPv6 Destination|
       |       |Address is a function of N)   |
       |       +--------------|---------------+
       |                      |                     
       |               +------v------+
       |               |     N=N+1   |
       |               +------|------+
       |                      |
       |           +----------v------------+
       ------------|Restart the test stream|
                   +-----------------------+
                   ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Results">
          <t>The test report includes the following:</t>

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>A description of the DUT (make, model, processor, memory, and
              interfaces)</t>

              <t>Rate at which the Tester offers test traffic to the DUT
              (measured in packets per second)</t>

              <t>A log that records the time at which each flow was introduced
              to the test stream and the final value of all counters</t>

              <t>The expected value of NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS</t>

              <t>The actual value of NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS is equal to the number of counter pairs where
          packets-sent is equal to packets-received. Two counters are members
          of a pair if they are both associated with the same flow. If
          packets-sent is equal to packets-received for every counter pair,
          the test should be repeated with a larger expected value of
          NDP-MAX-NEIGHBORS.</t>

          <t>If an implementation abides by the recommendation of Section 7.1
          of RFC 6583, for any given counter pair, packets-received will
          either be equal to zero or packets-sent.</t>

          <t>The log documents the time at which each flow was introduced to
          the test stream. This log reveals the effect of NC size to the time
          required to discover a new IPv6 neighbor.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurements Explicitly Excluded">
      <t>These measurements aren't recommended because of the itemized reasons
      below:</t>

      <section title="DUT CPU Utilization">
        <t>This measurement relies on the DUT to provide utilization
        information, which is not externally observable (not black-box).
        However, some testing organizations may find the CPU utilization is
        useful auxiliary information specific to the DUT model, etc.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Malformed Packets">
        <t>This benchmarking test is not intended to test DUT behavior in the
        presence of malformed packets.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Benchmarking activities as described in this memo are limited to
      technology characterization using controlled stimuli in a laboratory
      environment, with dedicated address space and the constraints specified
      in the sections above.</t>

      <t>The benchmarking network topology will be an independent test setup
      and MUST NOT be connected to devices that may forward the test traffic
      into a production network or misroute traffic to the test management
      network.</t>

      <t>Further, benchmarking is performed on a "black-box" basis, relying
      solely on measurements observable external to the DUT or System Under
      Test (SUT). Special capabilities SHOULD NOT exist in the DUT/SUT
      specifically for benchmarking purposes.</t>

      <t>Any implications for network security arising from the DUT/SUT SHOULD
      be identical in the lab and in production networks.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6583"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="no" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Helpful comments and suggestions were offered by Al Morton, Joel
      Jaeggli, Nalini Elkins, Scott Bradner, and Ram Krishnan on the BMWG
      email list and at BMWG meetings. Precise grammatical corrections and
      suggestions were offered by Ann Cerveny.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
