<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="5068" category="bcp" seriesNo="134" >
    <front>

        <title abbrev="Email Submission">Email Submission Operations: Access
            and Accountability Requirements</title>
        <author fullname="Carl Hutzler" initials="C." surname="Hutzler">
            <organization />
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>2512 Freetown Drive</street>
                    <city>Reston</city>
                    <code>20191</code>
                    <region>VA</region>
                </postal>
                
                <phone>703-915-6862</phone>
                <email>cdhutzler@aol.com</email>
                <uri>http://carlhutzler.com/blog/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." surname="Crocker">
            <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <code>94086</code>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                
                <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
                <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
                <uri>http://bbiw.net</uri>
                
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Peter Resnick" initials="P." surname="Resnick">
            <organization>QUALCOMM Incorporated</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>5775 Morehouse Drive</street>
                    <city>San Diego</city>
                    <code>92121-1714</code>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                
                <phone>+1 858 651 4478</phone>
                <email>presnick@qualcomm.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.qualcomm.com/~presnick/</uri>
                </address>
        </author>


        <author fullname="Eric Allman" initials="E." surname="Allman">
            <organization>Sendmail, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>6745 Christie Ave., Suite 350</street>
                    <city>Emeryville</city>
                    <code />
                    <code>94608</code>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                
                <phone>+1 510 594 5501</phone>
                <email>eric+ietf-smtp@sendmail.org</email>    
                </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Tony Finch" initials="T." surname="Finch">
            <organization>University of Cambridge Computing Service</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>New Museums Site</street>
                    <street>Pembroke Street</street>
                    <city>Cambridge</city>
                    <code>CB2 3QH</code>
                    <country>ENGLAND</country>
                </postal>
                
                <phone>+44 797 040 1426</phone>
                <email>dot@dotat.at</email>
                <uri>http://dotat.at/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>


        <date month="October" year="2007" />
        <area>Applications</area>
        <workgroup>SMTP</workgroup>
        <keyword>spam, email abuse, phishing, email, e-mail, service, mime,
            rfc2822, rfc 2822, rfc822, rfc 822, rfc2821, rfc 2821, rfc821, rfc
            821, architecture, mta, mua, msa, mda, user, delivery, relay,
            header, gateway agent, sieve, dsn, mdn, tussle, mhs, mail handling
            service, message transfer agent, message user agent, mail
            submission agent, mail delivery agent</keyword>


        <abstract>

            <t>Email has become a popular distribution service for a variety
                of socially unacceptable, mass-effect purposes. The most
                obvious ones include spam and worms. This note recommends
                conventions for the operation of email submission and
                transport services between independent operators, such as
                enterprises and Internet Service Providers. Its goal is to
                improve lines of accountability for controlling abusive uses
                of the Internet mail service. To this end, this document offers
                recommendations for constructive operational policies between
                independent operators of email submission and transmission
                services.</t>

            <t>Email authentication technologies are aimed at providing
                assurances and traceability between internetworked networks.
                In many email services, the weakest link in the chain of
                assurances is initial submission of a message. This document
                offers recommendations for constructive operational policies
                for this first step of email sending, the submission (or
                posting) of email into the transmission network. Relaying and
                delivery entail policies that occur subsequent to submission
                and are outside the scope of this document.</t>

        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">

            <t>The very characteristics that make email such a convenient
                communications medium -- its near ubiquity, rapid delivery,
                low cost, and support for exchanges without prior arrangement
                -- have made it a fertile ground for the distribution of
                unwanted or malicious content. Spam, fraud, and worms have
                become a serious problem, threatening the viability of email
                and costing end users and providers millions of dollars in
                damages and lost productivity. In recent years, independent
                operators including enterprises and ISPs have turned to a
                number of different technologies and procedures, in an attempt
                to combat these problems. The results have been
                mixed, at best.</t>

            <t>En route to its final destination, email will often travel
                between multiple independent providers of email transmission
                services. These services will generally have no prior
                arrangement with one another and may employ different rules on
                the transmission. It is therefore difficult both to debug
                problems that occur in mail transmission and to assign
                accountability if undesired or malicious mail is injected into
                the Internet mail infrastructure.</t>

            <t>Many email authentication technologies exist. They provide some
                accountability and traceability between disparate networks.
                This document aims to build upon the availability of these
                technologies by exploring best practices for authenticating
                and authorizing the first step of an email's delivery, from a
                Mail User Agent (MUA) to a Mail Submission Agent (MSA), known
                as submission. Without strong practices on email submission,
                the use of authentication technologies elsewhere in the
                service provides limited benefit.</t>

            <t>This document specifies operational policies to be used for the
                first step of email sending, the submission -- or posting from
                an MUA to an MSA as defined below -- of email into the
                transmission service. These policies will permit continued,
                smooth operation of Internet email, with controls added to
                improve accountability. Relaying and delivering employ
                policies that occur after submission and are outside the scope
                of this document. The policies listed here are appropriate for
                operators of all sizes of networks and may be implemented by
                operators independently, without regard for whether the other
                side of an email exchange has implemented them.</t>

            <t>It is important to note that the adoption of these policies
                alone will not solve the problems of spam and other
                undesirable email. However, these policies provide a useful step in
                clarifying lines of accountability and interoperability
                between operators. This helps 
<?rfc needLines="3"?>
raise the bar against abusers
                and provides a foundation for additional tools to preserve the
                utility of the Internet email infrastructure.</t>

            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="NOTE:  "> This document does not delve into
                        other anti-spam operational issues such as standards
                        for rejection of email. The authors note that this
                        could be a valuable effort to undertake and encourage
                        its pursuit.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Terminology">

            <t>The Internet email architecture distinguishes four
                message-handling components:</t>

            <t>
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Mail User Agents (MUAs)</t>

                    <t>Mail Submission Agents (MSAs)</t>

                    <t>Mail Transfer Agents (MTAs)</t>

                    <t>Mail Delivery Agents (MDAs)</t>
                </list>
            </t>

            <t>At the origination end, an MUA works on behalf of end users to
                create a message and perform initial "submission" into the
                transmission infrastructure, via an MSA. An MSA accepts the
                message submission, performs any necessary preprocessing on
                the message, and relays the message to an MTA for transmission.
                MTAs 'relay' messages to other MTAs, in a sequence reaching a
                destination MDA that, in turn, 'delivers' the email to the
                recipient's inbox. The inbox is part of the recipient-side MUA
                that works on behalf of the end user to process received mail.</t>

            <t>These architectural components are often compressed, such as
                having the same software do MSA, MTA and MDA functions.
                However the requirements for each of these components of the
                architecture are becoming more extensive, so that their
                software and even physical platform separation is increasingly
                common.</t>

                    <t> The key words "MUST",
                        "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                        described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>

        </section>

<?rfc needLines="10"?>

        <section title="Submission, Relaying, Delivery">

            <t>Originally the MSA, MTA, and MDA architectural components were
                considered to be a single unit. This was reflected in the
                practice of having MSA, MTA, and MDA transfers all be performed
                with SMTP <xref target="RFC2821" />
                <xref target="RFC0821" />, over TCP port 25. Internet mail
                permits email to be exchanged without prior arrangement and
                without sender authentication. That is, the confirmed identity
                of the originator of the message is not necessarily known by
                the relaying MTAs or the MDA.</t>

            <t>It is important to distinguish MUA-to-MSA email submission,
                versus MTA relaying, versus the final MTA-to-MDA transition.
                Submission typically does entail a pre-established
                relationship between the user of the client and operator of
                the server; equally, the MDA is performing final delivery and
                can determine that it has an existing relationship with the
                recipient. That is, MSAs and MDAs can take advantage of having
                prior relationships with users in order to constrain their
                transfer activities.</t>

            <t>Specifically, an MSA can choose to reject all postings from
                MUAs for which it has no existing relationship. Similarly, an
                MDA can choose to reject all mail to recipients for which it
                 has no arrangement to perform delivery. Indeed, both of
                these policies are already in common practice.</t>

            <section title="Best Practices for Submission Operation">


                        <t>Submission Port Availability: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t>If external submissions are supported --
                                    that is, from outside a site's
                                    administrative domain -- then the domain's
                                    MSAs MUST support the SUBMISSION port 587
                                       <xref target="RFC4409" />. Operators
                                    MAY standardize on the SUBMISSION port for
                                    both external AND LOCAL users; this can
                                    significantly simplify submission
                                    operations.</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>Submission Port Use: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t>MUAs SHOULD use the SUBMISSION port for
                                    message submission.</t>
                            </list>

                        </t>

                        <t>Submission Authentication: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t>MSAs MUST perform authentication on the
                                    identity asserted during all mail
                                    transactions on the SUBMISSION port, even
                                    for a message having a RCPT TO address
                                    that would not cause the message to be
                                    relayed outside of the local
                                    administrative domain.</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>

<?rfc needLines="6"?>
                        <t>Submission Authorization: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t>An operator of an MSA MUST ensure that the
                                    authenticated identity is authorized to
                                    submit email, based on an existing
                                    relationship between the submitting entity
                                    and the operator. This requirement applies
                                    to all mail submission mechanisms (MUA to
                                    MSA).</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>Submission Accountability after Submission: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t> For a reasonable period of time after
                                    submission, the message SHOULD be
                                    traceable by the MSA operator to the
                                    authenticated identity of the user who
                                    sent the message. Such tracing MAY be
                                    based on transactional identifiers stored
                                    in the headers (received lines, etc.) or
                                    other fields in the message, on audit data
                                    stored elsewhere, or on any other
                                    mechanism that supports sufficient
                                    post-submission accountability. The
                                    specific length of time, after message
                                    submission, that traceability is supported
                                    is not specified here. However, issues
                                    regarding transit often occur as much as
                                    one week after submission. </t>

                                <t>Note that <xref target="RFC3848" /> defines
                                    a means of recording submission-time
                                    information in Received header fields.
                                    This information can help receive-side
                                    analysis software establish a sending
                                    MSA's accountability and then make
                                    decisions about processing the message.</t>
                            </list>

                        </t>

            </section>
            <section title="Transitioning to Submission Port">

                <t>In order to promote transition of initial message
                    submission from port 25 to port 587, MSAs MUST listen on
                    port 587 by default and SHOULD have the ability to listen
                    on other ports. MSAs MUST require authentication on port
                    587 and SHOULD require authentication on any other port
                    used for submission. MSAs MAY also listen on other ports.
                    Regardless of the ports on which messages are accepted,
                    MSAs MUST NOT permit relaying of unauthenticated messages
                    to other domains. That is, they must not be open relays. </t>
                <t>As a default, MUAs SHOULD attempt to find the best possible
                    submission port from a list of alternatives. The SUBMISSION port 587
                    SHOULD be placed first in the list.
                    Since most MUAs available today do not permit falling back
                    to alternate ports, sites SHOULD pre-configure or
                    encourage their users to connect on the SUBMISSION port
                    587, assuming that site supports that port.</t>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="External Submission">

            <t>An MUA might need to submit mail across the Internet, rather
                than to a local MSA, in order to obtain particular services
                from its home site. Examples include active privacy protection
                against third-party content monitoring, timely processing, and
                being subject to the most appropriate authentication and
                accountability protocols. Further, the privacy requirement
                might reasonably include protection against monitoring by the
                operator of the MUA's access network. This requirement creates
                a challenge for the provider operating the IP network through
                which the MUA gains access. It makes that provider an
                involuntary recruit to the task of solving mass-effect email
                problems: When the MUA participates in a problem that affects
                large numbers of Internet users, the provider is expected to
                effect remedies and is often expected to prevent such
                occurrences.</t>

            <t>A proactive technique used by some providers is to block all
                use of port 25 SMTP for mail that is being sent outbound, or
                to automatically redirect this traffic through a local SMTP
                proxy, except for hosts that are explicitly authorized. This
                can be problematic for some users, notably legitimate mobile
                users attempting to use their "home" MSA, even though those
                users might already employ legitimate, port 25-based
                authentication.</t>

            <t>This document offers no recommendation concerning the blocking
                of SMTP port 25 or similar practices for controlling abuse of
                the standard anonymous mail transfer port. Rather, it pursues
                the mutually constructive benefit of using the official
                SUBMISSION port 587 <xref target="RFC4409" />. </t>

            <t>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="NOTE:  "> Many established practices for
                        controlling abuse of port 25, for mail that is being
                        sent outbound, currently do exist. These include the
                        proxy of SMTP traffic to local hosts for screening,
                        combined with various forms of rate limits. The
                        authors suggest that a separate document on this topic
                        would benefit the email operations community.</t>
                </list>
            </t>

            <section
                title="Best Practices for Support of External Submissions">

                        <t>Open Submission Port: </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>
                                <t>Access Providers MUST NOT block users from
                                    accessing the external Internet using the
                                    SUBMISSION port 587 <xref target="RFC4409"
                                     />.</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>Traffic Identification -- External Posting (MSA)
                            Versus Relaying (MX): </t>
                        <t>
                            <list>

                                <t>When receiving email from outside their
                                    local operational environment, email
                                    service providers MUST distinguish between
                                    unauthenticated email addressed to local
                                    domains (MX traffic) versus
                                    submission-related authenticated email
                                    that can be addressed anywhere (MSA
                                    traffic). This allows the MTA to restrict
                                    relaying operations, and thereby prevent
                                    "open" relays. Note that there are
                                    situations where this may not apply, such
                                    as secondary MXs and related
                                    implementations internal to an operator's
                                    network and within their control.</t>
                            </list>
                        </t>


            </section>

            <t><xref target="port587" /> depicts a local user (MUA.l)
                submitting a message to an MSA (MSA). It also shows a
                remote user (MUA.r), such as might be in a coffee shop
                offering "hotspot" wireless access, submitting a
                message to their "home" MSA via an authenticated port
                587 transaction. The figure shows the alternative of
                using port 587 or port 25 within the MSA's network.
                This document makes no recommendations about the use
                of port 25 for submission. The diagram merely seeks to
                note that it is in common use and to acknowledge that
                port 25 can be used with sufficient accountability
                within an organization's network.</t>

            <figure anchor="port587"
                title="Example of Port 587 Usage via Internet">
                <?rfc needLines="25" ?>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
              HOME  NETWORK                       DESTINATION
   +-------+         
   | MUA.l |
   +---+---+
port   |  port     port                          port
587/25 V   25       25          --------          25
    +-----+  +-----+  ******   /        \   ******  +-----+  +-----+
    | MSA |->| MTA |->* AP *->|          |->* AP *->| MTA |->| MDA |
    +--^--+  +-----+  ******  | INTERNET |  ******  +-----+  +-----+
       |                      |          |
       +-------<--------------|----+     |
                               \   |    /
                                ---^----
                                   |
                                 ******
     AP = Access Provider        * AP *
                                 ******
                                   | port 587
                               +---+----+
                               |  MUA.r |
                               +--------+
                               HOTSPOT]]>
</artwork>
            </figure>

        </section>

        <section
            title="Message Submission Authentication/Authorization Technologies">

            <t>There are many competent technologies and standards for
                authenticating message submissions. Two component mechanisms
                that have been standardized include SMTP AUTH <xref
                    target="RFC4954" /> and TLS <xref target="RFC3207" />.
                Depending upon the environment, different mechanisms can be
                more or less effective and convenient. Mechanisms might also
                have to be used in combination with each other to make a
                secure system. Organizations SHOULD choose the most secure
                approaches that are practical. </t>

<?rfc needLines="3"?>
            <t>This document does not provide recommendations on specific
                security implementations. It simply provides a warning that
                transmitting user credentials in clear text over insecure
                networks SHOULD be avoided in all scenarios as this could
                allow attackers to listen for this traffic and steal account
                data. In these cases, it is strongly suggested that an
                appropriate security technology MUST be used.</t>

        </section>

            <section title="Security Considerations">

                <t>Email transfer between independent administrations can be
                    the source of large volumes of unwanted email and email
                    containing malicious content designed to attack the
                    recipient's system. This document addresses the
                    requirements and procedures to permit such exchanges while
                    reducing the likelihood that malicious mail will be
                    transmitted.</t>

            </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">


            <reference anchor="RFC2119">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to
                        Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
                    <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S."
                        surname="Bradner">
                        <organization>Harvard University</organization>
                        <address>
                        <postal>
                            <street>1350 Mass. Ave. </street>
                            <street>Cambridge</street>
                            <street>MA 02138</street>
                        </postal>
                        <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
                        <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
                    </address>
                    </author>
                    <date month="March" year="1997" />
                    <area>General</area>
                    <keyword>keyword</keyword>
                    <abstract>
                        <t> In many standards track documents several words
                            are used to signify the requirements in the
                            specification. These words are often capitalized.
                            This document defines these words as they should
                            be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who
                            follow these guidelines should incorporate this
                            phrase near the beginning of their document: <list>
                                <t> The key words &quot;MUST&quot;,
                                    &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
                                    &quot;REQUIRED&quot;,
                                    &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL
                                    NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
                                    &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
                                    &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
                                    &quot;MAY&quot;, and
                                    &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
                                    document are to be interpreted as
                                    specified in RFC 2119. </t>
                            </list>
                        </t>
                        <t> Note that the force of these words is modified by
                            the requirement level of the document in which
                            they are used. </t>
                    </abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
                <format octets="14486"
                    target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                    type="HTML" />
                <format octets="5661"
                    target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                    type="XML" />
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="RFC2821">
                <front>
                    <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
                    <author fullname="J. Klensin" initials="J."
                        surname="Klensin">
                        <organization />
                    </author>
                    <date month="April" year="2001" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2821" />
                <format octets="192504"
                    target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2821.txt" type="TXT"
                 />
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="RFC4409">
                <front>
                    <title>Message Submission for Mail</title>
                    <author fullname="Randall Gellens" initials="R."
                        surname="Gellens">
                        <organization>QUALCOMM Incorporated</organization>
                        <address>
                            <postal>
                                <street>6455 Lusk Blvd. </street>
                                <city>San Diego</city>
                                <region>CA</region>
                                <code>92121-2779</code>
                                <country>USA</country>
                            </postal>
                            <phone>+1 619 651 5115</phone>
                            <facsimile>+1 619 651 5334</facsimile>
                            <email>Randy@Qualcomm.Com</email>
                        </address>
                    </author>
                    <author fullname="John C. Klensin" initials="J.C."
                        surname="Klensin">
                        <organization>MCI Telecommunications</organization>
                        <address>
                            <postal>
                                <street>800 Boylston St, 7th floor</street>
                                <city>Boston</city>
                                <region>MA</region>
                                <code>02199</code>
                                <country>USA</country>
                            </postal>
                            <phone>+1 617 960 1011</phone>
                            <email>klensin@mci.net</email>
                        </address>
                    </author>
                    <date month="April" year="2006" />
                    <area>Applications</area>
                    <keyword>SMTP</keyword>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4409" />
                <format octets="47918"
                    target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4409.html"
                    type="HTML" />
                <format octets="50997"
                    target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4409.xml"
                    type="XML" />
            </reference>

        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">

            <reference anchor="RFC0821">
                <front>
                    <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
                    <author fullname="Jonathan B. Postel" initials="J.B."
                        surname="Postel">
                        <organization>University of Southern California
                            (USC)/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
                        <address>
                            <postal>
                                <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                                <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                                <region>CA</region>
                                <code>90291</code>
                                <country>US</country>
                            </postal>
                            <phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
                        </address>
                    </author>
                    <date day="1" month="August" year="1982" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="STD" value="10" />
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="821" />
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="RFC4954">
                <front>
                    <title>SMTP Service Extension for Authentication</title>
                    <author fullname="Robert Siemborski" initials="R."
                        surname="Siemborski" role="editor">
                        <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author fullname="Alexey Melnikov" initials="A."
                        surname="Melnikov" role="editor">
                        <organization>Isode Limited</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2007" month="July" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4954" />
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="RFC3207">
                <front>
                    <title>SMTP Service Extension for Secure SMTP over
                        Transport Layer Security</title>
                    <author fullname="P. Hoffman" initials="P."
                        surname="Hoffman">
                        <organization />
                    </author>
                    <date month="February" year="2002" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3207" />
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="RFC3848">
                <front>
                    <title>ESMTP and LMTP Transmission Types Registration</title>
                    <author fullname="Chris Newman" initials="C." surname="Newman">
                        <organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="July" year="2005" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3848" />
            </reference>

        </references>

<vspace blankLines="100"/> <!-- page break before appendix -->

        <section title="Acknowledgments">

            <t>These recommendations were first formulated during informal
                discussions among members of Anti-Spam Technical Alliance
                (ASTA) and some participants from the Internet Research Task
                Force's Anti-Spam Research Group (ASRG).</t>
            <t>Later reviews and suggestions were provided by: M. Allman, L.H.
                Aestrand, N. Borenstein, S. Bortzmeyer, K. Chon, R. Clayton, B.
                Cole, W. Dnes, V. Duchovni, E. Edelstein, F. Ellermann, M.
                Elvey, J.D. Falk, N. Freed, J. Glube, A. Herzberg, J. Klensin,
                J. Levine, S. Moonesamy, K. Moore, R. Nelson, C. Newman, C.
                O'Malley, S. Ramasubramanian, R. Rognlie, J. St. Sauver, W.
                Schlitt, B. Shein, B. Sullivan. </t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
