<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3931 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3931.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4591 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4591.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4349 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4349.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4454 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4454.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4719 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4719.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4446 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4446.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4447 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4447.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5085 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5085.xml'>
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std"
     number="5641"
     updates="3931, 4349, 4454, 4591, 4719">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="L2TPv3 Extended Circuit Status Values">Layer 2
        Tunneling Protocol Version 3 (L2TPv3) Extended&nbsp;Circuit&nbsp;Status&nbsp;Values</title>
        <author initials="N." fullname="Neil McGill" surname="McGill">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>7025-4 Kit Creek Road</street>
                    <street>PO Box 14987</street>
                    <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
                    <region>NC 27709</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email>nmcgill@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
	<author fullname="Carlos Pignataro" initials="C.M." surname="Pignataro">
	<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
	<address>
	    <postal> 
		<street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
		<street>PO Box 14987</street>
		<city>Research Triangle Park</city>
		<code>27709</code>
		<region>NC</region>
		<country>USA</country>
	    </postal>

	    <email>cpignata@cisco.com</email>
	    </address>
	</author>
        <date month="August" year="2009" />

<keyword>L2TPv3</keyword>
<keyword>Circuit Status</keyword>
<keyword>Pseudowire</keyword>
<keyword>Status Change Notification</keyword>

<note title="">
<t>
This document may contain material from IETF Documents or IETF
Contributions published or made publicly available before November 10,
2008.  The person(s) controlling the copyright in some of this material
may not have granted the IETF Trust the right to allow modifications
of such material outside the IETF Standards Process.  Without
obtaining an adequate license from the person(s) controlling the
copyright in such materials, this document may not be modified outside
the IETF Standards Process, and derivative works of it may not be
created outside the IETF Standards Process, except to format it for
publication as an RFC or to translate it into languages other than
English.
</t>
</note>

        <abstract>
	  <t> 
	    This document defines additional Layer 2 Tunneling
	    Protocol Version 3 (L2TPv3) bit values to be used within
	    the "Circuit Status" Attribute Value Pair (AVP) to
	    communicate finer-grained error states for Attachment
	    Circuits (ACs) and pseudowires (PWs).  It also generalizes
	    the Active bit and deprecates the use of the New bit in
	    the Circuit Status AVP, updating RFC 3931, RFC 4349, RFC
	    4454, RFC 4591, and RFC 4719.
	  </t>
        </abstract>

    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
	    <t> 
		Currently, the L2TPv3 Circuit Status AVP <xref target="RFC3931"/>
		is able to convey the UP/DOWN status of an access circuit. 
		However, a finer granularity is often useful to determine the direction of the
		fault, as has been added for MPLS-based pseudowires
                and is used in the pseudowire control protocol using 
                the Label Distribution Protocol (LDP); see 
		Section 3.5 of
		<xref target="RFC4446"/> and
		Section 5.4.2 of <xref target="RFC4447"/>.
	    </t>
	    <t> 
		Additionally, it is useful (in session-level
		redundancy scenarios) to be able to indicate if a
		pseudowire is in a standby state, where it is fully
		established by signaling and allows Operations,
		Administration, and Maintenance, but is not
		switching data. Again, such functionality is available
		for MPLS-based pseudowires using LDP, see
		<xref target="PREF-FWD"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
		This document provides extended circuit status bit
		values for L2TPv3 and adds them in a manner
		such that it is backwards compatible with the current
		Circuit Status AVP. These new bits are applicable 
		to all pseudowire types that use the Circuit Status AVP.
	    </t>

            <section title="Specification of Requirements" anchor="reqs">
                <t>
		    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
		    "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
		    interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
		</t>
            </section>

	    <section title="Abbreviations">
	      
	      <t>The following abbreviations are used in this document
		and in the documents that it updates. L2TPv3 Control
		Message Types are listed in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC3931"/>.
	      </t>
	      <figure>
		<artwork>
  AC    Attachment Circuit
  AVP   Attribute Value Pair
  LCCE  L2TP Control Connection Endpoint 
  NNI   Network-Network Interface
  PE    Provider Edge
  PSN   Packet Switched Network		 
  PW    Pseudowire
		</artwork>
	      </figure>
	    </section>
	    
        </section>

        <section title="L2TPv3 Extended Circuit Status Values" anchor="circuit_status">
	    <t> 
		The Circuit Status AVP (ICRQ, ICRP, ICCN, OCRQ, OCRP, OCCN, SLI),
		Attribute Type 71, indicates the initial status of, or
		a status change in, the circuit to which the session is bound.
	    </t> 
	    <t> 
		The Attribute Value field for this AVP, currently
		defined in <xref target="RFC3931"/>, has the following
		format:</t> 
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |         Reserved          |N|A|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

  Bit  Bit-Value   Name
  ----------------------------------------------------------------
  (A)  15  0x0001  Active
  (N)  14  0x0002  New
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
	    <t> 
As currently defined in <xref target="RFC3931"/> and replicated
in 
<xref target="RFC4349"/>,
<xref target="RFC4454"/>,
<xref target="RFC4591"/>, and
<xref target="RFC4719"/>,
the two bits have the following meanings: 
<list style="symbols"><t>
      The A (Active) bit indicates whether the circuit is
      up/active/ready (1) or down/inactive/not-ready (0).
</t><t>
      The N (New) bit indicates whether the circuit status indication is
      for a new circuit (1) or an existing circuit (0).
</t></list>
	    </t> 
	    <t> 
This document updates the semantics of the A and N bits as follows
(see also <xref target="updates"/>):
	    </t> 
	    <t> 
   The A (Active) bit indicates whether the local pseudowire endpoint
   (including the local Attachment Circuit (AC) and local Packet Switched
   Network (PSN)-facing pseudowire termination) has no faults present and is
   up/active/ready (1) or has faults present and is
   down/inactive/not-ready (0).

	    </t> 
	    <t> 

  The N (New) bit indicates if the notification is for a new circuit
  (1) or an existing circuit (0), and is provided to emulate 
  Network-Network Interface (NNI) signaling between Provider
  Edge (PE) routers, e.g., Frame Relay NNI.

It MAY be used to convey that a 
		circuit has been re-provisioned or newly provisioned at
		the PE, which can already be inferred from the L2TP control
                message type.

		It is therefore uncertain as to what use the receiving PE can make 
		of this bit, although it MAY include logging. 
		
		This document deprecates this bit as it is of little or 
		no use, hence this bit SHOULD be ignored on receipt and is 
		OPTIONAL to set on sending.

		For reference, see Section 3.4 of <xref target="RFC4591"/>,
		which does not specify any additional usage beyond the setting 
		of the N bit in the ICRQ, ICRP (and OCRQ, OCRP) and
		the clearing of it in all other control messages.
	    </t> 
	    <t> 
                This document also extends this bitmap of values to allow for finer granularity of
local pseudowire (i.e., Attachment Circuit or PSN-facing endpoint) status reporting. 
	    </t> 
	    <t> 
The Attribute Value field for the Circuit Status AVP, including
the new values, has the following format:
	    </t> 
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |     Reserved    |S|E|I|T|R|N|A|
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


  Bit  Bit-Value   Name
  -----------------------------------------------------------------
  (A)  15  0x0001  Active: Pseudowire has no faults
  (N)  14  0x0002  New [use deprecated]
  (R)  13  0x0004  Local Attachment Circuit (ingress) Receive Fault
  (T)  12  0x0008  Local Attachment Circuit (egress) Transmit Fault
  (I)  11  0x0010  Local PSN-facing PW (ingress) Receive Fault
  (E)  10  0x0020  Local PSN-facing PW (egress) Transmit Fault
  (S)   9  0x0040  Pseudowire is in Standby mode
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

	    <t> 
	    The new bit values have the following meanings:

	    </t> 
                    <t>
            <figure>
<preamble>
                    (R), Local Attachment Circuit (ingress) Receive Fault
</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[       
 Fault Here
      |
      |
      |   +----------------------+         +----------------------+
      | Rx|         LCCE         |Egress   |       Peer LCCE      |
    --X-->|                      |-------->|                      |
          |             L2TPv3   |  [PSN]  |   L2TPv3             |
        Tx| Circuit   Pseudowire |Ingress  | Pseudowire   Circuit |
    <-----|                      |<--------|                      |
          +----------------------+         +----------------------+
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
                        <list>
			    <t> 
			An alarm or fault has occurred at the local Attachment Circuit such that
				it is unable to receive traffic. It can still transmit traffic.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
            <figure>
<preamble>
                    (T), Local Attachment Circuit (egress) Transmit Fault
</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[       
          +----------------------+         +----------------------+
        Rx|         LCCE         |Egress   |       Peer LCCE      |
    ----->|                      |-------->|                      |
          |             L2TPv3   |  [PSN]  |   L2TPv3             |
        Tx| Circuit   Pseudowire |Ingress  | Pseudowire   Circuit |
    <--X--|                      |<--------|                      |
       |  +----------------------+         +----------------------+
       |
       |
  Fault Here
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
                        <list>
			    <t> 
				A fault has occurred at the local Attachment Circuit such that
				it is unable to transmit traffic. It can still receive traffic.
                            </t>
                        </list>
		    </t>
                    <t>
            <figure>
<preamble>
                    (I), Local PSN-facing PW (ingress) Receive Fault
</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[       
          +----------------------+         +----------------------+
        Rx|         LCCE         |Egress   |       Peer LCCE      |
    ----->|                      |-------->|                      |
          |             L2TPv3   |  [PSN]  |   L2TPv3             |
        Tx| Circuit   Pseudowire |Ingress  | Pseudowire   Circuit |
    <-----|                      |<---X----|                      |
          +----------------------+    |    +----------------------+
                                      |
                                      |
                                 Fault Here
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
                        <list>
			    <t> 
				A fault has occurred in the receive direction between the
				local endpoint and the remote L2TP endpoint. 
                            </t>
                        </list>
                            </t>
                            <t>
                        <list>
                            <t>
			Note that a fault at the session level would not necessarily trigger an L2TP 
			control connection timeout. The means of detecting this fault are outside the 
				scope of this document; as an example,
			detection may be via PW Type-specific means,
			Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD), or
			other methods.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
            <figure>
<preamble>
                    (E), Local PSN-facing PW (egress) Transmit Fault
</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[       
                                   Fault Here
                                        |
                                        |
          +----------------------+      |  +----------------------+
        Rx|         LCCE         |Egress|  |       Peer LCCE      |
    ----->|                      |------X->|                      |
          |             L2TPv3   |  [PSN]  |   L2TPv3             |
        Tx| Circuit   Pseudowire |Ingress  | Pseudowire   Circuit |
    <-----|                      |<--------|                      |
          +----------------------+         +----------------------+
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
                        <list>
			    <t> 
				A fault has occurred in the transmit direction between the
				local endpoint and the remote L2TP endpoint. 
                            </t>
                        </list>
                            </t>
                            <t>
                        <list>
                            <t>
			Note that a fault at the session level would not necessarily trigger an L2TP 
			control connection timeout. The means of detecting this fault are outside the 
			scope of this document; as an example,
			detection may be via PW Type-specific means,
			BFD, or other methods.
                            </t>
                        </list>
		    </t>
                    <t>
            <figure>
<preamble>
                    (S), Pseudowire is in Standby mode
</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[       
                                   Standby
                                     |
                                     |
          +----------------------+   |     +----------------------+
        Rx|         LCCE         |Egress   |       Peer LCCE      |
    ----->|                      |---X---->|                      |
          |             L2TPv3   |  [PSN]  |   L2TPv3             |
        Tx| Circuit   Pseudowire |Ingress  | Pseudowire   Circuit |
    <-----|                      |<--X-----|                      |
          +----------------------+   |     +----------------------+
                                     |
                                     |
                                   Standby
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
                        <list>
			    <t> 
  The pseudowire has been placed into a Standby mode, which means that
  although it was signaled (during setup of the PW) and is operational, it is
  NOT switching user traffic.

	 Any received user
		traffic SHOULD be dropped. User traffic MUST NOT be transmitted. 
                            </t>
                            <t>
A standby pseudowire also allows for means to check its data plane
liveness in order to ensure its ability to switch data packets end-to-end.
This is achieved, for example, as detailed in 
<xref target="RFC5085"/> or
<xref target="VCCV-BFD"/>.
However, data is not forwarded from an Attachment Circuit (AC) into the 
L2TPv3 session, or from the L2TPv3 session out to the AC.

                            </t>
                        </list>
		    </t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Circuit Status Usage and Clarifications" anchor="clarifications">
	    <t>
In implementations prior to this specification, bits 0-13 MUST be set to
zero (see Section 5.4.5 of <xref target="RFC3931"/>).
This allows for legacy implementations to interwork properly with new
implementations.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The following are clarifications regarding the usage
		of the Circuit Status AVP bits as defined in this
		specification:

<list style='symbols'>
		<t>
The (R), (T), (I), and (E) bits are collectively referred to as "fault status bits".
		</t>
		<t>
		  <xref target="RFC3931"/> defined the (A) bit as pertaining to local
		access circuit state only. This document redefines it as meaning that
		"no faults are present on the local pseudowire endpoint."
		</t>
		<t>
		  If multiple faults occur, all the fault status bits corresponding to each
fault MUST be set (i.e., they MUST be bitwise ORed together).
		</t>
		<t>
		  The (A) bit MUST NOT be set until all fault status bits are cleared. 
		This behavior allows an endpoint to be backwards compatible with a 
		remote endpoint that does not understand these new status bits. 
		</t>
		<t>
		  If any of the fault status bits are set, then the (A) bit 
		MUST be cleared. That is, the fault status bits (R, T,
		I, E) are a more granular definition of 
		(A), such that ORing the bits provides an inverted (A).
		</t>
		<t>
		  If (A) is clear and the fault status bits (R, T, I,
		  E) are clear, it means that there is no
		extended circuit status. That is, the circuit is
		  down/inactive/not-ready (from the (A) bit), without
		  a more granular (extended) indication.
		</t>
		<t>
		  The (S) bit can be set in conjunction with any other
		  bit, including (A).
   A pseudowire endpoint in Standby (S bit set) can be up/active/ready
   (A bit set) or experiencing a fault (A bit cleared and one or more
   of the fault status bits (R, T, I, E) set.

		</t>
		<t>
		  Leaving Standby mode is indicated by the clearing of the (S) bit.
		</t>
		<t>
		  The usage of the (N) bit has been deprecated.
		</t>
</list>
		</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Updates to Existing RFCs" anchor="updates">
            <t>
This document updates existing RFCs that define (either generically
or in the context of a specific set of PW Types) the Active and New bits
of the Circuit Status AVP.
The Active and New bits of the
Circuit Status AVP are specified in Section 5.4.5 of
<xref target="RFC3931"/>.
Those definitions are adapted to specific Attachment Circuits
and replicated in
Section 3.4 of <xref target="RFC4349"/> (High-Level Data Link Control Frames over L2TPv3),
Section 8 of <xref target="RFC4454"/> (Asynchronous Transfer Mode over L2TPv3),
Section 3.4 of <xref target="RFC4591"/> (Frame Relay over L2TPv3), and
Section 2.3.3 of <xref target="RFC4719"/> (Ethernet Frames over L2TPv3).
This document updates the definitions in all five of these references to say:

<list style="empty">
<t>
   The A (Active) bit indicates whether the local pseudowire endpoint
   (including the local Attachment Circuit and local PSN-facing pseudowire termination) has
   no faults present and is up/active/ready (1) or has faults present
   and is down/inactive/not-ready (0).

</t>
<t>
   The N (New) bit usage is deprecated; it SHOULD be ignored on
   receipt and is OPTIONAL to set on sending.  
</t>
</list>


This document also updates Section 2.2 (bullet c) of <xref target="RFC4719"/>,
removing the following two sentences:

<list style="empty"><t>
For ICRQ and ICRP, the Circuit Status AVP MUST indicate
      that the circuit status is for a new circuit (refer to N bit in
      Section 2.3.3).  
</t><t>
For ICCN and SLI (refer to Section 2.3.2), the
      Circuit Status AVP MUST indicate that the circuit status is for an
      existing circuit (refer to N bit in Section 2.3.3) and reflect the
      current status of the link (refer to A bit in Section 2.3.3).
</t></list>

And finally, this document updates Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC4349"/>,
Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC4454"/>, Section 3.1 of 
<xref target="RFC4591"/>, and Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC4719"/>
with the following paragraph addition:
<list style="empty"><t>
The usage of the N bit in the Circuit Status AVP 
is deprecated. Therefore, for ICRQ and ICRP,
the Circuit Status AVP need not indicate on sending (nor check on
receipt) that the circuit status is for a new circuit,
and for ICCN and SLI, the Circuit Status AVP need not indicate
on sending (nor check on receipt) that the circuit status is for an existing circuit.
</t></list>

</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec">
            <t>
Security considerations for the Circuit Status AVP are covered in  
the base L2TPv3 specification (see Section 8 of <xref target="RFC3931"/>).
No additional security considerations exist with extending this attribute.
</t>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
            <t>
The Circuit Status Bits number space 
<xref target="IANA-l2tp"/>
is managed by IANA as per Section 10.7 of <xref target="RFC3931"/>.
Five new bits (bits 9 through 13)
and one updated bit (bit 14) have been assigned as follows:

<figure>
<artwork>
Circuit Status Bits - per [RFC3931] 
-------------------

Bit  9 - S (Standby) bit
Bit 10 - E (Local PSN-facing PW (egress) Tx Fault) bit
Bit 11 - I (Local PSN-facing PW (ingress) Rx Fault) bit
Bit 12 - T (Local AC (egress) Tx Fault) bit
Bit 13 - R (Local AC (ingress) Rx Fault) bit
Bit 14 - N (New) bit [use deprecated]
</artwork>
</figure>

</t>
        </section>         
        <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks">
	    <t>The authors wish to thank Muhammad Yousuf, Mark Townsley, George Wilkie, Prashant Jhingran, Pawel Sowinski, and Ignacio Goyret
for useful comments received.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> &rfc2119; &rfc3931; &rfc4591; &rfc4349; &rfc4454; &rfc4719; </references>
        <references title="Informative References"> &rfc4446;
	  &rfc4447; &pwe3-vccv-bfd; &rfc5085;


<!-- draft-ietf-pwe3-vccv-bfd -->

	<reference anchor="VCCV-BFD">
	<front>
	<title>Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) for the Pseudowire Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV)</title>
	<author initials="T" surname="Nadeau" fullname="Thomas Nadeau">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="C" surname="Pignataro" fullname="Carlos Pignataro">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="July" day="12" year="2009"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-pwe3-redundancy-bit -->
	<reference anchor="PREF-FWD">
	<front>
<title>Preferential Forwarding Status bit definition</title>
	<author initials="P" surname="Muley" fullname="Praveen Muley">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="M" surname="Bocci" fullname="Matthew  Bocci">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="L" surname="Martini" fullname="Luca Martini">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="September" day="30" year="2008"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>

                <reference anchor='IANA-l2tp'
                   target='http://www.iana.org'>
                   <front>
                   <title>
                        Layer Two Tunneling Protocol 'L2TP'
                   </title>
                   <author
                        fullname=''>
                   <organization>
                        Internet Assigned Numbers Authority
                   </organization>
                   </author>
                   <date />
                   </front>
                </reference>


        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
