<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="5712" category="std">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS-TE Soft Preemption">MPLS Traffic
    Engineering Soft Preemption</title>

    <author fullname="Matthew R. Meyer" initials="M" role="editor"
            surname="Meyer">
      <organization>British Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <email>matthew.meyer@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="JP Vasseur" initials="JP" role="editor"
            surname="Vasseur">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>11, Rue Camille Desmoulins</street>

          <city>Issy Les Moulineaux</city>

          <code>92782</code>

          <region></region>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jpv@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2009" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

    <keyword>example</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Traffic
      Engineering Soft Preemption, a suite of protocol modifications extending
      the concept of preemption with the goal of reducing or eliminating traffic
      disruption of preempted Traffic Engineering Label Switched Paths (TE
      LSPs). Initially, MPLS RSVP-TE was defined with support for only immediate TE
      LSP displacement upon preemption. The utilization of a reroute request
      notification helps more gracefully mitigate the reroute process of
      preempted TE LSP. For the brief period soft preemption is activated,
      reservations (though not necessarily traffic levels) are in effect
      under-provisioned until the TE LSP(s) can be rerouted. For this reason,
      the feature is primarily, but not exclusively, interesting in MPLS-enabled
      IP networks with Differentiated Services and Traffic Engineering
      capabilities.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In a Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Resource Reservation
      Protocol Traffic Engineering (RSVP-TE) (see <xref
      target="RFC3209"></xref>) enabled IP network, hard preemption is the
      default behavior. Hard preemption provides no mechanism to allow
      preempted Traffic Engineering Label Switched Paths (TE LSPs) to be
      handled in a make-before-break fashion: the hard preemption scheme
      instead utilizes a very intrusive method that can cause traffic
      disruption for a potentially large amount of TE LSPs. Without an
      alternative, network operators either accept this limitation, or remove
      functionality by using only one preemption priority or using invalid
      bandwidth reservation values. 

      Understandably desirable features like TE reservation
      adjustments that are automated by the ingress Label Edge Router
      (LER) are less palatable when preemption is intrusive and maintaining high
      levels of network stability levels is a concern.
</t>

      <t>This document defines the use of additional signaling and maintenance
      mechanisms to alert the ingress LER of the preemption that is pending
      and allow for temporary control-plane under-provisioning while the
      preempted tunnel is rerouted in a non-disruptive fashion
      (make-before-break) by the ingress LER. During the period that the
      tunnel is being rerouted, link capacity is under-provisioned on the
      midpoint where preemption initiated and potentially one or more links
      upstream along the path where other soft preemptions may have
      occurred.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document follows the nomenclature of the MPLS Architecture
      defined in <xref target="RFC3031"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Acronyms and Abbreviations">
        <t>CSPF: Constrained Shortest Path First.</t>

        <t>DS: Differentiated Services.</t>

        <t>LER: Label Edge Router.</t>

        <t>LSR: Label Switching Router.</t>

        <t>LSP: Label Switched Path.</t>

        <t>MPLS: MultiProtocol Label Switching.</t>

        <t>RSVP: Resource ReSerVation Protocol.</t>

        <t>TE LSP: Traffic Engineering Label Switched Path.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Nomenclature">
        <t>Point of Preemption - the midpoint or ingress LSR which due to RSVP
        provisioning levels is forced to either hard preempt or
        under-provision and signal soft preemption.</t>

        <t>Hard Preemption - The (typically default) preemption process in
        which higher numeric priority TE LSPs are intrusively displaced at the
        point of preemption by lower numeric priority TE LSPs. In hard
        preemption, the TE LSP is torn down before reestablishment.</t>
      </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Motivations">
      <t>Initially, MPLS RSVP-TE <xref
      target="RFC3209"></xref> was defined with support for only one method of TE
      LSP preemption, which immediately tears down TE LSPs, disregarding the
      preempted in-transit traffic. This simple but abrupt process nearly
      guarantees preempted traffic will be discarded, if only briefly, until
      the RSVP Path Error message reaches and is processed by the ingress LER
      and a new data path can be established. The Error Code and Error Values
      carried within the RSVP Path Error message to report a preemption action
      are documented in <xref target="RFC5711"></xref>.
      Note that such preemption is also referred to as a fatal error in <xref
      target="RFC5711"></xref>. In cases of actual resource
      contention this might be helpful; however, preemption may be triggered by
      mere reservation contention, and reservations may not reflect data-plane
      contention up to the moment. The result is that when conditions that
      promote preemption exist and hard preemption is the default behavior,
      inferior priority preempted traffic may be needlessly discarded when
      sufficient bandwidth exists for both the preempted TE LSP and the preempting TE LSP(s).</t>

      <t>Hard preemption may be a requirement to protect numerically lower
      preemption priority traffic in a non-Diffserv-enabled architecture, but
      in a Diffserv-enabled-architecture, one need not rely exclusively upon
      preemption to enforce a preference for the most valued traffic since the
      marking and queuing disciplines should already be aligned for those
      purposes. Moreover, even in non-Diffserv-aware networks, depending on
      the TE LSP sizing rules (imagine all LSPs are sized at double their
      observed traffic level), reservation contention may not accurately
      reflect the potential for data-plane congestion.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="RSVP Extensions">
      <t></t>

      <section title="SESSION-ATTRIBUTE Flags">
        <t>To explicitly signal the desire for a TE LSP to benefit from the
        soft preemption mechanism (and thus not to be hard preempted if the soft
        preemption mechanism is available), the following flag of the
        SESSION-ATTRIBUTE object (for both the C-Type 1 and 7) is defined:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <preamble>Soft Preemption Desired bit</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[
Bit Flag  Name Flag                                
  0x40    Soft Preemption Desired      
            ]]></artwork>

            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Path Error - &quot;Reroute Request Soft Preemption&quot; Error Value">
        <t><xref target="RFC5710"></xref> specifies
        defines a new reroute-specific error code that allows a midpoint to
        report a TE LSP reroute request (Error Code=34 - Reroute). This
        document specifies a new Error Value sub-code for the case of soft
        preemption.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Error-value               Meaning                    Reference
  1            Reroute Request Soft Preemption     This document     
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Upon (soft) preemption, the preempting node MUST issue a PathErr
        message with the Error Code=34 ("Reroute") and a value=1 ("Reroute
        Request Soft Preemption").</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Mode of Operation">
      <t>Let's consider the following example:</t>

      <t><figure title="Example of Soft Preemption Operation" anchor="fig_soft">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
              
 R0--1G--R1---155----R2        
          | \         |
          |   \      155        
          |    \      |         
         155   1G     R3        
          |       \   |         
          |        \ 155
          |          \|
          R4----1G----R5

      
          LSP1:        LSP2:
         
          R0-->R1      R1<--R2
                \      |
                V      V    
                R5     R4
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

	In the network depicted above in <xref target="fig_soft"/>, consider the
      following conditions:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Reservable BW on R0-R1, R1-R5, and R4-R5 is 1 Gbit/s.</t>

          <t>Reservable BW on R1-R2, R1-R4, R2-R3, and R3-R5 is 155 Mbit/s.</t>

          <t>Bandwidths and costs are identical in both directions.</t>

          <t>Each circuit has an IGP metric of 10, and the IGP metric is used by
          CSPF.</t>

          <t>Two TE tunnels are defined: 
	    <list>
	      <t>
		LSP1: 155 Mbit/s, setup/hold priority 0 tunnel, path
		R0-R1-R5.
	      </t>

	      <t>
		LSP2: 155 Mbit/s, setup/hold priority 7 tunnel, path R2-R1-R4. 
	      </t>

	    </list>
	    Both TE LSPs are signaled with the "Soft Preemption
            Desired" bit of their SESSION-ATTRIBUTE object set.</t>

          <t>Circuit R1-R5 fails.</t>

          <t>Soft Preemption is functional.</t>
        </list>When the circuit R1-R5 fails, R1 detects the failure and sends
      an updated IGP LSA/LSP and Path Error message to all the head-end LSRs
      that have a TE LSP traversing the failed link (R0 in the example above).
      Either form of notification may arrive at the head-end LSRs first. Upon
      receiving the link failure notification, R0 triggers a TE LSP reroute
      of LSP1, and re-signals LSP1 along shortest path available satisfying
      the TE LSP constraints: R0-R1-R4-R5 path. The Resv messages for LSP1
      travel in the upstream direction (from the destination to the head-end
      LSR -- R5 to R0 in this example). LSP2 is soft preempted at R1 as it has
      a numerically lower priority value, and both bandwidth reservations
      cannot be satisfied on the R1-R4 link.</t>

      <t>Instead of sending a PathTear message for LSP2 upon
      preemption as with hard preemption (which would result in an
      immediate traffic disruption for LSP2), R1's local bandwidth
      accounting for LSP2 is zeroed, and a PathErr message with error
      code "Reroute" and a value "Reroute Request Soft Preemption" for
      LSP2 is issued.</t>

      <t>Upon reception of the PathErr message for LSP2, R2 may update the
      working copy of the TE-DB before calculating a new path for the
      new LSP. In the case that Diffserv <xref target="RFC3270"></xref> and
      TE <xref target="RFC3209"></xref> are deployed, receiving a "preemption
      pending" notification may imply to a head-end LSR that the available
      bandwidth for the affected priority level and numerically greater
      priority levels has been exhausted for the indicated node interface. R2
      may choose to reduce or zero the available bandwidth for the implied
      priority range until more accurate information is available (i.e., a new
      IGP TE update is received). It follows that R2 re-computes a new path
      and performs a non-traffic-disruptive rerouting of the new TE LSP T2 by
      means of the make-before-break procedure. The old path is then torn
      down.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Elements Of Procedures">
      <t></t>

      <section title="On a Soft Preempting LSR" anchor="on_a_soft">
        <t>When a new TE LSP is signaled that requires a set of TE
        LSP(s) to be preempted because not all TE LSPs can be accommodated on a specific
        interface, a node triggers a preemption action that consists of
        selecting the set of TE LSPs that must be preempted so as to free up
        some bandwidth in order to satisfy the newly signaled numerically
        lower preemption TE LSP.</t>

        <t>With hard preemption, when a TE LSP is preempted, the preempting
        node sends an RSVP PathErr message that serves as notification
        of a fatal action as
        documented in <xref target="RFC5711"></xref>. Upon
        receiving the RSVP PathErr message, the head-end LSR sends an RSVP
        PathTear message, that would result in an immediate traffic
        disruption for the preempted TE LSP. By contrast, the mode of
        operation with soft preemption is as follows: the preempting node's
        local bandwidth accounting for the preempted TE LSP is zeroed and a
        PathErr with error code "Reroute", and a error value "Reroute Request
        Soft Preemption" for that TE LSP is issued upstream toward the
        head-end LSR.</t>

        <t>If more than one soft preempted TE LSP has the same head-end LSR,
        these soft preemption PathErr notification messages may be bundled
        together.</t>

        <t>The preempting node MUST immediately send a PathErr with error code
        "Reroute" and a error value "Reroute Request Soft Preemption" for each
        soft preempted TE LSP. The node MAY use the occurrence of soft
        preemption to trigger an immediate IGP update or influence the
        scheduling of an IGP update.</t>

        <t>To guard against a situation where bandwidth under-provisioning
        will last forever, a local timer (named the "Soft preemption timer")
        MUST be started on the preemption node upon soft preemption. If this
        timer expires, the preempting node SHOULD send an RSVP PathTear and
        either a ResvTear message or a PathErr with the 'Path_State_Removed'
        flag set.</t>

        <t>Should a refresh event for a soft preempted TE LSP arrive before
        the soft preemption timer expires, the soft preempting node MUST
        continue to refresh the TE LSP.</t>

        <t>When the MESSAGE-ID extensions defined in <xref
        target="RFC2961"></xref> are available and enabled, PathErr messages
        with the error code "Reroute" and error value "Reroute Request Soft
        Preemption" SHOULD be sent in reliable mode.</t>

        <t>The preempting node MAY preempt TE LSPs that have a numerically
        higher Holding priority than the Setup priority of the newly admitted
        LSP. Within the same priority, first it SHOULD attempt to preempt LSPs with
        the "Soft Preemption Desired" bit of the SESSION ATTRIBUTE object
        cleared, i.e., the TE LSPs that are considered as Hard Preemptable.</t>

        <t>
   Selection of the preempted TE LSP at a preempting midpoint: when a
   numerically lower priority TE LSP is signaled that requires the
   preemption of a set of numerically higher priority LSPs, the node
   where preemption is to occur has to make a decision on the set of TE
   LSP(s) that are candidates for preemption. 

This decision is a local decision
        and various algorithms can be used, depending on the objective (e.g,
        see <xref target="RFC4829"></xref>). As already mentioned, soft
        preemption causes a temporary link under-provisioning condition while
        the soft preempted TE LSPs are rerouted by their respective head-end
        LSRs. In order to reduce this under-provisioning exposure, a
        soft preempting LSR MAY check first if there exists soft preemptable
        TE LSP bandwidth that is flagged by another node but still available for
        soft preemption locally. If sufficient overlap bandwidth exists, the
        LSR MAY attempt to soft preempt the same TE LSP. This would help
        reduce the temporarily elevated under-provisioning ratio on the
        links where soft preemption occurs and reduce the number of preempted TE
        LSPs. Optionally, a midpoint LSR upstream or downstream from a soft
        preempting node MAY choose to flag the TE LSPs in soft preempted
        state.

        In the event a local preemption is needed, the LSPs that are
        in the cache and of the relevant priority level
        are soft preempted first, followed by the normal
        soft and hard preemption selection process for the given priority.</t>

        <t>Under specific circumstances such as unacceptable link congestion,
        a node MAY decide to hard preempt a TE LSP (by sending a fatal Path
        Error message, a PathTear, and either a ResvTear or a Path Error
        message with the 'Path_State_Removed' flag set) even if its head-end
        LSR explicitly requested soft preemption (by setting the "Soft Preemption Desired"
        flag of the corresponding SESSION-ATTRIBUTE object). Note that
        such a decision MAY also be made for TE LSPs under soft preemption
        state.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="On Head-end LSR of a Soft Preempted TE LSP">
        <t>Upon reception of a PathErr message with error code "Reroute" and
        an error value "Reroute request soft preemption", the head-end LSR MAY
        first update the working copy of the TE-DB before computing a new path
        (e.g., by running CSPF) for the new LSP. In the case that Diffserv
        <xref target="RFC3270"></xref> and MPLS Traffic Engineering <xref
        target="RFC3209"></xref> are deployed, receiving "preemption pending"
        may imply to a head-end LSR that the available bandwidth for the
        affected priority level and numerically greater priority levels has
        been exhausted for the indicated node interface. A head-end LSR MAY
        choose to reduce or zero the available bandwidth for the implied priority
        range until more accurate information is available (i.e., a new IGP TE
        update is received).</t>

        <t>Once a new path has been computed, the soft preempted TE LSP is
        rerouted using the non-traffic-disruptive make-before-break procedure.
        The amount of time the head-end node avoids using the node interface
        identified by the IP address contained in the PathErr is based on a
        local decision at the head-end node.</t>

        <t>As a result of soft preemption, no traffic will be needlessly black-holed due to mere reservation contention. If loss is to occur, it will
        be due only to an actual traffic congestion scenario and according to
        the operator's Diffserv (if Diffserv is deployed) and queuing
        scheme.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Interoperability">
      <t>Backward compatibility should be assured as long as the
      implementation followed the recommendations set forth in <xref
      target="RFC3209"></xref>.</t>

      <t>As mentioned previously, to guard against a situation where bandwidth
      under-provisioning will last forever, a local timer (soft preemption
      timer) MUST be started on the preemption node upon soft preemption.
      When this timer expires, the soft preempted TE LSP SHOULD be hard
      preempted by sending a fatal Path Error message, a PathTear message, and
      either a ResvTear message or a PathErr message with the
      'Path_State_Removed' flag set. This timer SHOULD be configurable, and a
      default value of 30 seconds is RECOMMENDED.</t>

      <t>It is RECOMMENDED that configuring the default preemption timer to 0
      will cause the implementation to use hard-preemption.</t>

      <t>Soft preemption as defined in this document is designed for use in
      MPLS RSVP-TE enabled IP networks and may not functionally translate to
      some GMPLS technologies. As with backward compatibility, if a device
      does not recognize a flag, it should pass the subobject
      transparently.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Management">
      <t>Both the point of preemption and the ingress LER SHOULD provide some
      form of accounting internally and to the network operator interface with
      regard to which TE LSPs and how much capacity is under-provisioned due
      to soft preemption. Displays of under-provisioning are recommended for
      the following midpoint, ingress, and egress views: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Sum of current bandwidth per preemption priority per local
          interface</t>

          <t>Sum of current bandwidth total per local interface</t>

          <t>Sum of current bandwidth per local router (ingress, egress,
          midpoint)</t>

          <t>List of current LSPs and bandwidth in PPend (preemption pending) status</t>

          <t>List of current sum bandwidth and session count in PPend status per
          observed Explicit Route Object (ERO) hops (ingress and egress views only).</t>

          <t>Cumulative PPend events per observed ERO hop.</t>

        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <section title="New Session Attribute Object Flag">
        <t>A new flag of the Session Attribute Object has been registered by IANA.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <preamble>Soft Preemption Desired bit</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[
Bit Flag       Name                           Reference           
  0x40    Soft Preemption Desired             This document
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="New Error Sub-Code Value">
        <t><xref target="RFC5710"></xref> defines a
        new reroute-specific error code that allows a midpoint to report a TE
        LSP reroute request. This document specifies a new error sub-code
        value for the case of Soft Preemption.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Error-value               Meaning                    Reference
  1            Reroute Request Soft Preemption     This document     
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   This document does not introduce new security issues.  The security
   considerations pertaining to the original RSVP protocol <xref target="RFC3209"/>
   remain relevant. Further details about MPLS security considerations
   can be found in <xref target="SEC_FMWK"/>.
</t>
<t>
   As noted in <xref target="on_a_soft"/>, soft preemption may result in temporary link
   under provisioning condition while the soft preempted TE LSPs are
   rerouted by their respective head-end LSRs. Although this is a less
   serious condition than false hard preemption, and despite the
   mitigation procedures described in <xref target="on_a_soft"/>, network operators
   should be aware of the risk to their network in the case that the soft
   preemption processes are subverted, and should apply the relevant MPLS
   control plane security techniques to protect against attacks.
</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Carol Iturralde, Dave Cooper, Loa
      Andersson, Arthi Ayyangar, Ina Minei, George Swallow, Adrian Farrel, and
      Mustapha Aissaoui for their valuable comments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  Denver Maddux
  Limelight Networks
  USA
  EMail: denver@nitrous.net

  Curtis Villamizar
  AVICI
  EMail:curtis@faster-light.net

  Amir Birjandi
  Juniper Networks
  2251 Corporate Park Dr., Ste. 100
  Herndon, VA 20171
  USA
  EMail: abirjandi@juniper.net]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3209'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3031'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-mpls-gmpls-lsp-reroute in AUTH48, assigned 5710 -->

<reference anchor='RFC5710'>
<front>
<title>PathErr Message Triggered MPLS and GMPLS LSP Reroute</title>

<author initials='L' surname='Berger' fullname='Lou Berger'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Papadimitriou' fullname='Dimitri  Papadimitriou'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Vasseur' fullname='JP Vasseur'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5710'/>
</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-mpls-3209-patherr-06 -->

      <reference anchor='RFC5711'>
<front>
<title>Node Behavior upon Originating and Receiving Resource Reservation Protocol (RSVP) Path Error Message</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Vasseur' fullname='JP Vasseur'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Swallow' fullname='George Swallow'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='I' surname='Minei' fullname='Ina Minei'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5711'/>

</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2961'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3270'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4829'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-mpls-mpls-and-gmpls-security-framework -->

<reference anchor='SEC_FMWK'>
<front>
<title>Security Framework for MPLS and GMPLS Networks</title>

<author initials='L' surname='Fang' fullname='Luyuan Fang' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='25' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Work" value="in Progress"/>

</reference>


    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
