<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
  <?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="no"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2865 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2866 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2866.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2867 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2867.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2977 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2977.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3344 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3344.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3957 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3957.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4004 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4004.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4721 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4721.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4962 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4962.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2868 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2868.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2869 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2869.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3576 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3576.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3579 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3580 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3580.xml'>
]>

<rfc number="5030" category="info" >  
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Mobile IP4 RADIUS Requirements">Mobile IPv4 RADIUS Requirements</title>

    <author fullname="Madjid Nakhjiri" initials="M.N." role="editor"
            surname="Nakhjiri">
      <organization>Motorola</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>

        </postal>

        <email>madjid.nakhjiri@motorola.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kuntal Chowdhury" initials="K.C." surname="Chowdhury">
      <organization>Starent Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <email>kchowdhury@starentnetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Avi Lior" initials="A.L." surname="Lior">
      <organization>Bridgewater Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>avi@bridgewatersystems.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kent Leung" initials="K.L." surname="Leung">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
        <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city> 
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kleung@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2007" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides an applicability statement as well as a scope
      definition for specifying Remote Authentication Dial-In User
Service (RADIUS) extensions to support Mobile IPv4. The goal is to
      allow specification of RADIUS attributes to assist the Mobile IPv4 signaling procedures.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>To kick start the Mobile IPv4 <xref target="RFC3344"></xref>
processing of its packets by Mobile IP agents, a mobile node (MN)
needs to be able to acquire a pair of home and care of addresses (HoA
and CoA, respectively), find a willing agent to act as a Home Agent
(HA) for the MN and perform a registration process with the HA. The
registration process consists of an exchange of a registration request
and a registration reply message between the MN and the HA. The specification in
<xref target="RFC3344"></xref> allows an MN to start the registration
process prior to having acquired its home address or the address of
its HA. Acquiring those parameters by the MN is typically part of a
process referred to as bootstrapping. </t> 
      
      <t> Successful processing of registration request and reply messages, among
other things, depends on successful creation and verification of a
number of authentication extensions developed specifically to protect
the integrity and security of these messages and the entities
processing them, i.e., MN, HA and some times, Foreign Agents (FAs)
<xref target="RFC3344"></xref>. Creation as well
as verification of these extensions requires existence of trust
relationships and shared keys between MN and each of the mobility
agents. However, creation of these trust relationships, typically
referred to as mobility security associations (MSAs), is considered
outside the scope of the base Mobile IPv4 specification defined in
<xref target="RFC3344"></xref>. 
Avoiding the scalability issues arising from
creating static security associations between an MN and all possible
mobility agents is desired.  Thus, establishing the associations
dynamically, using the pre-existing relationship between the MN and
the AAA server, is preferred.</t>
      
      <t>To allow for utilization of an existing AAA infrastructure in
the bootstrapping of the Mobile IPv4 parameters and security
relationships, the Mobile IPv4 working group has developed Mobile
IPv4 extensions to allow the MN to authenticate to the home AAA server
<xref target="RFC4721"></xref>. The extensions also allow the MN to request assistance from
the AAA server in creation of mobility security associations <xref target="RFC3957"></xref>
with the mobility agents, using the pre-established trust relationship
between the MN and its home AAA server.</t>

      <t>While Mobile IPv4 extensions are necessary for implementing a
utilization of the AAA infrastructure for Mobile IPv4 purposes, they
are not sufficient. The interaction between the MN and the mobility agents (HA and FA) is
based on Mobile IP signaling. However, the signaling beyond the mobility
agents to the AAA server is typically based on AAA protocols. Around
the time, when the specification of the aforementioned Mobile IP
extensions was being developed, the AAA community
was in the process of designing a successor to RADIUS.
Thus, the Mobile IP group developed a set of guidelines and
requirements from the Mobile IP standpoint <xref
target="RFC2977"></xref> specifically for
such a successor (which turned out to be Diameter). These requirements led
to the development of a specification for using Diameter in Mobile IPv4 bootstrapping <xref
        target="RFC4004"></xref>. The requirements for Mobile IP
Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting <xref
target="RFC2977"></xref> were standardized after the standardization of RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"></xref>.</t>.

      <t>Thus, it is obvious that RADIUS does not and cannot meet all
the requirements listed in <xref target="RFC2977"></xref> without undergoing an extensive
design change. Consequently, within IETF no RADIUS attributes have
been standardized for Mobile IP support thus far. However, in the absence of IETF
standardized RADIUS attributes, different wireless
SDOs have taken the path of developing Vendor Specific Attributes
(VSAs) for providing Mobile IPv4 support. The use of different vendor
specific RADIUS attributes and procedures for the same purpose of Mobile IPv4 bootstrapping at
different SDOs is deemed to cause a lack interoperability between these
wireless standards, potentially hindering mobility across these
wireless networks.</t>

      <t>To respond to the described issue, it is desired to standardize a
      set of RADIUS attributes within IETF to allow a consistent and interoperable interaction with RADIUS based AAA infrastructure during the Mobile
      IPv4 Registration procedure. The bootstrapping attributes can include
      configuration parameters as well as material used for provisioning
        security of Mobile IPv4 messaging (authentication) as defined by <xref target="RFC4721"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC3957"></xref>.</t>
      
      <t>As it stands today, RADIUS cannot meet all the requirements
in <xref target="RFC2977"></xref>. The purpose of these requirements is
to define a set of goals and non-goals specifically for RADIUS
when it comes to assisting mobile nodes and mobility agents in
bootstrapping Mobile IPv4 operation. </t> 
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
        NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Goals and Non-Goals">
      <t>Since this document serves as a requirement specification for
RADIUS extensions that support Mobile IPv4 interaction with RADIUS infrastructure, the goals and non-goals refer to only those RADIUS extensions that are required to support Mobile IPv4.</t>
 
      <section title="Goals">
        <t>The scope of the work is to standardize RADIUS attributes and
        to define the procedure by which the Mobile IPv4 agents (e.g., Home agent
        (HA) and Foreign Agent (FA)) map the Mobile IP registration message
        fields into the proposed RADIUS attributes, and vice versa. </t>
        
        <list style='symbols'>
      <t>RADIUS servers are REQUIRED
        to be able to understand and process the attributes to be defined for Mobile IPv4 support and to perform verification of authentication extensions
        specified in <xref target="RFC4721"></xref>. RADIUS proxies are expected to be able to forward messages including the Mobile IPv4 related attributes as they would with any other RADIUS messages and attributes.</t>
      
      <t>All RADIUS work MUST be backward compatible with existing RADIUS
        RFCs, including RFCs the following: <xref target="RFC2865"></xref>, <xref target="RFC2866"></xref>, <xref target="RFC2867"></xref>, <xref target="RFC2868"></xref>, <xref target="RFC2869"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3576"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3579"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC3580"></xref>.</t>
      
      <t>Mobile IP agents (FA and HA) are REQUIRED to operate as
        RADIUS clients (NASes in context of <xref target="RFC2865"></xref>) when translating RADIUS
        signaling into Mobile IP signaling, and vice versa. Details on the
        behavior of Mobile IP agents as RADIUS clients are to be provided by the solution document describing the RADIUS extensions for Mobile IP support.</t>
        </list>
        
      </section>
      <section title="Non-Goals">
        
      <t>The scope of this work is to only standardize RADIUS attributes and
      to define the procedure by which the Mobile IPv4 agents (e.g., Home agent
      (HA) and Foreign Agent (FA)) map the Mobile IP registration message
      fields into the proposed RADIUS attributes, and vice
versa. Extension of the functionality of the existing protocol or RADIUS servers
      is not intended. More specifically, the following are NON-GOALS:</t>
<list style='symbols'>
      <t>Enhancing RADIUS Security: Creating new security properties for RADIUS, such as
      creating key transport capabilities is not the goal. No new security
      mechanisms are to be defined for the transport of RADIUS Access
Requests in relation to the support of Mobile IPv4 bootstrapping. Existing RADIUS
      authentication procedures, e.g., Message-Authenticator (80) described in
        <xref target="RFC2869"></xref>, are used. The security considerations for using RADIUS in bootstrapping Mobile IPv4 are described in a later
      section of this document.</t>

      <t >Enhancing RADIUS transport reliability: The transport properties
      of RADIUS remain intact. No new reliability mechanisms are defined in
      the transport of such Access Requests.</t>

      <t>Extending RADIUS message set: RADIUS extensions for bootstrapping Mobile IPv4 are not to
      define new RADIUS messages. The Diameter Mobile IP application <xref
      target="RFC4004"></xref> has defined new command codes to support
      Mobile IP signaling, depending on whether Diameter server is dealing
      with a Mobile IP HA or an FA. RADIUS currently does not have any
      messages that correspond to these Diameter commands. Instead, RADIUS extensions for Mobile IPv4 bootstrapping need to provide proposals for new
      RADIUS attributes that facilitate Diameter-RADIUS messaging translation
      without defining any new RADIUS messaging. At the same time, the RADIUS extensions for Mobile IPv4 need to re-use Diameter AVPs to
      the fullest extent possible.</t>

      <t>RFC 2977 compatibility: Extending RADIUS in a way that fulfills
        the full list of requirements in <xref target="RFC2977"></xref> will not be attempted.</t>
</list>
      </section>
      
    </section>
      <section title="Attributes">

      <t>A specification of the RADIUS extensions for Mobile IPv4 needs to describe the full set
      of attributes required for RADIUS-Mobile IP interaction. While some of the
      attributes may already be standardized, others will require
      standardization and IANA type assignments.</t>

</section>
      <section title="IANA Considerations">
        
        <t>This requirement document does not allocate any numbers, so
there are no IANA considerations. On the other hand, future solution documents for RADIUS support of Mobile IPv4 will likely introduce new
      RADIUS attributes. Thus, those documents will need new attribute type numbers assigned by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Enhancing security properties of RADIUS are a specific
non-goal for the RADIUS extensions providing support for Mobile
IP. Also, as this is a requirements document and not a solution
specification document, no new security considerations are noted,
aside from those that already exist for RADIUS. As such, the existing
RADIUS security considerations described previously apply, and no
additional security considerations are added here. For instance, the
assumption in RADIUS is that intermediary nodes are trusted, while at
the same time there is a concern on using AAA protocols that use
hop-by-hop security to distribute keys. Use of hop-by-hop security for
key distribution can be in conflict with some of the requirements
stated in <xref target="RFC4962"></xref>, such as the requirement on
binding a key to its context and the requirement on limitation of the
key scope. The former for instance states that a key MUST be bound to
the parties that are expected to have access to the keying material,
while the latter implies that parties that do not require access to a
key to perform their role MUST not have access to the key. Both of
these requirements rule against trusting intermediary nodes and
proxies with distribution of keys. Due to lack of end-to-end security
mechanisms for RADIUS, imposing a MUST requirement for not trusting
proxies is not possible. The RADIUS Extension working group is in the process of specifying procedures for wrapping key materials within RADIUS attributes. For the time being, support of Mobile IP within RADIUS may need to be based on trust of intermediaries, despite the security considerations described.</t>
      
      <t>When it comes to protecting attributes in the Access Request, <xref target="RFC2868"></xref>, Section 3.5 provides a
      mechanism for encrypting RADIUS attributes, such as passwords. There is also work under progress for specifying wrapping of sensitive attributes, such as key material within RADIUS Access Accept messages. This work is currently considered part of RADIUS crypto-agility extensions and when completed can be used in the process of distributing sensitive attributes, such as keying material from RADIUS servers. </t>

      <t> It is also possible to protect RADIUS transactions using IPsec (e.g., as in RFC3579).</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title='Acknowledgements'>
      <t> The authors would like to thank Alan DeKok for review and
feedback, and Pete McCann and Jari Arkko for diligent shepherding of this document. </t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
 
&rfc2119;
&rfc2865;
&rfc2866;
&rfc2867;
&rfc2977;
&rfc3344;
&rfc3957;
&rfc4004;
&rfc4721;
&rfc4962;
      
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">

&rfc2868;
&rfc2869;
&rfc3576;
&rfc3579;
&rfc3580;

      </references>
  </back>
</rfc>