<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc number="5185" category="std">

<front>
<title>OSPF Multi-Area Adjacency</title>
  <author initials='S' surname="Mirtorabi" fullname='Sina Mirtorabi'>
    <organization>Nuova Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal> 
        <street>3 West Plumeria Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region> 
        <country>USA</country>
        <code>95134</code> 
      </postal> 
      <email>sina@nuovasystems.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author  initials='P' surname="Psenak" fullname='Peter Psenak'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal> 
        <street>Apollo Business Center</street>
        <street>Mlynske nivy 43</street>
        <city>821 09 Bratislava</city> <region>Sovakia</region>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </postal>
      <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem' role="editor">
    <organization>Redback Networks</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>102 Carric Bend Court</street>
        <city>Cary</city> <region>NC</region> 
        <country>USA</country>
        <code>27519</code> 
       </postal>
       <email>acee@redback.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='A' surname="Oswal" fullname='Anand Oswal'>
    <organization>Redback Networks</organization>
    <address>
      <postal> 
        <street>300 Holger Way</street>
        <city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region> 
        <country>USA</country>
        <code>95134</code> 
      </postal> 
      <email>aoswal@redback.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <date month="May" year="2008"/>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfceditor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

  <abstract><t>This document describes an extension to the Open Shortest Path First (OSPF) 
     protocol to allow a single physical link to be shared by
     multiple areas.  This is necessary to allow the link to be considered an intra-area
     link in multiple areas. This would create an intra-area path in each of the
     corresponding areas sharing the same link.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<section title="Motivation">
  <t>It is often a requirement to have an Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)
     <xref target="OSPF"/> link in multiple areas. This will allow the link
     to be considered as an intra-area path in each area and be preferred
     over higher cost links. A simple example of this requirement is to use a high-speed link
     between two Area Border Routers (ABRs)in multiple areas.</t>
   <t>Consider the following topology:
   <figure title="Multi-Link Topology">
     <artwork>

                       R1-------Backbone------R2
                        |                      |
                      Area 1                 Area 1
                        |                      |
                       R3--------Area 1--------R4

     </artwork> 
  </figure></t>
   <t>The backbone area link between R1 and R2 is a high-speed link, and it is 
      desirable to forward Area 1's traffic between R1 and R2 over that link.
      In the current OSPF specification [OSPF], intra-area paths are preferred 
      over inter-area paths.  As a result, R1 will always route traffic 
      to R4 through Area 1 over the lower speed links.  R1 will even use the 
      intra-area Area 1 path though R3 to get to Area 1 networks 
      connected to R2.  An OSPF virtual link cannot be used to solve this problem
      without moving the link between R1 and R2 to Area 1.  This is not desirable 
      if the physical link is, in fact, part of the network's backbone topology.</t>

   <t>The protocol extension described herein will rectify this problem by allowing
      the link between R1 and R2 to be part of both the backbone area and Area 1.</t> 
 </section>

<section title="Possible Solutions">
  <t>For numbered interfaces, the OSPF (Open Shortest Path First)
      specification <xref target="OSPF"/> allows a 
      separate OSPF interface to be configured in each area using a 
      secondary address. The disadvantages of this approach are that 
      it requires additional IP address configuration, it doesn't apply to
      unnumbered interfaces, and advertising secondary addresses will
      result in a larger overall routing table.</t>

   <t>Allowing a link with a single address to simply be configured in 
      multiple areas would also solve the problem. However, this would 
      result in the subnet corresponding to the interface residing in 
      multiple areas that is contrary to the definition of an OSPF 
      area as a collection of subnets.</t>  

    <t>Another approach is to simply allow unnumbered links to be 
       configured in multiple areas. Section 8.2. of the OSPF 
       specification  [OSPF] already specifies that the OSPF area ID should
       be used to de-multiplex received OSPF packets. One limitation
       of this approach is that multi-access networks are not supported.
       Although this limitation may be overcome for LAN media with 
       support of "Point-to-Point operation over LAN in link-state 
       routing protocols" <xref target="P2PLAN"/>, it may not be acceptable to 
       configure the link as unnumbered due to network management policies. 
       Many popular network management applications individually test the
       path to each interface by pinging its IP address.</t> 
</section>

<section title="Proposed Solution">
    <t>ABRs will simply establish multiple adjacencies belonging to different 
       areas. Each multi-area adjacency is announced as a point-to-point 
       link in the configured area. However, unlike numbered point-to-point links, 
       no type 3 link is advertised for multi-area adjacencies. This 
       point-to-point link will provide a topological path for that area.
       The first or primary 
       adjacency using the link will operate and advertise the link 
       in a manner consistent with RFC 2328 <xref target="OSPF"/>.</t>
</section>
<section title="Requirements Notation">

   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
       and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
       described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC-KEYWORDS"/>.</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="Functional Specifications">
<section title="Multi-Area Adjacency Configuration and Neighbor Discovery">
   <t>Multi-area adjacencies are configured between two routers having a
      common interface. On point-to-point interfaces, there is no
      need to configure the neighbor's address since there can be only
      one neighbor. For all other network types, the neighbor address of each
      multi-area adjacency must be configured or automatically discovered
      via a mechanism external to OSPF.</t>
</section>

<section title="Multi-Area Adjacency Packet Transmission">
   <t>On point-to-point interfaces, OSPF control packets are
     sent to the AllSPFRouters address.  For all other network types,
     OSPF control packets are unicast to the remote neighbor's IP address.</t>
</section>

<section title="Multi-Area Adjacency Control Packet Reception Changes">
   <t>Receiving protocol packets is described in Section 8.2 of <xref target="OSPF"/>.
      The text starting with the second paragraph and continuing through the third
      bullet beneath that paragraph is changed as follows:</t>
   <t>Next, the OSPF packet header is verified. The fields specified in
      the header must match those configured for the receiving interface.
      If they do not, the packet should be discarded:
      <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>The version number field must specify protocol version 2.</t>
      <t>The Area ID found in the OSPF header must be verified. If all of
         the following cases fail, the packet should be discarded.
         The Area ID specified in the header must either:
         <list style="numbers"> 
           <t>Match the Area ID of the receiving interface. In this case,
              the packet has been sent over a single hop. Therefore,
              the packet's IP source address is required to be on the
              same network as the receiving interface. This can be verified
              by comparing the packet's IP source address to the interface's
              IP address, after masking both addresses with the interface
	      mask. This comparison should not be performed on
	      point-to-point networks. On point-to-point networks, the
	      interface addresses of each end of the link are assigned
	      independently, if they are assigned at all.</t>
          <t>Indicate a non-backbone area. In this case, the packet has
             been sent over a multi-area adjacency. If the area-id matches
             the configured area for a multi-area adjacency, the packet is 
             accepted and is from now on associated with the multi-area
            adjacency for that area.</t>
         <t>Indicate the backbone. In this case, the packet has been sent
            over a virtual link or a multi-area adjacency.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>For virtual links, the receiving router must be an ABR, 
           and the Router ID specified in the packet (the source router) must be
           the other end of a configured virtual link. The receiving
           interface must also attach to the virtual link's configured 
 	   transit area. If all of these checks succeed, the packet is
           accepted and is from now on associated with the virtual link.</t>

         <t>For multi-area adjacencies, if the area-id matches the configured 
            area for the multi-area adjacency, the packet is accepted and is 
            from now on associated with the multi-area adjacency for that area.</t>

          <t>Note that if there is a match for both a virtual link and a multi-area
             adjacency then this is a configuration error that should be handled 
             at the configuration level.</t> 

    <t>Packets whose IP destination is AllDRouters should only be
       accepted if the state of the receiving interface is DR or
       Backup (see Section 9.1 of <xref target="OSPF"/>).</t>
    <t>[...] The remainder of Section 8.2 of <xref target="OSPF"/> is unchanged.</t>
   </list>
   </t>
</section>

<section title="Interface Data Structure">
   <t>An OSPF interface data structure is built for each configured
      multi-area adjacency as specified in Section 9 of <xref target="OSPF"/>.  The 
      interface type will always be point-to-point.</t>
</section>

<section title="Interface FSM">
   <t>The interface Finite State Machine (FSM) will be the same as a point-to-point link
      irrespective of the underlying physical link.</t>
</section>

<section title="Neighbor Data Structure and Neighbor FSM">
   <t>Both the neighbor data structure and neighbor FSM are the same as 
      for standard OSPF, specified in Section 10 of <xref target="OSPF"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="MA-LSA" title="Advertising Multi-Area Adjacencies">
   <t>Multi-area adjacencies are announced as point-to-point 
      links. Once the router's multi-area adjacency reaches the FULL state, 
      it will be added as a link type 1 to the Router Link State Advertisement
      (LSA) with:
      <list style="hanging"> 
        <t>Link ID   = Remote's Router ID</t>
        <t>Link Data = Neighbor's IP Address or IfIndex (if the underlying interface
         is unnumbered).</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Unlike numbered point-to-point links, 
         no type 3 link is advertised for multi-area adjacencies.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Compatibility">
    <t>All mechanisms described in this document are backward compatible
       with standard OSPF implementations <xref target="OSPF"/>.</t>
<section title="Adjacency Endpoint Compatibility">
    <t>Since multi-area adjacencies are modeled as point-to-point links, it is only necessary for the router at the 
    other end of the adjacency to model the adjacency as a point-to-point 
    link. However, the network topology will be easier to represent
    and troubleshoot if both neighbors are symmetrically configured as
    multi-area adjacencies.</t> 
</section>
</section>

<section title="OSPFv3 Applicability">
   <t>The mechanisms defined in this document also apply to OSPFv3 <xref target="OSPFV3"/>.
      As in OSPF, a multi-area adjacency is advertised as a point-to-point link in the advertising router's router-LSA.
      Since OSPFv3 router-LSA links are independent of addressing semantics and
      unambiguously identify OSPFv3 neighbors (refer to
      Section 3.4.3.1 of <xref target="OSPFV3"/>), the change to router-LSA links
      described in <xref target="MA-LSA"/> is not applicable to OSPFv3. 
      Furthermore, no prefixes corresponding to the multi-area adjacency 
      are advertised in the router's intra-area-prefix-LSA.</t> 
   <t>A link-LSA SHOULD NOT be advertised for a multi-area adjacency. The neighbor's
      IPv6 link local address can be learned in other ways, e.g., it can be extracted
      from the IPv6 header of Hello packets received over the
      multi-area adjacency. The neighbor IPv6 link local address is required for
      the OSPFv3 route next-hop calculation on multi-access networks (refer to Section
      3.8.1.1 of <xref target="OSPFV3"/>).</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>This document does not raise any security issues that are not 
      already covered in <xref target="OSPF"/> or <xref target="OSPFV3"/>.</t>
</section>


</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<reference anchor="RFC-KEYWORDS">
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
</author>
<date month="March" year="1997" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="OSPF">
<front>
<title>OSPF Version 2</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Moy" fullname="John Moy">
<organization>Ascend Communications, Inc</organization>
</author>
<date month="April" year="1998" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="STD" value="54" />
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2328" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="OSPFV3">
<front>
<title>OSPF for IPv6</title>
<author initials="R." surname="Coltun" fullname="Rob Coltun">
<organization>Siara Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="D." surname="Ferguson" fullname="Dennis Ferguson">
<organization>Juniper Network, Inc</organization>
</author>
<author initials="J." surname="Moy" fullname="John Moy">
<organization>Sycamore Systems, Inc</organization>
</author>
<date month="December" year="1999" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2740" />
</reference>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor="P2PLAN">
<front>
<title>Point-to-point operation over LAN in link-state routing protocols</title>
<author initials="N." surname="Shen" fullname="Naiming Shen">
<organization>Redback Networks</organization>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Zinin" fullname="Alex Zinin">
<organization>Alcatel Communications</organization>
</author>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
</reference>

</references>
<section title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>The authors wish to acknowledge Pat Murphy for convincing the OSPF WG to address the requirement.</t>
  <t>Thanks to Mitchell Erblich's for his last call review and comments.</t>
  <t>Thanks to Padma Pillay-Esnault for her last call review and comments.
     Also, thanks to Padma for comments on the OSPFv3 applicability section that was
     last called separately.</t>
  <t>Thanks to Nischal Seth for pointing out that the document inadvertently 
     precluded point-to-point over LAN interfaces.</t>
  <t>Thanks to Ben Campbell for performing the General Area review.</t>
  <t>Thanks to Jari Arkko for comments during the IESG review.</t>
  <t>The RFC text was produced using Marshall Rose's xml2rfc tool.</t>
</section>
</back>
<vspace blankLines="100" />
</rfc>
