<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY RFC5389 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC4361 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4361.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC3972 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3972.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC2865 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC4795 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4795.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC2113 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2113.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC4119 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4119.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC3068 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3068.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC5491 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5491.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC4479 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4479.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC5201 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5201.xml'>
 <!ENTITY RFC5012 PUBLIC ''
 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5012.xml'>
 
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?> 
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc number="5687" category="info" >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="GEOPRIV L7 LCP: Problem Statement">GEOPRIV Layer 7 Location Configuration
      Protocol: Problem&nbsp;Statement&nbsp;and&nbsp;Requirements</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne" fullname="Henning Schulzrinne">
      <organization>Columbia University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
          <street>450 Computer Science Building</street>
          <city>New York</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <code>10027</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 212 939 7004</phone>
        <email>hgs+ecrit@cs.columbia.edu</email>
        <uri>http://www.cs.columbia.edu</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2010"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a problem statement, lists requirements, and captures design aspects
        for a GEOPRIV Layer 7 (L7) Location Configuration Protocol (LCP). This protocol aims to allow
        an end host to obtain location information, by value or by reference, from a Location
        Information Server (LIS) that is located in the access network. The obtained location
        information can then be used for a variety of different protocols and purposes. For example,
        it can be used as input to the Location-to-Service Translation
        (LoST) Protocol or to convey
        location within the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) to other entities.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document provides a problem statement, lists requirements, and captures design aspects
        for a GEOPRIV Layer 7 (L7) Location Configuration Protocol (LCP). The protocol has two
        purposes:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>It is used by a device to obtain its own location (referred as "Location by Value" or LbyV)
            from a dedicated node, called the Location Information Server (LIS).</t>
          <t>It enables the device to obtain a reference to location information (referred as
            "Location by Reference" or LbyR). This reference can take the form of a subscription
            URI, such as a SIP presence-based Uniform Resource Identifier (URI), an HTTP/HTTPS URI, or another URI. The requirements
            related to the task of obtaining an LbyR are described in a separate document, see <xref
              target="LBYR-REQS"/>.</t>
        </list>The need for these two functions can be derived from the scenarios presented in <xref
          target="scenarios"/>. </t>
      <t>For this document, we assume that the GEOPRIV Layer 7 LCP runs between the device and the LIS.</t>
      <t>This document is structured as follows. <xref target="discovery"/> discusses the challenge
        of discovering the LIS in the access network. <xref target="identifier"/> compares different
        types of identifiers that can be used to retrieve location information. A list of
        requirements for the L7 LCP can be found in <xref target="requirements"/>. </t>
      <t>This document does not describe how the access network provider determines the location of
        the device since this is largely a matter of the capabilities of specific link-layer
        technologies or certain deployment environments.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>In this document, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as
        described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>, with the qualification that unless otherwise
        stated these words apply to the design of the GEOPRIV Layer 7 Location Configuration
        Protocol.</t>
      <t> The term Location Information Server (LIS) refers to an entity capable of determining the
        location of a device and of providing that location information, a reference to it, or both
        via the Location Configuration Protocol (LCP) to the Target.</t>      
      <t>This document also uses terminology from <xref target="RFC5012"/> (such as Internet Access Provider (IAP),
        Internet Service Provider (ISP), and Application Service
          Provider (ASP)).</t>
      <t>With the term "Access Network Provider" we refer to the IAP and
        the ISP) without further distinguishing these two entities, as it
        is not relevant for the purpose of this document. An additional requirements document on
        LIS-to-LIS protocol <xref target="LIS2LIS"/> shows a scenario where the
        separation between IAP and ISP is important.</t>

    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="scenarios" title="Scenarios">
      <t>This section describes a few network scenarios where the L7 LCP may be used. Note that this
        section does not aim to exhaustively list all possible deployment environments. Instead, we
        focus on the following environments:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>DSL/Cable networks, WiMAX-like (Worldwide Interoperability for Microwave Access) fixed access</t>
          <t>Airport, city, campus wireless networks, such as 802.11a/b/g, 802.16e/WiMAX</t>
          <t>3G networks</t>
          <t>Enterprise networks</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Note that we use the term 'host' instead of device for better readability.</t>
      <section anchor="fixed-wireless" title="Fixed-Wired Environment">
        <t><xref target="dsl-figure"/> shows a Digital Subscriber Line (DSL) network scenario with the Access Network Provider
          and the customer premises. The Access Network Provider operates link- and network-layer
          devices (represented as a node) and the LIS. </t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="dsl-figure" title="Fixed-Wired Scenario">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------------------------+
|                           |
|  Access Network Provider  |
|                           |
|   +--------+              |
|   | Node   |              |
|   +--------+ +----------+ |
|       |  |   | LIS      | |
|       |  +---|          | |
|       |      +----------+ |
|       |                   |
+-------+-------------------+
        | Wired Network
<----------------> Access Network Provider demarc
        |
+-------+-------------------+
|       |                   |
|   +-------------+         |
|   | NTE         |         |
|   +-------------+         |
|       |                   |
|       |                   |
|   +--------------+        |
|   | Device with  | Home   |
|   | NAPT and     | Router |
|   | DHCP server  |        |
|   +--------------+        |
|       |                   |
|       |                   |
|    +------+               |
|    | Host |               |
|    +------+               |
|                           |
|Customer Premises Network  |
|                           |
+---------------------------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>


        <t> The customer premises network consists of a router with a Network Address Translator with Port
          Address Translation (NAPT) and a DHCP server as used in most Customer Premises Networks
          (CPNs) and the Network Termination Equipment (NTE) where Layer 1 and sometimes Layer 2
          protocols are terminated. The router in the home network (e.g., broadband router, cable or
          DSL router) typically runs a NAPT and a DHCP server. The NTE is a legacy device and in
          many cases cannot be modified for the purpose of delivering location information to the
          host. The same is true of the device with the NAPT and DHCP server. </t>
        <t> It is possible for the NTE and the home router to physically be in the same box, or for
          there to be no home router, or for the NTE and host to be in the same physical box
          (with no home router). An example of this last case is where Ethernet service is delivered
          to customers' homes, and the Ethernet network interface card (NIC) in their PC serves as the NTE.</t>
        <t>Current CPN deployments generally fall into one of the
          following classifications: </t>
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Single PC <list style="numbers">
              <t>with Ethernet network interface card (NIC), with Point-to-Point Protocol Over Ethernet (PPPoE), or Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) on PC; there may be a bridged DSL or cable
                  modem as the NTE, or the Ethernet NIC might be the NTE. </t>
              <t> with USB-based DSL access or a cable modem access using Point-to-Point Protocol over ATM (PPPoA), PPPoE, or DHCP on PC.</t>
              </list> Note that the device with NAPT and DHCP of <xref target="dsl-figure"/> is not
              present in such a scenario. </t>
            <t>One or more hosts with at least one router (DHCP client or PPPoE, DHCP server in
              router; Voice over IP (VoIP) can be a soft client on a PC, a stand-alone VoIP device, or an Analog Terminal
              Adaptor (ATA) function embedded in a router):<list style="numbers">
                <t>combined router and NTE. </t>
                <t>separate router with NTE in bridged mode. </t>
                <t>separate router with NTE (NTE/router does PPPoE or DHCP to WAN, router provides
                  DHCP server for hosts in LAN; double NAT).</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t> The majority of fixed-access broadband customers use a router. The placement of the VoIP
          client is mentioned to describe what sorts of hosts may need to be able to request
          location information. Soft clients on PCs are frequently not launched until long after
          bootstrapping is complete, and are not able to control any options that may be specified
          during bootstrapping. They also cannot control whether a VPN client is running on the end
          host. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Mobile Network">
        <t> One example of a moving network is a WiMAX-fixed wireless scenario. This also applies to
          "pre-WiMAX" and "WiMAX-like" fixed wireless networks. In implementations intended to
          provide broadband service to a home or other stationary location, the customer-side
          antenna/NTE tends to be rather small and portable. The LAN-side output of this device is
          an Ethernet jack, which can be used to feed a PC or a router. The PC or router then uses
          DHCP or PPPoE to connect to the access network, the same as
          for wired access networks.
          Access providers who deploy this technology may use the same core network (including
          network elements that terminate PPPoE and provide IP addresses) for DSL, fiber to the
          premises (FTTP), and fixed wireless customers. </t>
        <t> Given that the customer antenna is portable and can be battery-powered, it is possible
          for a user to connect a laptop to it and move within the coverage area of a single base
          antenna. This coverage area can be many square kilometers in size. In this case, the
          laptop (and any SIP client running on it) would be completely unaware of their mobility.
          Only the user and the network are aware of the laptop's mobility. </t>
        <t> Further examples of moving networks (where end devices may not be aware that they are
          moving) can be found in busses, trains, and airplanes. </t>
        <t>
          <xref target="moving-network"/> shows an example topology for a moving network.</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="moving-network" title="Moving Network">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------------------------+
| Wireless                 |
| Access Network Provider  |
|                          |
|              +----------+|
|      +-------+ LIS      ||
|      |       |          ||
|  +---+----+  +----------+|
|  | Node   |              |
|  |        |              |
|  +---+----+              |
|      |                   |
+------+-------------------+
       | Wireless Interface
       |
+------+-------------------+
|      |    Moving Network |
|  +---+----+              |
|  | NTE    |   +--------+ |
|  |        +---+ Host   | |
|  +-+-----++   |  B     | |
|    |     \    +--------+ |
|    |      \              |
|+---+----+  \  +---+----+ |
|| Host   |   \ | Host   | |
||  A     |    \+  B     | |
|+--------+     +--------+ |
+--------------------------+
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="wireless" title="Wireless Access">
        <t>
          <xref target="wireless-figure"/> shows a wireless access network where a moving host
          obtains location information or references to location information from the LIS. The
          access equipment uses, in many cases, link-layer devices. <xref target="wireless-figure"/>
          represents a hotspot network found, for example, in hotels, airports, and coffee shops.
          For editorial reasons we only describe a single access point and do not depict how the LIS
          obtains location information since this is very deployment specific.</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="wireless-figure" title="Wireless Access Scenario">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------------------------+
| Access Network Provider  |
|                          |
|              +----------+|
|      +-------| LIS      ||
|      |       |          ||
|  +--------+  +----------+|
|  | Access |              |
|  | Point  |              |
|  +--------+              |
|      |                   |
+------+-------------------+
       |
   +------+
   | Host |
   +------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="discovery" title="Discovery of the Location Information Server">

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Note that this section lists mechanisms that were discussed in the
            GEOPRIV Layer 7 Location Configuration Protocol design team. They are included to show
            challenges in the problem space and are listed for completeness reasons. They do not in
            any way mean that there is consensus about any of the mechanisms or
            that the IETF recommends any of the procedures described in this section.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>When a device wants to retrieve location information from the LIS, it first needs to
        discover it. Based on the problem statement of determining the location of the device, which
        is known best by entities close to the device itself, we assume that the LIS is located in
        the local subnet or in the access network. Several procedures have been investigated that aim to
        discover the LIS in such an access network.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="DHCP-based Discovery:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>In some environments, the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
            (DHCP) might be a good choice for discovering the fully-qualified domain name (FQDN) or the IP address of the LIS. In
            environments where DHCP can be used, it is also possible to use the already defined
            location extensions. In environments with legacy devices, such as the one shown in <xref
              target="fixed-wireless"/>, a DHCP-based discovery solution may not be possible.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="DNS-based Discovery:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>Before a Domain Name System (DNS) lookup can be started, it is necessary to learn the
            domain name of the access network that runs an LIS. Several ways to learn the domain name
            exist. For example, the end host obtains its own public IP address via Simple Traversal of the UDP Protocol through NAT (STUN) <xref target="RFC5389"/>, and performs a reverse DNS lookup (assuming the data is provisioned into the DNS). Then, the DNS Service (SRV) record or the DNS Naming Authority Pointer (NAPTR) record for that domain is retrieved. A
            more detailed description of this approach can be found in <xref
              target="LIS-DISC"/>.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Redirect Rule:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>A redirect rule at an entity in the access network could be used
            to redirect the L7 LCP signaling messages (destined to a specific port) to the LIS. The
            device could then discover the LIS by sending a packet with a specific (registered)
            port number to almost any address as long as the destination IP address does not target
            an entity in the local network. The packet would be redirected to the respective LIS
            being configured. The same procedure is used by captive portals whereby any HTTP traffic
            is intercepted and redirected.<vspace blankLines="1"/> To some extent, this approach is
            similar to packets that are marked with a Router Alert option <xref target="RFC2113"/>
            and intercepted by entities that understand the specific marking. In the above-mentioned
            case, however, the marking is provided via a registered port number instead of relying
            on a Router Alert option. <vspace blankLines="1"/> This solution approach would require
            a deep packet inspection capability at an entity in the access provider's networks that
            scans for the occurrence of particular destination port numbers. <vspace blankLines="1"
            />
          </t>
          <t hangText="Multicast Query:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>A device could also discover an LIS by sending a DNS query to
            a well-known address. An example of such a mechanism is multicast DNS (see <xref
              target="RFC4795"/> and <xref target="mDNS"/>).
            Unfortunately, these mechanisms only work on the local link. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

          <t hangText="Anycast:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> With this solution, an anycast address is defined (for IPv4 and
            IPv6) in the style of <xref target="RFC3068"/> that allows the device to route
            discovery packets to the nearest LIS. 
            
            Note that this procedure would be used purely for discovery and
            is therefore similar to the local Teredo server discovery
            approach outlined in Section 4.2 of <xref target="TEREDO-SEL"/>.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The LIS discovery procedure raises deployment and security issues. The access network needs
        to be designed to prevent man-in-the-middle adversaries from presenting themselves as an LIS
        to devices. When a device discovers an LIS, it needs to ensure (and be able to ensure)
        that the discovered entity is indeed an authorized LIS.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="identifier" title="Identifier for Location Determination">

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Note that this section lists mechanisms that were discussed in the
            GEOPRIV Layer 7 Location Configuration Protocol design team. They are included to show
            challenges in the problem space and are listed for completeness reasons. They do not in
            any way mean that there is consensus about any of the mechanisms or
            that the IETF recommends any of the procedures described in this section.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The LIS returns location information to the device when it receives a request. Some form
        of identifier is therefore needed to allow the LIS to retrieve the device's current location,
        or a good approximation, from a database.</t>
      <t>The chosen identifier needs to have the following properties:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Ability for Device to learn or know the identifier:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The device MUST know or MUST be able to learn of the identifier
            (explicitly or implicitly) in order to send it to the LIS. Implicitly refers to the
            situation where a device along the path between the device and the LIS modifies the
            identifier, as it is done by a NAT when an IP address based identifier is used.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Ability to use the identifier for location determination:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The LIS MUST be able to use the identifier (directly or
            indirectly) for location determination. Indirectly refers to the case where the LIS uses
            other identifiers internally for location determination, in addition to the one provided
            by the device.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Security properties of the identifier:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>Misuse needs to be minimized whereby an off-path adversary MUST NOT
            be able to obtain location information of other devices. An on-path adversary in the same
            subnet SHOULD NOT be able to spoof the identifier of another device in the same
          subnet.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The following list discusses frequently mentioned identifiers and their properties:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Media Access Control (MAC) Address:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The MAC address is known to the device itself, but not
            carried beyond a single IP hop and therefore not accessible to the LIS in most deployment
            environments (unless carried in the L7 LCP itself).<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Asynchronous Transfer Mode (ATM) Virtual Path
            Identifier / Virtual Circuit Identifier (VPI/VCI):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The VCI/VPI is generally only seen by the DSL modem. Almost all
            routers in the United States use 1 of 2 VPI/VCI value pairs: 0/35 and 8/35. This VC is terminated
            at the digital subscriber line access multiplexer (DSLAM), which uses a different VPI/VCI (per end customer) to connect to the ATM
            switch. Only the network provider is able to map VPI/VCI values through its network.
            With the arrival of Very high rate Digital Subscriber Line (VDSL), ATM will slowly be phased out in favor of Ethernet. <vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Ethernet Switch (Bridge)/Port Number:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> This identifier is available only in certain networks, such as
            enterprise networks, typically available via the IEEE 802.1AB
            protocol <xref target="802.1AB"/> or proprietary protocols like the Cisco Discovery
            Protocol (CDP) <xref target="CDP"/>.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Cell ID:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> This identifier is available in cellular data networks and the
            cell ID may not be visible to the device.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
  

          <t hangText="Host Identifier:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The Host Identifier introduced by the Host Identity Protocol (HIP)
              <xref target="RFC5201"/> allows identification of a particular host.
            Unfortunately, the network can only use this identifier for location determination if
            the operator already stores a mapping of host identities to location information.
            Furthermore, there is a deployment problem since the host identities are not used in
            today's networks. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Cryptographically Generated Address (CGA):">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The concept of a Cryptographically Generated Address (CGA) was
            introduced by <xref target="RFC3972"/>. The basic idea is to put the truncated hash of a
            public key into the interface identifier part of an IPv6 address. In addition to the
            properties of an IP address, it allows a proof of ownership. Hence, a return routability
            check can be omitted. It is only available for IPv6 addresses.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Network Access Identifiers:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>A Network Access Identifier <xref target="RFC4282"/> is used
            during the network access authentication procedure, for example, in RADIUS <xref
              target="RFC2865"/> and Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/>. In DSL networks, the user
            credentials are, in many cases, only known by the home router and not configured at the
            device itself. To the network, the authenticated user identity is only available if a
            network access authentication procedure is executed. In case of roaming, the user's
            identity might not be available to the access network since security protocols might
            offer user identity confidentiality and thereby hide the real identity of the user
            allowing the access network to only see a pseudonym or a randomized string.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Unique Client Identifier">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The Broadband Forum has defined that all devices that expect to be
            managed by the TR-069 interface, see <xref target="TR069"/>, have to be able to generate an identifier
            that uniquely identifies the device. It also has a requirement that routers
            that use DHCP to the WAN use RFC 4361 <xref target="RFC4361"/> to provide the DHCP
            server with a unique client identifier. This identifier is, however, not visible to the
            device when legacy NTE devices are used.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="IP Address:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The device's IP address may be used for location determination.
            This IP address is not visible to the LIS if the device is behind one or multiple
            NATs. This may not be a problem since the location of a device that is located behind a
            NAT cannot be determined by the access network. The LIS would in this case only see the
            public IP address of the NAT binding allocated by the NAT, which is the expected
            behavior. The property of the IP address for a return routability check is attractive to
            return location information only to the address that submitted the request. If an
            adversary wants to learn the location of a device (as identified by a particular IP
            address), then it does not see the response message (unless it is on the subnetwork or at
            a router along the path towards the LIS).<vspace blankLines="1"/> On a shared medium, an
            adversary could ask for location information of another device. The adversary would be
            able to see the response message since it is sniffing on the shared medium unless
            security mechanisms, such as link-layer encryption, are in place. With a network
            deployment as shown in <xref target="fixed-wireless"/> with multiple devices in the
            Customer Premises being behind a NAT, the LIS is unable to differentiate the individual
            devices. For WLAN deployments as found in hotels, as shown in <xref target="wireless"
            />, it is possible for an adversary to eavesdrop data traffic and subsequently to spoof
            the IP address in a query to the LIS to learn more detailed location information (e.g.,
            specific room numbers). Such an attack might, for example, compromise the privacy of
            hotel guests. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
  
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="requirements" title="Requirements">
      <t>The following requirements and assumptions have been identified: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-1: Identifier Choice">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The L7 LCP MUST be able to carry different identifiers or MUST
            define an identifier that is mandatory to implement. Regarding the latter aspect, such
            an identifier is only appropriate if it is from the same realm as the one for which the
            location information service maintains identifier-to-location mapping.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-2: Mobility Support ">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The L7 LCP MUST support a broad range of mobility from devices
            that can only move between reboots, to devices that can change attachment points with
            the impact that their IP address is changed, to devices that do not change their IP
            address while roaming, to devices that continuously move by being attached to the same
            network attachment point.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-3: ASP and Access Network Provider Relationship">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of the L7 LCP MUST NOT assume that a business or trust
            relationship between the Application Service Provider (ASP) and the Access Network
            Provider. Requirements for resolving a reference to location information are not
            discussed in this document.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-4: Layer 2 and Layer 3 Provider Relationship">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of the L7 LCP MUST assume that there is a trust and
            business relationship between the L2 and the L3 provider. The L3 provider operates the
            LIS that the device queries. It, in turn, needs to obtain location information from the
            L2 provider since this one is closest to the device. If the L2 and L3 provider for the
            same device are different entities, they cooperate for the purposes needed to determine
            locations.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-5: Legacy Device Considerations">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of the L7 LCP MUST consider legacy devices, such as
            residential NAT devices and NTEs in a DSL environment, that cannot be upgraded to
            support additional protocols, for example, to pass additional information towards the
              device.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
        <t hangText="Requirement L7-6: Virtual Private Network (VPN) Awareness">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The design of the L7 LCP MUST assume that at least one end of a
            VPN is aware of the VPN functionality. In an enterprise scenario, the enterprise side
            will provide the LIS used by the device and can thereby detect whether the LIS request
            was initiated through a VPN tunnel.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-7: Network Access Authentication">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of the L7 LCP MUST NOT assume that prior network access
              authentication.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-8: Network Topology Unawareness">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The design of the L7 LCP MUST NOT assume that devices are aware
            of the access network topology. Devices are, however, able to determine their public
            IP address(es) via mechanisms, such as Simple Traversal of User Datagram Protocol (UDP) Through Network Address Translators (NATs) (STUN) <xref target="RFC5389"/> or Next Steps in Signaling (NSIS) NAT/Firewall NSIS Signaling Layer Protocol (NSLP)
              <xref target="NSLP"/>.<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-9: Discovery Mechanism">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> The L7 LCP MUST define a mandatory-to-implement LIS discovery
            mechanism. </t>
          <t hangText="Requirement L7-10: PIDF-LO Creation">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> When an LIS creates a Presence Information Data Format (PIDF) Location Object (LO) <xref target="RFC4119"/>, then it
            MUST put the &lt;geopriv&gt; element into the &lt;device&gt; element of
            the presence document (see <xref target="RFC4479"/>). This ensures that the resulting
            PIDF-LO document, which is subsequently distributed to other entities, conforms to the
            rules outlined in <xref target="RFC5491"/>.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t> By using a Geolocation L7 Location Configuration Protocol, the device
  (and a human user of such a device, if applicable) exposes themselves 
  to a privacy risk whereby an unauthorized entity receives location 
  information.
 Providing
        confidentiality protected location to the requestor depends on the success of four steps:
 </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The client MUST have a means to discover a LIS. </t>
          <t>The client MUST authenticate the discovered LIS. </t>
          <t>The LIS MUST be able to determine location and return it to the authorized entity.</t>
          <t>The LIS MUST securely exchange messages without intermediaries eavesdropping or
            tampering with them.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>This document contains various security-related requirements throughout the document
        addressing the above-mentioned steps. For a broader security discussion of the overall
        geolocation privacy architecture, the reader is referred to <xref
          target="GEOPRIV-ARCH"/>.</t>
    </section>
   
    <section title="Contributors">
      <t> This contribution is a joint effort of the GEOPRIV Layer 7 Location Configuration
        Requirements Design Team of the IETF GEOPRIV Working Group. The contributors include Henning
        Schulzrinne, Barbara Stark, Marc Linsner, Andrew Newton, James Winterbottom, Martin Thomson,
        Rohan Mahy, Brian Rosen, Jon Peterson, and Hannes Tschofenig. </t>
      <t>We would like to thank the GEOPRIV Working Group Chairs, Andy Newton, Randy Gellens, and
        Allison Mankin, for creating the design team. Furthermore, we would like thank Andy Newton
        for his support during the design team mailing list, for setting up Jabber chat conferences,
        and for participating in the phone conference discussions.</t>
      <t>The design team members can be reached at:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Marc Linsner:"> mlinsner@cisco.com</t>
          <t hangText="Rohan Mahy:"> rohan@ekabal.com</t>
          <t hangText="Andrew Newton:"> andy@hxr.us</t>
          <t hangText="Jon Peterson:"> jon.peterson@neustar.biz</t>
          <t hangText="Brian Rosen:"> br@brianrosen.net</t>
          <t hangText="Henning Schulzrinne:"> hgs@cs.columbia.edu</t>
          <t hangText="Barbara Stark:"> Barbara.Stark@bellsouth.com</t>
          <t hangText="Martin Thomson:"> Martin.Thomson@andrew.com</t>
          <t hangText="Hannes Tschofenig:"> Hannes.Tschofenig@nsn.com</t>
          <t hangText="James Winterbottom:"> James.Winterbottom@andrew.com</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would also like to thank Murugaraj Shanmugam, Ted Hardie, Martin Dawson, Richard Barnes,
        James Winterbottom, Tom Taylor, Otmar Lendl, Marc Linsner, Brian Rosen, Roger Marshall, Guy
        Caron, Doug Stuard, Eric Arolick, Dan Romascanu, Jerome Grenier, Martin Thomson, Barbara
        Stark, Michael Haberler, and Mary Barnes for their WGLC review comments.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank NENA for their work on <xref target="NENA"/> as it helped
        to provide some of the initial thinking. </t>

      <t>The authors would also like to thank Cullen Jennings for his feedback as part of the IESG
        processing. Additionally, we would like to thank Alexey Melnikov, Dan Romascanu, and Robert Sparks. 
 </t>

    </section>
    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>-</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference> 
<!--&I-D.ietf-ecrit-requirements; -->
&RFC5012;


</references>
    <references title="Informative References"> 
<!--&I-D.ietf-geopriv-lbyr-requirements;-->


<reference anchor='LBYR-REQS'>
<front>
<title>Requirements for a Location-by-Reference Mechanism</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Marshall' fullname='Roger Marshall'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='2' year='2009' />

<abstract><t>This document defines terminology and provides requirements relating to Location-by-Reference approach using a location Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) to handle location information within signaling and other Internet messaging.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>

      
&RFC4361; 
&RFC3972; 
&RFC3588; 
&RFC2865; 
&RFC5389;
&RFC2113;
&RFC4119; 

<!--&I-D.ietf-nsis-nslp-natfw; -->
<reference anchor='NSLP'>
<front>
<title>NAT/Firewall NSIS Signaling Layer Protocol (NSLP)</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Stiemerling' fullname='Martin Stiemerling'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Aoun' fullname='Cedric Aoun'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E' surname='Davies' fullname='Elwyn Davies'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' day='3' year='2008' />

<abstract><t>This memo defines the NSIS Signaling Layer Protocol (NSLP) for Network Address Translators (NATs) and firewalls.  This NSLP allows hosts to signal on the data path for NATs and firewalls to be configured according to the needs of the application data flows.  For instance, it enables hosts behind NATs to obtain a public reachable address and hosts behind firewalls to receive data traffic.  The overall architecture is given by the framework and requirements defined by the Next Steps in Signaling (NSIS) working group.  The network scenarios, the protocol itself, and examples for path-coupled signaling are given in this memo.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>




&RFC4282; 
<!--&I-D.ietf-hip-base; -->
&RFC5201;

&RFC3068; 
&RFC4479; 
<!--&I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns; -->

<reference anchor='mDNS'>
<front>
<title>Multicast DNS</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Cheshire' fullname='Stuart Cheshire'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Krochmal' fullname='Marc Krochmal'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>


&RFC4795;

<reference anchor='GEOPRIV-ARCH'>
<front>
<title>An Architecture for Location and Location Privacy in Internet Applications</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Barnes' fullname='Richard Barnes'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Lepinski' fullname='Matt Lepinski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Cooper' fullname='Alissa Cooper'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Morris' fullname='John Morris'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='Henning Schulzrinne'>
    <organization />

</author>

<date month='July' day='9' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-geopriv-pdif-lo-profile was published as RFC 5491 -->
&RFC5491;

<!--&I-D.winterbottom-geopriv-lis2lis-req; -->

<reference anchor='LIS2LIS'>
<front>
<title>LIS to LIS Protocol Requirements</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Winterbottom' fullname='James Winterbottom'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Norreys' fullname='Steve Norreys'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' day='19' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>This document describes requirements for a LIS to LIS protocol and provides examples of where such a protocol is applicable.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>


<!--&I-D.thomson-geopriv-lis-discovery; -->
<reference anchor='LIS-DISC'>
<front>
<title>Discovering the Local Location Information Server (LIS)</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Winterbottom' fullname='James Winterbottom'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='26' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>A method is described for the discovery of a Location Information Server.  The method consists of attempting to use a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) option, followed by a URI-enabled NAPTR (U-NAPTR).  DHCP options are defined for both IPv4 and IPv6 DHCP. This document also defines a U-NAPTR Application Service for a LIS, with a specific Application Protocol for the HTTP Enabled Location Delivery (HELD) protocol.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>



<!--&I-D.nward-v6ops-teredo-server-selection; -->

<reference anchor='TEREDO-SEL'>
<front>
<title>Teredo Server Selection</title>

<author initials='N' surname='Ward' fullname='Nathan Ward'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='3' year='2007' />

<abstract><t>This document describes performance, reliability and privacy problems inherent when using a remotely situated vendor-provided Teredo server, which is a common default in current implementations, and then discussed why configuring servers manually is bad and difficult. It recommends two partial solutions, and gives a final recommendation combining both solutions using anycast IPv4 and a well known DNS hostname.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>



<reference anchor="NENA" target="http://www.nena.org/sites/default/files/08-505_20061221.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>NENA 08-505, Issue 1, 2006 (December 21, 2006), NENA Recommended Method(s) for
            Location Determination to Support IP-Based Emergency Services - Technical Information
            Document (TID)</title>
          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization/>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2006"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="802.1AB" target="http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.1AB-2005.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.1AB-2005 IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks
            Station and Media Access Control Connectivity Discovery</title>
          <author fullname="IEEE" initials="" surname="">
            <organization/>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>      
      
      <reference anchor="CDP" target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cisco_Discovery_Protocol">
        <front>
          <title>Cisco Discovery Protocol (CDP)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Wikipedia</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>      
      
      
      <reference anchor="TR069" target="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-069_Amendment-2.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>TR-069, CPE WAN Management Protocol v1.1, Version: Issue 1 Amendment 2</title>
          <author fullname="Broadband Forum" initials="" surname="">
            <organization/>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference> 

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
