<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2607 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2607.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM
	 "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3162 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3162.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3411 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3576 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3576.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3580 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3580.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4252 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4252.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5080 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5080.xml"> ]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="5608" category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RADIUS Usage for SNMP Transport Models">Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS) Usage for Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Transport Models</title>

    <author fullname="Kaushik Narayan" initials="K" surname="Narayan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1.408.526.8168</phone>
        <email>kaushik_narayan@yahoo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Nelson" initials="D" surname="Nelson">
      <organization>Elbrys Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>282 Corporate Drive</street>
          <city>Portsmouth</city>
          <region>NH</region>
          <code>03801</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1.603.570.2636</phone>
        <email>dnelson@elbrysnetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2009" />

<note title="">
<t>
This document may contain material from IETF Documents or IETF
Contributions published or made publicly available before November 10,
2008.  The person(s) controlling the copyright in some of this material
may not have granted the IETF Trust the right to allow modifications
of such material outside the IETF Standards Process.  Without
obtaining an adequate license from the person(s) controlling the
copyright in such materials, this document may not be modified outside
the IETF Standards Process, and derivative works of it may not be
created outside the IETF Standards Process, except to format it for
publication as an RFC or to translate it into languages other than
English.
</t>
</note>


<!--[rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

<!--[rfced] Please note that we have adopted the following forms for consistency throughout the document.  Please let us know any objections:

"hint" attribute
RADIUS server
RADIUS client 
-->

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo describes the use of a Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS)
      authentication and authorization service with Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)
      secure Transport Models to authenticate users and authorize creation of secure 
      transport sessions.  While the recommendations of this memo are generally applicable to
      a broad class of SNMP Transport Models, the examples focus on the Secure Shell (SSH) Transport Model.</t>
    </abstract>

<!-- [rfced] Please note that as of 1 July 2009, the RFC Editor is
publishing RFCs with the abstract immediately following the title so
that the abstract appears on the front page of the RFC.  We will
reorder the sections just prior to final publication, as xml2rfc does
not currently provide for this order.  Please see our announcement at:
http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ietf-announce/current/msg06215.html.
-->

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    <section title="General">
      <t>This memo describes the use of a Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS)
      authentication and authorization service by Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)
      secure Transport Models to authenticate users and authorize creation of secure 
      transport sessions.  While the recommendations of this memo are generally applicable to
      a broad class of SNMP Transport Models, the examples focus on the Secure Shell Transport Model.</t>
      
     <t>In the context of this document, a Network Access Server (NAS) is a network device or host
     that contains an SNMP engine implementation, utilizing SNMP Transport
     Models.  It is customary in SNMP documents to indicate which subsystem
     performs specific processing tasks.  In this document, we leave such decisions to
     the implementer, as is customary for RADIUS documents, and simply specify NAS behavior.
     Such processing would quite likely be implemented in the secure transport 
     module.
     </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="System Block Diagram">
        <t>A block diagram of the major system components referenced in this document
         may be useful to understanding the text that follows.</t>
         <t>
            <figure title="Block Diagram">
                <artwork>

                                      +--------+
           +......................... |RADIUS  |....+
           .                          |Server  |    .
         Shared                       +--------+    .
         User                             |         .
         Credentials             RADIUS   |      Shared      
           .                              |      RADIUS 
           .                              |      Secret
           .                              |         .
  +-------------+                  +-----------------+        
  | Network     |                  | RADIUS Client / |
  | Management  |       SNMP       | SNMP Engine /   |
  | Application |------------------| Network Device  |
  +-------------+       SSH        +-----------------+

                </artwork>
            </figure>
         </t>
         <t>This diagram illustrates that a network management application communicates
         with a network device, the managed entity, using SNMP over SSH.  The network
         devices uses RADIUS to communicate with a RADIUS server to authenticate the network
         management application (or the user whose credentials that application provides)
         and to obtain authorization information related to access via SNMP for purpose
         of device management.  Other secure transport protocols might be used instead of SSH.
         </t>
    </section>

    <section title="RADIUS Operational Model">
     <t>The RADIUS protocol <xref target="RFC2865"></xref> provides authentication and authorization
     services for network access devices, usually referred to as a Network Access Server (NAS).
     The RADIUS protocol operates, at the most simple level, as a request-response mechanism. 
     RADIUS clients, within the NAS, initiate a transaction by sending a RADIUS Access-Request 
     message to a RADIUS server, with which the client shares credentials. The RADIUS server will
     respond with either an Access-Accept message or an Access-Reject message.</t>
  
     <t>RADIUS supports authentication methods compatible with plaintext
     username and password mechanisms, MD5 Challenge/Response mechanisms,
     Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) mechanisms, and HTTP Digest
     mechanisms.  Upon presentation of identity and credentials, the user
     is either accepted or rejected.  RADIUS servers indicate a successful
     authentication by returning an Access-Accept message.  An Access-
     Reject message indicates unsuccessful authentication.</t>
  
    <t>Access-Accept messages are populated with one or more
     service provisioning attributes, which control the type and extent
     of service provided to the user at the NAS.  The authorization
     portion may be thought of as service provisioning.  Based on the
     configuration of the user's account on the RADIUS server, upon
     authentication, the NAS is provided with instructions as to what
     type of service to provide to the user.  When that service
     provisioning does not match the capabilities of the NAS, or of the
     particular interface to the NAS over which the user is requesting
     access, RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/> requires that the NAS MUST reject the
     access request.  RFC 2865 describes service provisioning
     attributes for management access to a NAS, as well as various
     terminal emulation and packet forwarding services on the NAS.  This
     memo describes specific RADIUS service provisioning attributes that
     are useful with secure transports and SNMP Transport
     Models.</t>

     <t>RADIUS servers are often deployed on an enterprise-wide or organization-wide
     basis, covering a variety of disparate use cases.  In such deployments, all 
     NASes and all users are serviced by a common pool of RADIUS servers.  In many
     deployments, the RADIUS server will handle requests from many different
     types of NASes with different capabilities, and different types of interfaces,
     services, and protocol support.</t>
        
     <t>In order for a RADIUS server to make the correct
     authorization decision in all cases, the server will often need to know something
     about the type of NAS at which the user is requesting access, the type of service
     that the user is requesting, and the role of the user in the organization.
     For example, many users may be authorized to receive network access via a 
     Remote Access Server (RAS), Virtual Private Network (VPN) server, or LAN access
     switch.  Typically only a small sub-set of all users are authorized to access the
     administrative interfaces of network infrastructure devices, e.g., the Command
     Line Interface (CLI) or SNMP engine of switches and routers.
     </t>
        
     <t>In order for the RADIUS server to have information regarding the type of
     access being requested, it is common for the NAS (i.e., the RADIUS client)
     to include "hint" attributes in the RADIUS Access-Request message, describing
     the NAS and the type of service being requested.  This document recommends
     appropriate "hint" attributes for the SNMP service type.</t>
    </section>
        
    <section title="RADIUS Usage with Secure Transports" >  
        <t>Some secure transport protocols that can be used with SNMP Transport Models
        have defined authentication protocols supporting several authentication methods.
        For example, the Secure Shell (SSH) Authentication protocol <xref target="RFC4252"></xref>
        supports multiple methods (including public key, password, and
        host-based) to authenticate SSH clients.
        </t>
        
        <t>SSH Server integration with RADIUS traditionally uses the username and 
        password mechanism.</t>
        
        <t>Secure transport protocols do not, however, specify how the transport
        interfaces to authentication clients, leaving such as implementation specific.
        For example, the "password" method of SSH authentication primarily describes 
        how passwords are acquired from the SSH client and transported to the SSH 
        server, the interpretation of the password and validation against password
        databases is left to SSH server implementations. SSH server
        implementations often use the Pluggable Authentication Modules
        <xref target="PAM"/>

<!-- [rfced] An informative reference has been added for the URL that
appeared in the original: http://www.opengroup.org/rfc/rfc86.0.html 

   [PAM]      Samar, V. and R. Schemers, "UNIFIED LOGIN WITH PLUGGABLE
              AUTHENTICATION MODULES (PAM)", Open Group RFC 86.0,
              October 1995,
              <http://www.opengroup.org/rfc/mirror-rfc/rfc86.0.txt>.

(Please note that we have updated the reference to point to the text
version of the same document, so that it does not appear
with the warning that is on the HTML version:

"Warning: This HTML rendition of the RFC is experimental. It is
programmatically generated, and small parts may be missing, damaged,
or badly formatted. However, it is much more convenient to read via
web browsers, however. Refer to the PostScript or text renditions for
the ultimate authority.")
-->

        interface provided by operating systems such as Linux and Solaris to
        integrate with password-based network authentication mechanisms such
        as RADIUS, TACACS+ (Terminal Access Controller Access-Control System Plus), Kerberos, etc.</t>
        
        <t>Secure transports do not typically specify how to utilize authorization 
        information obtained from a AAA service, such as RADIUS.  More often, user 
        authentication is sufficient to cause the secure transport server to begin
        delivering service to the user.  Access control in these situations is supplied
        by the application to which the secure transport server session is attached.
        For example, if the application is a Linux shell, the user's access rights are
        controlled by that user account's group membership and the file system access
        protections.  This behavior does not closely follow the traditional service 
        provisioning model of AAA systems, such as RADIUS.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Domain of Applicability">
            <t>
                Most of the RADIUS Attributes referenced in this document have broad applicability for
                provisioning remote management access to NAS devices using SNMP.  However, the selection
                of secure transport protocols has special considerations. 
                This document does not specify details of the integration of secure transport protocols
                with a RADIUS client in the NAS implementation.  However, there are functional
                requirements for correct application of framed management protocols and secure transport protocols that
                will limit the selection of such protocols that can be considered for use with RADIUS.
                Since the RADIUS user credentials are obtained by the RADIUS client from the secure transport
                protocol server, or in some cases directly from the SNMP engine, the
                secure transport protocol, and its implementation in the NAS, MUST support forms of credentials that 
                are compatible with the authentication methods supported by RADIUS.
            </t>
            <t>
              RADIUS currently supports the following user authentication methods, although others may be
                added in the future:

             <list style="symbols">
                 <t>
                 Password - RFC 2865
                 </t>
                 <t>
                 CHAP (Challenge Handshake Authentication Protocol) - RFC 2865
                 </t>
                 <t>
                 ARAP (Apple Remote Access Protocol) - RFC 2869
                 </t>
                 <t>
                 EAP (Extensible Authentication Protocol) - RFC 2869, RFC 3579
                 </t>
                 <t>
                 HTTP Digest - RFC 5090
                 </t>
                 </list>

             The secure transport protocols selected for use with RADIUS and SNMP obviously need to support
             user authentication methods that are compatible with those that exist in RADIUS.
             The RADIUS authentication methods most likely usable with these protocols are Password,
             CHAP, and possibly HTTP Digest, with Password being the distinct common denominator.  There are
             many secure transports that support other, more robust, authentication mechanisms,
             such as public key. &nbsp;RADIUS has no support for public key authentication, except within
             the context of an EAP Method.  The applicability statement for EAP indicates that it is
             not intended for use as an application-layer authentication mechanism, so its use with
             the mechanisms described in this document is NOT RECOMMENDED.
             In some cases, Password may be the only compatible RADIUS authentication method available.
            </t>
            </section>

    <section title="SNMP Transport Models">
      <t>The Transport Subsystem for SNMP <xref target="RFC5590"></xref> defines a
      mechanism for providing transport layer security (TLS) for SNMP, allowing
      protocols such as SSH and TLS to be used to secure SNMP communication.
      The Transport Subsystem allows the modular definition of Transport Models for
      multiple secure transport protocols.  Transport Models rely upon the underlying
      secure transport for user authentication services.  The Transport Model (TM) 
      then maps the authenticated identity to a model-independent principal, which
      it stores in the tmStateReference.  When the selected security model is the
      Transport Security Model (TSM), the expected behavior is for the securityName
      to be set by the TSM from the authenticated principal information stored in
      the tmStateReference by the TM.
      </t>
      
      <t>The Secure Shell protocol provides 
      a secure transport channel with support for channel authentication via 
      local accounts and integration with various external authentication and 
      authorization services such as RADIUS, Kerberos, etc. 
      The Secure Shell Transport Model <xref target="RFC5592"></xref>
      defines the use  of the Secure Shell protocol as the basis for a Transport Model.
      </t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="RADIUS Usage for SNMP Transport Models">
      <t>There are two use cases for RADIUS support of management access via SNMP.
      These are (a) service authorization and (b) access control authorization.
      RADIUS almost always involves user authentication as prerequisite to
      authorization, and there is a user
      authentication phase for each of these two use cases.  The first use case
      is discussed in detail in this memo, while the second use case is a topic
      of current research, and beyond the scope of this document.  This document 
      describes the way in which RADIUS attributes and messages are applied to 
      the specific application area of SNMP Transport Models.  User authentication
      and service authorization via RADIUS are undertaken by the secure transport
      module, that underlies the SNMP Transport Model.</t>
 
      <t>User authentication for SNMP Transport Models has the same syntax and
      semantics as user authentication for any other network service.  In the
      context of SNMP, the "user" is thought of as a "principal" and may represent
      a host, an application, or a human.</t>

      <t>Service authorization allows a RADIUS server to authorize an authenticated
      principal to use SNMP, optionally over a secure transport, typically using
      an SNMP Transport Model.
      This memo describes mechanisms by which such information can be requested
      from a RADIUS server and enforced within the NAS.  An SNMP architecture, <xref target="RFC3411"/>, does not make
      a distinction between user authentication and service authorization.
      In the case of existing, deployed security models, such as the User-based
      Security Model (USM), this distinction is not significant.  For SNMP Transport
      Models, this distinction is relevant and important.</t>
      
      <t>It is relevant because of the way in which SSH implementations have
      traditionally integrated with RADIUS clients.  Those SSH implementations
      traditionally seek to obtain user authentication (e.g., validation of a
      username and password) from an outside authentication service, often via a
      PAM-style interface.  The service
      authorization in traditional SSH server implementations comes via the
      restrictions that the operating system (OS) shell (and file system, etc.)
      place on the user by means of access controls tied to the username or the
      username's membership in various user groups.  These OS-style access
      controls are distinct from the service provisioning features
      of RADIUS.  If we wish to use existing SSH server implementations, or
      slightly adapt them, for use with SNMP Transport Models, and we wish
      to support RADIUS-provisioned service authorization, we need to be aware
      that the RADIUS service authorization information will need to be
      obtained by the relevant SNMP models from the SSH module.</t>
      
      <t>One reason that RADIUS-provisioned service authorization is important
      is that in many deployments, the RADIUS server's back-end authentication
      database contains credentials for many classes of users, only a small portion
      of which may be authorized to access the management interfaces of managed
      entities (NASes) via SNMP.  This is in contrast to the way USM for SNMP works,
      in which all principals entered to the local configuration data-store are
      authorized for access to the managed entity.  In the absence of 
      RADIUS-provisioned service authorization, network management access
      may be granted to unauthorized, but properly authenticated, users.  With
      SNMPv3, an appropriately configured Access Control Model would serve to
      alleviate the risk of unauthorized access.</t>

      <section title="RADIUS Authentication for Transport Protocols">
        
        <t>This document will rely on implementation specific integration of
        the transport protocols with RADIUS clients for user authentication.</t>
        
        <t>It is REQUIRED that the integration of RADIUS clients with
        transport protocols utilize appropriate "hint" attributes in RADIUS
        Access-Request messages, to signal to the RADIUS server the type
        of service being requested over the transport session.  Specific
        attributes for use with SNMP Transport Models are recommended in
        this document.</t>
        
        <t>RADIUS servers, compliant to this specification, MAY use RADIUS
        "hint" attributes, as described herein, to inform the decision whether
        to accept or reject the authentication request.</t>
        
      </section>

      <section title="RADIUS Authorization for Transport Protocols">
        <t>In compliance with RFC 2865, NASes MUST enforce implicitly mandatory
        attributes, such as Service-Type, within an Access-Accept message. 
        NASes MUST treat Access-Accept messages that attempt to provision 
        unsupported services as if they were an Access-Reject.  NASes SHOULD 
        treat unknown attributes as if they were provisioning unsupported services.
        See <xref target="RFC5080"></xref> for additional details.</t>
        
        <t>A NAS that is compliant to this specification MUST treat any RADIUS
   Access-Accept message that provisions a level of transport protection
   (e.g., SSH) that cannot be provided, and/or application service (e.g.,
   SNMP) that cannot be provided over that transport, as if an Access-Reject message had been received instead.  The RADIUS Service-Type 
   Attribute is the primary indicator of the service being provisioned,
   although other attributes may also convey service provisioning 
   information.</t>
        
        <t>For traditional SSH usage, RADIUS servers typically provision management
        access service, as SSH is often used to access the command line shell
        of a host system, e.g., the NAS. RFC 2865 defines two types of management
        access service attributes, one for privileged access to the Command Line
        Interface (CLI) of the NAS and one for non-privileged CLI access.  These
        traditional management access services are not used with SNMP.
        <xref target="RFC5607"></xref> describes
            further RADIUS service provisioning
        attributes for management access to the NAS, including SNMP access.</t>
        
        </section>

        <section title="SNMP Service Authorization">
          <t>The Transport Subsystem for SNMP <xref target="RFC5590"></xref> 
          defines the notion of a session, although the specifics of how sessions are
          managed is left to Transport Models.  The Transport Subsystem defines
          some basic requirements for transport protocols around creation and
          deletion of sessions.  This memo specifies additional requirements for
          transport protocols during session creation and for session
          termination.
          </t>
          
          <t>RADIUS servers compliant to this specification MUST use RADIUS
   service provisioning attributes, as described herein, to specify SNMP
   access over a secure transport.  Such RADIUS servers MAY use RADIUS
   "hint" attributes included in the Access-Request message, as described
   herein, in determining what, if any, service to provision.</t>
          
          <t>NASes compliant to this specification MUST use RADIUS
          service provisioning attributes, as described in this section, when 
          they are present in a RADIUS Access-Accept message, to determine 
          whether the session can be created, and they MUST enforce the service 
          provisioning decisions of the RADIUS server.</t>
          
          <t>The following RADIUS attributes MUST be used, as "hint" attributes 
          included in the Access-Request message to signal use of SNMP over a secure 
          transport (i.e., authPriv) to the RADIUS server:</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>Service-Type with a value of Framed-Management.</t>
              <t>Framed-Management-Protocol with a value of SNMP.</t>
              <t>Management-Transport-Protection with a value of Integrity-Confidentiality-Protection.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The following RADIUS attributes MUST be used in an Access-Accept message
          to provision SNMP over a secure transport that provides both integrity and confidentiality (i.e., authPriv): </t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>Service-Type with a value of Framed-Management.</t>
              <t>Framed-Management-Protocol with a value of SNMP.</t>
              <t>Management-Transport-Protection with a value of Integrity-Confidentiality-Protection.</t>
            </list></t>
          
          <t>The following RADIUS attributes MUST be optionally used, to authorize 
          use of SNMP without protection (i.e., authNoPriv):</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>Service-Type with a value of Framed-Management.</t>
              <t>Framed-Management-Protocol with a value of SNMP.</t>
              <t>Management-Transport-Protection with a value of No-Protection.</t>
            </list></t>
          
          <t>There are no combinations of RADIUS attributes that denote the equivalent
          of SNMP noAuthNoPriv access, as RADIUS always involves the authentication of a user
          (i.e., a principal) as a prerequisite for authorization.  RADIUS can be used to
          provide an "Authorize-Only" service, but only when the request contains a
          "cookie" from a previous successful authentication with the same RADIUS server
          (i.e., the RADIUS State Attribute).</t>
          
          <t>The following RADIUS attributes are used to limit the extent of a secure
          transport session carrying SNMP traffic, in conjunction with an SNMP Transport
          Model:</t>
          
          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>Session-Timeout</t>
              <t>Inactivity-Timeout.</t>
            </list></t>
            
          <t>Refer to <xref target="RFC2865"></xref> for a detailed description 
          of these attributes.
   The Session-Timeout Attribute indicates the maximum number of seconds
   that a session may exist before it is unconditionally disconnected.
   The Inactivity-Timeout Attribute indicates the maximum number of
   seconds that a transport session may exist without any protocol
   activity (messages sent or received) before the session is
   disconnected.  These timeouts are enforced by the NAS.</t>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section title="Table of Attributes" anchor="ATTRS">
        <t>
        Table 1 provides a guide to which attributes may be found
        in which kinds of packets, and in what quantity.
        </t>
            <figure title="Table 1">
                <artwork>
Access-
Request Accept Reject Challenge  #    Attribute
---------------------------------------------------------------------
0-1     0        0        0       1   User-Name        [RFC2865]
0-1     0        0        0       2   User-Password    [RFC2865]
0-1 *   0        0        0       4   NAS-IP-Address   [RFC2865]
0-1 *   0        0        0      95   NAS-IPv6-Address [RFC3162]
0-1 *   0        0        0      32   NAS-Identifier   [RFC2865]
0-1     0-1      0        0       6   Service-Type     [RFC2865]
0-1     0-1      0        0-1    24   State            [RFC2865]
0       0-1      0        0      27   Session-Timeout  [RFC2865]
0       0-1      0        0      28   Idle-Timeout     [RFC2865]
0-1     0-1      0-1      0-1    80   Message-Authenticator [RFC3579]
0-1     0-1      0        0     133   Framed-Management-Protocol  
                                       [RFC5607]
0-1     0-1      0        0     134   Management-Transport-Protection
                                       [RFC5607]
                </artwork>
            </figure>

<!-- Should the other two Radius Attribute Types that are defined in RFC 5607 be
     listed as well? They are:

             135  Management-Policy-Id
             136  Management-Privilege-Level

(from http://www.iana.org/assignments/radius-types)
-->

<t>Table 2 defines the meaning of the entries in Table 1.</t>

            <figure title="Table 2">
                <artwork>
0    This attribute MUST NOT be present in a packet.
0+   Zero or more instances of this attribute MAY be present in 
     a packet.
0-1  Zero or one instance of this attribute MAY be present in 
     a packet.
1    Exactly one instance of this attribute MUST be present in 
     a packet.
*    Only one of these attribute options SHOULD be included.
            </artwork>
            </figure>
<t>SSH integration with RADIUS traditionally uses usernames and passwords
(with the User-Password Attribute), but other secure transports
could use other authentication mechanisms, and would include
RADIUS authentication attributes appropriate for that mechanism instead
of User-Password.</t>

<t>This document does not describe the usage of RADIUS Accounting or
Dynamic RADIUS Re-Authorization.  Such RADIUS usages are not currently envisioned for
SNMP, and are beyond the scope of this document.</t>    
            
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This specification describes the use of RADIUS for purposes of
      authentication and authorization. Threats and security issues for this
      application are described in <xref target="RFC3579"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC3580"></xref>; security issues encountered in roaming are
      described in <xref target="RFC2607"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Additional security considerations for use of SNMP with secure 
      Transport Models <xref target="RFC5590"></xref> and the Transport 
      Security Model
      <xref target="RFC5591"></xref> are found in the 
      "Security Considerations" sections of the respective documents.</t>

      <t>If the SNMPv1 or SNMPv2c Security Model is used, then securityName
   comes from the community name, as per RFC 3584. If the User-based 
   Security Model is selected, then securityName is determined using
   USM.  This may not be what is expected when using an SNMP secure
   Transport Model with an external authentication service, such as
   RADIUS.</t>

      <t>Simultaneously using a secure transport with RADIUS authentication and authorization,
   and the SNMPv1 or SNMPv2c or USM security models is NOT RECOMMENDED.
   See the "Coexistence, Security Parameters, and Access Control" section of <xref target="RFC5590"></xref>.</t>
      
      <t>There are good reasons to provision USM access to supplement AAA-based access, however.
      When the network is under duress, or the AAA-service is unreachable, for any reason, it
      is important to have access credentials stored in the local configuration data-store
      of the managed entity.  USM credentials are a likely way to fulfill this requirement.
      This is analogous to configuring a local "root" password in the "/etc/passwd" file of a UNIX
      workstation, to be used as a backup means of login, for times when the Network 
      Information Service (NIS) authentication service is unreachable.</t>

      <t>The Message-Authenticator (80) Attribute <xref target="RFC3579"></xref> SHOULD be used with RADIUS
       messages that are described in this memo.  This is useful because the Message-Authenticator Attribute
      is the best available mechanism in RADIUS as it stands today to provide tamper-evident integrity
      protection of the service provisioning attributes in an Access-Accept packet.  It is slightly
      less important for Access-Request packets, although it may be desirable to protect any "hint" 
      attributes contained in those messages.  This protection mitigates the fact that RADIUS messages 
      are not encrypted and that attributes could be added, deleted or modified by an adversary in a 
      position to intercept the packet.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to acknowledge the contributions of David Harrington
      and Juergen Schoenwaelder for numerous helpful discussions in this space, and Wes Hardaker
      for his thoughtful review comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
    
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc2865;
      &rfc5080;
<!--     &tmsm; -->

<reference anchor='RFC5590'>
<front>
<title>Transport Subsystem for the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Harrington' fullname='David Harrington'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Schoenwaelder' fullname='Juergen Schoenwaelder'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June'  year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5590' />

</reference>

<!--      &tsm; -->

<reference anchor='RFC5591'>
<front>
<title>Transport Security Model for Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Harrington' fullname='David Harrington'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Hardaker' fullname='Wesley Hardaker'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5591' />

</reference>

<!--      &radman; -->

<reference anchor='RFC5607'>
<front>
<title>Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS) Authorization for Network Access Server (NAS) Management</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Nelson' fullname='David Nelson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Weber' fullname='Greg Weber'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' year='2009' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5607' />

</reference>

      
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
    
      &rfc2607;
      &rfc3162;
      &rfc3411;  
      &rfc3579;
      &rfc3580;
      &rfc4252;
    
<reference anchor='RFC5592'>
<front>
<title>Secure Shell Transport Model for Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Harrington' fullname='David Harrington'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Salowey' fullname='Joseph Salowey'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Hardaker' fullname='Wesley Hardaker'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2009' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5592' />

</reference>

<reference anchor="PAM" target="http://www.opengroup.org/rfc/mirror-rfc/rfc86.0.txt">
<front>
<title>UNIFIED LOGIN WITH PLUGGABLE AUTHENTICATION MODULES (PAM)</title>

<author initials="V" surname="Samar">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials="R" surname="Schemers">
    <organization />
</author>

<date month="October" year="1995" />

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Open Group RFC" value="86.0" />

</reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
