<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc number="5365" category="std">
<front>
    <title abbrev="SIP Multiple-Recipient MESSAGE Requests">
       Multiple-Recipient MESSAGE Requests in the&nbsp;Session&nbsp;Initiation&nbsp;Protocol&nbsp;(SIP)
    </title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Garcia-Martin" fullname="Miguel A. Garcia-Martin">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
          <street>Via de los Poblados 13</street>
          <city>Madrid</city> <code>28033</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
 	</postal>
        <email>miguel.a.garcia@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo" fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
	  <code>02420</code> 
	  <city>Jorvas</city> 
	  <country>Finland</country>
 	</postal>
	<email>Gonzalo.Camarillo@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2008" />

    <keyword>SIP</keyword>
    <keyword>multiple</keyword>
    <keyword>MESSAGE</keyword>
    <abstract>
    <t>
      This document specifies a mechanism that allows a SIP User Agent
      Client (UAC) to send a SIP MESSAGE request to a set of 
      destinations, by using a SIP URI-list (Uniform Resource
      Identifier list) service. The UAC sends a SIP MESSAGE request
      that includes the payload along with the URI list to the MESSAGE
      URI-list service, which sends a MESSAGE request including the
      payload to each of the URIs included in the list.
    </t>
    </abstract>
</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
<t>
<xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261 (SIP)</xref> is extended by <xref
target="RFC3428">RFC 3248</xref> to carry
instant messages in MESSAGE requests. SIP-based messaging, as
described in <xref target="RFC3428">RFC 3428</xref>, does not provide
a mechanism to send the same request to multiple recipients or
replying to all recipients of a SIP MESSAGE request. This memo
addresses these functions.
</t>
<t>
A first requirement can be expressed as:
</t>

<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t>REQ-1: It must be possible for a user to send an instant message
    request to an ad hoc group, where the identities of the recipients
    are carried in the message itself.</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>One possibility to fulfill the above requirement is to establish a
session of instant messages with an instant messaging conference
server, and exchange the messages, for example,
using <xref target="RFC4975">MSRP (Message Session Relay
Protocol)</xref>. While this option seems to be reasonable in many
cases, in other situations the sending user just wants to send a small
pager-mode instant message to an ad hoc group without the burden of
setting up a session. This document focuses on sending a pager-mode
instant message to a number of intended recipients.
</t>
<t>
To meet the requirement with a pager-mode instant message, we allow
SIP MESSAGE requests carry recipient-list bodies, i.e., URI lists in
body parts whose <xref target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition (RFC 2183)
</xref> is 'recipient-list', as specified in <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref>. A SIP MESSAGE
URI-list service, which is a specialized application service, receives
the request and sends a MESSAGE request including the received payload
to each of the URIs in the list. Each of these MESSAGE requests
contains a copy of the body included in the original MESSAGE request.
</t>
<t>
A second requirement addresses the "Reply-To-All" functionality:
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t>REQ-2: It MUST be possible for the recipient of a group
    instant message to send a message to all other participants that
    received the same group instant message (i.e., Reply-To-All).</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
To meet this requirement, we provide a mechanism whereby the MESSAGE
URI-list service also includes a URI list in body parts whose <xref
target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition (RFC 2183)</xref> is
'recipient-list-history', as specified in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. The 'recipient-list-history' body is sent
along with the instant message payload in each of the instant messages
sent to the recipients.
</t>
<t>
The User Agent Client (UAC) that sends a MESSAGE request to a MESSAGE
URI-list service needs to be configured with the SIP URI of the
service that provides the functionality. Discovering and provisioning
of this URI to the UAC is outside the scope of this document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Terminology">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref
target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref> and indicate requirement levels for
compliant implementations.
</t>
<t>
This document reuses the following terminology defined in <xref
target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref>:
</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Address-of-Record (AOR)</t>
  <t>User Agent (UA)</t>
  <t>User Agent Client (UAC)</t>
  <t>User Agent Server (UAS)</t>
</list></t>

<t>
This document defines the following new terms:
</t>
<t>
<list style='hanging'>
  <t hangText='MESSAGE URI-list service:'> 
       A specialized URI-list service that receives a MESSAGE request with a
       URI list and sends a similar MESSAGE request to each URI in the
       list. In this context, similar indicates that some SIP header
       fields can change, but the MESSAGE URI-list service will not
       change the instant message payload. MESSAGE URI-list services behave
       effectively as specialized B2BUAs (Back-to-Back-User-Agents). A
       server providing MESSAGE URI-list services can also offer
       URI-list services for other methods, although this
       functionality is outside the scope of this document. In this
       document, we only discuss MESSAGE URI-list services.
  </t>
  <t hangText='Incoming MESSAGE request:'> 
       A SIP MESSAGE request that a UAC creates and addresses to a
       MESSAGE URI-list service. Besides the regular instant message
       payload, an incoming MESSAGE request contains a URI list.
  </t>
  <t hangText='Outgoing MESSAGE request:'> 
       A SIP MESSAGE request that a MESSAGE URI-list service creates
       and addresses to a UAS (User Agent Server). It contains the
       regular instant message payload.
  </t>
  <t hangText='Intended recipient:'> 
       The intended final recipient of the request to be generated by
       MESSAGE URI-list service.
  </t>
  <t hangText='Reply-To-All:'>
       The ability of an intended recipient to receive a MESSAGE
       request that includes the payload and the list of recipients,
       and compose and send a MESSAGE request to the sender and the rest
       of the recipients. The replying entity can use a MESSAGE
       URI-list service if one is at its disposal or can create a
       sequence of regular single-recipient MESSAGE requests to each
       SIP AOR.
  </t>

 </list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Overview" anchor="overview">
<t>
A UAC creates a MESSAGE request that contains a multipart body
including a list of URIs (intended recipients) and an instant
message. The list of URIs is formatted according to the resource list
document format specified in <xref target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref>
and extended with the attributes defined in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. The
UAC sends this MESSAGE request to the MESSAGE URI-list service. On
reception of this incoming MESSAGE request, the MESSAGE URI-list
service creates a MESSAGE request per intended recipient (listed in
the URI list) and copies the instant message payload to each of those
MESSAGES. The MESSAGE URI-list service also manipulates the XML
resource list according to the procedures indicated in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>,
and attaches the result to each of the MESSAGE requests, along with
the instant message payload. Then the MESSAGE URI-list service sends
each of the created outgoing MESSAGE request to the respective
receiver.
</t>
<t>
The MESSAGE URI-list mechanism allows a sender to specify multiple
targets for a MESSAGE request by including an XML resource list
document according to <xref target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref> in the body of the
MESSAGE request extended with the attributes defined in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. This
resource list, whose <xref target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition (RFC
2183)</xref> is 'recipient-list', as specified in <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref>, includes the URIs of
the targets. Each target URI may also be marked to indicate in what
role the URI-list service will place the target (e.g., "to", "cc", or
"bcc"), and whether the target URI is expected to be anonymized or
not, according to the procedures described in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. When
the MESSAGE URI-list server expands the MESSAGE request to each
recipient, it includes (along with the instant message payload) a new
URI list (based on the received one), whose <xref
target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition (RFC 2183)</xref> is
'recipient-list-history', as specified in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. This
new URI list includes the list of non-anonymous "to" and "cc" targets,
allowing recipients both to get knowledge of other recipients and
to reply to them.
</t>



</section>
<section title="URI-List Document" anchor="sec-uri-list-document">
<t>
As described in <xref target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref>,
specifications of individual URI-list services, like the MESSAGE
URI-list service described here, need to specify a default format for
'recipient-list' bodies used within the particular service.
</t>
<t>
The default format for 'recipient-list' bodies for MESSAGE URI-list
services is the resource list document specified in <xref
target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref> extended with the <xref
target="RFC5364">copy control attributes</xref>. UACs
and MESSAGE URI-list services handling 'recipient-list' bodies MUST
support both of these formats and MAY support other formats.
</t>
<t>
As described in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>, each
URI can be tagged with a 'copyControl' attribute set to either "to",
"cc", or "bcc", indicating the role in which the recipient will get
the MESSAGE request. Additionally, URIs can be tagged with the
'anonymize' attribute to prevent that the MESSAGE URI-list server
discloses the target URI in a URI list.
</t>
<t>
Additionally, <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>
defines a 'recipient-list-history' body that contains the list of
intended recipients. The default format for 'recipient-list-history'
bodies for MESSAGE URI-list services is also the resource list
document specified in <xref target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref> extended
with the <xref target="RFC5364">copy control attributes</xref>. MESSAGE URI-list services MUST support both of these
formats; UASs MAY support these formats. MESSAGE URI-list servers and
UASs MAY support other formats.
</t>
<t>
The resource list document specified in <xref target="RFC4826">RFC
4826</xref> provides a number of features that are not needed by the
MESSAGE URI-list service defined in this document. The MESSAGE
URI-list service needs to transfer a simple flat list of URIs between
a UAC and the MESSAGE URI-list server and between the MESSAGE URI-list
server and the UAS. The service does not need hierarchical lists or
the ability to include entries by reference relative to the <xref
target="RFC4825">Extensible Configuration Access Protocol (XCAP)
</xref> root URI. Therefore, the MESSAGE URI-list service specified
herein only uses flat resource lists documents that do not contain
relative references.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Option-Tag"
anchor="sec-option">
<t>
This document defines the 'recipient-list-message' option-tag for use
in the Require and Supported SIP header fields.
</t>
<t>
  <list style='hanging'>
    <t>
      This option-tag is used to ensure that a server can process the
      'recipient-list' body used in a MESSAGE request. It also
      provides a mechanism to discover the capability of the server in
      responses to OPTIONS requests.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<xref target="sec-uac-procedures"/> provides normative procedures for the
usage of this option tag.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Procedures at the User Agent Client"
anchor="sec-uac-procedures">
<t>
A UAC that wants to create a multiple-recipient MESSAGE request
creates a MESSAGE request that MUST be formatted according to <xref
target="RFC3428">RFC 3428</xref> Section 4. The UAC populates the
Request-URI with the SIP or SIPS URI of the MESSAGE URI-list
service. In addition to the regular instant message body, the UAC adds
a recipient-list body whose Content-Disposition type is 'recipient-list',
specified in <xref target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref>. This body contains a URI list with the recipients of the
MESSAGE. Target URIs in this body MAY also be tagged with the
'copyControl' and 'anonymize' attributes specified in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. The UAC
MUST also include the 'recipient-list-message' option-tag, defined in
<xref target="sec-option"/>, in a Require header field.
</t>
<t>
UACs generating MESSAGE requests that carry recipient-list bodies, as
described in previous sections, MUST include this option-tag in a
Require header field. UAs that are able to receive and process
MESSAGEs with a recipient-list body, as described in previous
sections, SHOULD include this option-tag in a Supported header field
when responding to OPTIONS requests.
</t>
<t>
Multiple-recipient MESSAGE requests contain a multipart body that
contains the body carrying the list and the actual instant message
payload. In some cases, the MESSAGE request can contain bodies other
than the text and the list bodies (e.g., when the request is protected
with <xref target="RFC3851">S/MIME as per RFC 3851</xref>).
</t>
<t>
Typically, the MESSAGE URI-list service will copy all the significant
header fields in the outgoing MESSAGE request. However, there might be
cases where the SIP UA wants the MESSAGE URI-list service to add a
particular header field with a particular value, even if the header
field wasn't present in the MESSAGE request sent by the UAC. In this
case, the UAC MAY use the "?" mechanism described in Section 19.1.1 of
<xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref> to encode extra information in
any URI in the list. However, the UAC MUST NOT use the special "body"
hname (see Section 19.1.1 of <xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref>)
to encode a body, since the body is present in the MESSAGE request
itself.
</t>
<t>
The following is an example of a URI that uses the "?" mechanism:
</t>

<t>
sip:bob@example.com?Accept-Contact=*%3bmobility%3d%22mobile%22
</t>
<t>
The previous URI requests the MESSAGE URI-list service to add the
following header field to a MESSAGE request to be sent to
bob@example.com:
</t>

<t>
Accept-Contact: *;mobility="mobile"
</t>
<t>

The resource list document format specified in <xref
target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref> provides features, such as
hierarchical lists and the ability to include entries by reference
relative to the XCAP root URI. However, these features are not needed
by the multiple MESSAGE URI-list service defined in this
document. Therefore, when using the default resource list document,
UAs SHOULD use flat lists (i.e., no hierarchical lists) and SHOULD NOT
use &lt;entry-ref&gt; elements.
</t>


</section>

<section title="Procedures at the MESSAGE URI-List Service"
anchor="sec-exploder">
<t>
On reception of a MESSAGE request containing a URI list, the MESSAGE
URI-list service answers to the UAC with a 202 (Accepted)
response. 
</t>
<t>
  <list style='hanging'>
    <t>Note that the status code in the response to the MESSAGE does
    not provide any information about whether or not the MESSAGEs
    generated by the URI-list service were successfully delivered to
    the URIs in the list. That is, a 202 (Accepted) response means
    that the MESSAGE URI-list service has received the MESSAGE and
    that it will try to send a similar MESSAGE to the URIs in the
    list. Designing a mechanism to inform a client about the delivery
    status of an instant message is outside the scope of this
    document.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>
Since the MESSAGE URI-list service does not use hierarchical lists nor
lists that include entries by reference to the XCAP root URI, a
MESSAGE URI-list server receiving a URI list with more information
than what has just been described MAY discard all the extra
information.
</t>

<t>
If a MESSAGE request contains a Request-URI containing a URI that uses
the "?" mechanism (see Section 19.1.1 of <xref target="RFC3261">RFC
3261</xref>) and such URI contains the special "body" hname to include
an additional body, the MESSAGE URI-list server MAY discard the
contents of the "body" parameter.
</t>
<section title="Determining the Intended Recipient">
<t>
On reception of a MESSAGE request containing a URI list, a MESSAGE URI-list
service determines the list of intended recipients by inspecting the
URI list contained in the body. 
</t>

<t>
Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5363">
RFC 5363</xref>
discusses cases when duplicated URIs are found in a URI list.  In
order to avoid duplicated requests, MESSAGE URI-list services MUST
take those actions specified in <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref> into account to avoid
sending duplicated requests to the same recipient.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Creating an Outgoing MESSAGE Request" anchor="sec-exploder-outgoing">
<t>
Since the MESSAGE URI-list service behaves as a UAC for outgoing MESSAGE
requests, for each of the intended recipients, the MESSAGE URI-list
service creates a new MESSAGE request according to the procedures
described in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC3428">RFC
3428</xref>. Additionally, Section 5.3 of <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref> provides additional
general guidance in creating outgoing requests. This document also
specifies the following procedures:
</t> 
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service MUST include a From header field whose
value is the same as the From header field included in the incoming
MESSAGE request, subject to the privacy requirements (see <xref
target="RFC3323">RFC 3323</xref> and <xref target="RFC3325">RFC 3325
</xref>) expressed in the incoming MESSAGE request.
<list style="hanging">
  
  <t> 
  Note that this does not apply to the "tag" parameter.
  </t>
  <t>Failure to copy the From header field of the sender results in
  unacceptable security and privacy failures. Note also that
  this requirement does not intend to contradict requirements for
  additional services running on the same physical node. 
  Specifically, a privacy service (see <xref target="RFC3323">RFC 3323</xref>) can be co-located with the MESSAGE URI-list service, in
  which case, the privacy service has precedence over the MESSAGE
  URI-list service.
  </t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD generate a new To header field value
set to the intended recipient's URI. According to the procedures of
<xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref> Section 8.1.1.1, this value is
also expected to be equal to the Request-URI of the outgoing MESSAGE
request.
<list style="empty">
  <t>
  The MESSAGE URI-list service behaves as a User Agent Client; thus,
  the To header field should be populated with the recipient's URI.
  </t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD create a new Call-ID header field
value.
<list style="empty">
  <t>A Call-ID header field might contain addressing information that
  the sender wants to remain private. Since there is no need to keep
  the same Call-ID on both sides of the MESSAGE URI-list service, and
  since the MESSAGE URI-list service behaves as a User Agent Client, it
  is recommended to create a new Call-ID header field value according
  to the regular SIP procedures.
  </t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
If a P-Asserted-Identity header field was present in the incoming
MESSAGE request and the request was received from a trusted source, as
specified in <xref target="RFC3325">RFC 3325</xref>, and the first
hop of the outgoing MESSAGE request is also trusted, a MESSAGE
URI-list service MUST include a P-Asserted-Identity header field in
the outgoing MESSAGE request with the same received value. However, if
the first hop of the outgoing MESSAGE request is not trusted and the
incoming MESSAGE request included a Privacy header field with a value
different than 'none', the MESSAGE URI-list service MUST NOT include a
P-Asserted-Identity header field in the outgoing MESSAGE request.
</t>
<t>
If a MESSAGE URI-list service is able to assert the identity of a user
(e.g., using <xref target="RFC2617">HTTP Digest authentication scheme
as per RFC 2617 </xref>, <xref target="RFC3851">S/MIME as per RFC 3851
</xref>, etc.) and the service implements a mechanism where it can map
that authentication scheme to a user's SIP or SIPS URI, and subject to
the privacy requirements expressed in the incoming MESSAGE request
(see <xref target="RFC3323">RFC 3323 </xref>), the MESSAGE URI-list
service MAY insert a P-Asserted-Identity header with the value of the
user's asserted URI.
</t>
<t>
If the incoming MESSAGE request contains an Authorization or
Proxy-Authorization header field whose realm is set to the MESSAGE
URI-list server's realm, then the MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD NOT
copy it to the outgoing MESSAGE request; otherwise (i.e., if the
Authorization or Proxy-Authorization header field of incoming MESSAGE
request contains a different realm), the MESSAGE URI-list service MUST
copy the value to the respective header field of the outgoing
MESSAGE request.
</t>
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD create a separate count for the
CSeq header field <xref target="RFC3261"/> of the outgoing MESSAGE request.
</t>
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD initialize the value of the
Max-Forward header field of the outgoing MESSAGE request.
</t>
<t>
A MESSAGE URI-list service MUST include its own value in the Via
header field.
</t>


</list></t>
</section>

<section title="Composing Bodies in the Outgoing MESSAGE Request" anchor="sec-exploder-bodies">
<t>
When creating the body of each of the outgoing MESSAGE requests, the
MESSAGE URI-list service keeps the relevant bodies of the incoming
MESSAGE request and copies them to the outgoing MESSAGE request. The
following guidelines constitute exceptions to the general body
handling:
</t>

<t><list style="symbols">

<t>
A MESSAGE request received at a MESSAGE URI-list service can contain
one or more security bodies (e.g., <xref target="RFC3851">S/MIME, RFC
3851 </xref>) encrypted with the public key of the MESSAGE URI-list
service. These bodies are deemed to be read by the URI-list service
rather than the recipient of the outgoing MESSAGE request (which will
not be able to decrypt them). Therefore, a MESSAGE URI-list service
MUST NOT copy any security body (such as an <xref target="RFC3851">
S/MIME as per RFC 3851</xref> encrypted body) addressed to the
MESSAGE URI-list service to the outgoing MESSAGE request. This
includes bodies encrypted with the public key of the URI-list service.
</t>

<t>
The incoming MESSAGE request typically contains a recipient-list body
or reference, as indicated in <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref> with the actual list
of recipients. If this URI list includes resources tagged with the
'copyControl' attribute set to a value of "to" or "cc", the URI-list
service SHOULD include a URI list in each of the outgoing MESSAGE
requests. This list SHOULD be formatted according to the resource list
document format specified in <xref target="RFC4826">RFC 4826</xref>
and the copyControl extension specified in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref>. The
MESSAGE URI-list service MUST follow the procedures specified in <xref
target="RFC5364">RFC 5364</xref> with respect to handling of the
'anonymize', 'count', and 'copyControl' attributes.
</t>

<t>
If the MESSAGE URI-list service includes a URI list in an outgoing
MESSAGE request, it MUST include a <xref
target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition header field as per RFC 2183
</xref> with the value set to 'recipient-list-history' and a <xref
target="RFC3204">"handling" parameter as per RFC 3204</xref> set to
"optional".
</t>

<t>
If a MESSAGE URI-list service includes a URI list in an outgoing
MESSAGE request, it SHOULD use <xref
target="RFC3851"> S/MIME (RFC 3851)</xref> to encrypt the
URI list with the public key of the receiver.
</t>


<t>
The MESSAGE URI-list service SHOULD copy all the remaining message
bodies (e.g., text messages, images, etc.) of the incoming MESSAGE
request to the outgoing MESSAGE request.
</t>

<t>
If there is only one body left, the MESSAGE URI-list service MUST
remove the multipart/mixed wrapper in the outgoing MESSAGE request.
</t>
</list></t>


<t>
The rest of the MESSAGE request corresponding to a given URI in the
URI list MUST be created following the rules in Section 19.1.5, "Forming
Requests from a URI", of <xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref>. In
particular, Section 19.1.5 of <xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref>
states:
</t>
<t>
  <list style="empty">
    <t>
      "An implementation SHOULD treat the presence of any headers or
      body parts in the URI as a desire to include them in the
      message, and choose to honor the request on a per-component
      basis."  
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
SIP allows to append a "method" parameter to a URI. Therefore, it is
legitimate that the 'uri' attribute of the &lt;entry&gt; element in the
XML resource list contains a "method" parameter. MESSAGE URI-list
services MUST generate only MESSAGE requests, regardless of the
"method" parameter that the URIs in the list indicate. Effectively,
MESSAGE URI-list services MUST ignore the "method" parameter in each
of the URIs present in the URI list.
</t>

</section>
</section>


<section title="Procedures at the UAS">
<t>
A UAS (in this specification, also known as intended recipient UAS)
that receives a MESSAGE request from the MESSAGE URI-list service
behaves as specified in <xref target="RFC3428">RFC 3428</xref>
Section 7.
</t>
<t>
If the UAS supports this specification and the MESSAGE request
contains a body with a <xref target="RFC2183">Content-Disposition
header field as per RFC 2183</xref> set to 'recipient-list-history',
then the UAS will be able to determine the SIP Address-of-Record (AOR)
of the other intended recipients of the MESSAGE request. This allows
the user to create a reply request (e.g., MESSAGE, INVITE) to the
sender and the rest of the recipients included in the URI list.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Examples" anchor="sec-example">

<t>
<xref target="example-flow" /> shows an example of operation. A SIP
UAC issuer sends a MESSAGE request. The MESSAGE URI-list service
answers with a 202 (Accepted) response and sends a MESSAGE request to
each of the intended recipients.
</t>

<figure anchor="example-flow" title="Example of operation"><artwork><![CDATA[
+--------+        +---------+      +--------+ +--------+ +--------+
|SIP UAC |        | MESSAGE |      |intended| |intended| |intended|
| issuer |        | URI-list|      | recip. | | recip. | | recip. |
|        |        | service |      |   1    | |   2    | |   n    |
+--------+        +---------+      +--------+ +--------+ +--------+
    |                  |               |          |          |
    | F1 MESSAGE       |               |          |          |
    | ---------------->|               |          |          |
    | F2 202 Accepted  |               |          |          |
    |<---------------- |  F3 MESSAGE   |          |          |
    |                  | ------------->|          |          |
    |                  |  F4 MESSAGE   |          |          |
    |                  | ------------------------>|          |
    |                  |  F5 MESSAGE   |          |          |
    |                  | ----------------------------------->|
    |                  |  F6 200 OK    |          |          |
    |                  |<------------- |          |          |
    |                  |  F7 200 OK    |          |          |
    |                  |<------------------------ |          |
    |                  |  F8 200 OK    |          |          |
    |                  |<----------------------------------- |
    |                  |               |          |          |
    |                  |               |          |          |
    |                  |               |          |          |
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
The MESSAGE request F1 (shown in <xref
target="fig-incoming-message-to-exploder" />) contains a
multipart/mixed body that is composed of two bodies: a text/plain body
containing the instant message payload and an
application/resource-lists+xml body containing the list of
recipients.
</t>

<figure anchor="fig-incoming-message-to-exploder" title="MESSAGE
  request received at the MESSAGE URI-list server"> <artwork><![CDATA[
MESSAGE sip:list-service.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP uac.example.com
    ;branch=z9hG4bKhjhs8ass83
Max-Forwards: 70
To: MESSAGE URI-list service <sip:list-service.example.com>
From: Alice <sip:alice@example.com>;tag=32331
Call-ID: d432fa84b4c76e66710
CSeq: 1 MESSAGE
Require: recipient-list-message
Content-Type: multipart/mixed;boundary="boundary1"
Content-Length: 501

--boundary1
Content-Type: text/plain

Hello World!

--boundary1
Content-Type: application/resource-lists+xml
Content-Disposition: recipient-list

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resource-lists xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:resource-lists"
          xmlns:cp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:copycontrol">
  <list>
    <entry uri="sip:bill@example.com" cp:copyControl="to" />
    <entry uri="sip:randy@example.net" cp:copyControl="to"
                                       cp:anonymize="true"/>
    <entry uri="sip:eddy@example.com" cp:copyControl="to" 
                                      cp:anonymize="true"/>
    <entry uri="sip:joe@example.org" cp:copyControl="cc" />
    <entry uri="sip:carol@example.net" cp:copyControl="cc" 
                                       cp:anonymize="true"/>
    <entry uri="sip:ted@example.net" cp:copyControl="bcc" />
    <entry uri="sip:andy@example.com" cp:copyControl="bcc" />
  </list>
</resource-lists>
--boundary1--
]]></artwork></figure> 

<t>
The MESSAGE requests F3, F4, and F5 are similar in nature. All those
MESSAGE requests contain a multipart/mixed body that is composed of
two other bodies: a text/plain body containing the instant message
payload and an application/resource-lists+xml containing the list of
recipients. Unlike the text/plain body, the
application/resource-lists+xml bodies of MESSAGE requests F3, F4, and F5 are not equal to the
application/resource-lists+xml body included in the incoming MESSAGE
request F1. This is because the URI-list service has anonymized those URIs
tagged with the 'anonymize' attribute and has removed those URIs
tagged with a "bcc" 'copyControl' attribute; besides, the content
disposition of these bodies is different. <xref
target="fig-outgoing-message-from-exploder" /> shows an example of
the MESSAGE request F3.
</t>


<figure anchor="fig-outgoing-message-from-exploder" title="MESSAGE
 request sent by the MESSAGE URI-list server"> <artwork><![CDATA[
MESSAGE sip:bill@example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP list-service.example.com
    ;branch=z9hG4bKhjhs8as34sc
Max-Forwards: 70
To: <sip:bill@example.com>
From: Alice <sip:alice@example.com>;tag=210342
Call-ID: 39s02sdsl20d9sj2l
CSeq: 1 MESSAGE
Content-Type: multipart/mixed;boundary="boundary1"
Content-Length: 501

--boundary1
Content-Type: text/plain

Hello World!

--boundary1
Content-Type: application/resource-lists+xml
Content-Disposition: recipient-list-history; handling=optional

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resource-lists xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:resource-lists"
          xmlns:cp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:copycontrol">
  <list>
    <entry uri="sip:bill@example.com" cp:copyControl="to" />
    <entry uri="sip:anonymous@anonymous.invalid" cp:copyControl="to" 
                                                 cp:count="2"/>
    <entry uri="sip:joe@example.org" cp:copyControl="cc" />
    <entry uri="sip:anonymous@anonymous.invalid" cp:copyControl="cc" 
                                                 cp:count="1"/>
  </list>
</resource-lists>
--boundary1--
]]></artwork></figure> 

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations"
anchor="sec-security">
<t>
<xref target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref> discusses
issues related to SIP URI-list services. Implementations of MESSAGE
URI-list services MUST follow the security-related rules in <xref
target="RFC5363">RFC 5363</xref>. 
These rules include opt-in lists and
mandatory authentication and authorization of clients.
</t>
<t>
If the contents of the instant message needs to be kept private, the
User Agent Client SHOULD use <xref target="RFC3851">S/MIME as per RFC
3851</xref> to prevent a third party from viewing this
information. In this case, the user agent client SHOULD encrypt the
instant message body with a content encryption key. Then, for each
receiver in the list, the UAC SHOULD encrypt the content encryption
key with the public key of the receiver, and attach it to the MESSAGE
request.
</t>
</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
<t>
This document defines the SIP option tag 'recipient-list-message'
</t>
<t>
The following row has been added to the "Option Tags" section of the
SIP Parameter Registry:
</t>


<texttable anchor="ianatable2" title="Registration of the
	   'recipient-list-message' Option-Tag in&nbsp;SIP">
<ttcol width="37%">Name</ttcol>
<ttcol>Description</ttcol>
<ttcol width="15%" align="center">Reference</ttcol>
<c>recipient-list-message</c>
<c>The body contains a list of URIs that indicates the recipients of
the SIP MESSAGE request</c>
<c>[RFC&rfc.number;]</c>

</texttable>

</section>



<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks">
<t>
Duncan Mills supported the idea of having 1 to n MESSAGEs. Ben
Campbell, Paul Kyzivat, Cullen Jennings, Jonathan Rosenberg, Dean
Willis, and Keith Drage provided helpful comments.
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2183"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2617"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3204"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3323"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3325"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3428"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3851"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4826"?>

<!-- draft-ietf-sipping-uri-services became
      RFC 5363 -->

<reference anchor='RFC5363'>
<front>
<title>Framework and Security Considerations for Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) URI-List Services</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Camarillo' fullname='Gonzalo Camarillo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Roach' fullname='Adam Roach'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2008' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5363'/>

</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-sipping-capacity-attribute became RFC 5364 -->

<reference anchor='RFC5364'>
<front>
<title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) Format Extension for Representing Copy Control Attributes in Resource Lists</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Garcia-Martin' fullname='Miguel Garcia'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Camarillo' fullname='Gonzalo Camarillo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2008' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5364'/>

</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4825"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4975"?>

    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>

<!-- LocalWords: xref CDATA exploders BUA -->
