<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="5885" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" category="std">

        <front>
                <title abbrev="BFD VCCV">
Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) for
the&nbsp;Pseudowire&nbsp;Virtual&nbsp;Circuit&nbsp;Connectivity&nbsp;Verification&nbsp;(VCCV)
                        </title>

                <author role="editor" fullname="Thomas D. Nadeau" initials="T."
                        surname="Nadeau">
                        <organization>BT</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>BT Centre</street>
                                        <street>81 Newgate Street</street>
                                        <city>London</city>
                                        <code>EC1A 7AJ</code>
                                        <country>United Kingdom</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>tom.nadeau@bt.com</email>
                        </address>
                </author>

                <author role="editor" fullname="Carlos Pignataro" initials="C.M."
                        surname="Pignataro">
                        <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>7200 Kit Creek Road</street>
                                        <street>PO Box 14987</street>
                                        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
                                        <code>27709</code>
                                        <region>NC</region>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </postal>
<!--
                                <phone>+1-919-392-7428</phone>
                                <facsimile>+1-919-869-1438</facsimile>
-->
                                <email>cpignata@cisco.com</email>
                        </address>
                </author>



                <date month="May" year="2010"/>
                <area></area>

                <workgroup>PWE3</workgroup>

                <keyword>Pseudowire</keyword>
                <keyword>VCCV</keyword>
                <keyword>BFD</keyword>
                <keyword>VCCV-BFD</keyword>
                <keyword>PW OAM</keyword>


                <abstract>
                        <t>
   This document describes Connectivity Verification (CV) Types
   using Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) with 
   Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV).
   VCCV provides a control channel that is associated with a 
   pseudowire (PW), as well as the corresponding operations and 
   management functions such as connectivity verification to be 
   used over that control channel.
                        </t>


                </abstract>


        </front>


        <middle>

                <section anchor="Intro" title="Introduction">
                        <t>

   This document describes Connectivity Verification (CV) Types
   using Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) with
   Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV).
   VCCV 
   <xref target="RFC5085"/>
   provides a control channel that is associated with a
   pseudowire (PW), as well as the corresponding operations and
   management functions such as connectivity/fault verification to be
   used over that control channel.
                        </t>
                        <t>
BFD
<xref target="RFC5880"/>
is used over the VCCV control channel primarily as a pseudowire
fault detection mechanism, for detecting data-plane failures.
   Some BFD CV Types can additionally carry fault
   status between the endpoints of the pseudowire.  
   Furthermore, this information can then be translated into the native 
   Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) status codes used by the native access technologies, such as ATM,  
   Frame Relay, or Ethernet.  The specific details of such status 
   interworking are out of the scope of this document, and are only noted 
   here to illustrate the utility of BFD over
   VCCV for such purposes. Those details can be found in 
<xref target="OAM-MSG-MAP"/>.

                        </t>
                        <t>
   The new BFD CV Types are PW demultiplexer-agnostic, and hence
   applicable for both MPLS and Layer Two Tunneling Protocol version 3 
   (L2TPv3) pseudowire demultiplexers.
   This document concerns itself with the BFD VCCV operation
   over single-segment pseudowires (SS-PWs).
This specification
   describes procedures only for BFD asynchronous mode.

                        </t>
                </section> <!-- EO Intro -->

                <section anchor="Req" title="Specification of Requirements">
                    <t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
                    &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;,
                    &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
   		    &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
		    &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document
                    are to be interpreted as described in <xref
                    target="RFC2119"/>.
                    </t>
                        <t>
The reader is expected to be familiar with the terminology
and abbreviations defined in <xref target="RFC5085"/>.
			</t>

                </section> <!-- EO Req -->

                      <section anchor="BFD"
                       title="Bidirectional Forwarding Detection Connectivity Verification">
                              <t>
   VCCV can support several Connectivity Verification (CV) Types.
   This section defines new CV Types for use when BFD is
   used as the VCCV payload.

                              </t>

                              <t>

Four CV Types are defined for BFD.
<xref target="Table1"/> summarizes the BFD CV Types, grouping them by
encapsulation (i.e., with versus without IP/UDP headers) and by
functionality (i.e., fault detection only versus fault detection and status
signaling).


                              </t>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
    <texttable anchor='Table1' title='Bitmask Values for BFD CV Types' style='full'>
        <preamble/>
        <ttcol align='right'></ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>Fault Detection Only</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>Fault Detection and Status Signaling</ttcol>

        <c>BFD, IP/UDP Encapsulation (with IP/UDP Headers)</c>
        <c>0x04</c>
        <c>0x08</c>

        <c>BFD, PW-ACH Encapsulation (without IP/UDP Headers)</c>
        <c>0x10</c>
        <c>0x20</c>

        <postamble/>
    </texttable>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>



                      <section anchor="BFD-Oper"
                       title="BFD CV Type Operation">
                              <t>
   When heart-beat indication is necessary for one or more PWs, the
   Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) 
<xref target="RFC5880"/> provides a 
   means of continuous monitoring of the PW data path and,
   in some operational modes,
   propagation of PW receive and transmit defect state indications.
                              </t>

                              <t>
   In order to use BFD, both ends of the PW connection 
   need to agree on the BFD CV Type to use: 
<list style='empty'>
<t>
For statically provisioned
   pseudowires, both ends need to be statically configured to use the same
   BFD CV Type (in addition to being statically configured for VCCV with
   the same CC Type).
</t>
<t>
   For dynamically established pseudowires, both ends of the
   PW
   must have 
   signaled the existence of a control channel and the ability to run 
   BFD on it (see Sections <xref target="BFD-CV-Types" format="counter"/> and
   <xref target="Capa" format="counter"/>).
</t></list>
   Once a node has selected a valid BFD CV Type to use (either
   statically provisioned or selected dynamically after the node has
   both signaled and received signaling from 
   its peer of these capabilities),
   it begins sending BFD Control 
   packets:
                              </t>
                              <t>
<list style='symbols'><t>
   The BFD Control packets are sent on the VCCV control channel. The use 
   of the VCCV control channel provides the context required to bind and 
   bootstrap the BFD session, since discriminator values are not
   exchanged;
   the pseudowire demultiplexer field (e.g., MPLS PW Label or L2TPv3
   Session ID) provides the context to demultiplex the first BFD
   Control packet, and thus single-hop BFD initialization 
   procedures are followed 
(see Section 3 of <xref target="RFC5881"/>
and Section 6 of <xref target="RFC5882"/>).
</t><t>
A single BFD session exists per pseudowire. Both PW endpoints
take the Active role sending initial BFD Control packets with
a Your Discriminator field of zero, and BFD Control packets received
with a Your Discriminator field of zero are associated to the
BFD session bound to the PW.
</t><t>
BFD MUST be run in asynchronous 
   mode
(see <xref target="RFC5880"/>).
</t></list>
                              </t>

                              <t>
The operation of BFD VCCV for PWs is therefore symmetrical.
Both endpoints of the bidirectional pseudowire MUST send BFD messages
on the VCCV control channel.
                              </t>

                              <t>
The details of the BFD state machine are as per Section 6.2
of <xref target="RFC5880"/>.
The following scenario exemplifies the operation:
   when the downstream PE (D-PE) does not receive BFD Control
   messages from its upstream peer PE (U-PE) during a certain
   number of transmission intervals (a number provisioned by the
   operator as "Detect Mult" or detection time multiplier
   <xref target="RFC5880"/>),
   D-PE declares that the PW in its receive direction is down.
   In other words, D-PE enters the "PW receive defect" state for this PW.
   After this calculated Detection Time (see Section 6.8.4 of
   <xref target="RFC5880"/>),
   D-PE declares the session Down, and
   signals this to the remote end via the State (Sta)
   with Diagnostic code 1 (Control Detection Time Expired).
   In turn, U-PE declares the PW is down in
   its transmit direction, setting the State to Down
   with Diagnostic code 3 (Neighbor signaled session down)
   in its control
   messages to D-PE. U-PE enters the "PW transmit defect" state for this PW.
   How it further processes this error condition, and potentially conveys this
   status to the attachment circuits, is out of the scope of this
   specification, and is defined in
<xref target="OAM-MSG-MAP"/>.
                              </t>

                      </section> <!-- EO BFD Oper -->

                      <section anchor="BFD-Encap"
                       title="BFD Encapsulation">
                              <t>
   The VCCV message comprises a BFD Control packet
<xref target="RFC5880"/>
encapsulated as specified by the CV Type.

   There are two ways in which a BFD connectivity verification packet
   may be encapsulated over the
   VCCV control channel.
   This document defines four BFD CV Types (see
<xref target="BFD"/>), which
   can be grouped into two pairs of BFD CV Types
   from an encapsulation point of view.
See
   <xref target="Table1"/> 
   in <xref target="BFD"/>, which summarizes the BFD
   CV Types.


                              </t>
                              <t>

<list style='symbols'><t>
IP/UDP BFD Encapsulation (BFD with IP/UDP Headers)
</t></list>

<list style='empty'>
<t>
   In the first method,
   the VCCV encapsulation of BFD includes the IP/UDP headers
   as defined in Section 4 of
<xref target="RFC5881"/>. 
BFD Control packets are therefore transmitted in UDP with destination
port 3784 and source port within the range 49152 through 65535.
   The IP Protocol Number and UDP
   Port numbers discriminate among the possible VCCV payloads
   (i.e., differentiate among ICMP Ping and LSP Ping defined in
   <xref target="RFC5085"/> and BFD).
</t><t>
The IP version (IPv4 or IPv6) MUST match the IP version used for
signaling for dynamically established pseudowires or MUST be
configured for statically provisioned pseudowires.
The source IP address is an address of the sender.
   The destination IP address is a (randomly chosen) IPv4 address from
   the range 127/8 or IPv6 address from the range
   0:0:0:0:0:FFFF:127.0.0.0/104.
The rationale is explained in Section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC4379"/>.
The Time to Live/Hop Limit 
and Generalized TTL Security Mechanism (GTSM) procedures from Section 5 of
<xref target="RFC5881"/> apply to this encapsulation,
and hence the TTL/Hop Limit is set to 255.
</t><t>
If the PW is established by signaling, then the BFD CV Type
used for this encapsulation is either 0x04 or 0x08.
</t></list>
                              </t>
                              <t>
<list style='symbols'><t>
PW-ACH BFD Encapsulation (BFD without IP/UDP Headers)
</t></list>

<list style='empty'>
<t>

   In the second method, a BFD Control 
   packet (format defined in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC5880"/>)
   is encapsulated directly in the VCCV
   control channel (see Sections 6 and 8 of 
   <xref target="RFC5882"/>)
   and the IP/UDP headers are omitted
   from the BFD encapsulation.
      Therefore, to utilize this encapsulation,
      a pseudowire MUST use the PW Associated Channel Header (PW-ACH)
      Control Word format (see <xref target="RFC5586"/>)
      for its Control Word (CW) or L2-Specific
      Sublayer (L2SS, used in L2TPv3).
</t><t>
   In this encapsulation, a "raw" 
BFD Control packet (i.e., a BFD Control packet as defined in
Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC5880"/> without IP/UDP headers)
follows directly the PW-ACH.
The PW-ACH Channel Type indicates that the Associated Channel carries
"raw" BFD.
The PW Associated Channel (PWAC) is defined in Section 5
of <xref target="RFC4385"/>,
and its Channel Type field 
is used
to discriminate the VCCV payload types.
</t><t>
The usage of the PW-ACH on different VCCV CC Types is specified 
for CC Type 1, Type 2, and Type 3 respectively in
Sections 5.1.1, 5.1.2, and 5.1.3 of <xref target="RFC5085"/>,
and in all cases requires the use of a CW (see Section 7
of <xref target="RFC4385"/>).
When VCCV carries PW-ACH-encapsulated BFD (i.e., "raw" BFD),
the PW-ACH (pseudowire CW's or L2SS')
Channel Type MUST be set to 0x0007
to indicate "BFD Control, PW-ACH-encapsulated" (i.e.,
BFD without IP/UDP headers;
see <xref target="IANA.2"/>). This is to allow the identification
of the encased BFD payload when demultiplexing the VCCV control channel.
</t><t>
If the PW is established by signaling, then the BFD CV Type
used for this encapsulation is either 0x10 or 0x20.
</t></list>


                              </t>
                              <t>
In summary, for the IP/UDP encapsulation of BFD (BFD with IP/UDP headers),
if a PW Associated Channel Header is used, the Channel Type 
MUST indicate either IPv4 (0x0021) or IPv6 (0x0057). For the
PW-ACH encapsulation of BFD (BFD without IP/UDP headers),
the PW Associated Channel Header
MUST be used and the Channel Type MUST
indicate BFD Control packet (0x0007).


                              </t>
                      </section> <!-- EO BFD Encap -->

                      <section anchor="BFD-CV-Types"
                       title="CV Types for BFD">
                              <t>
   The CV Type is defined as a bitmask field
   used to indicate the specific CV Type or Types (i.e., none,
   one, or more) of VCCV packets that may be sent on
   the VCCV control channel. The CV Types shown in the table below augment
   those already defined in
<xref target="RFC5085"/>. Their values shown in parentheses
   represent the numerical
   value corresponding to the actual bit being set in the
   CV Type bitfield.

                              </t>
                              <t>
   BFD CV Types:

<list hangIndent="3" style="empty"><t>
The defined values for the different BFD CV Types for MPLS and L2TPv3 PWs are:
<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>   Bit (Value)   Description
   ============  ====================================================
   Bit 2 (0x04)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 3 (0x08)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
   Bit 4 (0x10)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 5 (0x20)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>
</t></list>

It should be noted that four BFD CV Types have been defined by
combining two types of encapsulation with two types of
functionality;
   see <xref target="Table1"/> in <xref target="BFD"/>.

                              </t>

                              <t>

   Given the bidirectional nature of BFD, 
   before selecting a given BFD CV Type capability to be used
   in dynamically established pseudowires, there 
   MUST be common CV Types in the VCCV capability advertised and 
   received.  That is, only BFD CV Types that were both advertised and 
   received are available to be selected.  Additionally, only one BFD CV 
   Type can be used (selecting a BFD CV Type excludes all the remaining BFD 
   CV Types).
                              </t>
                              <t>
   The following list enumerates rules, restrictions, and clarifications
   on the usage 
   of BFD CV Types:
   
<list style="numbers"><t>

BFD CV Types used for fault detection and status signaling
    (i.e., CV Types 0x08 and 0x20) SHOULD NOT be used when a
       control protocol such as LDP
       <xref target="RFC4447"/> or L2TPV3
       <xref target="RFC3931"/> is available that can
       signal the AC/PW status to the remote endpoint of the PW.
More details can be found in 
       <xref target="OAM-MSG-MAP"/>.

</t><t>

BFD CV Types used for fault detection only
    (i.e., CV Types 0x04 and 0x10) can be used whether or not a protocol
that can signal AC/PW status is available. This includes both
statically provisioned and dynamically signaled pseudowires.

 <list style='format 2.%d.' hangIndent='6'> <t>
    In this case, BFD is used exclusively to 
       detect faults on the PW;
       if it is desired to convey
       AC/PW fault status, some means other than BFD are to be used.
       Examples include using LDP 
       status messages when using MPLS as a transport (see 
       Section 5.4 of <xref target="RFC4447"/>), 
       and the Circuit Status Attribute Value Pair (AVP) in an L2TPv3 SLI message for L2TPv3
       (see Section 5.4.5 of <xref target="RFC3931"/>).
 </t></list>

</t><t>
Pseudowires that do not use a CW or L2SS using the PW
   Associated Channel Header MUST NOT use the BFD CV Types 0x10 or
   0x20 (i.e., PW-ACH encapsulation of BFD, without IP/UDP headers).

 <list style='format 3.%d.' hangIndent='6'> <t>
   PWs that use a PW-ACH include CC Type 1 (for both MPLS and L2TPv3
   as defined in Sections 5.1.1 and 6.1 of
   <xref target="RFC5085"/>), and MPLS CC Types 2 and 3 when
   using a Control Word (as specified in Sections 5.1.2 and 5.1.3 of
   <xref target="RFC5085"/>).
This restriction stems from the fact that the encapsulation
uses the Channel Type in the PW-ACH.
 </t><t>
        PWs that do not use a PW-ACH can use the VCCV BFD encapsulation 
	with IP/UDP headers, as the only VCCV BFD encapsulation 
	supported. Using the IP/UDP encapsulated BFD CV Types allows for
	the concurrent use of other VCCV CV Types that use an 
	encapsulation with IP headers (e.g., ICMP Ping or LSP Ping 
	defined in <xref target="RFC5085"/>).

 </t></list>

</t><t>

    Only a single BFD CV Type can be selected and used.
All BFD CV Types are mutually exclusive.
   After selecting a BFD CV Type, a node MUST NOT use any of the
   other three BFD CV Types.
</t><t>
Once a PE has chosen a single BFD CV Type to use, it MUST continue using it
until when the PW is re-signaled.
In order to change the negotiated and
selected BFD CV Type, the PW must be torn down and re-established.
</t></list>

                              </t>

                      </section> <!-- EO BFD CV Types -->



                </section> <!-- EO BFD -->



                <section anchor="Capa"
                 title="Capability Selection">

                              <t>



   The precedence rules for selection of various CC and CV Types
   is clearly outlined in Section 7 of
<xref target="RFC5085"/>. This section augments these rules
   when the BFD CV Types defined herein are supported. The selection 
   of a specific BFD CV Type to use out of the four available 
   CV Types defined is tied to multiple factors, as described in
<xref target="BFD-CV-Types"/>. Given that BFD 
   is bidirectional in nature, only CV Types that are both 
   received and sent in VCCV capability signaling advertisement can be 
   selected.  
   
                              </t>
                              <t>

When multiple BFD CV Types are advertised, and after applying the rules
in <xref target="BFD-CV-Types"/>, the set that both ends
of the pseudowire have in 
common is determined. If the two ends have more than one BFD CV Type in 
common,   the following list of BFD CV Types is considered in the order 
of the lowest list number CV Type to the highest list number CV Type, and the CV
Type with the lowest list number is used:

                        <list style="numbers">

<t>
      0x20 - BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated (without IP/UDP headers),
                 for PW Fault Detection and
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
</t><t>
      0x10 - BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated (without IP/UDP headers),
                 for PW Fault Detection only
</t><t>
      0x08 - BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
</t><t>
      0x04 - BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
</t></list>


                              </t>

                </section> <!-- Capa -->

                <section anchor="IANACons"
                 title="IANA Considerations">

                <section anchor="IANA.1"
                 title="MPLS CV Types for the VCCV Interface Parameters Sub-TLV">
                              <t>

   The VCCV Interface Parameters Sub-TLV codepoint is defined in 
<xref target="RFC4446"/>, and the
   VCCV CV Types registry is defined in <xref target="RFC5085"/>.
This section lists the new BFD CV Types.

                              </t>

                              <t>


   IANA has augmented the "VCCV Connectivity Verification (CV)
   Types" registry in the Pseudowire Name Spaces
   reachable from <xref target="IANA"/>.
   These are bitfield values. CV Type values 0x04,
   0x08, 0x10, and 0x20 are specified in 
<xref target="BFD"/> of this document.

                              </t>
<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
   MPLS Connectivity Verification (CV) Types:

   Bit (Value)   Description
   ============  ====================================================
   Bit 2 (0x04)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 3 (0x08)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and 
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
   Bit 4 (0x10)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 5 (0x20)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and 
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

                </section> <!-- IANA.1 -->

                <section anchor="IANA.2"
                 title="PW Associated Channel Type">
                              <t>

   The PW Associated Channel Types used by VCCV
   rely on previously allocated numbers from 
   the Pseudowire Associated Channel Types Registry 
<xref target="RFC4385"/> in the 
   Pseudowire Name Spaces reachable from 
   <xref target="IANA"/>.
                              </t>
                              <t>
   IANA has reserved a new Pseudowire Associated 
   Channel Type value as follows:

                              </t>

<figure>
<artwork>
Registry:
                                             TLV
 Value   Description                         Follows  Reference
 ------  ----------------------------------  -------  ---------------
 0x0007  BFD Control, PW-ACH encapsulation   No       [This document]
         (without IP/UDP Headers)
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

                </section> <!-- IANA.2 -->

                <section anchor="IANA.3"
                 title="L2TPv3 CV Types for the VCCV Capability AVP">
                              <t>

This section lists the new BFD CV Types
   to be added to the existing 
"VCCV Capability AVP" registry in the L2TP name spaces.
   The Layer Two Tunneling Protocol 
   "L2TP" Name Spaces are reachable from 
   <xref target="IANA"/>.

                              </t>

                              <t>

   IANA has reserved the following L2TPv3 Connectivity Verification (CV) 
   Types in the VCCV Capability AVP
Values registry.
                              </t>

<figure>
<artwork>
   VCCV Capability AVP (Attribute Type 96) Values
   ----------------------------------------------

   L2TPv3 Connectivity Verification (CV) Types:

   Bit (Value)   Description
   ============  ====================================================
   Bit 2 (0x04)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 3 (0x08)  BFD IP/UDP-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and 
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
   Bit 4 (0x10)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection only
   Bit 5 (0x20)  BFD PW-ACH-encapsulated, for PW Fault Detection and 
                 AC/PW Fault Status Signaling
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

                </section> <!-- IANA.3 -->
                </section> <!-- IANA -->

<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
                <section anchor="Congestion"
                 title="Congestion Considerations">
                              <t>
The congestion considerations that apply to
<xref target="RFC5085"/> apply to this mode of
operation as well.
This section describes explicitly how they apply.

                              </t>
                              <t>

BFD as a VCCV application is required to provide
details on congestion and bandwidth considerations.  BFD provides with a
desired minimum transmit interval and a required minimum receive interval,
negotiates the transmission interval 
using these configurable fields, and has a packet of
fixed size (setting the transmission rate).
Therefore, it results in a configuration limited bandwidth
utilization. As stated in <xref target="RFC5085"/>,
this is sufficient protection
against congestion as long as BFD's configured maximum bit-rate is
minimal compared to the bit-rate of the pseudowire the VCCV channel is
associated with. If the pseudowire
bit-rate can't be guaranteed to be minimal, like
potentially 
for highly variable bit-rate and/or congestion responsive pseudowires,
BFD will be required to operate using an adaptive congestion control
mechanism
(for example, including a throttled transmission rate on
           "congestion detected" situations, and a slow-start after
           shutdown due to congestion and until basic connectivity is
           verified).

                              </t>
                              <t>

Since the bandwidth utilized by BFD is configuration-limited, the VCCV
channel MUST NOT be rate-limited below this maximum configurable
bandwidth or BFD will not operate correctly. The VCCV channel could
provide rate-limiting above the maximum BFD rate, to protect from a
misbehaving BFD application, so that it does not conflict and can
coexist. Additionally, the VCCV channel SHOULD NOT use any additional
congestion control loop that would interfere or negatively interact with
that of BFD.

There are no additional congestion considerations.
                              </t>

                </section> <!-- Congestion -->

                <section anchor="Security"
                 title="Security Considerations">
                              <t>


   Routers that implement the additional CV Types defined herein
   are subject to the same security considerations as defined in
<xref target="RFC5085"/>,
<xref target="RFC5880"/>, and
<xref target="RFC5881"/>.
This specification does not raise any additional security issues beyond these.
The IP/UDP-encapsulated BFD makes use of the
TTL/Hop Limit procedures described in Section 5
of <xref target="RFC5881"/>,
including the use of the Generalized TTL Security Mechanism (GTSM)
as a security mechanism.

                              </t>

                </section> <!-- EO Security -->

                <section anchor="Acknowledgements"
                 title="Acknowledgements">
                        <t>

This work forks from a previous revision of the PWE3 WG document
that resulted in
<xref target="RFC5085"/>, to which a number of people
contributed, including
Rahul Aggarwal,
Peter B. Busschbach,
Yuichi Ikejiri,
Kenji Kumaki,
Luca Martini,
Monique Morrow,
George Swallow,
and others.

</t>
<t>
Mustapha Aissaoui,
Sam Aldrin,
Stewart Bryant,
Peter B. Busschbach,
Annamaria Fulignoli,
Vishwas Manral,
Luca Martini,
Dave McDysan,
Ben Niven-Jenkins,
Pankil Shah,
Yaakov Stein,
and
George Swallow
   provided useful feedback and
   valuable comments and suggestions improving newer versions of this document.
</t>

                </section> <!-- EO Ack -->


        </middle>
        <back>
                <references title="Normative References">

                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5085" ?>
                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4385" ?>

<!-- I-D.ietf-bfd-base to become RFC 5880 -->
<reference anchor='RFC5880'>
<front>
<title>Bidirectional Forwarding Detection</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Katz' fullname='Dave Katz'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ward' fullname='David Ward'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2010' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5880'/>

</reference>

<!-- I-D.ietf-bfd-v4v6-1hop to become RFC 5881 -->
<reference anchor='RFC5881'>
<front>
<title>Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD) for IPv4 and IPv6 (Single Hop)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Katz' fullname='Dave Katz'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ward' fullname='David Ward'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2010' />

</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5881'/>

</reference>

<!-- I-D.ietf-bfd-generic to become RFC 5882 -->
<reference anchor='RFC5882'>
<front>
<title>Generic Application of Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD)</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Katz' fullname='Dave Katz'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ward' fullname='David Ward'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2010' />

</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5882'/>

</reference>


                </references>
                <references title="Informative References">             

                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3931" ?>
                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4446" ?>
                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4447" ?>
                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4379" ?>


<!-- draft-ietf-pwe3-oam-msg-map -->
<reference anchor='OAM-MSG-MAP'>
<front>
<title>Pseudowire (PW) OAM Message Mapping</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Aissaoui' fullname='Mustapha Aissaoui'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Busschbach' fullname='Peter Busschbach'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Morrow' fullname='Monique Morrow'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Martini' fullname='Luca Martini'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Stein' fullname='Yaakov Stein'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Allan' fullname='David Allan'>
    <organization />

</author>

<author initials='T' surname='Nadeau' fullname='Thomas Nadeau'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='8' year='2010' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress'/>

</reference>


                        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5586" ?>

                <reference anchor="IANA" target="http://www.iana.org">
                    <front><title>Protocol Registries</title>
                   <author>
                   <organization>
                        Internet Assigned Numbers Authority
                   </organization>
                   </author>
                   <date />
                   </front>
                </reference>

                </references>

        </back>
</rfc>
