<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="4079" category="std">



    <front>
        <title abbrev="ACR Response Code">Rejecting Anonymous Requests in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>
    
        <author initials="J.R." surname="Rosenberg"
                fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
    
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <city>Edison</city> <region>NJ</region>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
    
                <email>jdrosen@cisco.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.jdrosen.net</uri>
            </address>
        </author>

    
        <date month="November" year="2007" />
    
        <area>RAI</area>
        <workgroup>SIP</workgroup>

        <abstract>
            <t>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) allows for users
            to make anonymous calls. However, users receiving such
            calls have the right to reject them because they are
            anonymous. SIP has no way to indicate to the caller that
            the reason for call rejection was that the call was
            anonymous. Such an indication is useful to allow the
            call to be retried without anonymity. This specification
            defines a new SIP response code for this purpose. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

<middle>


<section title="Introduction">

<t>
The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"/> allows
for users to make anonymous calls. In RFC 3261, this is done by
including a From header field whose display name has the value of
"Anonymous". Greater levels of anonymity were
subsequently defined in <xref target="RFC3323"/>, which
introduces the Privacy header field. The Privacy header field allows a
requesting User Agent (UA) to ask for various levels of anonymity,
including user 
level anonymity, header level anonymity, and session level
anonymity. <xref target="RFC3325"/> additionally defined the
P-Asserted-Identity header field, used to contain an asserted identity. RFC
3325 also defined the 'id' value for the Privacy header field, which
is used to request the network to remove the P-Asserted-Identity header field.
</t>

<t> Though users need to be able to make anonymous calls, users that
receive such calls retain the right to reject the call because it is
anonymous. SIP does not provide a response code that allows the User
Agent Server (UAS),
or a proxy acting on its behalf, to explicitly indicate that the
request was rejected because it was anonymous. The closest response
code is 403 (Forbidden), which doesn't convey a specific reason. While
it is possible to include a reason phrase in a 403 response that
indicates to the human user that the call was rejected because it was
anonymous, that reason phrase is not useful for automata and cannot be
interpreted by callers that speak a different language. An
indication that can be understood by an automaton would allow for
programmatic handling, including user interface prompts, or conversion to equivalent error codes in the Public 
Switched Telephone Network (PSTN) when the client is a gateway.  </t>

<t>
To remedy this, this specification defines the 433 (Anonymity
Disallowed) response code.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">

<t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119"/>.  </t>

</section>

<?rfc needLines="10" ?>
<section title="Server Behavior">

<t> A server (generally acting on behalf of the called party, though
this need not be the case) MAY generate a 433 (Anonymity Disallowed)
response when it receives an anonymous request, and the server
refuses to fulfill the request because the requestor is anonymous. A
request SHOULD be considered anonymous when the identity of the originator of
the request has been explicitly withheld by the originator. This occurs
in any one of the following cases: </t>

<list style="symbols">

<t>The From header field contains a URI within the anonymous.invalid
domain. 
</t>

<t>The From header field contains a display name whose value is either
'Anonymous' or 'anonymous'. Note that display names make a poor choice
for indicating anonymity, since they are meant to be consumed by
humans, not automata. Thus, language variations and even misspelling
can cause an automaton to miss a hint in the display name. Despite
these problems, a check on the display name is included here because RFC 3261
explicitly calls out the usage of the display name as a way to declare
anonymity. 
</t>

<t>The request contained a Privacy header field whose value indicates
  that the user wishes its identity withheld. Values meeting
  this criteria are 'id' <xref target="RFC3325"/> or 'user'. 
</t>

<t>The From header field contains a URI that has an
explicit indication that it is anonymous. One such example of a
mechanism that would meet this criteria is <xref
target="coexistence"/>. This criteria is true
even if the request has a validated Identity header field <xref
target="RFC4474"/>, which can be used in concert with anonymized From
header fields. 
</t>

</list>

<t>
Lack of a network-asserted identity (such as the P-Asserted-Identity
header field), in and of itself, SHOULD NOT be considered an
indication of anonymity. Even though a Privacy header field value of
'id' will cause the removal of a network-asserted identity, there is
no way to differentiate this case from one in which a network-asserted
identity was not supported by the originating domain. As a
consequence, a request without a network-asserted identity is
considered anonymous only when there is some other indication of this,
such as a From header field with a display name of 'Anonymous'.
</t>

<t>
In addition, requests where the identity of the requestor cannot be determined
or validated, but it is not a consequence of an explicit action on the
part of the requestor, are not considered anonymous. For example, if a
request contains a non-anonymous From header field, along with the
Identity and Identity-Info header fields <xref target="RFC4474"/>, but
the certificate could not be obtained from the reference in the
Identity-Info header field, it is not considered an anonymous request,
and the 433 response code SHOULD NOT be used. 
</t>

</section>

<section title="UAC Behavior">

<t>
A User Agent Client (UAC) receiving a 433 (Anonymity Disallowed) MUST NOT
retry the 
request without anonymity unless it obtains confirmation from the user
that this is desirable. Such confirmation could be obtained through
the user interface, or by accessing user-defined policy. If the user
has indicated that this is desirable, the UAC MAY retry the request
without requesting anonymity.  Note that if the UAC were to
automatically retry the request without anonymity in the absence of an
indication from the user that this treatment is desirable, then the
user's expectations would not be met.  Consequently, a user might
think it had completed a call anonymously when it is not actually
anonymous.
</t>

<t>
Receipt of a 433 response to a mid-dialog request SHOULD NOT cause the
dialog to terminate, and SHOULD NOT cause the specific usage of that
dialog to terminate <xref target="RFC5057"/>. 
</t>

<t>
A UAC that does not understand or care about the specific semantics of
the 433 response will treat it as a 400 response. 
</t>

</section>

<section title="433 (Anonymity Disallowed) Definition">

<t>
This response indicates that the server refused to fulfill the request
because the requestor was anonymous. Its default reason phrase is
"Anonymity Disallowed".
</t>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>
This section registers a new SIP response code according to the
procedures of RFC 3261.
</t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="RFC Number:"> RFC 5079</t>

<t hangText="Response Code Number:">433</t>

<t hangText="Default Reason Phrase:">Anonymity Disallowed</t>

</list>

</section>
<?rfc needLines="10" ?>

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t>
The fact that a request was rejected because it was anonymous does
reveal information about the called party -- that the called party does
not accept anonymous calls. This information may or may not be
sensitive. If it is, a UAS SHOULD reject the request with a 403
instead.
</t>

<t> In the Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN), the Anonymous
Call Rejection (ACR) feature is commonly used to prevent unwanted
calls from telemarketers (also known as spammers). Since telemarketers
frequently withhold their identity, anonymous call rejection has the
desired effect in many (but not all) cases. It is important to note
that the response code described here is likely to be ineffective in
blocking SIP-based spam. The reason is that a malicious caller can
include a From header field and display name that is not anonymous,
but is meaningless and invalid. Without a Privacy header field, such a
request will not appear anonymous and thus not be blocked by an
anonymity screening service. Dealing with SIP-based spam is not a
simple problem. The reader is referred to <xref
target="sipping-spam"/> for a discussion of the problem.
</t>

<t>
When anonymity services are being provided as a consequence of an
anonymizer function acting as a back-to-back user agent (B2BUA) <xref
target="RFC3323"/>, and the anonymizer receives a 433 response, the
anonymizer MUST NOT retry the request without anonymization unless
it has been explicitly configured by the user to do so. In essence,
the same rules that apply to a UA in processing of a 433 response
apply to a network-based anonymization function, and for the same
reasons.  
</t>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">

<t>
This document was motivated based on the requirements in <xref
target="tispan-req"/>, and has benefited
from the concepts in <xref
target="hautakorpi"/>. Thanks to Keith
Drage, Paul Kyzivat, and John Elwell for their reviews of this document.
</t>

</section>

</middle>
<?rfc needLines="35" ?>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3323"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4474"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3325"?>

<reference anchor="coexistence">
	<front>
<title>Coexistence of P-Asserted-ID and SIP Identity</title>
	<author initials="J" surname="Rosenberg" fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="June" year="2006"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-rosenberg-sip-identity-coexistence-00.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="tispan-req">
	<front>
	<title>
Input Requirements for the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) in support for  the European Telecommunications Standards Institute
</title>
	<author initials="R" surname="Jesske" fullname="Roland Jesske">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="July" day="3" year="2007"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-jesske-sipping-tispan-requirements-04.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="hautakorpi">
	<front>
	<title>
Extending the Session Initiation Protocol Reason Header with Warning Codes
</title>
	<author initials="J" surname="Hautakorpi" fullname="Jani Hautakorpi">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="G" surname="Camarillo" fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="October" year="2005"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hautakorpi-reason-header-for-warnings-00.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC5057">
	<front>
	<title>
Multiple Dialog Usages in the Session Initiation Protocol
</title>
	<author initials="R" surname="Sparks" fullname="Robert Sparks">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="November" year="2007"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC in" value="5057"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sipping-dialogusage-06.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="sipping-spam">
	<front>
<title>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and Spam</title>
	<author initials="C" surname="Jennings" fullname="Cullen Jennings">
<organization/>
</author>
	<author initials="J" surname="Rosenberg" fullname="Jonathan  Rosenberg">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="August" year="2007"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sipping-spam-04.txt"/>
</reference>

</references>

</back>
</rfc>


 
