<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC3777  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3777.xml'>

<!ENTITY RFC5078  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5078.xml'>

]>
<rfc category="bcp" updates="3777" number="5633" seriesNo="10"> 

  	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
 	<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
        <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
        
<front>
  <title abbrev="NomCom Issues">Nominating Committee Process: Earlier
  Announcement of Open Positions and Solicitation of
  Volunteers</title>

  <author initials="S." surname="Dawkins" fullname="Spencer Dawkins" role="editor">
    <organization abbrev="Huawei (USA)">Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
    <address>
      <phone>+1 214 755 3870</phone>
      <email>spencer@wonderhamster.org </email>
    </address>
  </author> 
  
  <date month="August" year="2009" />

<abstract>
<t>This document updates RFC 3777, Section 4, Bullet 13 to allow announcement of open positions 
	and solicitation of volunteers to be issued before a Nominating and Recall Committee 
		Chair has been named by the Internet Society President.
	</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

	<t>The Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), the Internet Architecture Board (IAB), 
		and the at-large IETF representatives to the IETF
		Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) are
		selected by a "Nominating and Recall Committee" (universally abbreviated as "NomCom").
		<xref target='RFC3777' /> defines how the NomCom is selected and the processes it follows as
		it selects candidates for these positions.
	</t>

	<t>This document describes an issue with <xref target='RFC3777' /> that causes an avoidable delay
		in the NomCom process and specifies a normative update to resolve the issue.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="background" title="Background" >

	<t><xref target='RFC3777' /> is the latest in a series of revisions to the NomCom process. 
		<xref target='RFC3777' /> has been updated once since 2004,
		but the update (<xref target='RFC5078' />) did not change normative text (it replaced a
		sample timeline).
	</t>

	<t><xref target='RFC5078' /> identifies a serial delay in the process described in 
		<xref target='RFC3777' />, in Section 4 
		("Nominating Committee Selection"), Bullet 13, which states:
	</t>

	<t><list>
		<t>The Chair obtains the list of IESG and IAB positions to be
       			reviewed and announces it along with a solicitation for names of
       			volunteers from the IETF community willing to serve on the
       			nominating committee.
		</t>
		
		<t>The solicitation must permit the community at least 30 days
       			during which they may choose to volunteer to be selected for the
      			nominating committee.
		</t>
	
		<t>The list of open positions is published with the solicitation to
  			facilitate community members choosing between volunteering for an
   			open position and volunteering for the nominating committee.
		</t>
	</list></t>

	<t>The result is that the Incoming NomCom Chair is the only
	person who can announce the list of open positions and
	solicitation for names of volunteers, a process that requires
	30 days for public solicitation.

	</t>
	
	<t>Since this is the first step in organizing the NomCom,
	delays in selecting the Incoming NomCom Chair translate
	directly into delays in issuing the solicitation and organizing the NomCom.
	</t>

	<t>This proved problematic in practice in 2008-2009, when Joel Halpern was named NomCom Chair less 
		than 30 days prior to the second IETF meeting of the
		year. If the 30-day solicitation had already taken 
		place, the NomCom could have conducted face-to-face interviews at the second IETF
		meeting, but since the required 30-day solicitation didn't start until Joel 
		was named, Joel was unable to assemble his NomCom before the second IETF meeting, 
		and the NomCom had to carry out these interviews using email and conference calls.
	</t>

	<t>It is desirable to allow the solicitation and announcement to take place in a timely manner 
		so that when 
		an Incoming NomCom Chair is named, the NomCom Chair can immediately begin executing the
		NomCom process.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="discussion" title="Discussion" >

	<t>  This document proposes that four weeks after the first IETF meeting each year, the Internet
		Society President will either announce an Incoming NomCom Chair, or will direct 
		the IETF Executive Director to issue the
  		announcement of open positions and the solicitation for names of
  		volunteers on behalf of the Incoming NomCom Chair.  
		This allows the search for the Incoming NomCom Chair and
  		volunteers to proceed in parallel.

	</t>

	<t>This process change covers only the announcement of open positions and solicitation for names
		of volunteers. This process change does not allow the NomCom process to move to
		completion without an Incoming NomCom Chair; 
		it is only to ensure that the Incoming NomCom Chair can begin
		executing the NomCom process without an avoidable
		delay and can use face-to-face time at 
		the second IETF meeting effectively for this purpose.
	</t>

	<t>During discussions in the IETF 74 timeframe, it was suggested that we also allow the Secretariat
		to perform other clerical tasks that aren't called out specifically in the NomCom 
		process but that clearly do not require NomCom Chair judgment. This document does
		not provide guidance about specific clerical tasks that would be appropriate for the 
		Secretariat to 
		carry out. Instead, either the Incoming NomCom Chair (if one has been selected)
		or the Outgoing NomCom Chair (if the search for an Incoming NomCom Chair is still underway)
		may request the Secretariat to perform these tasks, with appropriate notification to the 
		community.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="updatedtext" title="Updated Text from RFC 3777">

  <t><xref target='RFC3777' />, Section 4 ("Nominating Committee Selection"), Bullet 13, states:
	</t>

	<t><list>
		<t>The Chair obtains the list of IESG and IAB positions to be
       			reviewed and announces it along with a solicitation for names of
       			volunteers from the IETF community willing to serve on the
       			nominating committee.
		</t>
		
	</list></t>

	<t>This text is replaced with the following text:
	</t>

	<t><list>

		<t>The Chair (or the IETF Executive Director, if no Chair has been
     			named four weeks after the first IETF meeting
     			of the year) obtains the list of positions to
     			be reviewed and announces
     			it along with a solicitation for names of volunteers from the IETF
     			community willing to serve on the nominating committee.
		</t>

		<t>If the IETF Executive Director issues the solicitation for volunteers, the
			IETF Executive Director must also collect responses to the solicitation
			and provide the names of volunteers to the Incoming NomCom Chair when
			the Incoming NomCom Chair is named.
		</t>

		<t>At the Chair's request, the IETF Secretariat may perform other clerical
			support tasks, as long as the task being performed does not require NomCom Chair
			judgment, in the NomCom Chair's opinion, and as long as 
			the community is appropriately notified
			that this request is being made. This request may come from the Incoming
			NomCom Chair (if one has been selected for this NomCom cycle) or the Outgoing
			NomCom Chair (if the search for an Incoming NomCom Chair is still underway).
		</t>
		
	</list></t>

	<t>Note: This text no longer specifies the list of bodies that NomCom reviews, rather than adding
		IAOC to the list of bodies in the text, so that this text need not change further when 
		NomCom responsibilities change.
	</t>

</section>


<section anchor="nexttime" title="Possible Topics for Later Discussion">

	<t>This section contains topics that came up during discussion of this
  document but were ruled out of scope, because the goal for this document
  was incremental improvement, and these topics were more than incremental
  changes. They may be discussed further, or not, but we're less likely to
  forget them completely if we write them down.</t>

	<t><xref target='RFC3777' /> tightly couples the announcement of open positions and 
		call for volunteers, and this document didn't try to unravel these two separate
		actions. We had a request during discussion to separate them, so that a NomCom
		could consider the management structure of the IETF and the position descriptions
		that the leadership bodies provide, before announcing the positions being reviewed.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>This specification describes issues with the current IETF Nominating Committee process 
		<xref target='RFC3777' /> and proposes an update to
		avoid a serial delay.

<!--[rfced] As this document has been appoved for publication and,
presumably then, implementation, should the above "proposes" be 
changed to something like "provides"?-->

		No security considerations apply.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>The editor thanks the following folks who have provided useful observations and 
		guidance on previous versions of this document: Scott Bradner (who suggested that the
		IETF Secretariat have this responsibility), Brian Carpenter, Ralph Droms,
		Jim Galvin, Joel Halpern, Danny McPherson, and Pekka Savola.
	</t>

	<t>The editor also thanks the Wednesday evening plenary session participants during IETF 74
		who provided useful feedback on previous versions of this document <xref target='w74plen' />.

	</t>

</section> 

</middle>

<back>

	<references title="Normative References">

		&RFC3777;

	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">

		&RFC5078;

		<reference anchor='w74plen'>
       			<front>
            			<title>IETF 74 Wednesday Evening Plenary Minutes</title>
            			<author fullname='IETF Secretariat'>
					<organization/>
            			</author>

            			<date month='March' year='2009' />
        		</front>
        		<format type='TXT'
        		target='http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/09mar/plenaryw.html'
        		/>
    		</reference>

	</references>
</back>
</rfc>
