<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc number="5067" category="info">

	<front>
		<title abbrev="Infrastructure ENUM Requirements">Infrastructure ENUM Requirements</title>
		
		<author initials="S." surname="Lind" fullname="Steven Lind">
			<organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>180 Park Ave</street>
					<city>Florham Park</city>
					<region>NJ</region>
					<code>07932-0971</code>
					<country>USA</country>
				</postal>
				<email>sdlind@att.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="P." surname="Pfautz" fullname="Penn Pfautz">
			<organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>200 S. Laurel Ave</street>
					<city>Middletown</city>
					<region>NJ</region>
					<code>07748</code>
					<country>USA</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ppfautz@att.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date year="2007" month="November"/>
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>ENUM</workgroup>
		<keyword>ENUM</keyword>
		<keyword>Media Services</keyword>
		
		<abstract>
			<t>This document provides requirements for &quot;infrastructure&quot; or &quot;carrier&quot;
			 ENUM (E.164 Number Mapping), defined as the use of RFC 3761 technology to facilitate 
			interconnection of networks for E.164 number addressed services, 
			in particular but not restricted to VoIP (Voice over IP.) 
	 </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Infrastructure ENUM">
		<section title="Definition">

	<t>  Infrastructure ENUM is defined as the use of the
technology in <xref target="RFC3761">RFC 3761</xref> by the carrier-of-record (as defined below) for a specific E.164 
	number <xref target="ITU" /> to publish the mapping  of the E.164 number into a URI <xref target='RFC3986'></xref> that identifies a specific point of 
	interconnection to that service provider&apos;s network. 
	It is separate from any URIs that the end user, who registers their E.164 number,
	 may wish to associate with that E.164 number.
      </t>
<t>
"Infrastructure ENUM" is distinguished from "End User ENUM", defined in <xref target="RFC3761">RFC3761</xref>,
in which the entity or person having the right to use a
   number has the sole discretion about the content of the associated
   domain and thus the zone content. From a domain registration perspective, the end user number assignee
 is thus the registrant.

   Within the infrastructure ENUM namespace,  we use the term "carrier-of-record"
   for the entity having discretion over the domain and zone content and acting as the registrant.  
	The "carrier-of-record" is:
</t>
<t>
   o  The Service Provider to which the E.164 number was allocated for end user assignment, whether by the National Regulatory
   Authority (NRA)  or the International
   Telecommunication Union (ITU), for instance, a code under
   "International Networks" (+882) or "Universal Personal
   Telecommunications (UPT)" (+878) or,
</t>
<t>
   o  if the number is ported, the service provider to which the number was ported, or

</t>
<t>
   o  where numbers are assigned directly to end users, the service provider
that the end user number assignee has chosen to provide a Public Switched Telephone Network/Public Land Mobile Network (PSTN/PLMN) point-of-interconnect for the number.
</t>

<t>
It is understood that the definition of carrier-of-record within a given jurisdiction is subject to modification by national
authorities.  
	</t>
 		</section>
		<section title="Background">
	<t>
     Voice service providers use E.164 numbers currently as their main naming and routing vehicle.
 Infrastructure ENUM in e164.arpa or another publicly available tree allows service providers to link 
Internet-based resources such as URIs to E.164 numbers.
This allows service providers, in addition to interconnecting via the PSTN/PLMN (or exclusively), to peer 
via IP-based protocols. Service providers may announce all E.164 numbers or number ranges they host, 
regardless of whether the final end user device is on the Internet, on IP-based open or closed Next Generation Networks (NGNs), or
 on the PSTN or PLMN, provided that an access point of some type to the destination service provider's network
 is available on the Internet. There is also no guarantee that the originating service provider querying infrastructure ENUM is able to access the ingress network element of the destination 
provider's network. Additional peering and accounting agreements requiring authentication may be necessary.
 The access provided may also be to a shared network of a group of providers, resolving 
the final destination network within the shared network. 
</t>
 		</section>
</section>
<section title="Terminology">
			<t>
The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, 
&quot;MUST NOT&quot;, 
&quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
		
</section>
		<section title="Requirements for Infrastructure ENUM">
<t>
	  <list style='numbers'>
	
     <t>Infrastructure ENUM SHALL provide a means for a provider to populate DNS resource records (RRs) 
         for the E.164 numbering resources for which it is the carrier-of-record in a single common publicly 
	accessible namespace. The single common namespace ultimately designated may or may not be the same
         as that designated for End User ENUM (e164.arpa.) The
Fully-Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) in the resulting resource records will not necessarily 
   belong to or identify the carrier-of-record.

    	</t>
	<t> 
	Queries of infrastructure ENUM fully qualified domain names MUST return a result, even if the result is Refused (RCODE = 5). 
	Queries must not be rejected without response, e.g., based on access control lists.
	</t>

	<t>
	Infrastructure ENUM SHALL support RRs providing a URI that can identify a point 
	of interconnection for delivery to the carrier-of-record of communications addressed to the E.164 number.
	</t>

	<t>
	Infrastructure ENUM SHOULD be able to support an Internet
Registry Information Service (IRIS) <xref target='RFC3981'></xref> capability that allows qualified parties
	 to obtain information regarding the E.164 numbering resources and the corresponding
	 carrier-of-record.
	Determination of what information, if any, shall be available which parties for geographic numbers is a national matter.
	</t>

	<t>
	Implementation of infrastructure ENUM MUST NOT restrict the ability of an end user,
	 in a competitive environment, to choose a Registrar and/or name server
	 provider for End User ENUM registrations.
	</t>
	<t>
	The domain name chosen for infrastructure ENUM and any parent domains 
   MUST be hosted on name servers that have performance characteristics 
   and supporting infrastructure that is comparable to those deployed 
   for the Internet root name servers.  Those name servers for 
   infrastructure ENUM should be configured and operated according to 
   the guidelines described in <xref target='RFC2870'></xref>.
	</t>	
	<t>
	Infrastructure ENUM MUST meet all reasonable privacy concerns about visibility of
	 information over which an end user has no control. It should, for example, support mechanisms to
         prevent discovery of unlisted
	 numbers by comparison of ENUM registrations against directory listings, or inadvertent disclosure of user identity.
	</t>

	<t>
	Proposed implementations of infrastructure ENUM SHOULD:
	
	
<list style='letters'>
	<t>
	Minimize changes required to existing requirements that are part of RFC 3761.
	</t>
	<t>
	Work with open as well as closed numbering plans.
	</t>
	<t>
	Not require additional functionality of resolvers at large though they may require additional functionality in service provider resolvers
	that would make use of infrastructure ENUM.
	</t>
	<t>
	Minimize the number of lookups required to obtain as many NAPTR (Naming Authority Pointer) records
	 (end user and infrastructure) as possible.	
	</t>
	<t>
	Minimize knowledge of the numbering plan required of resolvers making use of Infrastructure ENUM.
	</t>
	<t>
	Maximize synergies with End User ENUM.
	</t>
	<t>
	Support interworking with private ENUM trees. (In this context, a private ENUM tree is one that is not under e164.arpa
        or whatever namespace is chosen for infrastructure ENUM but uses instead a privately held domain.)
</t>
</list>
</t>
	  </list>
</t>
	
  
		</section>




		<section anchor="S.security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>     Existing security considerations for ENUM (detailed in <xref target="RFC3761"></xref>) still 
     apply. Since infrastructure ENUM involves carriers where RFC 3761 mainly considered indviduals, implementations meeting
     these requirements SHOULD reconsider  the RFC 3761 security model given this difference in actors concerned.
     Note that some registration validation issues concerning 
     End User ENUM may not apply to infrastructure ENUM. Where the Tier 1 
     registry is able to identify the provider serving a number, e.g., 
     based on industry data for number block assignments and number 
     portability, registration might be more easily automated and a 
     separate registrar not required.
			</t>
			<t>

	Some parties have expressed concern that an infrastructure ENUM could compromise end user privacy
	by making it possible for others to identify unlisted or unpublished numbers based on their
	registration in ENUM. This can be avoided if providers register all of the their allocated (as 
	opposed to assigned) numbers. Unassigned numbers should be provisioned to route to the
	provider's network in the same fashion as assigned numbers and only then provide an indication
	that they are unassigned. In that way, provider registration of a number in ENUM provides
	no more information about the status of a number than could be obtained by dialing it.
</t>
<t>
	Implementers should take care to avoid inadvertent disclosure of user identities, for example, in the URIs returned
	in response to infrastructure ENUM queries.
</t>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
This document includes no actions to be taken by IANA. The architecture ultimately chosen to meet the requirements may require IANA actions.

</t>
		</section>

		

	</middle>
	<back>

		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="RFC2119">
				<front>
					<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
					<author surname="Bradner" initials="S.">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="1997" month="March"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC3761">
				<front>
					<title>The E.164 to Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI) Dynamic Delegation Discovery System (DDDS) Application (ENUM)</title>
					<author initials="P." surname="Faltstrom" fullname="P. Faltstrom">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Mealling" fullname="M. Mealing">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="April" year="2004"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3761"/>

			</reference>

			<reference anchor="ITU">
				<front>
					<title>The International Public Telecommunication Numbering Plan", Recommendation E.164</title>
					<author>
						<organization>
					International Telecommunication Union-Telecommunication Standardization Sector
						</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="February" year="2005"/>
				</front>

			</reference>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986" ?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3981" ?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2870" ?>

		</references>
 
	</back>
</rfc>
