<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI6741.1"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI6741.1"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.32 on 2008-01-31T18:55:35Z -->
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.32 on 2008-01-31T18:55:35Z -->
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.32 on 2008-01-31T18:40:00Z -->
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.32 on 2008-01-31T18:40:00Z -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!--
-->
<!--
-->
<!--
-->
<!--
-->
<!--
-->


]>

<rfc number="5139" category="std" updates="4119">
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Revised Civic LO">
      Revised Civic Location Format for Presence Information Data
      Format Location Object (PIDF-LO)
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson"
            fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Andrew</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box U40</street>
          <city>Wollongong University Campus</city>
          <region>NSW</region>
          <code>2500</code>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61 2 4221 2915</phone>
        <email>martin.thomson@andrew.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.andrew.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="J." surname="Winterbottom"
            fullname="James Winterbottom">
      <organization>Andrew</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box U40</street>
          <city>Wollongong University Campus</city>
          <region>NSW</region>
          <code>2500</code>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61 2 4221 2938</phone>
        <email>james.winterbottom@andrew.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.andrew.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2008"/>
    <area>Application</area>
    <workgroup>GEOPRIV WG</workgroup>
    <keyword>Location</keyword>
    <keyword>Civic Location</keyword>
    <keyword>PIDF-LO</keyword>
    <keyword>Civic Address</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>This document defines an XML format for the representation of
      civic location.  This format is designed for use with Presence
      Information Data Format Location Object (PIDF-LO) documents and
      replaces the civic location format in RFC 4119.  The format is
      based on the civic address definition in PIDF-LO, but adds
      several new elements based on the civic types defined for
      Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP), and adds a hierarchy to address complex road identity schemes.  The format also includes support for the xml&wj;:&wj;lang language tag and restricts the types of elements where appropriate.
      </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Since the publication of the original PIDF-LO civic specification, in <xref target="RFC4119"/>, it has been found that the specification is lacking a number of additional parameters that can be used to more precisely specify a civic location.  These additional parameters have been largely captured in <xref target="RFC4776"/>.
      </t>

      <t>This document revises the GEOPRIV civic form to include the additional civic parameters captured in <xref target="RFC4776"/>.  The document also introduces a hierarchical structure for thoroughfare (road) identification, which is employed in some countries. New elements are defined to allow for even more precision in specifying a civic location.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
      <t> The term <spanx style="verb">thoroughfare</spanx> is used in this document to describe a road or part of a road or other access route along which a final point is identified.  This is consistent with the definition used in <xref target="UPU-S42"/>.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Changes from PIDF-LO">

      <section title="Additional Civic Address Types">
        <t><xref target="RFC4776"/> provides a full set of parameters that may be used to describe a civic location.  Specifically, <xref target="RFC4776"/> lists several civic address types (CAtypes) that require support in the formal PIDF-LO definition that are not in <xref target="RFC4119"/>.
        </t>
        <t>These changes include new elements that are required to
        support more complex structures for naming street addresses.  This is described in more detail in <xref target="roadhier"/>.
        </t>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
        <texttable anchor="new_civic" title="New Civic PIDF-LO Types">
          <ttcol align="left">New Field</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">CAtype</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Example</ttcol>
          <c>BLD</c><c>25</c><c>Building (structure)</c><c>Hope Theatre</c>
          <c>UNIT</c><c>26</c><c>Unit (apartment, suite)</c><c>12a</c>
          <c>ROOM</c><c>28</c><c>Room</c><c>450F</c>
          <c>PLC</c><c>29</c><c>Place-type</c><c>office</c>
          <c>PCN</c><c>30</c><c>Postal community name</c><c>Leonia</c>
          <c>POBOX</c><c>31</c><c>Post office box (P.O. box)</c><c>U40</c>
          <c>ADDCODE</c><c>32</c><c>Additional Code</c><c>13203000003</c>
          <c>SEAT</c><c>33</c><c>Seat (desk, cubicle, workstation)</c><c>WS 181</c>
          <c>RD</c><c>34</c><c>Primary road or street</c><c>Broadway</c>
          <c>RDSEC</c><c>35</c><c>Road section</c><c>14</c>
          <c>RDBR</c><c>36</c><c>Road branch</c><c>Lane 7</c>
          <c>RDSUBBR</c><c>37</c><c>Road sub-branch</c><c>Alley 8</c>
          <c>PRM</c><c>38</c><c>Road pre-modifier</c><c>Old</c>
          <c>POM</c><c>39</c><c>Road post-modifier</c><c>Extended</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>A complete description of these types is included in <xref target="RFC4776"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
      <section anchor="roadhier" title="New Thoroughfare Elements">
        <t>In some countries, a thoroughfare can be broken up into
        sections, and it is not uncommon for street numbers to be
        repeated between sections.  A road section identifier is
        required to ensure that an address is unique.  For example,
        &quot;West Alice Parade&quot; in the figure below has 5 sections, each numbered from 1; unless the section is specified, "7 West Alice Parade" could exist in 5 different places.  The <spanx style="verb">RDSEC</spanx> element is used to specify the section.
        </t>

        <t>Minor streets can share the same name, so that they can only be distinguished by the major thoroughfare with which they intersect.  For example, both &quot;West Alice Parade, Section 3&quot; and &quot;Bob Street&quot; could both be intersected by a &quot;Carol Lane&quot;.  The <spanx style="verb">RDBR</spanx> element is used to specify a road branch where the name of the branch does not uniquely identify the road.  Road branches MAY also be used where a major thoroughfare is split into sections.
        </t>

        <t>Similar to the way that a road branch is associated with a road, a road sub-branch is associated with a road branch.  The <spanx style="verb">RDSUBBR</spanx> element is used to identify road sub-branches.</t>

        <t>The <spanx style="verb">A6</spanx> element is retained for use in those countries that require this level of detail.  Where <spanx style="verb">A6</spanx> was previously used for street names in <xref target="RFC4119"/>, it MUST NOT be used; the <spanx style="verb">RD</spanx> element MUST be used for thoroughfare data.
        </t>

         <figure>
           <preamble>The following figure shows a fictional arrangement of roads where these new thoroughfare elements are applicable.
           </preamble>
           <artwork>
      |                                                 ||
      |                                  ---------------||
      | Carol La.                           Carol La.   || Bob
      |                                                 || St.
      |              West Alice Pde.                    ||
 ==========/=================/===============/==========||===========
    Sec.1       Sec.2           Sec.3   |       Sec.4   ||   Sec.5
                                        |               ||
                              ----------| Carol         ||
                               Alley 2  |  La.          ||
                                        |               ||
</artwork>
         </figure>

         <section title="Street Numbering">
           <t>The introduction of new thoroughfare elements affects
	     the interpretation of several aspects of more specific civic
	     address data.

In particular, street numbering (the <spanx style="verb">HNO</spanx> element) applies to the most specific road element specified, that is, the first specified element from <spanx style="verb">RDSUBBR</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">RDBR</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">RDSEC</spanx>, or <spanx style="verb">RD</spanx>.
           </t>
         </section>

         <section title="Directionals and Other Qualifiers">
           <t>The <spanx style="verb">PRM</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">POM</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">PRD</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">POD</spanx>, and <spanx style="verb">STS</spanx> elements always apply to the value of the <spanx style="verb">RD</spanx> element only.  If road branches or sub-branches require street suffixes or qualifiers, they MUST be included in the <spanx style="verb">RDBR</spanx> or <spanx style="verb">RDSUBBR</spanx> element text.
           </t>
         </section>

      </section>

      <section title="Country Element">
        <t>The <spanx style="verb">country</spanx> element differs from that defined in <xref target="RFC4119"/> in that it now restricts the value space of the element to two uppercase characters, which correspond to the alpha-2 codes in <xref target="ISO.3166-1"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="A1 Element">
        <t>The <spanx style="verb">A1</spanx> element is used for the top-level subdivision within a country.  In the absence of a country-specific guide on how to use the A-series of elements, the second part of the ISO 3166-2 code <xref target="ISO.3166-2"/> for a country subdivision SHOULD be used.  The ISO 3166-2 code is formed of a country code and hyphen plus a code of one, two, or three characters or numerals.  For the <spanx style="verb">A1</spanx> element, the leading country code and hyphen are omitted and only the subdivision code is included.
        </t>

        <t>For example, the codes for Canada include CA-BC, CA-ON,
        CA-QC; Luxembourg has just three single-character codes, LU-D,
        LU-G, and LU-L; Australia uses both two- and three-character
        codes, AU-ACT, AU-NSW, AU-NT; and France uses numerical codes for mainland France and letters for territories, FR-75, FR-NC.  This results in the following fragments:
        <list>
          <t>&lt;country&gt;CA&lt;/country&gt;&lt;A1&gt;ON&lt;/A1&gt;</t>
          <t>&lt;country&gt;LU&lt;/country&gt;&lt;A1&gt;L&lt;/A1&gt;</t>
          <t>&lt;country&gt;AU&lt;/country&gt;&lt;A1&gt;ACT&lt;/A1&gt;</t>
          <t>&lt;country&gt;FR&lt;/country&gt;&lt;A1&gt;75&lt;/A1&gt;</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Languages and Scripts">
        <t>The XML schema defined for civic addresses allows for the addition of the <spanx style="verb">xml&wj;:&wj;lang</spanx> attribute to all elements except <spanx style="verb">country</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">PLC</spanx>, which both contain language-neutral values.  The range of allowed values for <spanx style="verb">country</spanx> is defined in <xref target="ISO.3166-1"/>; the range of allowed values for <spanx style="verb">PLC</spanx> is described in the IANA registry defined by <xref target="RFC4589" />.
        </t>

        <t>The <spanx style="verb">script</spanx> field defined in <xref target="RFC4776"/> is omitted in favor of using the <spanx style="verb">xml&wj;:&wj;lang</spanx> attribute with a script subtag <xref target="RFC4646"/>.
        </t>

        <t>It is RECOMMENDED that each <spanx style="verb">civicAddress</spanx> element use one language only, or a combination of languages that is consistent.  Where a civic location is represented in multiple languages, multiple <spanx style="verb">civicAddress</spanx> elements SHOULD be included in the PIDF-LO document.  For civic addresses that form a complex to describe the same location, these SHOULD be inserted into the same tuple.
        </t>

        <section title="Converting from the DHCP Format">
          <t>The <xref target="RFC4776">DHCP format for civic addresses</xref> permits the inclusion of an element multiple times with different languages or scripts.  However, this XML form only permits a single instance of each element.  Multiple <spanx style="verb">civicAddress</spanx> elements are required if any element is duplicated with different languages.  If the same language and script are used for all elements, or no elements are duplicated, the format can be converted into a single civic address.
          </t>

          <t>Where there are duplicated elements in different languages, a <spanx style="verb">civicAddress</spanx> element is created for each language that is present.  All elements that are in that language are included.  Elements that are language independent, like the <spanx style="verb">country</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">PLC</spanx> elements, are added to all <spanx style="verb">civicAddress</spanx> elements.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Combining Multiple Elements Based on Language Preferences">
          <t>If the receiver of the XML representation is known, and that receiver has indicated language preferences, a single XML format can be constructed using those preferences.  For example, language preferences can be indicated by the <spanx style="verb">Accept-Language</spanx> header in the SIP or HTTP protocols.
          </t>

          <t>All elements that have only one value, irrespective of language, are used.  Where multiple values exist, each value is assigned a weighting based on the language preferences.  The value with the highest weighting is selected.  An arbitrary value is selected if two values have the same preference, if there is no preference for the available languages, or if there are conflicting values with the same language.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Whitespace">
        <t>The XML schema <xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"/> defined in <xref target="schema"/> uses a base type of <spanx style="verb">token</spanx> instead of <spanx style="verb">string</spanx> as used in <xref target="RFC4119"/>.
        </t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>The <spanx style="verb">token</spanx> type ensures that whitespace within instance documents is normalized and collapsed before being passed to a processor.  This ensures that the following fragments are considered equivalent by XML processors:</preamble>
          <artwork>
&lt;A4&gt;North Wollongong&lt;/A4&gt;

&lt;A1&gt;North
  Wollongong&lt;/A1&gt;

&lt;A1&gt;
  North   Wollongong
  &lt;/A1&gt;
</artwork>
          <postamble>Whitespace may still be included in values by using character references, such as <spanx style="verb">&amp;#x20;</spanx>.</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="schema" title="Civic Address Schema">
        <figure>
          <artwork>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;xs:schema
  targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:ca="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr"
  xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
  elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified"&gt;

  &lt;xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
             schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/&gt;

  &lt;xs:simpleType name="iso3166a2"&gt;
    &lt;xs:restriction base="xs:token"&gt;
      &lt;xs:pattern value="[A-Z]{2}"/&gt;
    &lt;/xs:restriction&gt;
  &lt;/xs:simpleType&gt;

  &lt;xs:complexType name="caType"&gt;
    &lt;xs:simpleContent&gt;
      &lt;xs:extension base="xs:token"&gt;
        &lt;xs:attribute ref="xml:lang" use="optional"/&gt;
      &lt;/xs:extension&gt;
    &lt;/xs:simpleContent&gt;
  &lt;/xs:complexType&gt;

  &lt;xs:element name="civicAddress" type="ca:civicAddress"/&gt;
  &lt;xs:complexType name="civicAddress"&gt;
    &lt;xs:sequence&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="country" type="ca:iso3166a2" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A1" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A2" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A3" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A4" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A5" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="A6" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="PRM" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="PRD" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="RD" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="STS" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="POD" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="POM" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="RDSEC" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="RDBR" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="RDSUBBR" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="HNO" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="HNS" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="LMK" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="LOC" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="FLR" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="NAM" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="PC" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="BLD" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="UNIT" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="ROOM" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="SEAT" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="PLC" type="xs:token" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="PCN" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="POBOX" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="ADDCODE" type="ca:caType" minOccurs="0"/&gt;
      &lt;xs:any namespace="##other" processContents="lax"
              minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/&gt;
    &lt;/xs:sequence&gt;
    &lt;xs:anyAttribute namespace="##any" processContents="lax"/&gt;
  &lt;/xs:complexType&gt;
&lt;/xs:schema&gt;
</artwork>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example" title="Example">
        <figure>
          <artwork>

&lt;civicAddress xml:lang="en-AU"
  xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr"&gt;
  &lt;country&gt;AU&lt;/country&gt;
  &lt;A1&gt;NSW&lt;/A1&gt;
  &lt;A3&gt;     Wollongong
  &lt;/A3&gt;&lt;A4&gt;North Wollongong
  &lt;/A4&gt;
  &lt;RD&gt;Flinders&lt;/RD&gt;&lt;STS&gt;Street&lt;/STS&gt;
  &lt;RDBR&gt;Campbell Street&lt;/RDBR&gt;
  &lt;LMK&gt;
    Gilligan's Island
  &lt;/LMK&gt; &lt;LOC&gt;Corner&lt;/LOC&gt;
  &lt;NAM&gt; Video Rental Store &lt;/NAM&gt;
  &lt;PC&gt;2500&lt;/PC&gt;
  &lt;ROOM&gt; Westerns and Classics &lt;/ROOM&gt;
  &lt;PLC&gt;store&lt;/PLC&gt;
  &lt;POBOX&gt;Private Box 15&lt;/POBOX&gt;
&lt;/civicAddress&gt;
</artwork>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The XML representation described in this document is designed for inclusion in a PIDF-LO document.  As such, it is subject to the same security considerations as are described in <xref target="RFC4119"/>.  Considerations relating to the inclusion of this representation in other XML documents are outside the scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <section title="URN sub-namespace registration for 'urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr'">
        <t>This document defines a new XML namespace (as per the
guidelines in <xref target="RFC3688"/>) that has been registered with IANA.
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr</t>
          <t hangText="Registrant Contact:">IETF, GEOPRIV working group (geopriv@ietf.org), Martin Thomson (martin.thomson@andrew.com).</t>

          <t hangText="XML:">
            <figure>
              <artwork>
      BEGIN
        &lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
        &lt;!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
          "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd"&gt;
        &lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;GEOPRIV Civic Address&lt;/title&gt;
          &lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Format for Distributing Civic Address in GEOPRIV&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr&lt;/h2&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5139.txt"&gt;
                RFC5139&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/body&gt;
        &lt;/html&gt;
      END
</artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="XML Schema Registration">
        <t>This section registers an XML schema as per the procedures in <xref target="RFC3688"/>.
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:pidf:geopriv10:civicAddr</t>
          <t hangText="Registrant Contact:">IETF, GEOPRIV working group (geopriv@ietf.org), Martin Thomson (martin.thomson@andrew.com).</t>
          <t>The XML for this schema can be found as the entirety of <xref target="schema"/> of this document.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="CAtype Registry Update">
        <t>This document updates the civic address type registry established by <xref target="RFC4776"/>.  The <spanx style="verb">PIDF</spanx> column of the CAtypes table has been updated to include the types shown in the first column of <xref target="new_civic"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17491' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="429:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028.xml"?>

<reference anchor='W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028'
           target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028'>
<front>
<title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</title>

<author initials='P.' surname='Biron' fullname='Paul V. Biron'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A.' surname='Malhotra' fullname='Ashok Malhotra'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='28' year='2004' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation' value='REC-xmlschema-2-20041028' />
<format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="430:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4119.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4119'>

<front>
<title>A Presence-based GEOPRIV Location Object Format</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes an object format for carrying geographical information on the Internet.  This location object extends the Presence Information Data Format (PIDF), which was designed for communicating privacy-sensitive presence information and which has similar properties. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='53522' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4119.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="431:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4589.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4589'>

<front>
<title>Location Types Registry</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='H. Tschofenig'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This document creates a registry for describing the types of places a human or end system might be found.  The registry is then referenced by other protocols that need a common set of location terms as protocol constants.  Examples of location terms defined in this document include aircraft, office, and train station. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4589' />
<format type='TXT' octets='24037' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4589.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="432:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4646.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4646'>

<front>
<title>Tags for Identifying Languages</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Phillips' fullname='A. Phillips'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Davis' fullname='M. Davis'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='September' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the structure, content, construction, and semantics of language tags for use in cases where it is desirable to indicate the language used in an information object.  It also describes how to register values for use in language tags and the creation of user-defined extensions for private interchange.  This document, in combination with RFC 4647, replaces RFC 3066, which replaced RFC 1766.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='47' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4646' />
<format type='TXT' octets='135810' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4646.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="433:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4776.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4776'>

<front>
<title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCPv4 and DHCPv6) Option for Civic Addresses Configuration Information</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCPv4 and DHCPv6) option containing the civic location of the client or the DHCP server.  The Location Configuration Information (LCI) includes information about the country, administrative units such as states, provinces, and cities, as well as street addresses, postal community names, and building information.  The option allows multiple renditions of the same address in different scripts and languages. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4776' />
<format type='TXT' octets='45495' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4776.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="434:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>

      <reference anchor="ISO.3166-1">
        <front>
          <title>Codes for the representation of names of countries and their subdivisions - Part 1: Country codes</title>
          <author>
            <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1997"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 3166-1:1997"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISO.3166-2">
        <front>
          <title>Codes for the representation of names of countries and their subdivisions - Part 2: Country subdivision code</title>
          <author>
            <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 3166-2:1998"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3688'>

<front>
<title>The IETF XML Registry</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Mealling' fullname='M. Mealling'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2004' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes an IANA maintained registry for IETF standards which use Extensible Markup Language (XML) related items such as Namespaces, Document Type Declarations (DTDs), Schemas, and Resource Description Framework (RDF) Schemas.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='81' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3688' />
<format type='TXT' octets='17325' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3688.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="460:/tmp/CGI14283.1"?>
      <reference anchor="UPU-S42">
        <front>
          <title>International Postal Address Components and Templates</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Universal Postal Union (UPU)</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="06" month="July" year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="UPS" value="SB42-4"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Henning Schulzrinne for his assistance in defining the additional civic address types, particularly his research into different addressing schemes that led to the introduction of the thoroughfare elements.  Rohan Mahy suggested the ISO 3166-2 recommendation for A1.  In addition, we would like to thank Jon Peterson for his work in defining the PIDF-LO.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
