<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC3777 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3777.xml">
]>
	<rfc number="5078" category="info" updates="3777"> 

  	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>


<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

 	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>


<front>
  <title abbrev="NomCom Starting Earlier">IAB and IESG Selection, Confirmation, and Recall Process: 
       Revision of the Nominating and Recall Committees Timeline</title>

  <author initials="S." surname="Dawkins" fullname="Spencer Dawkins">
    <organization abbrev="Huawei (USA)">Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
	  <street> 1547 Rivercrest Blvd.</street>
	  <city> Allen</city> <region>TX </region>
	  <code>75002 </code> <country>USA</country> </postal>
      <phone>+1 469 229 5397</phone>
      <email>spencer@mcsr-labs.org </email>
    </address>
  </author>  
  
   <date month="October" year="2007" />

  <area>General</area>
  <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

  <abstract>
    <t>RFC 3777 defines the Nominations and Recall Committee's
    (NomCom's) operation, 
  	and includes a sample timeline for major steps in the NomCom process that meets the minimum normative
   	requirements for the process. Recent NomComs have been scheduling based on the sample timeline, and the 
	chairs of the last three NomComs -- Danny McPherson (2004-2005), 
  	Ralph Droms (2005-2006), and Andrew Lange (2006-2007) -- have all reported that
	this timeline is very aggressive and suggested starting earlier. This
   	document restructures the sample timeline, but makes no normative process changes.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

    	<t>   
   RFC 3777 (<xref target="RFC3777"/>) is a complete specification of the process by which members of the IAB and
   IESG are selected, confirmed, and recalled as of the date of its
   approval. <xref target="RFC3777"/> includes normative requirements for timing allowed
   for the various steps, and also includes an informative appendix, Appendix
   B, that contains a timeline based on the normative text.
	</t>
	<t>
   The normative time requirements in <xref target="RFC3777"/> are end-of-task, so adjusting 
   the informative timeline to get an earlier start does not require changes
   to the normative text in <xref target="RFC3777"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
   In IETF 68, IETF 65, and IETF 62 plenary reports, NomCom chairs suggested 
   starting the NomCom cycle earlier. This document describes a timeline
   that meets this need, replacing RFC 3777, Appendix B, and makes no other changes to 
	<xref target="RFC3777"/>.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="problem" title="The Problem">

    	<t> There are several reasons that have been cited for the schedule pressures 
	reported by recent NomComs.</t>
	
	<t>
		<list style="symbols">
        		<t>A few common practices are not accounted for in the Appendix B timeline
				<xref target="RFC3777"/>. 
				For example, it is common to allow a week for notifying unsuccessful nominees 
				before the formal announcement is made. This is not included in the timeline.</t>
        		<t>Some tasks just seem to take longer than the minimum interval. For example,
				a public "call for volunteers" must be open for 30 days, but the list of 
				voting NomCom participants probably isn't announced at midnight on the 
				30th day. Anecdotal evidence is that allowing about 6 weeks is more 
				consistent with recent experience.</t>
			<t>The NomCom, and the community it serves, tends to celebrate a variety of 
				holidays between the third IETF and the first IETF of the next year, so people 
				may be out of the office, may wait to respond, etc.</t>
			<t>The Appendix B timeline does not provide flexibility in case of problems.
				For example, the NomCom chair "reset" the random selection of volunteers for the 
				2006-2007 NomCom, requiring another seven-day delay for the announcement of 
				the date of random selection.</t>
   		</list>
	</t>
	<t>All of these reasons can be accommodated by simply starting earlier than is absolutely
		required.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="meetings" title="Interaction with IETF Face-to-Face Meeting Schedule">
	<t>In addition to these reasons for schedule pressure, it's worth noting that
	the NomCom schedule and the IETF face-to-face meeting cycle don't complement 
	each other. </t>
	<t><list style="symbols">
		<t>When the NomCom volunteers are selected after the second IETF, they
		don't have an opportunity to meet face-to-face and "get organized" until the 
		third IETF, when they should be winding up their deliberations.
		This missed opportunity forces them to use teleconferences and other less efficient means 
		of communications to get organized.
		</t>
		<t>The NomCom volunteers don't have a chance to conduct interviews with 
		the community, or with nominees, until the third IETF, during the height
		of the NomCom effort. If the NomCom effort took place before the third IETF,
		the NomCom could work on difficult nominations, and
		meet face-to-face with nominees under consideration.
		</t>
	<t>If the NomCom is able to start interviews during the second IETF meeting, 
		starting earlier than is absolutely required may also help NomCom be more effective.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="proposal" title="Proposed Solution">

    <t>The high-level description of the proposal is, of course, "start earlier", but
	more precision would be helpful.</t>

	<t>A sample, hypothetical timeline that meets these guidelines is shown in 
		<xref target="timeline"/>. Please note that, like Appendix B in <xref target="RFC3777"/>,
		this timeline is not normative, but it meets the normative requirements stated in
		<xref target="RFC3777"/>. </t>

		<t>Other timelines are certainly possible,
		including timelines that allow the NomCom to report its results
		more than one month before the first IETF, where the slate of 
		nominees is announced. Finishing early may be a good thing.</t>

	<t>It's worth noting that the first step in the timeline is "ISOC president appoints NomCom chair".
		This doesn't happen as an IETF responsibility, but 
		the reality is that the ISOC president needs to identify NomCom
		chair candidates around the time of the first IETF; she needs
		to have a shortlist 3 or 4 weeks after the first IETF. This document suggests (but does not add a normative
		requirement to  <xref target="RFC3777"/>) that the outgoing NomCom Chair should 
		verify that this process is triggered during the first IETF. </t>

	<t>
		<list style="numbers">
			<t>One week is allowed for the NomCom chair to
			publish milestones.</t>

			<t>Six weeks are allowed for solicitation of NomCom participants.</t>

			<t>One week is allowed for confirmation of the
			selection of voting members --
				to allow at least some time for resolution if there is a problem.</t>

			<t>The recommended time for NomCom self-organization is increased to six weeks.
				</t>

			<t>One week is allowed for NomCom establishing milestones.</t>

			<t>In the sample timeline (<xref target="table_timeline"/>), an additional five weeks is allowed for the nominating bodies
				to select candidates.</t>

			<t>The timeline is adjusted to allow one week at the end of the process 
				for notification of unsuccessful candidates.</t>
   		</list>
	</t>
	<t>This significantly increases the amount of time available for 
		NomCom to select candidates while still meeting the normative requirements of
		<xref target="RFC3777"/>.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="timeline" title="Sample Timeline for 2008-2009 NomCom Schedule">

	<t>The following table shows a sample timeline for the 2008-2009 NomCom schedule, based on the
		IETF dates for the second IETF (72nd IETF, held July 27 - August 1, 2008),
		third IETF (73rd IETF, held  November 16-21, 2008), and first IETF 
		(74 IETF, held March 22-27, 2009).</t>
	<t>Note that the duration of each milestone step is adjusted as necessary for each NomCom, since the
		scheduled dates for IETF meetings vary from year to year. This timeline allows the NomCom
		to begin self organizing at the Second IETF (this is what "on time") means in the table).</t>


	    <texttable anchor='table_timeline'>													
<ttcol align='center'>	RFC 3777 Appendix B reference 	</ttcol>	<ttcol align='center'>	What happens	</ttcol>	<ttcol align='center'>	new duration (weeks)	</ttcol>	<ttcol align='center'>	start date (YYYY/MM/DD)	</ttcol>	<ttcol align='center'>	old duration (weeks)	</ttcol>
<c>	1	</c>	<c>	ISOC president appoints NomCom chair	</c>	<c>	0	</c>	<c>	2008/05/25	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	2	</c>	<c>	NomCom chair publishes milestones	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2008/05/25	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	3	</c>	<c>	Solicitation of NomCom participants	</c>	<c>	6	</c>	<c>	2008/06/01	</c>	<c>	30 days	</c>
<c>	4	</c>	<c>	Announce date of random selection	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2008/07/13	</c>	<c>	1	</c>
<c>	5	</c>	<c>	Announce NomCom membership, challenge period	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2008/07/20	</c>	<c>	1	</c>
<c>	6	</c>	<c>	Verify NomCom membership during challenge period	</c>	<c>	0	</c>	<c>	2008/07/27	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	7	</c>	<c>	Confirm NomCom membership	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2008/07/27	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	8	</c>	<c>	NomCom self organizes (on time)	</c>	<c>	6	</c>	<c>	2008/08/03	</c>	<c>	4	</c>
<c>	9	</c>	<c>	END organization, BEGIN selection	</c>	<c>	0	</c>	<c>	2008/09/14	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	10	</c>	<c>	NomCom establishes milestones	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2008/09/14	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	11	</c>	<c>	Nominating bodies select candidates	</c>	<c>	17	</c>	<c>	2008/09/21	</c>	<c>	12	</c>
<c>	12	</c>	<c>	END selection, BEGIN confirmation of candidates	</c>	<c>	0	</c>	<c>	2009/01/18	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	13	</c>	<c>	Present slate of candidates to confirming bodies	</c>	<c>	0	</c>	<c>	2009/01/18	</c>	<c>	0	</c>
<c>	14	</c>	<c>	Confirming bodies accept or reject	</c>	<c>	4	</c>	<c>	2009/01/18	</c>	<c>	4	</c>
<c>	(added step)	</c>	<c>	Notify unsuccessful nominees	</c>	<c>	1	</c>	<c>	2009/02/15	</c>	<c>		</c>
<c>	15	</c>	<c>	Slate announced 1 month before 1st IETF	</c>	<c>	4	</c>	<c>	2009/02/22	</c>	<c>	4	</c>
<c>		</c>	<c>	1st IETF	</c>	<c>		</c>	<c>	2009/03/22	</c>	<c>		</c>

	        <postamble> 	New Step 1 Date:		2008/05/25,	  Old Step 1 Date:		2008/08/29	</postamble>						
	    </texttable>													


</section>

<section anchor="observations" title="Some Observations from the 2007-2008 NomCom Experience">

	<t>Since the timeline described in this specification makes no normative changes to <xref target="RFC3777"/>,
		the 2007-2008 NomCom process started using the new timeline to gain experience and 
		shake out unexpected consequences. We discovered the following things:
	</t>
	<t><list style="numbers">
		<t>It is worth pointing out
			that the <xref target="RFC3777"/> requirement for eligibility, "Members of the IETF community must have 
			attended at least 3 of the last 5 IETF meetings in order to volunteer.", is affected when the NomCom chair
			issues an earlier call for volunteers. For example, using the 2008-2009 
			NomCom example in the doc: under the old schedule, a prospective member would need to have 
			attended three of IETF meetings 68-72.  Under the new schedule, that becomes three of IETF meetings 67-71.
		</t>
		<t>It's worth noting that when NomCom uses the earlier timeline, incumbents under review who were appointed
			to one-year terms have only one
			IETF meeting cycle to establish a track record before NomCom begins considering whether they should 
			be retained. This situation is rare but not unknown. The recent split of the RAI area out of TSV 
			created two one-year terms (one in RAI, and one in TSV), and this can also happens if an IESG or 
			IAB member resigns with more than one year remaining in the member's term.
		</t>
	</list></t>

</section>

<section anchor='exclusions' title="Out-of-Scope Suggestions Requiring Normative Text Changes">

	<t>While there are very few avoidable serialized delays in <xref target="RFC3777"/>,
		we note that the minimum 30-day delay for volunteers is serialized after 
		the NomCom chair is named. This delay accounts for more than half the elapsed time 
		between the NomCom chair being named and the NomCom itself forming.
		If a future normative revision to <xref target="RFC3777"/>
		changed the mechanics for this call for volunteers, 
		this call could be issued while the NomCom chair is still being selected.
		This would allow the new NomCom chair to begin work by announcing the date of 
		random selection, instead of just waiting for the volunteers to volunteer.
	</t>
	<t>One possible trigger would be to have the outgoing NomCom chair issue the call for volunteers
		on behalf of the successor NomCom chair, who may not yet be identified, 
		at the first IETF meeting each year.
	</t>
</section>
  
  <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>The NomCom timeline changes suggested in this document do
	 not directly affect the security of the Internet.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>This draft is based on conversations with the chairs of the last three NomComs: Danny McPherson (2004-2005), 
  		Ralph Droms (2005-2006), and Andrew Lange (2006-2007), and on their corresponding plenary NomCom Report
		presentations at IETF 62, IETF 65, and IETF 68, respectively.</t>
    <t>The 2007 IESG discussed Andrew Lange's report at their face-to-face retreat and requested a
		proposal that adjusted the informative timeline with no normative changes.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Russ Housley, current General Area director, for reviewing an early version of this draft.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Brian Carpenter, who  pointed out that the IETF NomCom portion of the timeline depends 
		on the ISOC president appointing the NomCom chair soon after the first IETF
		("NomCom chairs don't appear magically"), and provided a suggestion for ensuring 
		that this happens in a timeframe that allows NomCom to begin self organizing 
		at the Second IETF meeting each year.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Sam Weiler, who pointed out the shift in meeting attendance requirements described in 
		<xref target="observations"/>. </t>
    <t>We should also thank the editors of previous NomCom procedures for developing a specification
		that we could "speed up" without changing normative text.</t>
  </section> 

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">

&RFC3777;

</references>

</back>
</rfc>
