<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!-- $Id: rfc5071.xml,v 1.2 2007/11/21 16:21:08 dhankins Exp $ -->

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629bis.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY rfc0854 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0854.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1350 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1350.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2131 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2132 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2132.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2939 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2939.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3118 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3118.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3942 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3942.xml'>
]>
<rfc number="5071" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PXELINUX Options">Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
	Options Used by PXELINUX</title>

    <author initials="D.H." surname="Hankins" fullname="David W. Hankins">
	<organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium,
		Inc.</organization>

	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	    <city>Redwood City</city>
	    <region>CA</region>
	    <code>94063</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650 423 1307</phone>
        <email>David_Hankins@isc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2007" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Dynamic Host Configuration Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>PXE</keyword>
    <keyword>pxelinux</keyword>
    <keyword>configfile</keyword>
    <keyword>path prefix</keyword>
    <keyword>reboot time</keyword>

    <abstract>
	<t>This document describes the use by PXELINUX of some DHCP Option
	Codes numbering from 208-211.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>PXE, the Preboot eXecution Environment, is a first-stage network
	bootstrap agent.  PXE is loaded out of firmware on the client host,
	and performs <xref target="RFC2131">DHCP</xref> queries to obtain
	an IP address.</t>

	<t>Once on the network, it loads a second-stage bootstrap agent
	as configured by DHCP header and option contents.</t>

	<t>PXELINUX is one such second-stage bootstrap agent.  Once PXE has
	passed execution to it, PXELINUX seeks its configuration from a cache
	of DHCP options supplied to the PXE first-stage agent, and then takes
	action based upon those options.</t>

	<t>Most frequently, this implies loading via
	<xref target="RFC1350">Trivial File Transfer Protocol
	(TFTP)</xref> one or more images that are
	decompressed into memory, then executed to pass execution to the final
	Host Operating System.</t>

	<t>PXELINUX uses DHCP options 208-211 to govern parts of this bootstrap
	process, but these options are not requested by the PXE DHCP client
	at the time it acquires its lease. At that time, the PXE bootloader
	has no knowledge that PXELINUX is going to be in use, and even so, would
	have no way to know what option(s) PXELINUX might digest.  Local
	installations that serve this PXELINUX image to its clients must also
	configure their DHCP servers to provide these options even though
	they are not on the <xref target="RFC2132">DHCP Parameter Request
	List</xref>.</t>

	<t>These options are:</t>

	<t/>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>"MAGIC" - 208 - An option whose presence and content
	  verifies to the PXELINUX bootloader that the options numbered
	  209-211 are for the purpose as described herein.</t>

	  <t>"ConfigFile" - 209 - Configures the path/filename component of
	  the configuration file's location, which this bootloader should use
	  to configure itself.</t>

	  <t>"PathPrefix" - 210 - Configures a value to be prepended to the
	  ConfigFile to discern the directory location of the file.</t>

	  <t>"RebootTime" - 211 - Configures a timeout after which the
	  bootstrap program will reboot the system (most likely returning it
	  to PXE).</t>
	</list>

	<t>Historically, these option codes numbering from 208-211 were
	designated 'Site Local', but after publication of
	<xref target="RFC3942">RFC3942</xref>, they were made available for
	allocation as new standard DHCP options.  This document marks these
	codes as assigned.</t>

	<t>This direct assignment of option code values in the option
	definitions below is unusual as it is not mentioned in
	<xref target="RFC2939">DHCP Option Code assignment guidelines</xref>.
	This document's Option Code assignments are done within RFC 3942's
	provisions for documenting prior use of option codes within the new
	range (128-223 inclusive).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <list style="symbols">
	<t>"first-stage bootloader" - Although a given bootloading order
	may have many stages, such as where a BIOS boots a DOS Boot Disk,
	which then loads a PXE executable, it is, in this example, only the
	PXE executable that this document describes as the "first-stage
	bootloader" -- in essence, this is the first stage of booting at
	which DHCP is involved.</t>

	<t>"second-stage bootloader" - This describes a program loaded by
	the first-stage bootloader at the behest of the DHCP server.</t>

	<t>"bootloader" and "network bootstrap agent" - These are synonyms,
	excepting that "bootloader" is intentionally vague in that its
	next form of bootstrapping may not in fact involve network
	resources.</t>
      </list>

	<t>The key words "MAY", "MUST", "MUST NOT",
	"SHOULD", and "SHOULD NOT" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in
	<xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="MAGIC Option">
      <section title="Description">
	<t>If this option is provided to the PXE bootloader, then the
	value is checked by PXELINUX to match the octet string f1:00:74:7e.
	If this matches, then PXELINUX bootloaders will also consume options
	209-211, as described below.  Otherwise, they are ignored.</t>

	<t>This measure was intended to ensure that, as the 'Site Local'
	option space is not allocated from a central authority, no
	conflict would result in a PXELINUX bootloader improperly digesting
	options intended for another purpose.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Packet Format">
	<figure>
	  <preamble>The MAGIC Option format is as follows:</preamble>
	  <artwork>
           Code    Length     m1       m2       m3       m4
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
        |   208  |    4   |  0xF1  |  0x00  |  0x74  |  0x7E  |
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
	  </artwork>
	  <postamble>The code for this option is 208.  The length is
		always four.</postamble>
	</figure>
      </section>


      <section title="Applicability">
	<t>This option is absolutely inapplicable to any other purpose.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Response to RFC 3942">
	<t>The option code 208 will be adopted for this purpose and immediately
	deprecated.  Future standards action may return this option to an
	available status should it be necessary.</t>

	<t>A collision of the use of this option is harmless (at least from
	PXELINUX' point of view) by design: if it does not match the
	aforementioned magic value, the PXELINUX bootloader will take no
	special action.</t>

	<t>The PXELINUX project will deprecate the use of this option;
	future versions of the software will not evaluate its contents.</t>

	<t>It is reasonable to utilize this option code for another
	purpose, but it is recommended to do this at a later time, given
	the desire to avoid potential collisions in legacy user bases.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Configuration File Option">
      <section title="Description">
	<t>Once the PXELINUX executable has been entered from the PXE
	bootloader, it evaluates this option and loads a file of that name
	via TFTP.  The contents of this file serve to configure PXELINUX
	in its next stage of bootloading (specifying boot image names,
	locations, boot-time flags, text to present the user in menu
	selections, etc).</t>

	<t>In the absence of this option, the PXELINUX agent will search
	the TFTP server (as determined by PXE prior to this stage) for a
	config file of several default names.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Packet Format">
        <figure>
          <preamble>The Configuration File Option format is as
		follows:</preamble>
          <artwork>
           Code    Length    Config-file...
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
        |   209  |    n   |   c1   |   c2   |   ...  |   c(n) |
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
          </artwork>
          <postamble>The code for this option is 209.  The Config-file
		(c1..c(n)) is an <xref target="RFC0854">NVT-ASCII</xref>
		printable string; it is not terminated by a zero or any
		other value.</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
	<t>Any bootloader, PXE or otherwise, that makes use of a separate
	configuration file rather than containing all configurations within
	DHCP options (which may be impossible due to the limited space
	available for DHCP options) may conceivably make use of this option.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Response to RFC 3942">
	<t>The code 209 will be adopted for this purpose.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Client and Server Behaviour">
	<t>The Config File Option MUST be supplied by the DHCP server if
	it appears on the Parameter Request List, but MUST also be supplied
	if the server administrator believed it would later be useful to
	the client (such as because the server is configured to offer a
	second-stage boot image, which they know will make use of it).  The
	option MUST NOT be supplied if no value has been configured for it,
	or if a value of zero length has been configured.</t>

	<t>The DHCP client MUST only cache this option in a location the
	second-stage bootloader may access.</t>

	<t>The second-stage bootloader MUST, in concert with other DHCP
	options and fields, use this option's value as a filename to be
	loaded via TFTP and read for further second-stage-loader-specific
	configuration parameters.  The format and content of such a file
	is specific to the second-stage bootloader, and as such, is out of
	scope of this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

<?rfc needLines="10" ?>
    <section title="Path Prefix Option">
      <section title="Description">
	<t>In PXELINUX' case, it is often the case that several different
	environments would have the same TFTP path prefix, but would have
	different filenames (for example: hosts' bootloader images and
	config files may be kept in a directory structure derived from their
	Media Access Control (MAC) address).  Consequently, it was deemed worthwhile to deliver a
	TFTP path prefix configuration option, so that these two things
	could be configured separately in a DHCP Server configuration: the
	prefix and the possibly host-specific file location.</t>

	<t>The actual filename that PXELINUX requests from its TFTP server is
	derived by prepending this value to the Config File Option above.
	Once this config file is loaded and during processing, any TFTP file
	paths specified within it are similarly processed -- prepending the
	contents of this option.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Packet Format">
        <figure>
          <preamble>The Path Prefix Option format is as follows:</preamble>
          <artwork>
           Code    Length   Path-Prefix...
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
        |   210  |    n   |   p1   |   p2   |   ...  |   p(n) |
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
          </artwork>
          <postamble>The code for this option is 210.  The Path Prefix
		is an NVT-ASCII printable string; it is not
		terminated by zero or any other value.</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
	<t>This option came into existence because server administrators found
	it useful to configure the prefix and suffix of the config file path
	separately.  A group of different PXE booting clients may use the
	same path prefix, but different filenames, or vice versa.</t>

	<t>The 'shortcut' this represents is worthwhile, but it is
	questionable whether that needs to manifest itself on the protocol
	wire.</t>
<?rfc needLines="10" ?>
	<t>It only becomes interesting from a protocol standpoint if other
	options are adopted that prefix this value as well -- performing a
	kind of string compression is highly beneficial to the limited
	available DHCP option space.</t>

	<t>But it's clearly inapplicable to any current use of, e.g., the FILENAME
	header contents or the DHCP Boot File Name option (#67).  Use of these
	fields is encoded on firmware of thousands of devices that can't or
	are not likely to be upgraded.  Altering any behaviour here is likely
	to cause severe compatibility problems.</t>

	<t>Although compression of the TFTP-loaded configuration file contents
	is not a compelling factor, contrived configurations using these values
	may also exist: where each of a large variety of different clients
	load the same configuration file, with the same contents, but due to a
	differently configured path prefix actually load different images.
	Whether this sort of use is truly needed remains unproven.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Response to RFC 3942">
	<t>The code 210 will be adopted for this purpose.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Client and Server Behaviour">
	<t>The Path Prefix option MUST be supplied by the DHCP server if
	it appears on the Parameter Request List, but MUST also be supplied
	if the server administrator believed it would later be useful to
	the client (such as because the server is configured to offer a
	second-stage boot image that they know will make use of it).  The
	option MUST NOT be supplied if no value has been configured for it,
	or if a value of zero length has been configured.</t>

	<t>The DHCP client MUST only cache this option in a location where
	the second-stage bootloader may access it.</t>

	<t>The second-stage bootloader MUST prepend this option's value, if
	any, to the contents of the ConfigFile option prior to obtaining the
	resulting value via TFTP, or the default 'Config File Search Path',
	which the second-stage bootloader iterates in the absence of a Config
	File Option.  The client MAY prepend the value to other configuration
	directives within that file once it has been loaded.  The client
	MUST NOT prepend this option's value to any other DHCP option
	contents or field, unless explicitly stated in a document describing
	that option or field.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Reboot Time Option">
      <section title="Description">
	<t>Should PXELINUX be executed, and then for some reason, be unable to
	reach its TFTP server to continue bootstrapping, the client will,
	by default, reboot itself after 300 seconds have passed.  This may be
	too long, too short, or inappropriate behaviour entirely, depending
	on the environment.</t>

	<t>By configuring a non-zero value in this option, admins can inform
	PXELINUX of which specific timeout is desired.  The client will reboot
	itself if it fails to achieve its configured network resources within
	the specified number of seconds.</t>

	<t>This reboot will run through the system's normal boot-time
	execution path, most likely leading it back to PXE and therefore
	PXELINUX.  So, in the general case, this is akin to returning the
	client to the DHCP INIT state.</t>

	<t>By configuring zero, the feature is disabled, and instead the
	client chooses to remove itself from the network and wait indefinitely
	for operator intervention.</t>

	<t>It should be stressed that this is in no way related to configuring
	a lease time.  The perceived transition to INIT state is due to client
	running state -- reinitializing itself -- not due to lease timer
	activity.  That is, it is not safe to assume that a PXELINUX client
	will abandon its lease when this timer expires.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Packet Format">
        <figure>
          <preamble>The Reboot Time Option format is as follows:</preamble>
          <artwork>
           Code    Length
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
        |   211  |    4   |            Reboot Time            |
        +--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+--------+
          </artwork>
          <postamble>The code for this option is 211.  The length is
		always four.  The Reboot Time is a 32-bit (4 byte)
		integer in network byte order.</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
<?rfc needLines="15" ?>
      <section title="Applicability">
	<t>Any network bootstrap program in any sufficiently complex
	networking environment could conceivably enter into such a similar
	condition, either due to having its IP address stolen out from
	under it by a rogue client on the network, by being moved between
	networks where its PXE-derived DHCP lease is no longer valid, or
	any similar means.</t>

	<t>It seems desirable for any network bootstrap agent to implement
	an ultimate timeout for it to start over.</t>

	<t>The client may, for example, get different working configuration
	parameters from a different DHCP server upon restarting.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Response to RFC 3942">
	<t>The code 211 will be adopted for this purpose.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Client and Server Behaviour">
	<t>The Reboot Time Option MUST be supplied by the DHCP server if
	it appears on the Parameter Request List, but MUST also be supplied
	if the server administrator believed it would later be useful to
	the client (such as because the server is configured to offer a
	second-stage boot image that they know will make use of it).  The
	option MUST NOT be supplied if no value has been configured for it,
	or if it contains a value of zero length.</t>

	<t>The DHCP client MUST only cache this option in a location the
	second-stage bootloader may access.</t>

	<t>If the value of this option is nonzero, the second-stage bootloader
	MUST schedule a timeout: after a number of seconds equal to this
	option's value have passed, the second-stage bootloader MUST reboot
	the system, ultimately returning the path of execution back to the
	first-stage bootloader.  It MUST NOT reboot the system once the
	thread of execution has been passed to the host operating system
	(at which point, this timeout is effectively obviated).</t>

	<t>If the value of this option is zero, the second-stage bootloader
	MUST NOT schedule such a timeout at all.  Any second-stage bootloader
	that finds it has encountered excessive timeouts attempting to obtain
	its host operating system SHOULD disconnect itself from the network to
	wait for operator intervention, but MAY continue to attempt to acquire
	the host operating system indefinitely.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Specification Conformance">
	<t>To conform to this specification, clients and servers MUST
	implement the Configuration File, Path Prefix, and Reboot Time
	options as directed.</t>

	<t>The MAGIC option MAY NOT be implemented, as it has been
	deprecated.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
	<t>PXE and PXELINUX allow any entity acting as a DHCP server to
	execute arbitrary code upon a system.  At present, no PXE
	implementation is known to implement
	<xref target="RFC3118">authentication mechanisms</xref> so
	that PXE clients can be sure they are receiving configuration
	information from the correct, authoritative DHCP server.</t>

	<t>The use of TFTP by PXE and PXELINUX also lacks any form of
	cryptographic signature -- so a 'Man in the Middle' attack may lead to
	an attacker's code being executed on the client system.  Since this is
	not an encrypted channel, any of the TFTP loaded data may also be
	exposed (such as in loading a "RAMDISK" image, which contains
	/etc/passwd or similar information).</t>

	<t>The use of the Ethernet MAC Address as the client's unique
	identity may allow an attacker who takes on that identity to gain
	inappropriate access to a client system's network resources by being
	given by the DHCP server whatever 'keys' are required, in
	fact, to be
	the target system (to boot up as though it were the target).</t>

	<t>Great care should be taken to secure PXE and PXELINUX
	installations, such as by using IP firewalls, to reduce or
	eliminate these concerns.</t>

	<t>A nearby attacker might feed a "Reboot Time" option value of 1
	second to a mass of unsuspecting clients, to effect a Denial Of
	Service (DoS) upon the DHCP server, but then again it may just as easily
	supply these clients with rogue second-stage bootloaders that
	simply transmit a flood of packets.</t>

	<t>This document in and by itself provides no security, nor does
	it impact existing DCHP security as described in
	<xref target="RFC2131">RFC 2131</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>IANA has done the following:</t>

	<list style="numbers">
	    <t>Moved DHCPv4 Option code 208 from 'Tentatively Assigned' to
	    'Assigned', referencing this document.  IANA has marked
	    this same option code, 208, as Deprecated.</t>

	    <t>Moved DHCPv4 Option code 209 from 'Tentatively Assigned' to
	    'Assigned', referencing this document.</t>

	    <t>Moved DHCPv4 Option code 210 from 'Tentatively Assigned' to
	    'Assigned', referencing this document.</t>

	    <t>Moved DHCPv4 Option code 211 from 'Tentatively Assigned' to
	    'Assigned', referencing this document.</t>
	</list>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>These options were designed and implemented for the PXELINUX
	project by H. Peter Anvin, and he was instrumental in producing
	this document.  Shane Kerr has also provided feedback that has
	improved this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	&rfc0854;
	&rfc2119;
	&rfc2131;
	&rfc2132;
	&rfc2939;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
	&rfc1350;
	&rfc3118;
	&rfc3942;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
