<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3344 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3344.xml'>      
    <!ENTITY rfc2794 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2794.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4282 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4721 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4721.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3629 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4303 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5149 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5149.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="5446" category="info">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Service Selection for MIPv4">Service Selection for Mobile IPv4</title>
        <author initials='J.' surname="Korhonen" fullname='Jouni Korhonen'>
           <organization abbrev="Nokia Siemens Networks">Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
                    <code>FIN-02600 Espoo</code>
                    <country>FINLAND</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
             </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='U.' surname="Nilsson" fullname='Ulf Nilsson'>
           <organization abbrev="TeliaSonera">TeliaSonera Corporation</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Marbackagatan 11</street>
                    <code>S-123 86 Farsta</code>
                    <country>SWEDEN</country>
                </postal>
                <email>ulf.s.nilsson@teliasonera.com</email>
             </address>
        </author>

        <date month="February" year="2009"/>
        
<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
    the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->
        
        <abstract>
         <t>
	   In some Mobile IPv4 deployments, identifying the mobile
            node or the mobility service subscriber is not enough to
            distinguish among the multiple services possibly
            provisioned to the mobile node.  The capability to specify
            different services in addition to the mobile node's
            identity can be leveraged to provide flexibility for
            mobility service providers to provide multiple services
            within a single mobility service subscription. This
            document describes a Service Selection extension for
            Mobile IPv4 that is intended to assist home agents to make
            specific service selections for their mobility service
            subscriptions during the registration procedure.
         </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
    
       <section title="Introduction">
         <t>Mobile IPv4 <xref target="RFC3344"/> can identify mobile
            nodes in various ways, including home addresses
            <xref target="RFC3344"/> and Network Access Identifiers
            (NAIs) <xref target="RFC4282"/> <xref target="RFC2794"/>.
            In some Mobile IPv4 deployments, identifying the mobile
            node (MN) or the mobility service subscriber via a Proxy
            Mobile IPv4 client <xref target="LEUNG"/> (hereafter, the
            mobile node and the Proxy Mobile IPv4 client are used
            interchangeably) is not enough to distinguish among the
            multiple services possibly provisioned to the mobile node.
         </t>

         <t>The capability to specify different services in addition to the mobile
            node's identity can be leveraged to
            provide flexibility for mobility service providers to provide multiple
            services within the same mobility service subscription. For example:
            
         <list style='hanging'>
           <t hangText="o">Provide an enterprise data access for which the mobility
              service provider hosts connectivity and mobility services on
              behalf of the enterprise.</t>

           <t hangText="o">Provide access to service domains that are otherwise
              not accessible from public networks because of some mobility service
              providers' business reasons.</t>

           <t hangText="o">Provide simultaneous access to different service domains
              that are separated based on policies of the mobility service provider.</t>

           <t hangText="o">Enable easier policy assignment for mobility service
              providers based on the subscribed services.
           </t>
         </list>
         </t>


         <t>This document describes a Service Selection extension for Mobile IPv4
            that is intended to assist home agents to make specific service
            selections for their mobility service subscriptions during the
            registration procedure. A Mobile IPv6-equivalent Service Selection
            Mobility Option has been described in <xref target="RFC5149"/>. 
            The service selection may affect home agent
            routing decisions, Home Address assignment policies, firewall
            settings, and security policies.  When the service selection is used,
            every Registration Request must contain the Service Selection extension.
            The Service Selection extension from the Registration Request may be
            echoed back in the Registration Reply.
         </t>
         <t>In absence of a specifically indicated service, the home agent must
            act as if the default service, plain Internet access, had been
            requested. There is no absolute requirement that this default service
            would be allowed to all subscribers, but it is highly recommended in
            order to avoid having normal subscribers employ operator-specific
            configuration values in order to get basic service.
         </t>
         <t>Some of the potential use cases were listed earlier in this section.
            The general aim is better manageability of services and service
            provisioning, from both operators' and service providers' points of
            view. However, it should be understood that there are potential
            deployment possibilities where selecting a certain service may
            restrict simultaneous access to other services from a user point
            of view (e.g., a "walled garden"). For example, services
            may be located in different
            administrative domains or external customer networks that
            practice excessive filtering of inbound and outbound traffic. 
         </t>


       </section>

       <section title="Requirements">
         <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
       </section>
            
       
       
       <section title="Service Selection Extension" anchor="serselopt">

         <t>At most one Service Selection extension 
            MAY be included in any Mobile
            IPv4 Registration Request message.  When the service selection is used,
            the Service Selection extension MUST be included in every Registration
            Request message. In absence of a specifically indicated service in the
            Registration Request for the initial registration or re-registration,
            the home agent MUST act as if the default service, such as plain Internet
            access, had been requested. The Service Selection extension MUST be placed
            in the Registration Request message as follows:
         </t>


         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>When  present, the extension MUST appear after
              the MN-NAI extension, if the MN-NAI is also present
              in the message.</t>

           <t>If the extension was added by the mobile node to
              a Registration Request, it MUST appear prior to any
              authentication-enabling extensions
              <xref target="RFC3344"/> <xref target="RFC4721"/>.
           </t>

           <t>In the event the foreign agent adds the Service
              Selection extension to a Registration Request,
              the extension MUST appear prior to any Foreign-Home
              authentication-enabling extensions <xref target="RFC3344"/>.
           </t>

         </list>
         </t>
         <t>The home agent MAY echo the received Service Selection extension
            option back in a Mobile IPv4 Registration Reply
            message. The echoed Service Selection
            extension MUST be an unchanged copy of the Service Selection
            extension received in the corresponding Registration
            Request message. The Service Selection extension MUST be placed in the
            Registration Reply message as follows:
         </t>
         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>If the extension was originally added by the mobile node to
              a Registration Request, it MUST appear in the
              Registration Reply prior to any
              authentication-enabling extensions
              <xref target="RFC3344"/> <xref target="RFC4721"/>.
           </t>

           <t>If the foreign agent added the Service
              Selection extension to a Registration Request,
              the extension MUST appear in the Registration Reply
              prior to any Foreign-Home authentication-enabling extensions
              <xref target="RFC3344"/>.
           </t>

         </list>
         </t>

         <t>The Service Selection extension has the following format:
         </t>



         <t>
         <figure title="Service Selection Extension">
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = 151   |   Length      | Identifier...                 ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
         </figure>

         <list style='hanging'>
         <t hangText="o">Type: 8-bit identifier set to 151 (the type of this skippable extension).
         </t>

         <t hangText="o">Length: 8-bit unsigned integer, representing
            the length of the 
            Service Selection extension in octets, excluding the
            Type and Length fields.  A value of zero (0) is not
            allowed.
         </t>

         <t hangText="o">Identifier: A variable-length, encoded service-identifier string 
            used to identify the requested service.  The identifier string
            length is between 1 and 255 octets.  This specification allows
            international identifier strings that are based on the use of
            Unicode characters, encoded as UTF-8 <xref
            target="RFC3629"/> and formatted using 
            Normalization Form KC (NFKC) as specified in <xref target="NFKC"/>.

            <vspace blankLines="1"/>

            'ims', 'voip', and
            'voip.companyxyz.example.com' are valid
            examples of Service Selection extension Identifiers. At minimum 
            the Identifier MUST be unique among the home agents to which the mobile node is
            authorized to register.</t>
         </list>
         </t>
       </section>
       
       <section title="Processing Considerations">
       
         <section title="Mobile Node Considerations">
           <t>A mobile node or its proxy representative MAY include the Service
              Selection extension into any Registration Request message.  The
              Service Selection extension can be used with any mobile node
              identification method.  The extension is used to identify the service
              to be associated with the mobility session; if the service selection
              is used, the Service Selection extension MUST be included into every
              Registration Request message sent to a home agent. If the mobile node
              wishes to change the selected service, it is RECOMMENDED that the
              mobile node de-register the existing binding with the home agent
              before proceeding with a binding registration for a different service.
              The provisioning of the service identifiers to the mobile node or its
              proxy representative is out of the scope of this specification.
           </t>

           <t>If the mobile node receives
              a Registration Reply message with
              a Code set to SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED and the
              mobile node has an existing binding with the Home Address
              used in the failed Registration Request
              message,
              the mobile node MUST delete the existing binding.  If there
              is no existing binding, the mobile node proceeds as with
              any failed initial registration.
           </t>

         </section>

         <section title="Home Agent Considerations">
           <t>Upon receiving the  Service Selection extension, the home
              agent authenticates and  authorizes the mobile node. If
              the home agent supports the Service Selection, it MUST 
              also verify  that the  mobile  node is
              authorized  to the  service identified by the Service
              Selection  extension. The  services the  mobile  node is
              authorized to SHOULD be part of the general mobile node
              subscription data. If the mobile node is not authorized
              to the service, or the home agent does not recognize the
              identified service, the home agent MUST   deny  the
              registration and send a Registration Reply with a Code
              SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED (error code 151). 
           </t>

           <t>The Service  Selection extension  is used to  assist the
              mobile  node   authorization  phase  and   identifies  a
              specific service that is  to be authorized.  The Service
              Selection  extension MAY  also affect  the  Home Address
              allocation  when,  for example, used  with  the  MN-NAI
              extension. For example, for the same NAI, there MAY be
              different Home Addresses, depending on the identified service.
              Furthermore,  the Service  Selection extension  MAY also
              affect  the routing of  the outbound  IP packets  in the
              home agent depending on the selected service.
              The home
              agent MAY also apply different policy or quality of
              service treatment to traffic flows based on the selected
              service.
           </t>
           
           <t>If the newly arrived Registration Request message with a Service
              Selection extension indicates a change in the selected service, then
              the home agent MUST re-authorize the mobile node. The absence of the
              Service Selection extension MUST be treated as a request for the
              default service, which may also cause the re-authorization of the
              mobile node. Depending on the home agent's policies, the services policies,
              the Home Address allocation policies, and the subscription policies, the home
              agent may or may not be able to authorize the mobile node to the new
              service.  For example the existing service and the new service could
              require different Home Addresses.  If the authorization fails, then the
              home agent MUST deny the registration, delete any binding with the
              existing Home Address, and send a Registration Reply with a Code set to
              SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED (error code 151).
           </t>
           <t>Depending on the local home agent's policy, the home agent MAY
              echo the Service Selection extension in
              the corresponding Registration Reply message towards the
              mobile node or the foreign agent. The home agent MUST
              NOT change the content of the echoed Service
              Selection extension.
           </t>
         </section>

         <section title="Foreign Agent Considerations">
           <t>A foreign agent MUST skip the Service Selection
              extension if the Registration Request already contains
              the Service Selection extension. If the Registration
              Request does not contain the Service Selection extension,
              the foreign agent MAY add the Service Selection
              extension to the Registration Request message. How the
              foreign agent learns the service that the mobile node needs
              to authorize is outside the scope of this document.
           </t>
           <t>In the case a foreign agent added the Service Selection
              extension to the Registration Request on behalf of the
              mobile node, it MUST verify whether the corresponding Registration
              Reply message from a home agent also contains an echoed
              Service Selection extension. If the received
              Registration Reply message contains the echoed Service
              Selection extension, the foreign agent MUST NOT include
              the extension to the Registration Reply message that
              gets forwarded to the mobile node.
           </t>
         </section>
       </section>

       <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>The protection for the Service Selection extension depends
            on  the service  that is  being identified  and eventually
            selected.  If the service selection information should not
            be revealed on the wire, it should be protected in a manner
            similar   to   Registration   Requests  and   Registration
            Replies. The  Service Selection extension  is protected by
            the same authentication-enabling  extension as the rest of
            the Registration Request message.
         </t>

         <t>The  home  agent  MUST  verify  that the  mobile  node  is
            authorized  to   the  service  included   in  the  Service
            Selection  extension.   The  Service  Selection  extension
            authorization   is  part   of  the   normal   mobile  node
            registration    and    authentication   procedure.    Both
            registration authentication and service authorization MUST
            succeed before  the mobile node is allowed  to register to
            the home agent.
         </t>
       </section>
        
       <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
   A new Mobile IPv4 Extension type has been assigned in the
   "Extensions appearing in Mobile IP control messages" registry for
   the extension described in <xref target="serselopt"/>.  The Extension type has been
   allocated from the 'skippable' range (128-255):

                <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    Service Selection Extension       is set to 151
                   ]]></artwork></figure>
           </t>

           <t>
   A new Mobile IPv4 error code has been assigned in the "Registration
   denied by the home agent" section of the "Code Values for Mobile IP
   Registration Reply Messages" registry.  The error code has been
   allocated from the 'Error Codes from the Home Agent' range
   (128-192):

                <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED      is set to 151
                   ]]></artwork></figure>
           </t>
      </section>
        
      <section title="Acknowledgments">
        <t>The authors would like to thank Henrik Levkowetz,
           Kent Leung, Spencer Dawkins, and Jari Arkko for their comments.
           Jouni Korhonen also
           acknowledges TeliaSonera and the TEKES MERCoNe project, where most
           of the work was conducted.
        </t>
      </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
      <references title="Normative References">
        &rfc2119;
        &rfc3344;
        &rfc3629;

        <reference anchor='NFKC'>
          <front>
            <title>Unicode Standard Annex #15; Unicode Normalization Forms</title>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Davis' fullname='Mark Davis'>
            <organization /></author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Durst' fullname='Martin Durst'>
            <organization /></author>
            <date year='2006' month='October' />
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='Unicode' value='5.0.0' />
        </reference>  

      </references>
      <references title="Informative References">
        &rfc4282;
        &rfc2794;
        &rfc4721;
        &rfc5149;

<!-- draft-leung-mip4-proxy-mode -->

<reference anchor="LEUNG">
	<front>
<title>WiMAX Forum/3GPP2 Proxy Mobile IPv4</title>
	<author initials="K" surname="Leung" fullname="Kent Leung">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="December" day="1" year="2008"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
</reference>
      </references>

    </back>

</rfc>
