<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" number="6221" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="3315" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="LDRA">Lightweight DHCPv6 Relay Agent</title>

    <author fullname="David Miles" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Miles">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>L3 / 215 Spring St.</street>
          <city>Melbourne</city>
          <region>Victoria</region>
          <code>3000</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+61 3 9664 3308</phone>
        <email>david.miles@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sven Ooghe" initials="S." surname="Ooghe">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Copernicuslaan 50</street>
          <city>2018 Antwerp</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sven.ooghe@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wojciech Dec" initials="W." surname="Dec">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Haarlerberdweg 13-19</street>
          <city>1101 CH Amsterdam</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>The Netherlands</country>
        </postal>
        <email>wdec@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S.K." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 Blvd. Decarie</street>
          <city>Town of Mount Royal</city>
          <region>Quebec</region>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alan Kavanagh" initials="A.K." surname="Kavanagh">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 Blvd. Decarie</street>
          <city>Town of Mount Royal</city>
          <region>Quebec</region>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>alan.kavanagh@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes a Lightweight DHCPv6 Relay Agent (LDRA) that
      is used to insert relay agent options in DHCPv6 message exchanges
      identifying client-facing interfaces. The LDRA can be implemented in
      existing access nodes (such as Digital Subscriber Link Access
      Multiplexers (DSLAMs) and Ethernet switches) that do not
      support IPv6 control or routing functions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>DHCPv6 Relay Agents <xref target="RFC3315"> </xref> are deployed to
      forward DHCPv6 messages between clients and servers when they are not on
      the same IPv6 link and are often implemented alongside a routing
      function in a common node. A Lightweight DHCPv6 Relay Agent (LDRA)
      allows Relay Agent Information to be inserted by an access node that
      performs a link-layer bridging (i.e., non-routing) function. An LDRA
      resides on the same IPv6 link as the client and a DHCPv6 Relay Agent or
      server, and is functionally the equivalent of the Layer 2 Relay Agent
      proposed for DHCPv4 operation in <xref target="L2RA"> </xref>.</t>

      <t>Unlike a DHCPv6 Relay Agent specified in <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref>, an LDRA does not implement any IPv6 control
      functions (e.g., ICMPv6) or have any routing capability in the node.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Background">
      <t>A variety of different link-layer network topologies exist for the
      aggregation of IPv6 nodes into one or more routers. In Layer 2
      aggregation networks (IEEE 802.1D bridging or similar) that have many
      nodes on a single link, a DHCPv6 server or DHCP Relay Agent would
      normally be unaware of how a DHCP client is attached to the network. The
      LDRA allows Relay Agent Information, including the Interface-ID option
      <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>, to be inserted by the access node so
      that it may be used by the DHCPv6 server for client identification. A
      typical application in a broadband service provider could be
      equivalent to a Layer 2 DHCP Relay Agent as described in the
      Broadband Forum TR-101 report <xref target="TR-101"></xref> and
      in <xref target="L2RA"></xref>.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t><list hangIndent="26" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Access Node">A device that combines many interfaces
          onto one link. An access node is not IP-aware in the data path.</t>

          <t hangText="Address">An IP layer identifier for an interface or set
          of interfaces.</t>

          <t hangText="Client-facing">An interface on the access node that
          carries traffic towards the DHCPv6 client.</t>

          <t hangText="Host">A non-routing IPv6 node that is participating in
          a DHCPv6 message exchange.</t>

          <t hangText="IP">Internet Protocol Version 6 (IPv6).</t>

          <t hangText="LDRA">Lightweight DHCPv6 Relay Agent.</t>

          <t hangText="Lightweight Relay Agent">A function on the access node
          that intercepts DHCP messages between clients and servers. The
          function exists as a bump in the wire on the IP link.</t>

          <t hangText="Link">A communication facility or medium over which
          nodes can communicate at the link layer.</t>

          <t hangText="Link-local address">An IP address having only
          local scope, indicated by having the address prefix fe80::/10, that
          can be used to reach neighbouring nodes attached to the same link.
          Every interface has a link-local address.</t>

          <t hangText="Network-facing">An interface on the access node that
          carries traffic towards the DHCPv6 server(s).</t>

          <t hangText="Node">A device that implements IPv6.</t>

          <t hangText="Router">A node that forwards packets not directly
          addressed to itself.</t>

          <t hangText="Relay Agent">A node that acts as an intermediary to
          deliver DHCP messages between clients and servers and being on the
          same link as the client.</t>

          <t hangText="Unspecified address">An IPv6 address that is comprised
          entirely of zeros.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Server Considerations">
      <t>This document updates the behaviour specified in Section 11 of
      DHCP for IPv6 <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.
       RFC 3315 states, in part:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>If the server receives the message from a forwarding relay agent,
          then the client is on the same link as the one to which the
          interface, identified by the link-address field in the message from
          the relay agent, is attached.</t>
        </list>

      DHCP server implementations conforming to this specification
      MUST, for the purposes of address selection, ignore any link-address
      field whose value is zero. In the above text from RFC 3315,
      "link-address" refers to both the link-address field of the
      Relay-Forward message, and the link-address fields in any
      Relay-Forward messages that may be nested within the Relay-Forward
      message.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Message Format">
      <t>The Lightweight DHCPv6 Relay Agent (LDRA) exchanges DHCP messages
      between clients and servers using the message formats established in
      <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>

      <t>To maintain interoperability with existing DHCP relays and servers,
      the message format is unchanged from <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>. The
      LDRA implements the same message types as a normal DHCPv6 Relay Agent.
      They are:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Relay-Forward Messages</t>

          <t>Relay-Reply Messages</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="Relay-Forward Message">
        <t>The Relay-Forward message is created by any DHCPv6 Relay Agent,
        including an LDRA, to forward messages between clients and servers or
        other relay agents. These messages are built as specified in <xref
        target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>

        <t>
  The Relay-Forward message contains relay agent parameters that
  identify the client-facing interface on which any reply messages
  should be forwarded.  These parameters are link-address, peer-address,
  and Interface-ID.  The link-address parameter MUST be set to the
  unspecified address.  The peer-address parameter MUST be set as
  specified in Section 6.1.  The Interface-ID Relay Agent option MUST be
  included in the Relay-Forward message.  The LDRA MAY insert
  additional relay agent options.
</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relay-Reply Message">
        <t>The Relay-Reply message is constructed by a DHCPv6 server to send
        parameters to a DHCP client when a relay agent is present between the
        server and the client. The Relay-Reply message may be sent after an
        initial Relay-Forward message as the parameters link-address,
        peer-address, and Interface-ID, as well as the relay agent's
        IP address, are learnt from the Relay-Forward message.</t>

        <t>The server MUST include the Interface-ID option in the Relay-Reply
        Message to indicate to the LDRA the interface on which the
        decapsulated message should be forwarded.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mandatory DHCP Options">
        <t>Parameters are exchanged between the DHCP client, Relay Agent, and
        server through the use of DHCP options. There is a set of mandatory
        DHCP options that MUST be included by the LDRA in all Relay-Forward
        messages. These are the:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Relay-Message Option</t>

            <t>Interface-ID Option</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>

        <section title="Relay-Message Option">
          <t>A DHCPv6 Relay Agent relays messages between clients and servers
          or other relay agents through Relay-Forward and Relay-Reply message
          types. The original client DHCP message (i.e., the packet payload,
          excluding UDP and IP headers) is encapsulated in a Relay Message
          option <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>

          <t>If a Relay-Message would exceed the MTU of the outgoing interface,
          it MUST be discarded, and an error condition SHOULD be logged.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Interface-ID Option">
          <t>The LDRA MUST include the Interface-ID option <xref
          target="RFC3315"></xref> in all Relay-Forward messages. When an LDRA
          receives a Relay-Reply message with an Interface-ID option present
          and link-address unspecified, the LDRA MUST relay the decapsulated
          message to the client on the interface identified in the
          Interface-ID option.</t>

          <t>Servers MAY use the Interface-ID for parameter assignment
          policies. The format of the Interface-ID is outside the scope of
          this contribution. The Interface-ID SHOULD be considered an opaque
          value; i.e., the server SHOULD NOT try to parse the contents of the
          Interface-ID option. The LDRA SHOULD use the same Interface-ID value
          for a given interface, and this value SHOULD be retained across
          restarts. This is because if the Interface-ID changes, a server
          will not be able to use it reliably in parameter assignment
          policies.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Agent Behaviour">
      <t>The LDRA MUST have each of its interfaces configured as either
      client-facing or network-facing. The LDRA uses the notion of
      client-facing and network-facing interfaces to process DHCPv6
      messages.</t>

      <section title="Relaying a Client Message">
        <t>The LDRA MUST intercept and process all IP traffic received on any
  client-facing interface that has:</t>

   <t><list style="symbols">
     <t>destination IP address set to All_DHCP_Relay_Agents_and_Servers
     (ff02::1:2);</t>

     <t>protocol type UDP; and</t>

     <t>destination port 547.</t>
   </list></t>

  <t>The LDRA MUST also prevent the original message from being
  forwarded on the network-facing interface.</t>

        <t>The lightweight relay agent adds any other options it is configured
        or required to include in the Relay-Forward message. The LDRA MUST set
        the link-address field of the Relay-Forward message to the Unspecified
        Address (::) and MUST include the Interface-ID option in all DHCP
        Relay-Forward messages.</t>

        <t>If the message received on the client-facing interface is a
        Relay-Forward message, the LDRA MUST set the hop-count field in the
        newly created Relay-Forward message to the value of the hop-count
        field in the received message, incremented by 1 as specified in <xref
        target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The LDRA MUST copy the IP destination and link-layer destination
        addresses from the client-originated message into the IP destination
        address and link-layer destination address of the Relay-Forward
        message.</t>

        <t>The LDRA MUST copy the IP source address from the client-originated
        message into the peer-address field of the Relay-Forward message. The
        LDRA MUST copy the link-layer source address from the
        client-originated message into the link-layer source address of the
        Relay-Forward message.</t>

        <section title="Client Message Validation">
          <t>On receipt of a DHCP message on a client-facing interface, the
          LDRA MUST discard a message if it is of one of the following message
          types:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>ADVERTISE (2)</t>

              <t>REPLY (7)</t>

              <t>RECONFIGURE (10)</t>

              <t>RELAY-REPL (13)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Options contained in the DHCPv6 message MUST NOT be validated by
          the LDRA, making it the responsibility of the DHCP server to check
          message option validity and allow new options to be introduced
          without changes on the LDRA.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Trusted and Untrusted Interfaces">
          <t>In <xref target="RFC3046"></xref>, DHCPv4 Relay Agents had their
          client-facing interfaces set to "trusted" and "untrusted".
          An LDRA MUST
          implement a configuration setting for all client-facing interfaces,
          marking them either as trusted or as untrusted. This setting SHOULD
          be configurable per interface. When a client-facing interface is
          deemed untrusted, the LDRA MUST discard any message of type
          RELAY-FORW (12) received from the client-facing interface.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Relaying a Relay-Reply Message from the Network">
        <t>The LDRA MUST intercept and process all IP traffic received on the
        network-facing interface that has:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>a link-local scoped source address;</t>

            <t>a link-local scoped destination address;</t>

            <t>protocol type UDP; and</t>

            <t>destination port 547</t>

          </list>An LDRA MUST inspect the DHCP message type and only forward
        Relay-Reply messages. Other DHCP message types MUST be silently
        discarded.</t>

        <t>The Relay-Reply message is considered valid by the LDRA if it
        passes the validity checks to be performed by a relay agent per <xref
        target="RFC3315"></xref> and</t>

        <?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>the Interface-ID option is present, and the value corresponds to a
        valid interface in the access node;</t>

        <t>the Relay-Reply peer-address and the destination IP address are
        identical, and it is a link-local scoped address when no IP address is
        configured on the LDRA; and</t>

        <t>the link-address is the Unspecified Address when no IP address is
        configured on the LDRA.</t></list>

<?rfc text-list-symbols="o*+-"?>

        <t>If the Relay-Reply message is valid, the LDRA copies the
        peer-address into the destination IP address field.
 The LDRA SHOULD
        forward the packet to the correct client-facing interface using the
        destination link-layer (Media Access Control (MAC)) address or
        the Interface-ID in the
        Relay-Reply. The LDRA SHOULD NOT retransmit the packet on any other
        interface. The contents of the Relay Message option are put into an
        IP/UDP packet and then forwarded to the client.</t>

        <t>The LDRA MUST copy the link-layer and IP source address from the
        Relay-Reply message into the IP/UDP packet that is forwarded to the
        client.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Topology">
      <t>The LDRA intercepts any DHCPv6 message received on client-facing
     interfaces with the traffic pattern specified in Section 6.1.
     The LDRA MUST NOT forward the original client message to a
     network-facing interface; it MUST process the message and add the
     appropriate Relay-Forward options as described in previous sections.</t>

      <section title="Client and Server on Same Link">
        <t>The access node acts as a bridge; it has no information about any
        IP prefixes that are valid on the link.  Thus, a server should consider
        address and parameter assignment as if the client DHCP message were not
        relayed.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[              +--------+
Client -------|        |
              | Access |
Client -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |     |
Client -------|        |     |
              +--------+     |
                             |      +--------+
                             |------| Server |
                             |      +--------+
              +--------+     |
Client -------|        |     |
              | Access |     |
Client -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |
Client -------|        |
              +--------+

       <--------- IPv6 Link -------->]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For example, if a client sent a DHCP Solicit message that was
        relayed by the LDRA to the server, the server would receive the
        following Relay-Forward message from the LDRA:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
src-ip:              client link-local address

dst-ip:              All_DHCP_Relay_Agents_and_Servers

  msg-type:          RELAY-FORW

  hop-count:         0

  link-address:      Unspecified_Address

  peer-address:      client link-local address

  Interface-ID Option:

    interface-id:    LDRA-inserted interface-id

  Relay-Message Option, which contains:

    msg-type:        SOLICIT

    Solicit Message Options: <from client>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Client and Server behind Relay Agent">
        <t>The client and server are on different IPv6 links, separated by one
        or more relay agents that will typically act as a router. The LDRA
        will send Relay-Forward messages upstream towards the second relay
        agent, which in turn will process the messages.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
              +--------+
Client -------|        |
              | Access |
Client -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |     |
Client -------|        |     |
              +--------+     |
                             |      +--------+       +--------+
                             |------| RelayB |-------| Server |
                             |      +--------+       +--------+
              +--------+     |
Client -------|        |     |
              | Access |     |
Client -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |
Client -------|        |
              +--------+

       <------- IPv6 Link A ------->      <--IPv6 Link B-->]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For example, if a client sent a DHCP Solicit message that was
        relayed by the LDRA to another relay agent and then to the server, the
        server would receive the following Relay-Forward message from the
        LDRA:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
src-ip:              relayB

dst-ip:              server

  msg-type:          RELAY-FORW

  hop-count:         1

  link-address:      relayB address from link A

  peer-address:      client link-local address

  Relay-Message Option, which contains:

    msg-type:        RELAY-FORW

    hop-count:       0

    link-address:    Unspecified_Address

    peer-address:    client link-local address

    Interface-ID Option:

      interface-id:  LDRA-inserted interface-id

    Relay-Message Option, which contains:

      msg-type:      SOLICIT

      Solicit Message Options: <from client>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Relay Agent in Front of LDRA">
        <t>The client and server are on different IPv6 links, separated by one
        or more relay agents that will typically act as a router, and there is
        an <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> Relay Agent on the client-facing
        interface of the LDRA. The LDRA will send Relay-Forward messages
        upstream towards the second relay agent, which in turn will process the
        messages.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
              +--------+
RelayC -------|        |
              | Access |
RelayC -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |     |
RelayC -------|        |     |
              +--------+     |
                             |      +--------+       +--------+
                             |------| RelayB |-------| Server |
                             |      +--------+       +--------+
              +--------+     |
RelayC -------|        |     |
              | Access |     |
RelayC -------|  Node  |-----+
              | (LDRA) |
RelayC -------|        |
              +--------+

      <------- IPv6 Link A ------->      <--IPv6 Link B-->]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For example, if a client sent a DHCP Solicit message that was
        relayed by RelayC and the LDRA to another relay agent, RelayB, and
        then to the server, the server would receive the following
        Relay-Forward message:</t>

         <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
src-ip:               relayB

dst-ip:               server

  msg-type:           RELAY-FORW

  hop-count:          2

  link-address:       relayB address from link A

  peer-address:       relayC

  Relay-Message Option, which contains:

    msg-type:         RELAY-FORW

    hop-count:        1

    link-address:     Unspecified_Address

    peer-address:     relayC

    Interface-ID Option:

      interface-id:   LDRA-inserted interface-id

    Relay-Message Option, which contains:

      msg-type:       RELAY-FORW

      hop-count:      0

      link-address:   global or Unspecified_Address

      peer-address:   end client address

      Interface-ID Option: (if required)

        interface-id: relayC-inserted Interface-ID

      Relay-Message Option, which contains:

        msg-type:      SOLICIT

        Solicit Message Options: <from end client>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>The authors would like to thank the following for their support:
      Lieven Levrau, Alastair Johnson, Robert Haylock, Mickey Vucic, Ludwig
      Pauwels, Fernando Cuervo, John Kaippallimalil, Fredrik Garneij, Alfred
      Hoenes, Ted Lemon, Tatuya Jinmei, David Hankins, and Ralph Droms.</t>

      <t>Comments are solicited and should be addressed to the DHC WG mailing
      list (dhcwg@ietf.org) and/or the authors.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security issues pertaining to DHCPv6 Relay Agents as specified in
      Section 23 of <xref target="RFC3315"> </xref> are also applicable
      to LDRAs. 
      The LDRA SHOULD implement some form of rate-limiting on
      client-originated traffic in order to prevent excessive process
      utilisation. The traffic to be rate-limited can be easily identified
      since the LDRA listens only to client-originated IPv6 traffic
      sent to the All_DHCPv6_Servers_and_Relay_Agents address on UDP port
      547 and does not process any other client-originated traffic. As DHCP is
      session-oriented, messages in excess of the rate-limit may be
      silently discarded.</t>

      <t>The hop-count-based determination of the trustworthiness of the LDRA
      can be easily defeated by a rogue relay agent on the network-facing
      interface of the LDRA.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

   <reference anchor='RFC3315'>
    <front>
    <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Droms' fullname='R. Droms' role="editor">
    <organization /></author>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Bound' fullname='J. Bound'>
    <organization /></author>
    <author initials='B.' surname='Volz' fullname='B. Volz'>
    <organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Lemon' fullname='T. Lemon'>
    <organization /></author>
    <author initials='C.' surname='Perkins' fullname='C. Perkins'>
    <organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Carney' fullname='M. Carney'>
    <organization /></author>
    <date year='2003' month='July' /></front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3315' />
   </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>
          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="TR-101">
        <front>
          <title>Migration to Ethernet-Based DSL Aggregation</title>
          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>The Broadband Forum</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2006" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Technical Report" value="TR-101" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3046">
        <front>
          <title>DHCP Relay Agent Information Option</title>
          <author fullname="Michael Patrick" initials="M." surname="Patrick">
            <organization>Motorola BCS</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2001" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3046" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="L2RA">
        <front>
          <title>Layer 2 Relay Agent Information</title>
          <author fullname="Bharat Joshi" initials="B." surname="Joshi">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Pavan Kurapati" initials="P" surname="Kurapati">
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2011" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>
     </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
