<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>


<rfc
    submissionType="IETF"
    consensus="yes"     
    category="std"
    ipr="trust200902"
    updates="792, 1122, 1812"
    number="6633" >

<front>
    <title abbrev="Deprecation of ICMP Source Quench">Deprecation of ICMP Source Quench Messages</title>

 <author
        fullname="Fernando Gont"
        initials="F."
        surname="Gont">
 
        <organization abbrev="UTN-FRH / SI6 Networks">UTN-FRH / SI6 Networks</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>               
             <street>Evaristo Carriego 2644</street>
		<code>1706</code><city>Haedo</city>
 		<region>Provincia de Buenos Aires</region>
		<country>Argentina</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+54 11 4650 8472</phone>
            <email>fgont@si6networks.com</email>
		<uri>http://www.si6networks.com</uri>
     
        </address>
    </author>    

<date month="May" year="2012"/> 

    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group (tsvwg)</workgroup>



<keyword>congestion control, icmp attacks, tcp, tcp security, udp, dccp, sctp</keyword>

     <abstract>     <t>
This document formally deprecates the use of ICMP Source Quench messages by transport protocols, formally updating RFC 792, RFC 1122, and RFC 1812.
</t>     </abstract> </front>  
<middle> 

<section title="Introduction">
<t>The ICMP specification <xref target="RFC0792"/> defined the ICMP Source Quench message (type 4, code 0), which was meant as a mechanism for congestion control. ICMP Source Quench has been known to be an ineffective (and unfair) antidote for congestion, and generation of ICMP Source Quench messages by routers has been formally deprecated by <xref target="RFC1812"/> since 1995. However, reaction to ICMP Source Quench messages in transport protocols has never been formally deprecated.
</t>

<t>This document formally deprecates reaction to ICMP Source Quench messages by transport protocols such as TCP <xref target="RFC0793"/>, formally updating  <xref target="RFC0792"/>, <xref target="RFC1122"/>, and <xref target="RFC1812"/>. Additionally, it provides a recommendation against the implementation of <xref target="RFC1016"/>. The rationale for these specification updates is as follows:</t>

<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Processing of ICMP Source Quench messages by routers has been deprecated for nearly 17 years <xref target="RFC1812"/>.</t>
<t>Virtually all popular host implementations have removed support for ICMP Source Quench messages since (at least) 2005 <xref target="RFC5927"/>.</t>
<t>Widespread deployment of ICMP filtering makes it impossible to rely on ICMP Source Quench messages for congestion control.</t>
<t>The IETF has moved away from ICMP Source Quench messages for congestion control (e.g., note the development of Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) <xref target="RFC3168"/> and the fact that ICMPv6 <xref target="RFC4443"/> does not even specify a Source Quench message).

<list style="hanging">
<t>ICMP Source Quench messages are not normally seen in the deployed Internet and were considered rare at least as far back as 1994 <xref target="Floyd1994"/>.
</t> 
</list>
</t>
</list>
</t>


<t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
   <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section title="ICMP Source Quench Messages">
<t>The ICMP specification <xref target="RFC0792"/> defined the ICMP Source Quench message (type 4, code 0), which was meant to provide a mechanism for congestion control. The Host Requirements RFC <xref target="RFC1122"/> stated in Section 4.2.3.9 that hosts MUST react to ICMP Source Quench messages by slowing transmission on the connection, and further added that the RECOMMENDED procedure was to put the corresponding connection in the slow-start phase of TCP's congestion control algorithm <xref target="RFC5681"/>.</t>

<t><xref target="RFC1812"/> noted that research suggested that ICMP Source Quench was an ineffective (and unfair) antidote for congestion, and formally deprecated the generation of ICMP Source Quench messages by routers, stating that routers SHOULD NOT send ICMP Source Quench messages in response to congestion.</t>

<t>
<xref target="RFC5927"/> discussed the use of ICMP Source Quench messages for performing "blind throughput-reduction" attacks, and noted that most TCP implementations silently ignore ICMP Source Quench messages.
</t>

<t>We note that TCP implements its own congestion control mechanisms <xref target="RFC5681"/> <xref target="RFC3168"/>, which do not depend on ICMP Source Quench messages.</t>

<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t>It is interesting to note that ICMPv6 <xref target="RFC4443"/> does not specify a Source Quench message.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Updating RFC 1122" anchor="updatingrfc1122">
<t>This document hereby updates Section 3.2.2.3 of <xref target="RFC1122"/> as follows:</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t>A host MUST NOT send ICMP Source Quench messages.</t>
<t>If a Source Quench message is received, the IP layer MAY silently discard it.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Section 4.2.3.9 of <xref target="RFC1122"/> is updated as follows:</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t>TCP MUST silently discard any received ICMP Source Quench messages.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>The consensus of the TSV WG was that there are no valid reasons for a host
to generate or react to an ICMP Source Quench message in the current
Internet. The recommendation that a sender "MUST NOT" send an ICMP Source
Quench message is because there is no known valid reason for a host to generate
this message. The only known impact of a sender ignoring this requirement is
that it may necessarily consume network and endpoint resources. Discarding ICMP
Source Quench messages at the Internet layer (rather than at the transport layer) is a performance optimization that is permitted by this update.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Updating RFC 1812" anchor="updatingrfc1812">
<t>This document hereby updates Section 4.3.3.3 of <xref target="RFC1812"/> as follows:</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t>A router MUST ignore any ICMP Source Quench messages it receives.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The consensus of the TSV WG was that there are no valid reasons for a router to react to ICMP Source Quench messages in the current Internet.</t>
</section>

<section title="Clarification for UDP, SCTP, and DCCP" anchor="SCTPDCCP">
<t>UDP <xref target="RFC0768"/> did not explicitly specify support for ICMP Source Quench messages. Hereby, we clarify that UDP endpoints MUST silently discard received ICMP Source Quench messages.</t>


<t>It is understood that SCTP <xref target="RFC4960"/> and DCCP <xref target="RFC4340"/> did not specify support for processing received ICMP Source Quench messages. Hereby, we clarify that DCCP and SCTP endpoints MUST silently discard received ICMP Source Quench messages. </t>
</section>


<section title="General Advice to Transport Protocols" anchor="updatingrfc792">
<t>If a Source Quench message is received by any other transport-protocol instance, it MUST be silently ignored.</t>

<t>The TSV WG is not aware of any mechanism that requires processing of these messages and therefore expects other transports to follow the recommendations in <xref target="updatingrfc1122"/>. Note that since generation of ICMP Source Quench messages has been deprecated for many years, and since this document additionally deprecates reaction to ICMP Source Quench messages by IETF-specified transports, future applications cannot expect to receive these messages.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Recommendation Regarding RFC 1016" anchor="1016tohistoric">
<t><xref target="RFC1016"/> describes an experimental approach to the handling
of ICMP Source Quench messages in hosts that was considered in 1987. Even though RFC 1016 has never been on the IETF Standards Track, for clarity and avoidance of doubt we note that the approach described in <xref target="RFC1016"/> MUST NOT be implemented. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>ICMP Source Quench messages could be leveraged for performing blind throughput-reduction attacks against TCP and similar protocols. This attack vector, along with possible countermeasures, has been discussed in great detail in <xref target="RFC5927"/> and <xref target="CPNI-TCP"/>. Silently ignoring ICMP Source Quench messages, as specified in this document, eliminates the aforementioned attack vector.
</t>

<t>For current TCP implementations, receipt of an ICMP Source Quench message should not result in security issues because, as noted in <xref target="RFC5927"/> and <xref target="CPNI-TCP"/>, virtually all current versions of popular TCP implementations already silently ignore ICMP Source Quench messages. This is also the case for SCTP and DCCP implementations.
</t>

<t>Hosts, security gateways, and firewalls MUST silently discard received ICMP Source Quench packets and SHOULD log such drops as a security fault with at least minimal details (IP Source Address, IP Destination Address, ICMP message type, and date/time the packet was seen).</t>

<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t>We note that security devices such as the Snort Network Intrusion Detection System (NIDS) have logged ICMP Source Quench messages as such for more than ten years <xref target="Anderson2002"/>.
</t> 
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>IANA has marked ICMP type 4 (Source Quench) as "Deprecated" in the ICMP Parameters registry <xref target="ICMPPARREG"/> with a reference to this document.</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t> The author of this document would like to thank Ran Atkinson, who contributed text that was incorporated into this document and also provided valuable feedback on earlier versions of this document.</t>

<t>The author of this document would like to thank (in alphabetical order) Fred Baker, David Black, Scott Bradner, James Carlson, Antonio De Simone, Wesley Eddy, Gorry Fairhurst, Alfred Hoenes, Mahesh Jethanandani, Kathleen Moriarty, Carlos Pignataro, James Polk, Anantha Ramaiah, Randall Stewart, Dan Wing, and Andrew Yourtchenko, for providing valuable feedback on earlier versions of this document. This document has also benefited from discussions within the TCPM Working Group while working on <xref target="RFC5927"/>.
</t>
<t>Fernando Gont wishes to thank Jorge Oscar Gont, Nelida Garcia, and Guillermo Gont for their love and support.</t>
<t>
Fernando Gont's attendance to IETF meetings was supported by ISOC's "Fellowship to the IETF" program.
</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.0768" ?> 
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.0792" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793" ?> 
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1122" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1812" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4340" ?> 
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960" ?> 
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5681" ?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1016" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3168" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4443" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5927" ?>

	<reference anchor="Floyd1994">
		<front>
			<title>TCP and Explicit Congestion Notification</title>
			<author initials="S. F." surname="Floyd" fullname="S. Floyd">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>

			<date month="October" year="1994"/>
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name="ACM CCR" value="New York, NY"/>
		<seriesInfo name="Volume" value="24"/>
		<seriesInfo name="Issue" value="5"/>

	</reference>


	<reference anchor="Anderson2002">
		<front>
			<title>Heterogeneous Sensor Correlation: A Case Study of Live Traffic Analysis</title>

			<author initials="D. A." surname="Anderson" fullname="D. Anderson">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>

			<author initials="M. F." surname="Fong" fullname="M. Fong">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>

			<author initials="A. V." surname="Valdes" fullname="A. Valdes">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>

			<date year="2002"/>
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 3rd Annual IEEE Information Assurance Workshop" value="New York, NY, USA"/>

	</reference>

	<reference anchor="CPNI-TCP" target="http://www.gont.com.ar/papers/tn-03-09-security-assessment-TCP.pdf">
		<front>
			<title>Security Assessment of the Transmission Control Protocol (TCP)</title>
			<author initials="" surname="CPNI" fullname= "CPNI">
				<organization></organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2009"/>
		</front>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="ICMPPARREG" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/icmp-parameters">
		<front>
			<title>Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP) Parameters</title>
			<author>
                                <organization>IANA</organization>
			</author>
			<date/>
		</front>
	</reference>

        <reference anchor="FreeBSD" target="http://www.freebsd.org">
                <front>
                        <title></title>
                        <author>
                                <organization>The FreeBSD Project</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date />
                </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="Linux" target="http://www.kernel.org">
                <front>
                        <title></title>
<author>
                                <organization>The Linux Project</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date />
                </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="NetBSD" target="http://www.netbsd.org">
<front>
                        <title></title>
                        <author>
                                <organization>The NetBSD Project</organization>
</author>
                        <date />
                </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OpenBSD" target="http://www.openbsd.org">
                <front>
                        <title></title>
                        <author>
                                <organization>The OpenBSD Project</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date />
                </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OpenSolaris" target="http://www.opensolaris.org">
                <front>
                        <title></title>
                        <author>
                                <organization>OpenSolaris</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date />
                </front>
        </reference>


</references>

<section title="Survey of Support of ICMP Source Quench in Some Popular TCP/IP Implementations" anchor="survey">
<t>A large number of implementations completely ignore ICMP Source Quench messages meant for TCP connections.  This behavior has been implemented in, at least, Linux <xref target="Linux"/> since 2004, and in
FreeBSD <xref target="FreeBSD"/>, NetBSD <xref target="NetBSD"/>, OpenBSD
<xref target="OpenBSD"/>, and Solaris 10 since 2005. Additionally, OpenSolaris <xref target="OpenSolaris"/> has always shipped with support for ICMP Source Quench messages disabled.</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
