<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [/]>

<rfc number="6395" category="std" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" >

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>  
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>


    <front>
        <title abbrev="An Interface ID Hello Option for PIM">An Interface Identifier (ID) Hello Option for PIM</title>
	<author initials='S.' surname='Gulrajani' fullname='Sameer Gulrajani'>
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
	    <address><postal>
                <street>Tasman Drive</street>
		<city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region>
		<code>95134</code>
		<country>USA</country>
  	    </postal>
	    <email>sameerg@cisco.com</email></address>
	</author>
        <author initials='S.' surname="Venaas" fullname='Stig Venaas'>
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
	    <address><postal>
                <street>Tasman Drive</street>
		<city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region>
		<code>95134</code>
		<country>USA</country>
  	    </postal>
	    <email>stig@cisco.com</email></address>
        </author>
        <date month="October" year="2011" />

        <abstract>
	  <t>This document defines a new PIM Hello option to advertise 
	  an Interface Identifier that can be used by PIM protocols to uniquely
	  identify an interface of a neighboring router.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
	<section title="Introduction">
	    <t>
	      This document defines a new option for use in PIM Hello
	      messages <xref target="RFC4601"/> to
	      carry an Interface Identifier. A router generates
	      identifiers for each of its PIM-enabled interfaces
	      such that each interface has a different identifier.
	      The identifiers can optionally be generated such that
	      they are unique within, e.g., an administrative domain.
	    </t>



	    <t>An example where this Interface Identifier can be used is with
	      PIM over Reliable Transport (PORT) <xref target="PIM-PORT"/>, where a single
	      Transport connection is used between two routers that have
	      multiple 
	      interfaces connecting them. If these interfaces have unnumbered 
	      or IPv6 link-local addresses, the Interface Identifier included in
	      the PORT Join/Prune message will identify with which interface the
	      message is associated. For PORT, the Router Identifier is
	      not needed, and it can be set to zero.
	    </t>

<t>
All multi-byte integers in this specification are transmitted in 
network byte order (i.e., most significant byte first).
</t>


            <section title="Requirements Notation">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
                and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
            </section>
	</section>

	<section title="Interface Identifier Option">
	  <t>
  The Interface Identifier option is used to identify the
  interface of a neighboring router through which a PIM Hello <xref target="RFC4601"/> was sent.  
  This allows PIM protocols to refer to, or identify, a particular
  interface on a neighboring router.
	  </t>

          <t>
	    The Interface Identifier option need only be included in PIM
	    Hello messages if the router supports protocols that require
	    it. An implementation MAY choose to always include it.
	    The usage of the Interface Identifier and the
	    uniqueness requirements are left to the specifications
	    of the PIM protocols that implement it. It is assumed
	    that different protocols have different minimum
	    requirements for stability and uniqueness of the Interface
            Identifier but that they
	    have no maximum requirement. When specified, these protocols
	    should indicate what their minimum requirements are.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>The Interface Identifier consists of 64 bits. The lower 32
	    bits form a Local Interface Identifier, and the high 32 bits
	    form a Router Identifier.
          </t> 
	  
	  <section title="Local Interface Identifier">
	    <t>
  The 32-bit Local Interface Identifier is selected such that it is
  unique among the router's PIM-enabled interfaces.  That is, there
  MUST NOT be two PIM interfaces with the same Local Interface
  Identifier. While an interface is up, the Identifier MUST always be
  the same once it has been allocated.  If an interface goes down and
  comes up, the router SHOULD use the same Identifier.  If a node goes
  down and comes up again, the Identifier for each interface MAY
  change.  Many systems make use of an ifIndex <xref target="RFC2863"/> as a Local
  Interface Identifier.
</t>
<t>
  The Local Interface Identifier MUST be non-zero.  The reason for
  this is that some protocols may have messages that optionally
  reference an Interface Identifier, and they may use the value of 0
  to show that no Interface Identifier is being referenced. Note that
  the value of 0 is not a valid ifIndex as defined in <xref target="RFC2863"/>.


	    </t>
	  </section>
	  <section title="Router Identifier">
	    <t>
  The 32-bit Router Identifier may be used to uniquely identify the
  router. The requirements for the scope in which the Router Identifier
  needs to be unique depend on the protocols that utilize it. It may 
  need to be unique within some administrative domain, or it may 
  possibly be globally unique. 
</t>
<t>
  A router implementation selects a Router Identifier according to a
  configured policy that defines the uniqueness scope. Thus, an 
  implementation MAY be configured to choose an IPv4 unicast address
  assigned to the router as the Router Identifier, but the 
  implementation MUST allow the identifier to be configured manually.
</t>
<t>
  Protocols such as BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/> and OSPFv2 <xref target="RFC2328"/> are other 
  protocols that make use of 32-bit identifiers for routers. Provided 
  that the stability and uniqueness requirements of the protocols that
  make use of the Router Identifier are met, an implementation MAY use
  the same identifier used by other protocols. 

	    </t>
	    <t>The value 0 has a special meaning for the Router
	      Identifier. It means that no Router Identifier is used.
	      If a router only supports protocols that require the Interface
	      Identifier to be unique for one router (only making use of the
	      Local Interface Identifier), then the implementation MAY set the
	      Router Identifier to zero.
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section title="Message Format" anchor="helloopts">
            <figure>
            <preamble>Option Type: Interface Identifier</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |           Type = 31           |         Length = 8            |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                       Router Identifier                       |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                   Local Interface Identifier                  |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]></artwork>
	    <postamble>Allocated Hello Type values can be found in 
	    <xref target="HELLO-OPT" />.</postamble>
            </figure>
        
	  <t><list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="Length: ">
	    In bytes for the value part of the Type/Length/Value encoding.
	    The Interface Identifier will be 8 bytes long.</t>
  
	    <t hangText="Router Identifier: ">
	    The Router Identifier is a 4-byte identifier uniquely identifying
	    the router within some scope. It MAY be 0 when no protocols
	    require a Router Identifier.  The field MUST contain a valid Router
Identifier or the value zero.</t>

	    <t hangText="Local Interface Identifier: ">
	    The Local Interface Identifier is a 4-byte identifier that is
	    unique among all PIM-enabled interfaces on a router.</t>
          </list></t>
	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations">
	  <t>
	    The Interface Identifier is included in PIM Hello messages.
            See <xref target="RFC4601"/> for security considerations
            regarding PIM Hello messages. In particular, PIM Hello messages
            may be forged and include an arbitrary Interface Identifier,
            or the Interface Identifier may be intentionally omitted.
	    The effects of this depend on
            how the Interface Identifier is used by other protocols.
	  </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="IANA-Considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
	  <t>IANA has assigned the value 31 for the
	    Interface ID PIM-Hello option defined in this document.
           
	  </t>
	</section>

        <section title="Acknowledgments">
	  <t>
	    The authors thank Yiqun Cai, Heidi Ou, Liming Wei,
	    Gorry Fairhurst, Bharat Joshi, and Bill Atwood for
            providing valuable feedback.
	  </t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
        <references title='Normative References'>
	  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119' ?>
	  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4601' ?>
        </references>

        <references title='Informative References'>
	  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2328' ?>
          <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2863' ?>
	  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4271' ?>


 
<reference anchor='PIM-PORT'>

<front>
<title>A Reliable Transport Mechanism for PIM</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Farinacci' fullname='Dino Farinacci'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='IJ' surname='Wijnands' fullname='IJsbrand Wijnands'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Venaas' fullname='Stig Venaas'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Napierala' fullname='Maria Napierala'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='August' day='29' year='2011' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />

</reference>




	    <reference anchor="HELLO-OPT" target="http://www.iana.org/">
  	        <front>
	            <title>PIM Hello Options</title>
		    <author surname="IANA">
		        <organization />
   		    </author>
	          
	        </front>
	    </reference>

	</references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
    </back>
</rfc>
