<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3022 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3022.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc number="6302" category="bcp" seriesNo="162" ipr="trust200902"
submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>

<title abbrev="Internet-Facing Server Logging">Logging Recommendations for Internet-Facing Servers</title>

<author fullname="Alain Durand" initials="A.D." surname="Durand">
<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal>
  <street>1194 North Mathilda Avenue</street>
  <city>Sunnyvale</city>
  <region>CA</region>
  <code>94089-1206</code>
  <country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>adurand@juniper.net</email>

</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Igor Gashinsky" initials="I.G." surname="Gashinsky">
<organization>Yahoo! Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
  <street>45 West 18th St.</street>
  <city>New York</city>
  <region>NY</region>
  <code>10011</code>
  <country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>igor@yahoo-inc.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Donn Lee" initials="D.L." surname="Lee">
<organization>Facebook, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
  <street>1601 S. California Ave.</street>
  <city>Palo Alto</city>
  <region>CA</region>
  <code>94304</code>
  <country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>donn@fb.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Scott Sheppard" initials="S.S." surname="Sheppard">
<organization>ATT Labs</organization>
<address>
<postal>
  <street>575 Morosgo Ave, 4d57</street>
  <city>Atlanta</city>
  <region>GA</region>
  <code>30324</code>
  <country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>Scott.Sheppard@att.com</email>
</address>
</author>


<date year="2011" month="June"/>

<area>General</area>

<workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

<keyword>port logging</keyword>

<abstract>

<t>
In the wake of IPv4 exhaustion and deployment of IP address sharing techniques,
this document recommends that Internet-facing servers log port number and
accurate timestamps in addition to the incoming IP address. 

<!-- [rfced] In the following sentence, should "port number" and "IP addess" be 
plural?  Otherwise, perhaps "timestamps" should be singular?

Original:
   In the wake of IPv4 exhaustion and deployment of IP address sharing 
   techniques, this document recommends that Internet-facing servers log port 
   number and accurate timestamps in addition to the incoming IP address.

Perhaps (plural):
   In the wake of IPv4 exhaustion and deployment of IP address sharing 
   techniques, this document recommends that Internet-facing servers log port 
   numbers and accurate timestamps in addition to the incoming IP addresses.

Perhaps (singular):
   In the wake of IPv4 exhaustion and deployment of IP address sharing
   techniques, this document recommends that Internet-facing servers log the
   port number and an accurate timestamp in addition to the incoming IP 
   address. 
-->

</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<t>
The global IPv4 address free pool at IANA was exhausted in February
2011. Service providers will now have a hard time finding enough IPv4 global
addresses to sustain product and subscriber growth. Due to the huge 
existing global infrastructure, both hardware and software, vendors, and service
providers must continue to support IPv4 technologies for the foreseeable
future. As legacy applications and hardware are retired, the reliance on IPv4
will diminish; however, this is a process that will take years, perhaps decades. 
</t>
<t>
To maintain legacy IPv4 address support, service providers will have little
choice but to share IPv4 global addresses among multiple customers. Techniques
to do so are outside of the scope of this document. All include some form of
address translation/address sharing, being <xref target="RFC3022">NAT44</xref>,
<xref target="RFC6146">NAT64</xref> or <xref
target="DS-LITE">DS-Lite</xref>. 

<!-- [rfced] In the following, does "all" refer to "all techniques"? 

   Techniques to do so are outside of the scope of this
   document.  All include some form of address translation/address
   sharing, being NAT44 [RFC3022], NAT64
   [RFC6146] or DS-Lite [DS-LITE].

If so, we recommend the following update:

   All techniques to do so include some form of address translation/address
   sharing, being NAT44 [RFC3022], NAT64
   [RFC6146], or DS-Lite [DS-LITE].  These techniques are outside the
   scope of this document.

-->


</t>
<t>
The effects on the Internet of the introduction of those address sharing
techniques have been documented in <xref target="RFC6269"/>. 
</t>
<t>
Address sharing techniques come with their own logging infrastructure to track
the relation between which original IP address and source port(s) were
associated with which user and external IPv4 address at any given point in
time. In the past, to support abuse mitigation or public safety requests, the
knowledge of the external global IP address was enough to identify a subscriber
of interest. With address sharing technologies, only providing information
about the external public address associated with a session to a service
provider is no longer sufficient information to unambiguously identify
customers.  
</t>
<t>
Note: This document provides recommendations for Internet-facing servers
logging incoming connections. It does not provide any recommendations about
logging on carrier-grade NAT or other address sharing tools. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Recommendations">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
</t>

<t>
It is RECOMMENDED as best current practice that Internet-facing servers logging
incoming IP addresses from inbound IP traffic also log: 
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The source port number.
</t>
<t>
A timestamp, RECOMMENDED in UTC, accurate to the second, from a traceable time
source (e.g., <xref target="RFC5905">NTP</xref>). 
</t>
<t>
The transport protocol (usually TCP or UDP) and destination port number, 
when the server application is defined to use multiple transports or multiple ports.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Discussion: Carrier-grade NATs may have different policies to recycle ports;
some implementations may decide to reuse ports almost immediately, some may
wait several minutes before marking the port ready for reuse. As a result,
servers have no idea how fast the ports will be reused and, thus, should log
timestamps using a reasonably accurate clock. At this point, the RECOMMENDED
accuracy for timestamps is to the second or better. Representation of
timestamps in UTC is preferred to local time with UTC-offset or time zone, as this
extra information can be lost in the reporting chain. 
</t>
<t>
Examples of Internet-facing servers include, but are not limited to, web
servers and email servers. 
</t>
<t>
Although the deployment of address sharing techniques is not foreseen in IPv6,
the above recommendations apply to both IPv4 and IPv6, if only for consistency
and code simplification reasons. 
</t>
<t>
Discussions about data-retention policies are out of scope for this
document. Server security and transport security are important for the
protection of logs for Internet-facing systems. The operator of the
Internet-facing server must consider the risks, including the data and services
on the server, to determine the appropriate measures. The protection of logs is
critical in incident investigations.  If logs are tampered with, evidence could
be destroyed. 
</t>
<t>
The above recommendations also apply to devices such as load-balancers logging
incoming connections on behalf of actual servers. 
</t>
<t>
The above recommendations apply to current
logging practices. They do not require any changes
in the way logging is performed; e.g., which packets are
examined and logged.
</t>
</section>



<section anchor="ISP" title="ISP Considerations">
<t>
ISP deploying IP address sharing techniques should also deploy a corresponding
logging architecture to maintain records of the relation between a customer's
identity and IP/port resources utilized. 
 However, recommendations on this topic are out of scope for this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
In the absence of the source port number and accurate timestamp information, operators
deploying any address sharing techniques will not be able to identify
unambiguously customers when dealing with abuse or public safety queries. 
</t>

</section>


</middle>

<!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>

<references title="Normative references">

<!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
&RFC2119;

</references>

<references title="Informative references">

<!-- &I-D.ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues; -->

<reference anchor='RFC6269'>
<front>
<title>Issues with IP Address Sharing</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Ford' fullname='Mat Ford' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Boucadair' fullname='Mohammed Boucadair'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Durand' fullname='Alain Durand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Levis' fullname='Pierre Levis'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Roberts' fullname='Phil Roberts'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>The completion of IPv4 address allocations from IANA and the RIRs is causing service providers around the world to question how they will continue providing IPv4 connectivity service to their subscribers when there are no longer sufficient IPv4 addresses to allocate them one per subscriber.  Several possible solutions to this problem are now emerging based around the idea of shared IPv4 addressing.  These solutions give rise to a number of issues and this memo identifies those common to all such address sharing approaches.  Such issues include application failures, additional service monitoring complexity, new security vulnerabilities and so on.  Solution- specific discussions are out of scope.  Deploying IPv6 is the only perennial way to ease pressure on the public IPv4 address pool without the need for address sharing mechanisms that give rise to the issues identified herein.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6269' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues-05.txt' />
</reference>


&RFC3022;

<!-- &I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful; -->

<reference anchor='RFC6146'>
<front>
<title>Stateful NAT64: Network Address and Protocol Translation from IPv6
Clients to IPv4 Servers
</title> 

<author initials='M' surname='Bagnulo' fullname='Marcelo Bagnulo'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Matthews' fullname='Philip Matthews'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='I' surname='van Beijnum' fullname='Iljitsch van Beijnum'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document describes stateful NAT64 translation, which allows IPv6-only clients to contact IPv4 servers using unicast UDP, TCP, or ICMP.  The public IPv4 address can be shared among several IPv6-only clients.  When the stateful NAT64 is used in conjunction with DNS64 no changes are usually required in the IPv6 client or the IPv4 server.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6146' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful-12.txt' />
</reference>


<!-- &I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite; -->
<reference anchor='DS-LITE'>
<front>
<title>Dual-Stack Lite Broadband Deployments Following IPv4 Exhaustion</title>

<author initials='A' surname='Durand' fullname='Alain Durand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Droms' fullname='Ralph Droms'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Woodyatt' fullname='James Woodyatt'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Yiu Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document revisits the dual-stack model and introduces the dual- stack lite technology aimed at better aligning the costs and benefits of deploying IPv6 in service provider networks.  Dual-stack lite enables a broadband service provider to share IPv4 addresses among customers by combining two well-known technologies: IP in IP (IPv4- in-IPv6) and Network Address Translation (NAT).</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite-07.txt' />
</reference>




&RFC5905;
</references>



</back>
</rfc>
