<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" number="6653" submissionType="independent">


<front>
    <title abbrev="Prefix Delegation">
    DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation in Long-Term Evolution (LTE) Networks
    </title>


       <author initials="B.S." surname="Sarikaya" fullname="Behcet Sarikaya">
    <organization>Huawei USA</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>5340 Legacy Dr.</street>
    <street></street>
    <city>Plano</city> <region>TX</region> <code>75074</code>
    </postal>
    <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
    </address>
    </author>  
    
    
       <author initials='F.X.' surname='Xia' fullname="Frank Xia">
    <organization>Huawei USA</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>1700 Alma Drive, Suite 500</street>
    <street></street>
    <city>Plano</city> <region>TX</region> <code>75075</code>
    </postal>
    <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>
    <email>xiayangsong@huawei.com</email>
    </address>
    </author> 
       
       <author initials='T.M.' surname='Lemon' fullname="Ted Lemon">
    <organization>Nominum</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>2000 Seaport Blvd.</street>
    <street></street>
    <city>Redwood City</city> <region>CA</region> <code>94063</code>
    </postal>
    <email>mellon@nominum.com</email>
    </address>
    </author> 
    
     
    <date month="July"  year="2012"/>
    <area>Internet</area>

    <abstract>
    <t>As interest in IPv6 deployment in cellular networks increases,
several migration issues have been being raised; IPv6 prefix management
is the issue addressed in this document.  Based on the idea that DHCPv6
servers can manage prefixes, we use DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation
to address such prefix management issues as an access router
offloading delegation of prefixes and release tasks to a DHCPv6
server.  The access router first requests a prefix for an incoming mobile node
from the DHCPv6 server.  The access router may next do stateless or stateful
address allocation to the mobile node, e.g., with a Router Advertisement or
using DHCP.  We also describe prefix management using Authentication,
Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) servers.</t> 
    </abstract>
</front>


<middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
    <t><xref target="elements"></xref> illustrates the key elements of a typical cellular 
    access network. In a Long-Term Evolution (LTE) network, the Access Router
(AR) is the Packet Data Network (PDN) Gateway <xref target="3GPP-23401"/>.</t>

     <figure anchor="elements" title="Key Elements of a Typical Cellular Network"> <artwork><![CDATA[
                                       +-------------+
                                       |   +------+  |
                                       |   |DHCP  |  |
+-----+   +-----+   +------+  +------+ |   |Server|  | +------+
| MN  |---| BS  |---+Access+--+Access+-+   +------+  +-+Border|
+-----+   +-----+   |  GW  |  |Router| |IP Network(s)| |Router+-Internet
                    +--+---+  +--+---+ |             | +------+
                       |         |     +-------------+
+-----+   +-----+      |         |    +------+
| MN  |---| BS  |------+         |    |AAA   |
+-----+   +-----+                +--- |Server|
                                      +------+
        ]]></artwork> </figure>
    
    <t>The Mobile Node (MN) attaches to a Base Station (BS) through an LTE
air interface. A BS manages connectivity of User Equipment (UE) and extends
connections to an Access Gateway (GW), e.g., the Serving Gateway (S-GW)
in an LTE network. The access GW and the AR are connected via an IP network.
The AR is the first-hop router of the MNs and is in charge of address/prefix
management.</t>
    <t>
    The AR is connected to an IP network that is owned by the
operator; this network is connected to the public Internet via a border
router. The network contains servers for subscriber management, including
Quality of Service, billing, and accounting, as well as a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) server <xref target="RFC6342"/>.
    </t>

    <t>With IPv6 addressing, because mobile network links are point-to-point
(P2P), the per-MN interface prefix model is used <xref target="RFC3314"/> <xref
target="RFC3316"/>.  In the per-MN interface prefix model, 
     prefix management is an issue.</t>

    <t>When an MN attaches to an AR, the AR requests one or more prefixes for
the MN. When the MN detaches from the AR, 
    the prefixes should be released. When the MN becomes idle, the AR should
keep (i.e., not release) the allocated prefixes. 
   </t>
   
    <t>
    This document describes how to use DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation (DHCPv6-PD)
in mobile
networks, such as networks based on standards developed by the 3rd Generation
Partnership Project (3GPP) and it could easily be adopted by the Worldwide
Interoperability for Microwave Access (WiMAX) Forum as well. In view of
migration to IPv6, the number of MNs connected to the network at a
given time may become very high. Traditional techniques such as prefix pools
are not scalable. In such cases, DHCPv6-PD becomes the viable approach to take.
        </t>
        <t>
        The techniques described in this document have not been approved
by the IETF or the 3GPP, except for those techniques described below in <xref
target="MNBased"/>. This document is not a Standard or Best Current
Practice. This document is published only for possible consideration by
operators.
        </t>
        <t>
        This document is useful when address space needs to be managed by
DHCPv6-PD. There are obviously other means of managing address space, including
having the AR track internally what address space is used by what mobile.
        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology and Acronyms">
    <t>
    3GPP - 3rd Generation Partnership Project
    </t>

    <t>
    AAA - Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting
    </t>

    <t>
    AR - Access Router
    </t>

    <t>
    BS - Base Station
    </t>

    <t>
    DHCP - Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
    </t>

    <t>
     E-UTRAN - Evolved Universal Terrestrial Radio Access Network 
    </t>

    <t>
    GPRS - General Packet Radio Service 
    </t>

    <t>
    LTE - Long-Term Evolution 
    </t>

    <t>
    MN - Mobile Node
    </t>

    <t>
    P2P - Point-to-Point
    </t>

    <t>
    PD - Prefix Delegation
    </t>

    <t>
    PDN - Packet Data Network
    </t>

    <t>
    S-GW - Serving Gateway
    </t>

    <t>
    WiMAX - Worldwide Interoperability for Microwave Access
    </t>
    </section> 

    <section anchor="prefixdel" title="Prefix Delegation Using DHCPv6">
    <t>
        "Access router" refers to the cellular network entity that has a DHCP
client. According to <xref target="3GPP-23401"/>, the DHCP client is located in
the PDN Gateway, and so the AR is the PDN Gateway in the LTE architecture.
        </t>

    <section anchor="PrefixRequest" title="Prefix Request Procedure for Stateless Address Configuration">
    
    <t>There are two function modules in the AR: the DHCP client and
the DHCP relay. DHCP messages should be relayed if the AR and a DHCP server are not 
directly connected; otherwise, the DHCP relay function in the AR is not necessary.  <xref target="RequestFigure"></xref> 
    illustrates a scenario in which the AR and the DHCP server aren't
directly connected:</t>

  <figure anchor="RequestFigure" title="Prefix Request"> <artwork> <![CDATA[
  +-------+               +----------------------+    +-----------+
  |  MN   |               |       AR             |    |DHCP Server|
  +-------+               |DHCP     |  Relay     |    +-----------+
      |                   |Client   |  Agent     |          |
      |                   +----------------------+          |
      |1 Initial NW entry |                                 |
      |or attach procedure|                                 |
      |<----------------->|                                 |
      |                   |2 Solicit                        |
      |                   |--------->         Relay-forward |
      |                   |                 --------------->|
      |                   |                   3 Relay-reply |
      |                   |Advertise        <---------------|
      |                   |<--------                        |
      |                   |4 Request                        |
      |                   |--------->         Relay-forward |
      |                   |                 --------------->|
      |                   |                   5 Relay-reply |
      |                   |Reply            <---------------|
      |                   |<--------                        |
      |6  Attach          |                                 |
      | Completed         |                                 |
      |<----------------->|                                 |
      |7 Router           |                                 |
      |  Solicitation     |                                 |
      |------------------>|                                 |
      | 8 Router          |                                 |
      |  Advertisement    |                                 |
      |<------------------|                                 |
    ]]></artwork> </figure>

    <t><list style="numbers">
    <t>An MN (also referred to as UE, or User Equipment, by the 3GPP)
performs initial network entry and authentication procedures, a.k.a. the
attach procedure. </t>

    <t>On successful completion of Step 1, the AR initiates the DHCP Solicit procedure to request 
    prefixes for the MN. The DHCP client in the AR creates and transmits a Solicit message as described in Sections&nbsp;17.1.1
    ("Creation of Solicit Messages") and 17.1.2 ("Transmission of Solicit Messages") of <xref target="RFC3315"/>.  
    The DHCP client in an AR that supports DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation <xref target="RFC3633"/> creates an Identity Association for Prefix Delegation (IA_PD) and assigns it an Identity Association IDentifier (IAID).  The client must include the IA_PD option in the 
    Solicit message. The DHCP client as Requesting Router (RR) must set the
prefix-length field to a value less than, e.g., 48 or equal to 64 to request a
/64 prefix.
    Next, the relay agent in the AR sends to the DHCP server a
Relay-forward message in which a Solicit message is encapsulated.</t>

    <t>The DHCP server sends an Advertise message to the AR in the same way as
that described 
    in Section 17.2.2 ("Creation and Transmission of Advertise Messages") of
<xref target="RFC3315"/>. An Advertise message with the IA_PD shows that
the DHCP
server is capable of delegating prefixes. This message is received encapsulated
in a Relay-reply message by the relay agent in the AR and is sent as an
Advertise message to the DHCP client in the AR.</t>

    <t>The AR (DHCP client and relay agent) uses the same message exchanges as
those described in Section 18 ("DHCP Client-Initiated Configuration Exchange")
of
<xref target="RFC3315"/> and in <xref target="RFC3633"/> to obtain or update
prefixes from the DHCP server.  The AR (DHCP client and relay agent) and 
    the DHCP server use the IA_PD Prefix option to exchange information about prefixes in much the 
    same way as IA Address options are used for assigned addresses. This is
accomplished by the AR sending a DHCP Request message and the DHCP server
sending a DHCP Reply message.</t>

    <t>The AR stores the prefix information it received in the Reply
       message.</t>

    <t>A connection between the MN and AR is established, and the link becomes
active. This step completes the Packet Data Protocol (PDP) Context Activation
Procedure in Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS) and PDN connection establishment in LTE networks.
    </t>

    <t>The MN may send a Router Solicitation message to solicit the AR to send
a Router Advertisement (RA) message.</t>

    <t>The AR advertises the prefixes received in the IA_PD option to the MN
via an RA once the PDP Context/PDN connection is
established, or in response to a Router Solicitation message sent from the
MN. </t>
    
    </list></t>
    <t>
    The 4-way exchange between the AR as RR and the DHCP server as Delegating
Router (DR), as shown in <xref target="RequestFigure"></xref>, may be reduced
to a two-message exchange by using the Rapid Commit option <xref
target="RFC3315"></xref>. The DHCP client in the AR acting as RR includes
a Rapid Commit option in the Solicit message. The DR then sends a Reply message
containing one or more prefixes.
    </t>

    </section> 

    <section anchor="PrefixRequestFull" title="Prefix Request Procedure for Stateful Address Configuration">
        <t>
        Stateful address configuration requires a different architecture than
that shown in <xref target="RequestFigure"></xref>; in this type of 
configuration, there are two function modules in the AR: the DHCP server
and the DHCP client. 
        </t>

        <t>
        After the initial attach is completed, a connection to the AR is
established for the MN. The DHCP client function at the AR as RR and the DHCP
server as DR follow Steps 2 through 5 of the procedure shown in
<xref target="RequestFigure"></xref> to get the new prefix for this interface
of the MN from the IA_PD option exchange defined in <xref target="RFC3633"></xref>.
        </t>

        <t>The DHCPv6 client at the MN sends the DHCP Request to the AR.
          The DHCP server function at the AR must use the IA_PD option received
in the DHCPv6-PD exchange to assign an address to the MN. The IA_PD option must
contain the prefix. The AR sends to the MN a DHCP Reply message containing
the IA address option (IAADDR). <xref target="DHCPRequestFigure"/> shows
the message sequence.
        </t>

        <t>
        The MN configures its interface with the address assigned by the
DHCP server in the DHCP Reply message.
        </t>

        <t>
        In <xref target="DHCPRequestFigure"/>, the AR may be the home
gateway of a fixed network to which the MN gets connected during the
MN's handover.
        </t>
        
 <figure anchor="DHCPRequestFigure" title="Stateful Address Configuration Following PD"> <artwork><![CDATA[
 +----------+             +--------------+             +-----------+
 |  MN      |             |    AR        |             |DHCP Server|
 |   |DHCP  |             | DHCP |DHCP   |             +-----------+
 |   |Client|             |Server|Client |
 +----------+             +--------------+
     |  Initial NW entry     |                           |
     |or attach procedure    |                           |
     |<----------------->    |                           |
     |                       |      DHCPv6-PD exchange   |
     |                       |      similar to Steps 2-5 |
     |   Solicit             |      of Figure 2 (IA_PD)  |
     |---------------------->|                           |
     |   Advertise           |                           |
     |<----------------------|                           |
     |    Request            |                           |
     |---------------------->|                           |
     |                       |                           |
     |                       |                           |
     |                       | Use prefix in IA_PD       |
     |    Reply              | to assign IAADDR          |
     |<--------------------- |                           |
   ]]></artwork> </figure> 

     </section>

     <section anchor="MNBased" title="The MN as Requesting Router in Prefix Delegation">
         <t>
    The AR may use a DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation exchange to get a delegated
prefix shorter than /64 by setting the prefix-length field to a value less
than 64, e.g., 56 to get a /56 prefix. Each newly attaching MN first goes
through the
steps in <xref target="RequestFigure"/>, in which the AR requests a 
shorter prefix to establish a default connection with the MN. 
        </t>

        <t>
    The MN may next request additional prefixes (/64 or shorter) from the AR
using DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation, where the MN is the RR and the AR is the
DR (see <xref target="RFC6459"/> and Section 5.3.1.2.6 of <xref
target="3GPP-23401"/>). In this case, the call flow is similar to that
shown in <xref target="DHCPRequestFigure"/>. The Solicit message must include
the IA_PD option
with the prefix-length field set to 64. The MN may request more than one /64
prefix. The AR as DR must delegate these prefixes, excluding the
prefix assigned to the default connection.  
    </t>
     </section>

    <section anchor="PrefixesRelease" title="Prefix Release Procedure">
 
    <t>Prefixes can be released in two ways: via prefix aging, or via 
the DHCP release procedure. In prefix aging, a prefix should not be used
by an MN when the prefix ages, 
    and the DHCP server can delegate it to another MN.  A prefix lifetime is
delivered from the DHCPv6 server to the MN via the DHCP IA_PD Prefix option
<xref target="RFC3633"></xref> and the RA Prefix Information option <xref
target="RFC4861"></xref>.  <xref target="ReleaseFigure"></xref> illustrates 
how the AR releases prefixes to a DHCP server that isn't directly
connected to the AR:</t>  

    <t><list style="numbers">   
    <t>A signal that an MN has detached, such as switch-off or handover,
triggers the prefix release procedure. </t> 
    
    <t>The AR initiates a Release message to give the prefixes back to
the DHCP server. 
     </t>

     <t>
    The server responds with a Reply message. The prefixes can then
be reused by other MNs.</t>
    </list></t>
    
  <figure anchor="ReleaseFigure" title="Prefix Release"> <artwork><![CDATA[
    +-------+               +-------+             +-----------+
    |  MN   |               |  AR   |             |DHCP Server|
    +-------+               +-------+             +-----------+
        |                       |                       |
        |  1 De-registration    |                       |
        |  handover, or other   |                       |
        |<--------------------->|                       |
        |                       |2 Relay-forward/Release|
        |                       |---------------------->|
        |                       |                       |
        |                       |3 Relay-reply/Reply    |
        |                       |<--------------------- |
        |                       |                       |
        |                       |                       |
        ]]></artwork> </figure>
    </section>     
    
    <section anchor="Miscellaneous" title="Miscellaneous Considerations">
      
    <section anchor="IAID" title="How to Generate an IAID">

    <t>The IAID is 4 bytes in length and should be unique in the scope
of an AR.
The prefix table should be maintained; this table contains the IAID, the
Media Access Control (MAC) address, and the prefix(es) assigned to the MN.
In LTE networks, the International Mobile Equipment Identity (IMEI)
uniquely identifies the MN's interface and thus corresponds to the MAC
address. The MAC address of the interface should be stored in the
prefix table and is used as the key for searching the table.
    </t>

    <t>
    The IAID should be set to Start_IAID; Start_IAID is an integer of
    4&nbsp;octets. The following algorithm is used to generate the IAID:</t> 
    <t><list style="numbers">
    
    <t>Set this IAID value in the IA_PD Prefix option.  Request a
prefix for this MN as described in <xref target="PrefixRequest"></xref> or <xref target="PrefixRequestFull"></xref>.
    </t>
    <t>Store the IAID, MAC address, and received prefix(es) in the
next entry of the prefix table.
    </t>
    <t>Increment the IAID.
    </t>
     </list></t> 
     <t>
     A prefix table entry for an MN that hands over to another AR must
be removed. The IAID value is released and can then be reused.
     </t> 
    </section>     

    <section anchor="Policy" title="Policy to Delegate Prefixes">
    <t>
    In P2P links, if /64 prefixes of all MNs connected to one or more
ARs are broadcast dynamically upstream as route information, high
routing-protocol traffic (IGP, OSPF, etc.) due to per-MN interface
prefixes will result.  There are two solutions to this problem.
One solution is to use static configuration, which would be preferable in many
cases. No routing protocols are needed, because each AR has a known piece of
address space. If the DHCP servers also know that address space, then they
will assign to a particular AR a prefix from that space.
      </t>
      
      <t>
       The other solution is to use route aggregation. For example, each AR can
be assigned a /48 or /32 prefix (an aggregate prefix, a.k.a service provider
common prefix),
     while each interface of an MN can be assigned a /64 prefix. The /64 prefix
is an extension of the /48 prefix -- for example, 
an AR's /48 prefix is 2001:db8:0::/48 -- while an interface of the MN is
assigned a 2001:db8:0:2::/64 prefix.  The border router in <xref target="elements"/> may be manually configured to 
     broadcast only an individual AR's /48 or /32 prefix information to the
Internet.
     </t>
     </section>
    </section>
   </section>
    
    <section anchor="PrefixRADIUS" title="Prefix Delegation Using RADIUS and Diameter">

    <t>
    In the initial network entry procedure shown in <xref target="RequestFigure"/>, the
AR as Remote Authentication Dial In User Service (RADIUS) client sends an
Access&nbhy;Request message with 
    MN information to the RADIUS server.  If the MN passes the authentication, the RADIUS server may send an
    Access&nbhy;Accept message with prefix information to the AR using the
Framed&nbhy;IPv6-Prefix attribute.  The AAA server also provides routing information
to be configured for the MN on the AR using the Framed&nbhy;IPv6-Route attribute.
Using such a process, the AR can handle initial prefix assignments to MNs,
but managing the lifetime
of the prefixes is totally left to the AR. The Framed-IPv6-Prefix is not
designed to support
   delegation of IPv6 prefixes. For this situation, the
Delegated-IPv6-Prefix attribute, which is discussed below, can be used.
    </t>

    <t><xref target="RFC4818"></xref> defines a RADIUS attribute,
Delegated-IPv6-Prefix, which carries an 
    IPv6 prefix to be delegated.  This attribute is usable within either RADIUS or Diameter. 
    <xref target="RFC4818"></xref> recommends that the DR use the AAA
server to receive the prefixes to be delegated, by using the
Delegated-IPv6-Prefix attribute/Attribute-Value Pair (AVP).
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The DHCP server as DR, as shown in <xref target="RequestFigure"></xref>,
may send an 
    Access&nbhy;Request packet containing the Delegated-IPv6-Prefix attribute to the
RADIUS server to request prefixes. In the Access-Request message, the DR may
provide a hint that it would prefer a prefix --
    for example, a /48 prefix.  As the RADIUS server is not required to honor
the hint, the server may delegate a longer prefix -- e.g., /56 or /64 -- 
in an Access-Accept message 
    containing the Delegated&nbhy;IPv6&nbhy;Prefix attribute <xref target="RFC4818"/>. 
     The attribute 
    can appear multiple times when the RADIUS server delegates multiple
prefixes to the DR. 
    The DR sends the prefixes to the RR using the IA_PD option, and the AR
as RR uses them for MNs, as described in <xref target="prefixdel"/>. 
    </t>

    <t>
    When Diameter is used, the DHCP server as DR, as shown
in <xref target="RequestFigure"></xref>, sends an AA-Request message.
    The AA-Request message may contain a Delegated-IPv6-Prefix AVP. 
    The Diameter server replies with an AA&nbhy;Answer message.
    The AA-Answer message may contain a Delegated&nbhy;IPv6-Prefix AVP.
    The AVP 
    can appear multiple times when the Diameter server assigns multiple
prefixes to an MN.
    The Delegated-IPv6-Prefix AVP may appear in an 
    AA-Request packet as a hint from the AR to the Diameter server that it
would
prefer a prefix -- 
    for example, a /48 prefix. The Diameter server may delegate in the
AA-Answer message a /64 prefix, which is an extension of the /48 prefix.
      As in the case of RADIUS, the DR sends the prefixes to the
RR using the IA_PD option, and the AR as RR uses them for the MNs as described
in <xref target="prefixdel"/>.
    </t>
    
    </section>     

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>This document does not introduce any additional message types
and therefore does not introduce any additional threats.
The security procedures for DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3633"></xref>,
RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"></xref>, and Diameter <xref
target="RFC3588"></xref> apply.</t>
    </section> 
  
  <section title='Acknowledgements'>
  <t>
  We are grateful to Suresh Krishnan, Hemant Singh, Qiang Zhao, Ole Troan, Qin
Wu, Jouni Korhonen, Cameron Byrne, Brian Carpenter, Jari Arkko, and Jason Lin,
whose in-depth reviews of this document led to several improvements.
  </t>
  </section>
</middle>


<back>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
<references title='Informative References'>

    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3633'?>
    
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3314'?>

    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315'?>

    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3316'?>
        
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2865'?>

    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3588'?>         
         
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4818'?>                            
      
      <reference anchor="3GPP-23401" >
        <front>
          <title abbrev="3GPP 23.401">
          General Packet Radio Service (GPRS)
enhancements for Evolved Universal Terrestrial Radio Access Network 
(E-UTRAN) access (Release 11)
          </title>
          <author><organization>3GPP</organization> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
<seriesInfo name="TS" value="23.401 V11.0.0"/>
        </reference>

            <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6342'?>

<reference anchor='RFC6459'>
<front>
<title>IPv6 in 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) Evolved Packet System (EPS)</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Korhonen' fullname='J. Korhonen' role="editor">
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Soininen' fullname='J. Soininen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Patil' fullname='B. Patil'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Savolainen' fullname='T. Savolainen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Bajko' fullname='G. Bajko'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Iisakkila' fullname='K. Iisakkila'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6459' />
</reference>

</references> 
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
</back>

</rfc>
