<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4291 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3633 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3646 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3646.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3963 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4885 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4885.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3041 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3041.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4877 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4877.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3776 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3776.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" subcompact="no" strict="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" category="std" ipr="trust200902"
        number="6276">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation for NEMO">
        DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation for Network Mobility (NEMO)
        </title>

    <author initials="R."
      surname="Droms"
      fullname="Ralph Droms">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <street>1414 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
          <city>Boxborough</city>
	  <region>MA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
	  <code>01719</code>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 978.936.1674</phone>
        <email>rdroms@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="P.T."
            surname="Thubert"
	    fullname="Pascal Thubert">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
	  <postal>
	     <street>Village d'Entreprises Green Side</street>
	     <street>400, Avenue Roumanille</street>
	     <code>06410</code>
	     <city>Biot - Sophia Antipolis</city>
	     <country>FRANCE</country>
	  </postal>
	  <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author fullname="Francis Dupont" initials="F." surname="Dupont">
     <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
     <address>
       <email>fdupont@isc.org</email>
     </address>
   </author>


    <author initials="W."
	    surname="Haddad"
	    fullname="Wassim Haddad">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6210 Spine Road</street>
          <city>Boulder</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <country>USA</country>
          <code>80301</code>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 303.473.6963</phone>
	<email>Wassim.Haddad@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="C.J."
            surname="Bernardos"
            fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">
        Universidad Carlos III de Madrid
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad, 30</street>
          <city>Leganes, Madrid</city>
          <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 91624 6236</phone>
        <email>cjbc@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2011" />

    <area>internet</area>
    <workgroup>Mobility Extensions for IPv6 (MEXT)</workgroup>

<keyword>IPv6, mobile router, home agent, mobile network prefix</keyword>


    <abstract>
    
      <t>
      One aspect of network mobility support is the assignment of a
      prefix or prefixes to a mobile router for use on the links in
      the mobile network. This document specifies how DHCPv6 prefix
      delegation can be used for this configuration task. The mobile
      router plays the role of requesting router, while the home agent
      assumes the role of delegating router. When the mobile router is
      outside its home network, the mobile router also assumes the role
      of DHCPv6 relay agent, co-located with the requesting router
      function.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
      One aspect of network mobility support is the assignment of a
      prefix or prefixes to a mobile router for use on the links in
      Network Mobility (NEMO). DHCPv6 prefix delegation (DHCPv6PD)
      <xref target="RFC3633" /> can be used for this configuration
      task.
      </t>

      <t>
      The model of operation of DHCPv6PD for prefix delegation is as
      follows <xref target="RFC3633" />. A delegating router is provided
      IPv6 prefixes to be delegated to requesting routers. A requesting
      router requests prefix(es) from the delegating router. The
      delegating router chooses prefix(es) for delegation, and responds
      with prefix(es) to the requesting router. The requesting router is
      then responsible for the delegated prefix(es). Note that DHCPv6
      options for prefix delegation defined in <xref target="RFC3633" />
      have been defined for general use across routers, and not only for
      mobile routers running the NEMO Basic Support protocol
      <xref target="RFC3963" />.
      </t>

      <t>
      To use DHCPv6PD as a prefix assignment mechanism in mobile networks,
      when the mobile router is located at home, the home agent assumes
      the role of the delegating router and the mobile router assumes the
      role of the requesting router. However, when the mobile router is
      away from home, in addition to the roles when the mobile router is
      located at home, the mobile router also assumes the role of a DHCPv6
      relay agent co-located with the requesting router function.
      </t>

      <t>
      The DHCPv6PD server running at the home agent is provisioned with
      prefixes to be assigned using any of the prefix assignment mechanisms
      described in the DHCPv6PD specification <xref target="RFC3633" />.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">

      <t> 
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
      this document are to be interpreted as described in
      <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
      </t>

      <t>The following terms used in this document are defined in the
      IPv6 Addressing Architecture document <xref target="RFC4291" />:

        <list style="empty">
	  <t>Link-Local Unicast address</t>
	  <t>Link-Local Scope Multicast address</t>
	</list>

      </t>

      <t>The following terms used in this document are defined in the
      Mobile IPv6 specification <xref target="RFC6275" />:

        <list style="empty">
	  <t>Home Agent (HA)</t>
	  <t>Home Link</t>
          <t>Home Address (HoA)</t>
          <t>Care-of Address (CoA)</t>
          <t>Binding Update (BU)</t>
          <t>Binding Acknowledgement (BA)</t>
	</list>

      </t>

      <t> The following terms used in this document are defined in the
      Mobile Network terminology document <xref target="RFC4885" />:

        <list style="empty">
	  <t>Mobile Router (MR)</t>
	  <t>Mobile Network (NEMO)</t>
          <t>Mobile Network Prefix (MNP)</t>
	</list>

      </t>

      <t> 
      The following terms used in this document are defined in the
      DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315" /> and DHCPv6 prefix delegation
      <xref target="RFC3633" /> specifications:

       <list style="empty">
	  <t>Delegating Router (DR; acts as a DHCPv6 server)</t>
	  <t>Requesting Router (RR; acts as a DHCPv6 client)</t>
	  <t>DHCPv6 Relay Agent (DRA)</t>
       </list>

      </t>

      <t>The following acronym is used in this document:

        <list style="empty">
	  <t>DHCPv6PD: DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation</t>
	</list>

      </t>

    </section>
      
    <section title="DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation of Mobile Network Prefixes">

      <t>
      The NEMO Basic Support protocol <xref target="RFC3963" /> extends
      the Mobile IPv6 protocol <xref target="RFC6275" />
      to enable network mobility. With the NEMO Basic Support protocol, a
      mobile router uses Mobile IPv6 to establish and maintain a session
      with its home agent and uses bidirectional tunneling between the
      mobile router and the home agent to provide a path through which
      nodes attached to links in the mobile network can maintain
      connectivity with nodes not in the NEMO.
      </t>

      <t>
      The requirements for Network Mobility <xref target="RFC4885" />
      include the ability of the mobile router to receive delegated
      prefixes that can then be assigned to links in the mobile network.
      DHCPv6PD can be used to meet this requirement for prefix delegation. 
      </t>

      <t>
      To use DHCPv6PD for mobile networks, when the mobile router is
      located at home, the home agent assumes the role of the delegating
      router and the mobile router assumes the role of the requesting
      router. However, when the mobile router is away from home, in
      addition to the roles when the mobile router is located at home,
      the mobile router also assumes the role of a DHCPv6 relay agent
      co-located with the requesting router function.
      </t>

      <t>
      When the mobile router is not at home, the home agent and the
      mobile router exchange DHCPv6PD protocol messages as specified
      in <xref target="RFC6275" />. This means that the
      messages sent by the mobile router MUST include the Home Address
      destination option and messages sent by the home agent MUST make
      use of a Routing Header type 2. See <xref target="fig:topologies" />
      for the deployment topologies when the MR is at home and when it
      is visiting a foreign network.
      </t>

      <figure anchor="fig:topologies" title="Deployment topologies
       of the use of DHCPv6PD for delegation of Mobile Network Prefixes">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
               ------                ------
               | MR |----------------| HA |
               |(RR)| (home network) |(DR)|
               ------                ------

           -------    /-----------\     ------
           | MR  |----|  Internet |-----| HA |
           |(RR) |    \-----------/     |(DR)|
           |(DRA)|                      ------
           -------
      (visited network)
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
      The DHCPv6PD server is provisioned with prefixes to be assigned 
      using any of the prefix assignment mechanisms described in the 
      DHCPv6PD specifications. Other updates to the home agent data
      structures required as a side effect of prefix delegation are
      specified by the particular network mobility protocol. For
      example, in the case of NEMO Basic Network Mobility Support
      <xref target="RFC3963" />, the HA would add an entry in its
      binding cache registering the delegated prefix to the mobile
      router to which the prefix was delegated.
      </t>

      <section title="Exchanging DHCPv6 Messages When the Mobile Router
                      Is Not at Home" anchor="MR_use_of_DHCPv6">

       <t>
       The case when the mobile router is away from home is described
       in this section. <xref target="mr_at_home" /> describes the
       protocol operation for the case when the mobile router is attached
       to its home link. 
       </t>

       <t>
       The mobile router MUST register at the home agent (i.e., by sending
       a Binding Update to the home agent) before initiating a DHCPv6
       message exchange for prefix delegation. The mobile router MUST use
       implicit BU signaling, since the mobile router may not have yet
       requested any prefixes.
       </t>

       <t>
       If the mobile router does not have any active delegated prefixes
       (with unexpired leases), the mobile router MUST initiate a DHCPv6
       message exchange with a DHCPv6 Solicit message as described in
       Section 17 of <xref target="RFC3315" /> and Section 11.1 of
       <xref target="RFC3633" />. The delegating router at the home
       agent responds with an Advertise message. Then, the mobile router
       MUST request a set of prefixes by sending a Request message. The
       delegating router includes the delegated prefixes in a Reply
       message. Note that in this case, the mobile router has previously
       sent a Binding Update to the home agent without knowing yet the set
       of prefixes that it can use as mobile network prefixes. The home
       agent, upon reception of the implicit Binding Update from the
       mobile router, MUST select (in case this was not pre-configured
       already) the prefixes that would then be delegated to the mobile
       router via DHCPv6PD. The home agent, once the DHCPv6 signaling has
       been completed, MUST add an entry in its binding cache including
       the delegated prefixes.
       </t>

       <t>
       In case the mobile router has one or more active delegated
       prefixes -- for example, as if the mobile router reboots or the
       mobile network prefix(es) currently used by the mobile router is
       about to expire -- the mobile router MUST initiate a DHCPv6
       message exchange with a DHCPv6 Rebind message as described in
       Section 18.1.2 of <xref target="RFC3315" /> and Section 12.1 of
       <xref target="RFC3633" />.
       </t>

       <t>
       A DHPCv6 relay agent function <xref target="RFC3315" /> MUST be
       used at the mobile router. This relay agent function is co-located
       in the mobile router with the DHCPv6 client function (see
       <xref target="fig:mr_acting_as_DRA" />). The DHCPv6 signaling
       between the mobile router and the home agent is exchanged between
       the DHCPv6 relay agent in the mobile router and the DHCPv6 server
       on the home agent. DHCPv6 messages from the mobile router to the
       home agent are unicast packets sent from the unicast home address
       of the mobile router to the global unicast address of the home
       agent, and therefore the Home Address destination option MUST be
       used. DHCPv6 replies from the home agent to the mobile router MUST
       be sent using the Routing Header type 2, as specified in
       <xref target="RFC6275" />. The DHCPv6 client in
       the mobile router MUST hand any outbound DHCPv6 messages to the
       co-located relay agent. Responses from the DHCPv6 server are
       delivered to the relay agent function in the mobile router, which
       MUST extract the encapsulated message and deliver it to the DHCPv6
       client in the mobile router.
       </t>

       <figure anchor="fig:mr_acting_as_DRA" title="Signaling sequence when
        the mobile router is not at home">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  -----------------------------                  --------
  |            MR             |                  |  HA  |
  | (RR)                (DRA) |                  | (DR) |
  ----------------------------                   --------
      |                   |       Binding Update    |
      |                   |------------------------>|
      |                   |       (HoA, CoA)        |
      |                   |                         |
      |                   |       Binding Ack       |
      |                   |<------------------------|
      |                   |                         |       
      | DHCPv6 Solicit    |   DHCPv6 Solicit        |
      |..................>|--=====================->|
      |                   |                         |
      |  DHCPv6 Advertise |       DHCPv6 Advertise  |
      |<..................|<-=====================--|
      |                   |                         |
      | DHCPv6 Request    |       DHCPv6 Request    |
      |..................>|--=====================->|
      |                   |                         |
      |      DHCPv6 Reply |       DHCPv6 Reply      |
      |<..................|<-=====================--|
      |                   | (Mobile Network Prefix) |
      |                   |                         |
]]></artwork>
       </figure>

       <t>
       Note that a mobile router using DHCPv6PD to obtain the set of
       prefixes to be used as mobile network prefixes cannot derive its
       home address from one of its mobile network prefix(es) (as the
       mobile router does not know them before registering to the home
       agent). Therefore, the mobile router MUST assign its home address
       from the prefix on its Home Link. 
       </t>

	  <section title="Relay Agent Configuration">

	    <t>
	    The use of the relay agent function in the mobile router
            allows the mobile router to unicast DHCPv6 messages to the
            DHCPv6 server. The relay agent MUST be configured with the
            address of the DHCPv6 server. For the purposes of this
            specification, the relay agent assumes that the home agent
            for the mobile router hosts the DHCPv6 server. Therefore,
            the mobile router MUST configure the DHCPv6 relay agent
            to forward DHCPv6 messages to the home agent.
	    </t>

            <t>
            The DHCPv6 specification supports in certain scenarios the
            use of unicast between the client and the server. However, its
            use presents some difficulties, as the client has to first
            receive a Server Unicast option (Section 22.12 of
            <xref target="RFC3315" />) from the server, which means that
            a Solicit/Advertise message exchange is required in advance. That
            signaling exchange would require the presence of a relay agent on
            the mobile router, and therefore little gain would be achieved in
            this case from the use of the Server Unicast option.
            </t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="Transmission of DHCPv6 Messages">

	    <t>
	    When the DHCPv6 client in the mobile router sends a message,
            it MUST hand the message to the DHCPv6 relay agent in the
            mobile router. The way in which the message is passed to the
            DHCP relay agent is beyond the scope of this document. The
            relay agent encapsulates the message from the client according
            to <xref target="RFC3315" /> in a Relay-forward message and
            sends the resulting DHCPv6 message to the home agent. The relay
            agent sets the fields in the Relay-forward message as follows:

	      <list style="hanging" hangIndent="15">
		<t hangText="msg-type">RELAY-FORW</t>
		<t hangText="hop-count">1</t>
		<t hangText="link-address">The home address of the mobile
                   router</t>
		<t hangText="peer-address">The home address of the mobile
                   router</t>
		<t hangText="options">MUST include a <xref target=
                "RFC3315">"Relay Message option"</xref>; MAY include 
                other options added by the relay agent.</t>
		</list>
	    </t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="Receipt of DHCPv6 Messages">

	    <t>
	    Messages from the DHCPv6 server will be returned to the
            DHCPv6 relay agent, with the message for the DHCPv6 client
            encapsulated in the Relay Message option
            <xref target="RFC3315" /> in a Relay-reply message. The
            relay agent function MUST extract the message for the client
            from the Relay Message option and hand the message to the
            DHCPv6 client in the mobile router. The way in which the
            message is passed to the client is beyond the scope of
            this document.
	    </t>

	  </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="mr_at_home" title="Exchanging DHCPv6 Messages
       When the Mobile Router Is at Home">

       <t>
       When the mobile router is on its home link, the home agent MUST
       use the home link to exchange DHCPv6PD messages with the mobile
       router (<xref target="fig:ha_acting_as_DR" />). In this case, the
       DHCPv6 co-located relay function MUST be disabled. It is the
       responsibility  of the implementation to determine when the mobile
       router is on its home  link. The Home Link Detection mechanism is
       described in Section 11.5.2 of 
       <xref target="RFC6275" />.
       </t>

       <figure anchor="fig:ha_acting_as_DR" title="Signaling sequence for
        the case the home agent is at home">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
               --------                   --------
               |  MR  |                   |  HA  |
               | (RR) |                   | (DR) |
               --------                   --------
                   |                         |
                   |       DHCPv6 Solicit    |
                   |------------------------>|
                   |                         |
                   |       DHCPv6 Advertise  |
                   |<------------------------|
                   |                         |
                   |       DHCPv6 Request    |
                   |------------------------>|
                   |                         |
                   |       DHCPv6 Reply      |
                   |<------------------------|
                   | (Mobile Network Prefix) |
                   |                         |
]]></artwork>
       </figure>

      </section>

      <section anchor="HASelect" title="Selecting a Home Agent That
       Provides DHCPv6PD">

       <t>
       Not all nodes that are willing to act as a home agent are
       required to provide DHCPv6PD. Therefore, when selecting a home
       agent, a mobile router that requires DHCPv6PD service MUST
       identify a home agent that will provide the service. The mobile
       router can determine if a home agent provides DHCPv6PD by
       initiating a DHCPv6 message exchange (i.e., sending a Solicit
       message) in which the mobile router requests delegated
       prefix(es). If the home agent does not respond or responds but
       does not delegate any prefix(es) in its response, the mobile
       router assumes that the home agent does not provide DHCPv6PD
       service. The mobile router continues to query all candidate home
       agents until it finds one that provides DHCPv6PD. Note that in
       this particular case and if the mobile router is away from home,
       the mobile router has to have already performed a Mobile IPv6
       registration with the home agent it queries.
       </t>

       <t>
       Querying a home agent to determine if it provides DHCPv6PD requires
       different operational variables than those recommended by the DHCPv6
       specification. <xref target="RFC3315" /> recommends that under normal
       circumstances, a host will continue to send DHCPv6 Solicit messages
       until it receives a response  (see Section 17 of
       <xref target="RFC3315" />), i.e., the Maximum Retransmission Duration
       (MRD) and Maximum Retransmission Count (MRC) are both set to zero.
       However, a home agent may not respond to the Solicit messages from
       the mobile router because the home agent does not support DHCPv6
       prefix delegation. Therefore, when querying a home agent to determine
       if the home agent provides DHCPv6PD service, it is RECOMMENDED that
       MRD and MRC be set to non-zero values so that the mobile router
       discontinues sending Solicit messages to the home agent after sending
       6 Solicit messages, and conclude that the home agent will not provide
       DHCPv6PD service. Sending 6 queries provides enough reliability for
       scenarios in which the wireless connectivity is lost for a short
       period after sending the first Binding Update message.
       </t>

       <t>
       It is RECOMMENDED that the mobile router uses a sequential probing
       of the home agents for DHCPv6PD service.
       </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Minimizing DHCPv6PD Messages">

       <t>
       The use DHCPv6PD in a mobile network can be combined with the
       Rapid Commit option <xref target="RFC3315" /> to provide DHCPv6
       prefix delegation with a two-message exchange between the 
       mobile router and the DHCPv6PD delegating router.
       </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Other DHCPv6 Functions">

	<t>
        The DHCPv6 messages exchanged between the mobile router and
        the home agent MAY also be used for other DHCPv6 functions in
        addition to DHCPv6PD. For example, the home agent MAY assign
        global addresses to the mobile router and MAY pass other
        configuration information such as a list of available 
        DNS recursive name servers <xref target="RFC3646" /> to the
        mobile router using the same DHCPv6 messages as used for
        DHCPv6PD.
        </t>

        <t>
        The home agent MAY act as a DHCPv6 relay agent for mobile nodes
        while it acts as a delegating router for mobile routers.
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-cons" title="Security Considerations">

     <t> 
     This document describes the use of DHCPv6 for prefix
     delegation in mobile networks. In addition to the security
     considerations for DHCPv6 described in the "Security
     Considerations" section of the <xref target="RFC3315">
     DHCPv6 base specification</xref> and the "Security
     Considerations" of the
     <xref target="RFC3633">DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation
     specification</xref>, there are two aspects that need
     to be considered.
     </t>

     <t>
     First, the NEMO Basic Support specification requires
     the home agent to prevent a mobile router from claiming
     mobile network prefixes belonging to another mobile router.
     Upon reception of an implicit Binding Update from a mobile
     router, the home agent MUST only add prefixes into the mobile
     router's Binding Cache Entry if the mobile router has a valid
     DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation lease for said prefixes. If the mobile
     router does not have a valid DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation lease,
     the home agent MUST NOT add any prefixes into the mobile
     router's Binding Cache Entry. Upon the mobile router obtaining
     a valid DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation lease for a given set of
     prefixes, the home agent MUST add these prefixes to the mobile
     router's Binding Cache Entry. This avoids the home agent
     forwarding traffic addressed to prefixes that have not been yet
     delegated to the mobile router.
     </t>

     <t>
     The use of DHCPv6, as described in this document, requires
     message integrity protection and source authentication. When
     the mobile router is at home, normal DHCPv6 operation is used
     between the mobile router and the home agent and therefore this
     specification does not add any new security issue. While the
     mobile router is away from home, the IPsec security mechanism
     mandated by Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC3776" /> MUST be used
     to secure the DHCPv6 signaling. In the following, we describe the
     Security Policy Database (SPD) and Security Association Database
     (SAD) entries necessary to protect the DHCPv6 signaling. We use
     the same format used by <xref target="RFC4877" />. The SPD and
     SAD entries are only example configurations. A particular mobile
     router implementation and a home agent implementation could
     configure different SPD and SAD entries as long as they provide
     the required security of the DHCPv6 signaling messages.
     </t>

     <t>
     For the examples described in this document, a mobile router
     with home address "home_address_1", and a home agent with
     address "home_agent_1" are assumed. If the home address of
     the mobile router changes, the SPD and SAD entries need to be
     re-created or updated for the new home address.
     </t>

     <t>
     <list>
       <t>
       mobile router SPD-S: <vspace />
       &nbsp; - IF local_address = home_address_1 &amp;<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;remote_address =
       home_agent_1 &amp; proto = UDP &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;local_port = any &amp;
       remote_port = DHCP <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; Then use SA1 (OUT) and SA2 (IN)
       </t>
     </list>

     <list>
       <t>
       mobile router SAD: <vspace />
       &nbsp; - SA1(OUT, spi_a, home_agent_1, ESP, TRANSPORT):<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; local_address = home_address_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; remote_address = home_agent_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; proto = UDP &amp; remote_port = DHCP <vspace />
       &nbsp; - SA2(IN, spi_b, home_address_1, ESP, TRANSPORT):<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; local_address = home_agent_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; remote_address = home_address_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; proto = UDP &amp; local_port = DHCP
       </t>
     </list>

     <list>
       <t>
       home agent SPD-S: <vspace />
       &nbsp; - IF local_address = home_agent_1 &amp;<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;remote_address =
       homa_address_1 &amp; proto = UDP &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;local_port = DHCP &amp;
       remote_port = any <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; Then use SA2 (OUT) and SA1 (IN)
       </t>
     </list>

     <list>
       <t>
       home agent SAD: <vspace />
       &nbsp; - SA2(OUT, spi_b, home_address_1, ESP, TRANSPORT):<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; local_address = home_agent_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; remote_address = home_address_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; proto = UDP &amp; local_port = DHCP <vspace />
       &nbsp; - SA1(IN, spi_a, home_agent_1, ESP, TRANSPORT):<vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; local_address = home_address_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; remote_address = home_agent_1 &amp; <vspace />
       &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; proto = UDP &amp; remote_port = DHCP
       </t>
     </list>

     </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
	<t>
           The authors would like to thank people who have given valuable
           comments on the mailing list. Specific suggestions from Ryuji
           Wakikawa, George Tsirtsis, Alexandru Petrescu, Vijay Devarapalli,
           and Marcelo Bagnulo were incorporated into this document.
        </t>

	<t>
           The authors would like to thank Julien Laganier, Michaela
           Vanderveen, and Jean-Michel Combes for their review of previous
           versions of this document.
        </t>

    </section>

 

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3315;
      &rfc3633;
      &rfc3646;
      &rfc3963;
      &rfc4291;
      &rfc4877;
<!--      &I-D.ietf-mext-rfc3775bis; -->


<reference anchor='RFC6275'>
<front>
<title>Mobility Support in IPv6</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Perkins' fullname='Charles Perkins'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Johnson' fullname='Dave Johnson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Arkko' fullname='Jari Arkko'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document specifies Mobile IPv6, a protocol which allows nodes to remain reachable while moving around in the IPv6 Internet.  Each mobile node is always identified by its home address, regardless of its current point of attachment to the Internet.  While situated away from its home, a mobile node is also associated with a care-of address, which provides information about the mobile node's current location.  IPv6 packets addressed to a mobile node's home address are transparently routed to its care-of address.  The protocol enables IPv6 nodes to cache the binding of a mobile node's home address with its care-of address, and to then send any packets destined for the mobile node directly to it at this care-of address.  To support this operation, Mobile IPv6 defines a new IPv6 protocol and a new destination option.  All IPv6 nodes, whether mobile or stationary, can communicate with mobile nodes.  This document obsoletes RFC 3775.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6275' />

</reference>


      &rfc3776;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &rfc4885;

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>

