<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6275 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3963 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5380 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5380.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4832 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4832.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4877 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4877.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5026 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5026.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3753 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3753.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4283 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4283.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" category="info" number="6612"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PMIPv6-MIPv6 Interactions">Interactions between Proxy Mobile
IPv6 (PMIPv6) and Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6): Scenarios and Related Issues</title>

    <author fullname="Gerardo Giaretta" initials="G." role="editor"
            surname="Giaretta">
      <organization>Qualcomm</organization>

      <address>
        <email>gerardog@qualcomm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2012" />

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>NETLMM Working Group</workgroup>



    <abstract>
      <t>The use of Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) and Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) in the
      same network requires some care. This document discusses scenarios where
      such mixed usage is appropriate and points out the need for interaction
      between the two mechanisms. Solutions and recommendations to enable
      these scenarios are also described.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5213"></xref> is a
      network-based IP mobility protocol standardized by the IETF. In some
      deployment scenarios, this protocol will be deployed together with Mobile
      IPv6 (MIPv6) <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>, for example, with PMIPv6 as
      local mobility protocol and MIPv6 as global mobility protocol. While the
      usage of a local mobility protocol should not have implications on how
      global mobility is managed, since PMIPv6 is partially based on MIPv6
      signaling and data structure, some considerations are needed to
      understand how the protocols interact and how the different scenarios
      can be enabled.</t>

      <t>Some standardization fora are also investigating more complex
      scenarios where the mobility of some nodes is handled using Proxy Mobile
      IPv6, while other nodes use Mobile IPv6; or the mobility of a node is
      managed in turn by a host-based and a network-based mechanism. This
      also needs to be analyzed as a possible deployment scenario.</t>

      <t>This document provides a taxonomy of the most common scenarios that
      require direct interaction between MIPv6 and PMIPv6. The list is not
      meant to be exhaustive. Moreover, this document presents and identifies
      most of the issues pertaining to these scenarios and discusses possible
      means and mechanisms that are recommended to enable them.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>General mobility terminology can be found in <xref
      target="RFC3753"></xref>. The following acronyms are used in this
      document:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>AR (Access Router): first hop router</t>

          <t>BCE (Binding Cache Entry): an entry of the MIPv6 or PMIPv6
          binding cache</t>

          <t>LMA (Local Mobility Anchor): the PMIPv6 mobility anchor as
          specified in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref></t>

          <t>MAG (Mobility Access Gateway): the PMIPv6 client as specified in
          <xref target="RFC5213"></xref></t>

          <t>MN-HoA: the Home Address (HoA) of a Mobile Node (MN) in a PMIPv6 domain</t>

          <t>MN-HNP: the IPv6 prefix that is always present in the Router
          Advertisements that the MN receives when it is attached to
          any of the access links in that PMIPv6 domain (MN-HoA always belongs
          to this prefix.)</t>

          <t>MIPv6-HoA: the HoA the MN includes in MIPv6 Binding
          Update messages</t>

          <t>MIPv6-CoA: the Care-of Address the MN includes in MIPv6 Binding
          Update messages</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
   
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview"
             title="Overview of the Scenarios and Related Issues">
      <t>Several scenarios can be identified where MIPv6 and PMIPv6 are
      deployed in the same network. This document not only focuses on
      scenarios where the two protocols are used by the same MN to
      manage local and global mobility but also investigates more complex
      scenarios where the protocols are more tightly integrated or where there
      is a coexistence of nodes that do or do not implement MIPv6.</t>

      <t>In particular, the scenario space can be split into hierarchical
      deployments and alternative deployments of Mobile IP (MIP) and Proxy
      Mobile IP (PMIP). Hierarchical deployments are scenarios where the two
      mobility protocols are used in the same network in a hierarchical manner
      for global and local mobility management. Alternative deployments are
      scenarios where only one of the two protocols is used for mobility
      management of a given MN.</t>

      <t>The following hierarchical scenarios are identified:</t>

      <t>Scenario A.1: In this scenario, PMIPv6 is used as a network-based
      local mobility management protocol whereas MIPv6 is used as a global
      mobility management protocol. This interaction is very similar to the
      interaction between Hierarchical Mobile IPv6 (HMIPv6) and MIPv6 <xref target="RFC5380"></xref>; MIPv6 is used
      to manage mobility among different access networks, while the mobility
      within the access network is handled by PMIPv6. The address managed by
      PMIPv6 (i.e., the MN-HoA) is registered as the Care-of Address by the MN at
      the Home Agent (HA). This means that the HA has a BCE for MIPv6-HoA
      that points to the MN-HoA.
          <figure title="Scenario A.1" anchor="FigA1">
          <preamble>The following figure illustrates this scenario.</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                        +----+
                        | HA |  MIPv6-HoA -> MN-HoA
                        +----+
                          /\
                         /  \
          +-------------/----\--------------+
         (             /      \              ) Global Mobile IPv6
         (            /        \             ) Domain
          +----------/----------\-----------+
                    /            \
                 +----+         +----+
 MN-HoA -> MAG1  |LMA1|         |LMA2|
                 +----+         +----+
                  //\\             \\
            +----//--\\---+   +-----\\------+
           (    //    \\   ) (       \\      ) Local Mobility Network
           (   //      \\  ) (        \\     ) PMIPv6 domain
            +-//--------\\+   +--------\\---+
             //          \\             \\
            //            \\             \\
           //              \\             \\
        +----+           +----+         +----+
        |MAG1|           |MAG2|         |MAG3|
        +----+           +----+         +----+
          |                |              |
         [MN]
                                ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Scenario A.2: In this scenario, the MN is moving across
      different access networks, some of them supporting PMIPv6 and some
      others not supporting it. Therefore, the MN is roaming from an
      access network where the mobility is managed through a network-based
      solution to an access network where a host-based management (i.e., Mobile
      IPv6) is needed. This scenario may have different sub-scenarios
      depending on the relations between the MIPv6 home network and the PMIPv6
      domain. The following figure illustrates an example of this scenario,
      where the MN is moving from an access network where PMIPv6 is supported
      (i.e., MAG functionality is supported) to a network where PMIPv6 is not
      supported (i.e., MAG functionality is not supported by the AR). This
      implies that the home link of the MN is actually a PMIPv6 domain. In
      this case, the MIPv6-HoA is equal to the MN-HoA (i.e., the address managed
      by PMIPv6).<figure title="Scenario A.2" anchor="FigA2">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                      MIPv6-HoA == MN-HoA -> MAG1
                            +------+
                            |HA/LMA|-----------------------+
                            +------+                       |
                              //\\                         |
                     +-------//--\\--------+               |
                    (       //    \\ PMIPv6 )              |
                    (      //      \\ domain)       +--------------+
                     +----//--------\\-----+       (   Non-PMIPv6   )
                         //          \\            (   domain       )
                        //            \\            +--------------+
                       //              \\                  |
                    +----+           +----+              +----+
                    |MAG1|           |MAG2|              | AR |
                    +----+           +----+              +----+
                      |                |                   |
                     [MN]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>In the scenario illustrated in <xref target="FigA2" />, the non-PMIPv6 domain
      can actually also be a different PMIPv6 domain that handles a different
      MN_HoA. The following figure illustrates this sub-case: the MIPv6-HoA is
      equal to the MN_HoA; however, when the MN hands over to MAG3, it gets a
      different IP address (managed by LMA2 using PMIPv6) and registers it as
      a MIPv6 CoA.<figure title="Scenario A.2 with Visited PMIPv6 Domain" anchor="FigA2Visited">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            MIPv6-HoA == MN-HoA -> MAG_1
                  +-------+
                  |HA/LMA1|-----------------------+
                  +-------+                       |
                    //\\                       +----+
           +-------//--\\--------+             |LMA2|
          (       //    \\  home  )            +----+
          (      //      \\ PMIPv6)       +------||------+
          (     //        \\domain)      (       ||visited)
           +---//----------\\----+       (       ||PMIPv6 )
              //            \\           (       ||domain )
             //              \\           +------||------+
          +----+           +----+              +----+
          |MAG1|           |MAG2|              |MAG3|
          +----+           +----+              +----+
            |                |                   |
           [MN]

                            (a)


           MIPv6-HoA -> MN_CoA
                  +-------+
                  |HA/LMA1|-----------------------+
                  +-------+                       |
                    //\\                       +----+
           +-------//--\\--------+             |LMA2|  MN_CoA -> MAG3
          (       //    \\  home  )            +----+
          (      //      \\ PMIPv6)       +------||------+
          (     //        \\domain)      (       ||visited)
           +---//----------\\----+       (       ||PMIPv6 )
              //            \\           (       ||domain )
             //              \\           +------||------+
          +----+           +----+              +----+
          |MAG1|           |MAG2|              |MAG3|
          +----+           +----+              +----+
            |                |                   |
                                                [MN]

                             (b)
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t> The following alternative deployment has been identified: </t>

      <t>Scenario B: In this scenario, some MNs use MIPv6 to manage
      their movements while others rely on a network-based mobility solution
      provided by the network as they don't support Mobile IPv6. There may be
      a common mobility anchor that acts as MIPv6 Home Agent and PMIPv6 LMA,
      depending on the type of the node as depicted in the figure. However,
      the LMA and HA can also be separated, and this has no impact on the
      mobility of the nodes.</t>

      <figure title="Scenario B" anchor="FigB">
        <artwork><![CDATA[                                  +--------+
                                  | HA/LMA |
                                  +--------+

             +------+                              +------+
             | MAG1 |                              | MAG2 |
             +------+                              +------+

                        +-----------+
                        | IPv6 host |   ----------------->
                        +-----------+       movement
                     +----------+
                     | MIPv6 MN |  ----------------->
                     +----------+       movement
                                 ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Note that some of the scenarios can be combined. For instance,
      Scenario B can be combined with Scenario A.1 or Scenario A.2.</t>

      <t>The following sections describe some possible issues for each
      scenario. Respective recommendations are described in Section 4.3. The
      specifications considered as a baseline for the analysis are the
      following: <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC4877"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="issues_A" title="Issues Related to Scenario A.1">
        <t>This scenario is very similar to other hierarchical mobility
        schemes, including an HMIPv6-MIPv6 scheme. No issues have been
        identified in this scenario. Note that a race condition where the MN
        registers the CoA at the HA before the CoA is actually bound to the
        MAG at the LMA is not possible. The reason is that per the PMIPv6
        specification <xref target="RFC5213" />, the MAG does not forward any packets sent by the MN
        until the PMIPv6 tunnel is up, regardless the mechanism used for
        address allocation.</t>

        <t><xref target="solutions_A"></xref> describes one message flow in
        case PMIPv6 is used as a local mobility protocol and MIPv6 is used as
        a global mobility protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="issues_C" title="Issues Related to Scenario A.2">
        <t>This section highlights some considerations that are applicable to
        scenario A.2. <list style="numbers">
            <t>HoA management and lookup key in the binding cache<list
                style="symbols">
                <t>In MIPv6 <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>, the lookup key in
                the binding cache is the HoA of the MN. In
                particular, the base specification <xref
                target="RFC6275"></xref> doesn't require the MN to include any
                identifier, such as the MN-ID <xref target="RFC4283"></xref>,
                in the Binding Update message other than its HoA. As
                described in <xref target="RFC4877"></xref>, the identifier of
                  the MN is known by the Home Agent after the Internet Key Exchange Protocol (IKEv2) exchange,
                but this is not used in the MIPv6 signaling or as a lookup
                key for the binding cache. On the other hand, as specified in
                <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>, a Proxy Binding Update
                contains the home prefix of the MN, the MN-ID and does not
                include the HoA of the MN (since it may not be known
                by the MAG and consequently by the HA/LMA). The lookup key in
                the binding cache of the LMA is either the home prefix or the
                MN-ID. This implies that lookup keys for MIPv6 and PMIPv6
                registrations are different. Because of that, when the MN
                moves from its home network (i.e., from the PMIPv6 domain) to
                the foreign link, the Binding Update sent by the MN is not
                identified by the HA as an update of the Proxy BCE containing the home prefix of the MN, but a new binding
                cache entry is created. Therefore, PMIPv6 and MIPv6 will always
                create two different BCEs in the HA/LMA, which
                implies that the HA and LMA are logically separated. How to
                handle the presence of the two BCEs for the
                same MN is described in <xref
                target="solutions_C"></xref>.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>MIPv6 de-registration Binding Update deletes PMIPv6 binding
            cache entry<list style="symbols">
                <t>When the MN moves from a MIPv6 foreign network to
                the PMIPv6 home domain, the MAG registers the MN at
                the LMA by sending a Proxy Binding Update. Subsequently, the
                LMA updates the MN's BCE with the MAG
                address and the MAG emulates the MN's home link. Upon
                detection of the home link, the MN will send a
                de-registration Binding Update to its home agent. It is
                necessary to make sure that the de-registration of the MIPv6
                Binding Update does not change the PMIPv6 BCE just created
                by the MAG.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Race condition between Binding Update and Proxy Binding Update
            messages (Sequence Numbers and Timestamps)<list style="symbols">
                <t>MIPv6 and PMIPv6 use different mechanisms for handling
                re-ordering of registration messages and they are sent by
                different entities. In MIPv6, Binding Update messages that are
                sent by the MN to the home agent are ordered by the
                sequence numbers. The other side, in PMIPv6, Proxy Binding
                Update messages that are sent by the MAG to the LMA are
                ordered by a timestamp option. When the MN moves from
                one access where Mobile IP is used to another access when
                Proxy Mobile IP is used, delay in the mobility signaling sent
                may imply adverse situations. For example, if the MN
                sends a Mobile IP Binding Update from access A before moving
                to access B and this Binding Update gets delayed (e.g., a
                refresh Binding Update), the Binding Update may reach the
                combined LMA/HA after the Proxy Binding Update sent by the
                MAG, re-directing packets to access A even after the MN
                has moved to access B.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Threat of compromised MAG<list style="symbols">
                <t>In the MIPv6 base specification <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>,
                there is a strong binding between the HoA registered
                by the MN and the Security Association (SA) used to modify
                the corresponding BCE.</t>

                <t>In the PMIPv6 specification <xref target="RFC5213" />, the MAG sends Proxy Binding
                Updates on behalf of a MN to update the BCE that corresponds to the MN's HoA.
                Since the MAG sends the Binding Updates, PMIPv6 requires
                SAs between each MAG and the LMA.</t>

                <t>As described in <xref target="RFC4832"></xref>, in PMIPv6,
                MAG compromise or impersonation is an issue. <xref target="RFC4832" />,
                Section 2.2, describes how a compromised MAG can harm the
                functionality of an LMA, e.g., manipulating the LMA's routing table
                (or binding cache).</t>

                <t>In this mixed scenario, both host-based and network-based
                SAs are used to update the same binding
                cache entry at the HA/LMA (but see the first bullet of this
                list, as the entry may not be the same). Based on this
                consideration, the threat described in <xref
                target="RFC4832"></xref> is worse as it also affects hosts
                that are using the LMA/HA as MIPv6 HA and not using
                PMIPv6.</t>
              </list></t>

            <!---->
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="issues_B" title="Issues Related to Scenario B">
        <t>In this scenario, there are two types of nodes in the access
        network: some nodes support MIPv6 while some others do not. The
        rationale behind such a scenario is that the nodes implementing MIPv6
        manage their own mobility to achieve better performance, e.g., for
        inter-technology handovers. Obviously, nodes that do not implement
        MIPv6 must rely on the network to manage their mobility; therefore,
        Proxy MIPv6 is used for those nodes.</t>

        <t>Based on the current PMIPv6 solution described in <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>, in any link of the PMIPv6 domain, the MAG
        emulates the MN's home link, advertising the home link prefix
        to the MN in a unicast Router Advertisement message. This ensures that
        the IP address of the MN is still considered valid by the MN itself.
        The home network prefix (and any other information needed to emulate
        the home link) is included in the MN's profile that is
        obtained by the MAG via context transfer or via a policy store.</t>

        <t>However, in case there are nodes that implement MIPv6 and want to
        use this protocol, the network must offer MIPv6 service to them. In
        such a case, the MAG should not emulate the home link. Instead of
        advertising the MN-HNP, the MAG should advertise the topologically
        correct local IP prefix, i.e., the prefix belonging to the MAG, so that
        the MN detects an IP movement, configures a new CoA, and sends a MIPv6
        Binding Update based on <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Analysis of Possible Solutions">
      <section anchor="solutions_A" title="Solutions Related to Scenario A.1">
        <t>As mentioned in <xref target="issues_A"></xref>, there are no
        significant issues in this scenario.</t>

        <t>Figures <xref target="FigLocalFlow" format="counter" /> and
        <xref target="GlobalFlow" format="counter" /> show a
        scenario where an MN is moving from one PMIPv6 domain
        to another, based on the scenario of <xref target="FigA1"
        />. In <xref target="FigLocalFlow"/>, the MN moves
        from an old MAG to MAG2 in the same PMIPv6 domain: this
        movement triggers a PBU to LMA1 and the updating of the
        binding cache at the LMA1.  There is no MIPv6 signaling as the
        CoA_1 registered at the HA is the HoA for the PMIPv6
        session.  In <xref target="GlobalFlow" />, the MN moves from MAG2 in the
        LMA1 PMIPv6 domain to MAG3 in a different PMIPv6 domain: this
        triggers the PMIPv6 signaling and the creation of a binding at
        the LMA2. On the other hand, the local address of the mobile
        node is changed, as the LMA has changed; therefore, the
        MN sends a MIPv6 Binding Update to the HA with the
        new CoA_2.</t>

        <t><figure title="Local Mobility Message Flow" anchor="FigLocalFlow">
            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 +----+            +------+            +------+       +----+
 | MN |            | MAG2 |            | LMA1 |       | HA |
 +----+            +------+            +------+       +----+
   |                  |                    |            | 
   |                  |                    |   +-----------------+    
   |                  |                    |   |  HoA -> CoA_1   |
   |                  |                    |   | binding present |
   |                  |                    |   +-----------------+ 
   |                  |                    |            |
   | CoA conf/confirm |  PBU(CoA_1,MAG_2)  |            |  
   | <--------------->|  ----------------->|            |
   |                  |              +-----------------+|    
   |                  |              | CoA_1 -> MAG_2  ||
   |                  |              | binding updated ||
   |                  |              +-----------------+| 
   |                  |          PBA       |            |
   |                  |   <----------------|            |
   |                  |                    |            | 
   ]]></artwork>
          </figure><figure title="Global Mobility Message Flow" anchor="GlobalFlow">
            <artwork><![CDATA[ +----+            +------+            +------+       +----+
 | MN |            | MAG3 |            | LMA2 |       | HA |
 +----+            +------+            +------+       +----+

   |   CoA config     |  PBU(CoA_2,MAG_3)  |             |
   |<---------------->|------------------->|             |
   |                  |              +-----------------+ |   
   |                  |              | CoA_2 -> MAG_3  | |
   |                  |              | binding created | |
   |                  |              +-----------------+ |
   |                  |          PBA       |             |
   |                  |<-------------------|             |
   |                  |                    |             |
   |                  |  BU (HoA, CoA_2)   |             |
   |---------------------------------------------------->|
   |                  |                    |             |
   |                  |                    |     +-----------------+    
   |                  |                    |     |  HoA -> CoA_2   |
   |                  |                    |     | binding updated |
   |                  |                    |     +-----------------+ 
   |                  | BA                 |             |
   |<----------------------------------------------------|
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="solutions_C" title="Solutions Related to Scenario A.2">
        <t>As described in <xref target="issues_C"></xref>, in this scenario,
        the MN relies on PMIPv6 as long as it is in the PMIPv6
        domain. The MN then uses MIPv6 whenever it moves out of the
        PMIPv6 domain, which basically implies that the MIPv6 home link is a
        PMIPv6 domain.</t>

        <t>Analyzing the issues described in <xref target="issues_C"></xref>,
        it is clear that most of them are applicable only to the case where
        there is a common BCE for the PMIPv6 registration and
        the MIPv6 registration. Issue 1, on how the two protocols identify
        the BCE, is valid only in the case in which we assume that a PMIPv6
        message has any value for a MIPv6 BCE. Also, Issues 2 and 3 are not
        applicable in the case in which different logical BCEs are used by the LMA and the
        HA. For this reason, it is recommended that when the MIPv6 home link
        is implemented as a PMIPv6 domain, the HA/LMA implementation treat
        the two protocols as independent.</t>

        <t>In more detail, the following principles should be followed by the
        HA/LMA implementation:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>PMIPv6 signaling does not overwrite any MIPv6 BCE. In
            particular, when a PMIPv6 BCE is created for an
            MN that has previously created a MIPv6 BCE, the MIPv6
            BCE of the MN is not overwritten, and a new PMIPv6
            BCE is created.</t>

            <t>The downlink packets in the case where both the MIPv6 BCE and PMIPv6 BCE exist are processed as
            follows: <list style="numbers">
                <t>The MIPv6 BCE is processed first. If the
                destination address of the received downlink packet matches
                the BCE of the HA, the packet is forwarded
                by encapsulating it with the CoA contained in the
                BCE.</t>

                <t>If the destination address does not match the MIPv6 BCE,
                the BCE created by PMIPv6 is applied, and the
                packets are encapsulated to the registered MAG.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following subsections provide a description of the procedures
        that will be followed by the MN and HA/LMA based on the
        above principles. The analysis is performed in two different
        subsections, depending on whether the MN moves from a PMIPv6 domain
        to a non-PMIPv6 domain or vice versa.</t>

        <section title="Mobility from a PMIPv6 Domain to a Non-PMIPv6 Domain">
          <t>Let's assume the MN is attached to a PMIPv6 domain and
          there is a valid Proxy BCE at the LMA. Then, the
          MN moves to a different access network and starts using
          MIPv6 (e.g., because PMIPv6 is not supported). The MN needs
          to bootstrap MIPv6 parameters and send a MIPv6 Binding Update in
          order to have service continuity. Therefore, the following steps must
          be performed by the User Equipment (UE):<list style="symbols">
              <t>HA/LMA address discovery: the MN needs to discover
              the IP address of the LMA that has a valid BCE
              for its home network prefix. This is described in <xref
              target="issues_C"></xref> as Issue 4.</t>

              <t>SA establishment: the MN needs to
              establish an IPsec Security Association with the HA/LMA as
              described in <xref target="RFC4877"></xref>.</t>

              <t>HoA or home network prefix assignment: as part of the MIPv6
              bootstrapping procedure, the HA assigns a MIPv6 HoA to the MN.
              This address must be the same the MN was using in the
              PMIPv6 domain.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Since all these steps must be performed by the MN before
          sending the Binding Update, they have an impact on the handover
          latency experienced by the MN. For this reason, it is recommended
          that the MN establish the IPsec SA (and,
          consequently, be provided by the HA/LMA with a MIPv6-HoA) when it is
          initialized. This implies that the MN has MIPv6 stack
          active while in the PMIPv6 domain, but as long as it is attached to
          the same PMIPv6 domain, it will appear to the MN as if it
          is attached to the home link.</t>

          <t>In order to establish the SA with the HA/LMA,
          the MN needs to discover the IP address of the LMA/HA while
          in the PMIPv6 domain. This can be done either based on DNS or based
          on DHCPv6, as described in <xref target="RFC5026"></xref> and <xref
          target="RFC6611"></xref>. The network should be configured
          so that the MN discovers or gets assigned the same HA/LMA
          that was serving as the LMA in the PMIPv6 domain. Details of the
          exact procedure are out of scope of this document.</t>

          <t>When the MN establishes the SA, it
          acquires an HoA based on <xref target="RFC5026"></xref>.
          However, based on PMIPv6 operations, the LMA knows only the home
          network prefix used by the MN and does not know the
          MN-HoA.&nbsp;  For this reason, the MN must be configured to
          propose the MN-HoA as the HoA in the IKEv2 INTERNAL_IP6_ADDRESS
          attribute during the IKEv2 exchange with the HA/LMA. Alternatively,
          the HA/LMA can be configured to provide the entire home network
          prefix via the MIP6_HOME_LINK attribute to the MN as
          specified in <xref target="RFC5026"></xref>; based on this home
          network prefix, the MN can configure an HoA. Note
          that the SA must be bound to the MN-HoA used in
          the PMIPv6 domain as per <xref target="RFC4877"></xref>. Note that
          the home network prefix is shared between the LMA and HA, and this
          implies that there is an interaction between the LMA and the HA in
          order to assign a common home network prefix when triggered by
          PMIPv6 and MIPv6 signaling.</t>

          <t>When the MN hands over to an access network
          that does not support Proxy Mobile IPv6, it sends a Binding
          Update to the HA.  The MN may set the R bit defined
          in the Network Mobility (NEMO) specification (implicit
          mode) <xref target="RFC3963"></xref> in order to indicate
          that the entire HNP is moved to the new CoA. A MIPv6 BCE is
          created irrespective of the existing PMIPv6 BCE. Packets
          matching the MIPv6 BCE are sent to the CoA present in the
          MIPv6 BCE. The PMIPv6 BCE will expire in the case in which the MAG does
          not send a refresh PBU.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Mobility from a Non-PMIPv6 Domain to a PMIPv6 Domain">
          <t>In this section, it is assumed that the MN is in a
          non-PMIPv6 access network, and it has bootstrapped MIPv6 operations
          based on <xref target="RFC5026"></xref>; therefore, there is valid
          binding cache for its MIPv6-HoA (or HNP in case of NEMO) at the HA.
          Then, the MN moves to a PMIPv6 domain that is configured to
          be the home link for the MIPv6-HoA the MN has been
          assigned.</t>

          <t>In order to provide session continuity, the MAG needs to send a
          PBU to the HA/LMA that was serving the MN. The MAG needs to discover
          the HA/LMA; however, <xref
          target="RFC5213"></xref> assumes that the LMA is assigned to the MAG
          or discovered by the MAG when the MN attaches to the MAG.
          The exact mechanism is not specified in <xref
          target="RFC5213"></xref>. A detailed description of the necessary
          procedure is out of the scope of this document. Note that the MAG
          may also rely on static configuration or lower-layer information
          provided by the MN in order to select the correct
          HA/LMA.</t>

          <t>The PBU sent by the MAG creates a PMIPv6 BCE for
          the MN that is independent of the MIPv6 BCE. Traffic
          destined to the MIPv6-HoA (or to the HNP in case the MN had
          set the flag R in the last BU) is still forwarded to the CoA present
          in the MIPv6 BCE. When the MN wants to use the HoA directly
          from the home link, it sends a de-registration message and, at that
          point only, the PMIPv6 BCE is present.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Solutions Related to Scenario B">
        <t>The solution for this scenario depends on the access network being
        able to determine that a particular MN wants to use Mobile
        IPv6. This requires a solution at the system level for the access
        network and may require knowledge of the detailed configuration and
        software capabilities of every MN in the system. These issues
        are out of the scope of this document</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t> Scenario A.1 does not introduce any new security issues in addition
      to those described in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref> or <xref
      target="RFC6275"></xref>. </t>

      <t>For Scenario A.2, this document requires that the a home agent that
      also implements the PMIPv6 LMA functionality should allow both the
      MN and the authorized MAGs to modify the BCEs
      for the MN. Note that the compromised MAG threat described in
      <xref target="RFC4832"></xref> also applies here in a more severe form
      as explained in <xref target="issues_C" />. Scenario B relies on the secure
      identification of MNs and their capabilities so that the right
      service can be provided for the right MNs. For instance, a
      malicious MN should not get the HoA of some other node
      assigned to it, and a MN that desires to employ its own
      mobility management should be able to do so. The ability to identify
      nodes is already a requirement in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>, but
      Scenario B adds a requirement on identification of node capabilities.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">

      <t>Kuntal Chowdhury - kuntal@hotmail.com</t>

      <t>Vijay Devarapalli - vijay.devarapalli@azairenet.com</t>

      <t>Sri Gundavelli - sgundave@cisco.com</t>

      <t>Suresh Krishnan - suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</t>
      
      <t>Ahmad Muhanna - amuhanna@nortel.com</t>
      
      <t>Hesham Soliman - Hesham@elevatemobile.com</t>

      <t>George Tsirtsis - tsirtsis@googlemail.com</t>

      <t>Genadi Velev - Genadi.Velev@eu.panasonic.com</t>
      
      <t>Kilian Weniger - Kilian.Weniger@googlemail.com</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is a merge of four different documents:
      "Proxy Mobile IPv6 and Mobile IPv6 interworking issues" (April 2007), 
      "Proxy Mobile IPv6 and Mobile IPv6 interworking" (April 2007), 
      "Behavior of Collocated HA/LMA" (October 2008), and 
      "Interactions between PMIPv6 and MIPv6: scenarios and related issues"
(November 2007).  Thanks to the authors and 
      editors of those documents.</t>

      <t>The authors would also like to thank Jonne Soininen and Vidya
      Narayanan, NETLMM WG chairs, for their support.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc6275;

      &rfc4832;


      &rfc5213;

      &rfc5026;

      &rfc3963;


      &rfc5380;


      &rfc4877;


      <reference anchor="RFC6611">
        <front>
          <title>Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) Bootstrapping for the Integrated Scenario</title>

          <author fullname="Kuntal Chowdhury" initials="K" role="editor"
                  surname="Chowdhury">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alper Yegin" initials="A"
                  surname="Yegin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2012" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6611"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3753;

      &rfc4283;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
