<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY rfc0822 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0822.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2195 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2195.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2617 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml'> <!--HTTP Digest-->
	<!ENTITY rfc2831 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2831.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc4013 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4013.xml'> <!--SASLPrep-->
	<!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'> <!--ABNF-->
	<!ENTITY rfc4422 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc5802 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5802.xml'> <!--SCRAM-->
	<!ENTITY rfc3766 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3766.xml'> <!--BCP on Key strenght-->
	<!ENTITY rfc5056 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5056.xml'> <!--Channel Bindings-->
	<!ENTITY rfc6151 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6151.xml'> <!--MD5 Security Considerations-->
        <!ENTITY rfc6229 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6229.xml'>
        <!ENTITY rfc3629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml'>
]>

	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
        <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?> 
	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
	<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
	<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
	<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
	<?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="6331" category="info" obsoletes="RFC 2831"
ipr="pre5378Trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title>Moving DIGEST-MD5 to Historic</title>
    
    <author initials='A.' surname="Melnikov" fullname='Alexey Melnikov'>
        <organization>Isode Limited</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
            <street>36 Station Road</street>
            <city>Hampton</city>
            <region>Middlesex</region>
            <code>TW12 2BX</code>
            <country>UK</country>
          </postal>
          <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
          <uri>http://www.melnikov.ca/</uri>
        </address>
    </author>
      
    <date year="2011" month="July"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Kitten Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SASL</keyword>
    <keyword>Kitten</keyword>
    <keyword>DIGEST-MD5</keyword>
    <keyword>Digest</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
      This memo describes problems with the DIGEST-MD5 Simple Authentication
      and Security Layer (SASL) mechanism as specified in RFC 2831.
      It marks DIGEST-MD5 as OBSOLETE in the IANA Registry of SASL mechanisms
      and moves RFC 2831 to Historic status.
	  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and Overview">


	<t><xref target="RFC2831"/> defines how HTTP Digest Authentication <xref target="RFC2617"/>
   	can be used as a Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) <xref target="RFC4422"/>
	mechanism for any protocol that has a SASL profile. It was intended both as an improvement
    over CRAM-MD5 <xref target="RFC2195"/> and as a convenient way to support a single
	authentication mechanism for web, email, the Lightweight Directory Access
Protocol (LDAP), and other protocols.
	While it can be argued that it is an improvement over CRAM-MD5, many implementors commented
	that the additional complexity of DIGEST-MD5 makes it difficult to implement fully and securely.
	</t>

      <t>Below is an incomplete list of problems with the DIGEST-MD5 mechanism
as specified in <xref target="RFC2831"/>:
        <list style="numbers">
		<t>The mechanism has too many options and modes. Some of them are not well described
		   and are not widely implemented. For example, DIGEST-MD5 allows the "qop" directive
		   to contain multiple values, but it also allows for multiple qop directives to be specified.
		   The handling of multiple options is not specified, which results in minor interoperability problems.
		   Some implementations amalgamate multiple qop values into one, while others treat multiple
		   qops as an error. Another example is the use of an empty
authorization identity. In SASL, an empty
		   authorization identity means that the client is willing to authorize as the authentication
		   identity. 

The document is not clear on whether the authzid must be omitted or
		   if it can be specified with an empty value to convey this.
		
		   The requirement for backward compatibility with HTTP Digest means that
		   the situation is even worse. For example, DIGEST-MD5 requires all usernames/passwords that
		   can be entirely represented in the ISO-8859-1 charset to be
down converted from UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/> to
		   ISO-8859-1 <xref target="ISO-8859-1"/>. Another example is the use of quoted strings. Handling of characters that need
		   escaping is not properly described, and the DIGEST-MD5 document has no examples to
		   demonstrate correct behavior.</t>

		<t>The DIGEST-MD5 document uses ABNF from RFC 822 <xref target="RFC0822"/>, which allows an extra construct
		   and allows for "implied folding whitespace" to be inserted in many places. The difference
		   from a more common ABNF defined in <xref target="RFC5234"/> is confusing for some implementors. As a result, many
		   implementations do not accept folding whitespace in many places where it is allowed.</t>

		<t>The DIGEST-MD5 document uses the concept of a "realm" to define a collection of accounts.
		   A DIGEST-MD5 server can support one or more realms.
		   The DIGEST-MD5 document does not provide any guidance on how realms should be named and,
		   more importantly, how they can be entered in User Interfaces (UIs).
		   As a result, many DIGEST-MD5 clients have confusing UIs, do
not allow users to enter a realm,
		   and/or do not allow users to pick one of the server-supported realms.</t>
			
		<t>Use of username in the inner hash is problematic. The inner hash of
DIGEST-MD5 is an MD5 hash of 
colon-separated username, realm, and password. Implementations may choose to store inner hashes
		   instead of clear text passwords. This has some useful properties, such as
		   protection from compromise of authentication databases containing the same username and password
		   on other servers if a server with the username and password is compromised;
		   however, this is rarely done in practice.

		   First, the inner hash is not compatible with
		   widely deployed Unix password databases, and second, changing the username would invalidate
		   the inner hash.</t>
			
		<t>Description of DES/3DES <xref target="DES"/> and RC4 security layers are inadequate to produce
		   independently developed interoperable implementations. In the DES/3DES case,
		   this is partly a problem with existing DES APIs.</t>

		<t>DIGEST-MD5 outer hash (the value of the "response"
directive) does not protect the whole
		   authentication exchange, which makes the mechanism vulnerable to "man-in-the-middle"
		   (MITM) attacks, such as modification of the list of supported qops or ciphers.</t>
			
		<t>The following features are missing from DIGEST-MD5, making it insecure or unsuitable
		   for use in protocols:
			<list style="letters">
				<t>Channel bindings <xref target="RFC5056"/>.</t>
				
				<t>Hash agility (i.e., no easy way to replace the MD5 hash function with another one).</t>
				
				<t>Support for SASLPrep <xref target="RFC4013"/> or any other type of Unicode character normalization of usernames and passwords. The original DIGEST-MD5 document predates SASLPrep
				and does not recommend any Unicode character normalization.</t>
			</list>
		</t>

		<t>The cryptographic primitives in DIGEST-MD5 are not up to today's standards, in particular:
			<list style="letters">
				<t>The MD5 hash is sufficiently weak to make a brute force attack
				   on DIGEST-MD5 easy with common hardware <xref target="RFC6151"/>.</t>

				<t>The RC4 algorithm is prone to attack when
                                   used as the security layer 
                                   without discarding the initial key stream output <xref target="RFC6229"/>.</t>

				<t>The DES cipher for the security layer is considered insecure
				   due to its small key space <xref target="RFC3766"/>.</t>
			</list>
		</t>
        </list>
	</t>

	<t>Note that most of the problems listed above are already present in the HTTP Digest
	authentication mechanism.</t>
		
	<t>Because DIGEST-MD5 is defined as an extensible mechanism, it is possible
	to fix most of the problems listed above. However, this would increase implementation complexity
	of an already complex mechanism even further, so the effort is not worth the cost.
	In addition, an implementation of a "fixed" DIGEST-MD5 specification would likely either
	not interoperate with any existing implementation of <xref target="RFC2831"/> or would be vulnerable
	to various downgrade attacks.</t>

    <t>Note that despite DIGEST-MD5 seeing some deployment on the Internet, this specification
	   recommends obsoleting DIGEST-MD5 because DIGEST-MD5, as implemented, is not a
	   reasonable candidate for further standardization and should be deprecated in favor of
	   one or more new password-based mechanisms currently being designed.
    </t>
	
    <t>The Salted Challenge Response Authentication Mechanism (SCRAM) family of SASL mechanisms <xref target="RFC5802"/> has been developed to provide
       similar features as DIGEST-MD5 but with a better design.
    </t>
	
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security issues are discussed throughout this document.</t>
      
    </section>


    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>IANA has changed the "Intended usage" of the
DIGEST-MD5 mechanism 
		   registration in the SASL mechanism registry to OBSOLETE. The SASL mechanism
		   registry is specified in <xref target="RFC4422"/> and is currently available at:
		</t>

		<figure>
			<artwork>
				<![CDATA[
   http://www.iana.org/assignments/sasl-mechanisms
    ]]>
			</artwork>
		</figure>
	</section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
		<t>The author gratefully acknowledges the feedback provided by
Chris Newman, Simon Josefsson, Kurt Zeilenga, Sean Turner, and Abhijit
Menon-Sen.

		Various text was copied from other RFCs, in particular, from
<xref target="RFC2831"/>.</t>
    </section>    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		&rfc2617;
		&rfc2831;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
		&rfc4422;
		&rfc2195;
		&rfc5234;
		&rfc4013;
		&rfc0822;
		&rfc5802;
		&rfc3766;
		&rfc5056;
		&rfc6151;
                &rfc6229;
                &rfc3629;

		<reference anchor="DES">
			<front>
				<title>Data Encryption Standard (DES)</title>
				<author surname="National Institute of Standards and Technology">
					<organization/>
				</author>
				<date year="1999" month="October"/>
			</front>
			<seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="PUB 46-3"/>
<!--		    
			<format type="TXT" target=""/>
-->
		</reference>
	    


<reference anchor="ISO-8859-1">
<front>
<title>Information technology - 8-bit single-byte coded graphic character
sets - Part 1: Latin alphabet No. 1</title>
<author>
<organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
</author>
<date month="" year="1998" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="8859-1" />

</reference>




    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
