<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc4862 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4191 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6106 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6106.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2868 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2868.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3162 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3162.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3315 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3646 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3646.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3633 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4818 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4818.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4861 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6614 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6614.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6158 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6158.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc number="6911" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RADIUS IPv6 Access">RADIUS Attributes for IPv6 Access
    Networks</title>

    <author fullname="Wojciech Dec" initials="W" role="editor" surname="Dec">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Haarlerbergweg 13-19</street>

          <city>Amsterdam, Noord-Holland 1101 CH</city>

          <country>Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wdec@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Behcet Sarikaya" initials="B" surname="Sarikaya">
      <organization>Huawei USA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Drive, Suite 500</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX</region>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>

        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Glen Zorn" initials="G." role="editor" surname="Zorn">
      <organization abbrev="Network Zen">Network Zen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>227/358 Thanon Sanphawut</street>

          <city>Bang Na</city>

          <region>Bangkok</region>

          <code>10260</code>

          <country>Thailand</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+66 (0) 8-1000-4155</phone>

        <email>glenzorn@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Miles" initials="D" surname="Miles">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <email>davidmiles@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Benoit Lourdelet" initials="B" surname="Lourdelet">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>blourdel@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2013" />


<keyword>AAA</keyword>
<keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
<keyword>IPv6</keyword>



<!-- [rfced] Throughout the text, the following terminology appears to be used 
inconsistently.  

Please review these occurrences and let us know if/how they may be made 
consistent.  

Attribute vs. attribute 
    (e.g., Framed-IPv6-Address Attribute vs. Framed-IPv6-Prefix attribute

-->



    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies additional IPv6 RADIUS Attributes useful in
      residential broadband network deployments. The Attributes, which are
      used for authorization and accounting, enable assignment of a host IPv6
      address and an IPv6 DNS server address via DHCPv6, assignment of an IPv6
      route announced via router advertisement, assignment of a named IPv6
      delegated prefix pool, and assignment of a named IPv6 pool for host
      DHCPv6 addressing.</t>
    </abstract>
</front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document specifies additional RADIUS Attributes used to support
      configuration of DHCPv6 and/or ICMPv6 Router Advertisement (RA)
      parameters on a per-user basis. The Attributes, which complement those
      defined in <xref target="RFC3162"/> and <xref target="RFC4818" />, support the following:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The assignment of specific IPv6 addresses to hosts via DHCPv6.</t>

          <t>The assignment of an IPv6 DNS server address, via DHCPv6 or Router
          Advertisement <xref target="RFC6106" />.</t>

          <t>The configuration of more specific routes to be announced to the user
          via the Route Information Option defined in <xref target="RFC4191" />, Section
          2.3.</t>

          <t>The assignment of a named delegated prefix pool for use with "IPv6 Prefix Options for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) version 6"
          <xref target="RFC3633" />.</t>

          <t>The assignment of a named stateful address pool for use with
          DHCPv6 stateful address assignment <xref target="RFC3315" />.</t>
        </list></t>

<section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t></section>
    </section>

    <section title="Deployment Scenarios">
      <t>The extensions in this document are intended to be applicable across a
      wide variety of network access scenarios in which RADIUS is involved. One
      such typical network scenario is illustrated in Figure 1. It is composed
      of an IP Routing Residential Gateway (RG) or host; a Layer 2 Access Node
      (AN), e.g., a Digital Subscriber Line Access Multiplexer (DSLAM); an IP
      Network Access Server (NAS) (incorporating an Authentication, Authorization,
      and Accounting (AAA) client); and a AAA server.</t>


      <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                                                +-----+
                                                | AAA |
                                                |     |
                                                +--+--+
                                                   ^
                                                   .
                                                   .(RADIUS)
                                                   .
                                                   v
                 +------+                      +---+---+
  +------+       |      |                      |       |
  |  RG/ +-------|  AN  +-----------+----------+  NAS  |
  | host |       |      |                      |       |
  +------+ (DSL) +------+      (Ethernet)      +-------+

                           Figure 1
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In the depicted scenario, the NAS may utilize an IP address
      configuration protocol (e.g., DHCPv6) to handle address
      assignment to RGs/hosts. The RADIUS server authenticates each RG/host
      and returns the Attributes used for authorization and accounting.

      These Attributes can include a host's IPv6 address, a DNS server address,
      and a set of IPv6 routes to be advertised via any suitable protocol, e.g.,
      ICMPv6 (Neighbor Discovery). The name of a prefix pool to be used for
      DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation or the name of an address pool to be used for
      DHCPv6 address assignment can also be Attributes provided to the NAS by
      the RADIUS AAA server.</t>

      <t>The following subsections discuss how these Attributes are 
      used in more detail.</t>

      <section title="IPv6 Address Assignment">
        <t>DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> provides a mechanism to
        assign one or more non-temporary IPv6 addresses to hosts. To provide
        a DHCPv6 server residing on a NAS with one or more IPv6 addresses to
        be assigned, this document specifies the Framed-IPv6-Address
        Attribute (<xref target="framed-ipv6-address"/>).</t>

        <t>While <xref target="RFC3162" /> permits the specification of an IPv6 address via the
        combination of the Framed-Interface-Id and Framed-IPv6-Prefix
        Attributes, this separation is more natural for use with PPP's IPv6
        Control Protocol than it is for use with DHCPv6, and the use of a
        single IPv6 address Attribute makes for easier processing of
        accounting records.</t>

        <t>Because DHCPv6 can be deployed on the same network as ICMPv6
        stateless address autoconfiguration (SLAAC) <xref target="RFC4862"></xref>, it is possible that
        the NAS will require both stateful and stateless configuration
        information. Therefore, it is possible for the Framed-IPv6-Address,
        Framed-IPv6-Prefix, and Framed-Interface-Id Attributes <xref target="RFC3162" /> to be
        included within the same packet. To avoid ambiguity in this case, the
        Framed-IPv6-Address Attribute is intended for authorization and
        accounting of DHCPv6-assigned addresses, and the Framed-IPv6-Prefix and
        Framed-Interface-Id Attributes are used for authorization and accounting
        of addresses assigned via SLAAC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Servers">
        <t>DHCPv6 provides an option for configuring a host with the IPv6
        address of a DNS server. The IPv6 address of a DNS server can also be
        conveyed to the host using ICMPv6 with Router Advertisements, via the
        Recursive DNS Server Option <xref target="RFC6106"></xref>.
        To provide the NAS with the
        IPv6 address of one or more DNS servers, this document specifies the
        DNS-Server-IPv6-Address Attribute (<xref target="DSIA"/>).</t>

      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 Route Information">
        <t>The IPv6 Route Information Option <xref target="RFC4191"></xref>, is intended to be used to inform a host
        connected to the NAS that a specific route is reachable via any given
        NAS.</t>

        <t>This document specifies the Route-IPv6-Information Attribute
        (<xref target="a"/>)
        that allows the AAA
        server to provision the announcement by the NAS of a specific Route
        Information Option to an accessing host. The NAS may advertise this
        route using the method defined in RFC 4191 or
        other equivalent methods. Any other information, such as
        preference or lifetime values, that is to be present in the actual
        announcement using a given method is assumed to be determined by the
        NAS using means not specified by this document (e.g., local configuration
        on the NAS).</t>

        <t>While the Framed-IPv6-Prefix Attribute (<xref target="RFC3162" />, Section
        2.3) allows the route to be advertised in an RA, it cannot be used to
        configure more specific routes. While the Framed-IPv6-Route Attribute
        (<xref target="RFC3162" />, Section 2.5) causes the route to be configured on
        the NAS and potentially to be announced via an IP routing protocol,
        depending on the value of Framed-Routing, it does not result in the
        route being announced in an RA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Delegated IPv6 Prefix Pool">
        <t>DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation (DHCPv6-PD) <xref target="RFC3633"></xref>
        involves a delegating router selecting a prefix and delegating it on a
        temporary basis to a requesting router. The delegating router may
        implement a number of strategies as to how it chooses what prefix is
        to be delegated to a requesting router, one of them being the use of a
        local named prefix pool. The Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool Attribute
        (<xref target="DIPP"/>)
        allows the RADIUS server to convey a prefix pool name to a NAS that is hosting
        a DHCPv6-PD server and that is acting as a delegating router.</t>

        <t>Because DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation can be used with SLAAC on the same
        network, it is possible for the Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool and
        Framed-IPv6-Pool Attributes to be included within the same packet. To
        avoid ambiguity in this scenario, use of the
        Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool Attribute should be restricted to
        authorization and accounting of prefix pools used in DHCPv6 Prefix
        Delegation, and the Framed-IPv6-Pool Attribute should be used for
        authorization and accounting of prefix pools used in SLAAC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stateful IPv6 Address Pool">
        <t>DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315" /> provides a mechanism to assign one or more
        non-temporary IPv6 addresses to hosts. <xref target="framed-ipv6-address"/>
        introduces the
        Framed-IPv6-Address Attribute to be used to provide a DHCPv6 server
        residing on a NAS with one or more IPv6 addresses to be assigned to
        the clients. An alternative way to achieve a similar result is for the
        NAS to select the IPv6 address to be assigned from an address pool
        configured for this purpose on the NAS. This document specifies the
        Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool Attribute (<xref target="SIAP"/>)
        to allow the RADIUS server to
        convey a pool name to be used for such stateful DHCPv6-based
        addressing and for any subsequent accounting.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Attributes">
      <t>The fields shown in the diagrams below are transmitted from left to
      right.</t>

      <section title="Framed-IPv6-Address" anchor="framed-ipv6-address">
        <t>The Framed-IPv6-Address Attribute indicates an IPv6 address that is assigned to the
        NAS-facing interface of the RG/host. It MAY be used in Access-Accept
        packets and MAY appear multiple times. It MAY be used in an
        Access-Request packet as a hint by the NAS to the RADIUS server that
        it would prefer this IPv6 address, but the RADIUS server is not
        required to honor the hint. Because it is assumed that the NAS will add
        a route corresponding to the address, it is not necessary for the
        RADIUS server to also send a host Framed-IPv6-Route Attribute for the
        same address.</t>

        <t>This Attribute can be used by a DHCPv6 process on the NAS to assign
        a unique IPv6 address to the RG/host.</t>

        <t>A summary of the Framed-IPv6-Address Attribute format is shown
        below. The format of the Address field is identical to that of
        the corresponding field in the NAS-IPv6-Address Attribute
        <xref target="RFC3162" />.
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |     Length    |            Address
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          Address (cont)         |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure> <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 168 for
            Framed-IPv6-Address</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 18</t>

            <t hangText="Address"><vspace blankLines="1" /> A 128-bit IPv6 address.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="DSIA" title="DNS-Server-IPv6-Address">
        <t>The DNS-Server-IPv6-Address Attribute contains the IPv6 address of
        a DNS server. This Attribute MAY be included multiple times in
        Access-Accept packets when the intention is for a NAS to announce
        more than one DNS server address to an RG/host. 


        The Attribute MAY be used in an Access-Request packet
        as a hint by the NAS to the RADIUS server regarding the DNS IPv6
        address, but the RADIUS server is not required to honor the hint.</t>

        <t>
          The content of this Attribute can be copied to an instance of
        the DHCPv6 DNS Recursive Name Server Option <xref target="RFC3646"></xref>
        or to an IPv6 Router
        Advertisement Recursive DNS Server Option <xref target="RFC6106"></xref>.
        If more than one DNS-Server-IPv6-Address Attribute is present in
        the Access-Accept packet, the
        addresses from the Attributes SHOULD be copied in the same order as received.</t>


        <t></t>

        <t>A summary of the DNS-Server-IPv6-Address Attribute format is given
        below. The format of the Address field
        is the same as that of the corresponding field in the NAS-IPv6-Address
        Attribute <xref target="RFC3162" />.
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |     Length    |            Address
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                           Address (cont)                        
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          Address (cont)         |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure> <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 169 for
            DNS-Server-IPv6-Address</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 18</t>

            <t hangText="Address"><vspace blankLines="1" /> The 128-bit IPv6
            address of a DNS server.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="a" title="Route-IPv6-Information">
        <t>The Route-IPv6-Information Attribute specifies a prefix (and corresponding route) for the
        user on the NAS, which is to be announced using the Route Information
        Option defined in "Default Router Preferences and More Specific
        Routes" <xref target="RFC4191" />, Section 2.3. It is used in the Access-Accept packet
        and can appear multiple times. It MAY be used in an Access-Request
        packet as a hint by the NAS to the RADIUS server, but the RADIUS
        server is not required to honor the hint. The Route-IPv6-Information
        Attribute format is depicted below. The format of the prefix is as per
        <xref target="RFC3162" />.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |     Type      |    Length     |   Reserved    | Prefix-Length |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                                                               |
      .                        Prefix (variable)                      .
      .                                                               .
      |                                                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 170 for
            Route-IPv6-Information</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1" /> Length, in bytes. At
            least 4 and no larger than 20; typically, 12 or less.</t>

            <t hangText="Prefix Length"><vspace blankLines="1" />8-bit
            unsigned integer. The number of leading bits in the prefix that
            are valid. The value can range from 0 to 128. The prefix field is 0,
            8, or 16 octets depending on Length.</t>

            <t hangText="Prefix"><vspace blankLines="1" />Variable-length
            field containing an IP prefix. The prefix length field contains
            the number of valid leading bits in the prefix. The bits in the
            prefix after the prefix length, if any, are reserved and MUST be
            initialized to zero.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <?rfc needLines="10"?>

      <section title="Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool" anchor="DIPP">
        <t>The Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool Attribute contains the name of an assigned pool that SHOULD be
        used to select an IPv6 delegated prefix for the user on the NAS. If a
        NAS does not support prefix pools, the NAS MUST ignore this Attribute.
        It MAY be used in an Access-Request packet as a hint by the NAS to the
        RADIUS server regarding the pool, but the RADIUS server is not
        required to honor the hint.</t>

        <t>A summary of the Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool Attribute format is
        shown below.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |    Length     |     String...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 171 for
            Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1" /> Length, in bytes. At
            least 3.</t>

            <t hangText="String"><vspace blankLines="1" />The string field
            contains the name of an assigned IPv6 prefix pool configured on
            the NAS. The field is not NULL (hexadecimal 00) terminated.</t>
          </list>Note: The string data type is as documented in <xref
        target="RFC6158"></xref> and carries binary data that is external to
        the RADIUS protocol, e.g., the name of a pool of prefixes configured on
        the NAS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool" anchor="SIAP">
        <t>The Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool Attribute contains the name of an assigned pool that SHOULD be
        used to select an IPv6 address for the user on the NAS. If a NAS does
        not support address pools, the NAS MUST ignore this Attribute. A
        summary of the Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool Attribute format is shown
        below. It MAY be used in an Access-Request packet as a hint by the NAS
        to the RADIUS server regarding the pool, but the RADIUS server is not
        required to honor the hint.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |    Length     |     String...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1" /> 172 for
            Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1" /> Length, in bytes. At
            least 3.</t>

            <t hangText="String"><vspace blankLines="1" />The string field
            contains the name of an assigned IPv6 stateful address pool
            configured on the NAS. The field is not NULL (hexadecimal 00)
            terminated.</t>
          </list>Note: The string data type is as documented in <xref
        target="RFC6158"></xref> and carries binary data that is external to
        the RADIUS protocol, e.g., the name of a pool of addresses configured on
        the NAS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Table of Attributes">
        <t>The following table provides a guide to which Attributes may be
        found in which kinds of packets, and in what quantity. The optional
        inclusion of the options in Access Request messages is intended to
        allow for a NAS to provide the RADIUS server
        with a hint of the Attributes in advance of user authentication, which
        may be useful in cases in which a user reconnects or has a static
        address. The server is under no obligation to honor such hints.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Request Accept Reject Challenge Accounting  #  Attribute
                                Request 
0+      0+     0      0         0+   168   Framed-IPv6-Address
0+      0+     0      0         0+   169   DNS-Server-IPv6-Address
0+      0+     0      0         0+   170   Route-IPv6-Information
0+      0+     0      0         0+   171   Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool
0+      0+     0      0         0+   172   Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Diameter Considerations">
      <t>Given that the Attributes defined in this document are allocated from
      the standard RADIUS type space (see <xref target="IANA"></xref>), no
      special handling is required by Diameter entities.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document specifies additional IPv6 RADIUS Attributes useful in
      residential broadband network deployments. In such networks, the RADIUS
      protocol may run either over IPv4 or over IPv6, and known security
      vulnerabilities of the RADIUS protocol, e.g., <xref target="SECI" />, apply to the
      Attributes defined in this document. A trust relationship between a NAS
      and RADIUS server is expected to be in place, with communication
      optionally secured by IPsec or Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC6614"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has assigned five new RADIUS Attribute
      types in the "Radius Attribute Types" registry (currently located at
      http://www.iana.org/assignments/radius-types) for the following
      Attributes: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Framed-IPv6-Address</t>

          <t>DNS-Server-IPv6-Address</t>

          <t>Route-IPv6-Information</t>

          <t>Delegated-IPv6-Prefix-Pool</t>

          <t>Stateful-IPv6-Address-Pool</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank 
 Bernard Aboba,
 Benoit Claise,
 Peter Deacon,
 Alan DeKok,
 Ralph Droms,
 Brian Haberman,
 Alfred Hines,
 Stephen Farrell,
 Jouni Korhonen,
 Roberta Maglione, 
 Pete Resnick,
 Mark Smith,
 and Leaf Yeh
  for their help and comments in reviewing this document.</t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc4862;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3162;

      &rfc3315;

      &rfc3633;

      &rfc3646;

      &rfc4191;

      &rfc4818;

      &rfc6106;

      &rfc6158;

      &rfc6614;

      <reference anchor="SECI" target="http://regul.uni-mb.si/~meolic/ptk-seminarske/radius.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>An Analysis of the RADIUS Authentication Protocol</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Hill" fullname="Joshua Hill">
            <organization>InfoGard Laboratories</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="24" month="November" year="2001" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
