<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6135" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MSRP">
    An Alternative Connection Model for the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP)
  </title>
    <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="S.B." surname="Blau" fullname="Staffan Blau">
      <organization>Ericsson AB</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <code>PO Box 407</code>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>staffan.blau@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
        <t>
      This document defines an alternative connection model for Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) User Agents (UAs);
      this model uses the connection-oriented media (COMEDIA) mechanism in order to create the MSRP transport connection. 
      The model allows MSRP UAs behind Network Address Translators (NATs) to negotiate which endpoint initiates the 
      establishment of the Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) connection, in order for MSRP messages to traverse the NAT.
        </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
        <t>
        The Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) core specification <xref target="RFC4975" /> 
        states that the MSRP User Agent (UA) that sends the Session Description Protocol (SDP) offer is "active", and it is
        responsible for creating the MSRP transport connection towards the remote UA if a new connection is required. The core 
        specification also allows, but does not define, alternate mechanisms for MSRP UAs to create MSRP transport connections.
        </t>

        <t>
        <xref target="RFC4145" /> defines a connection-oriented media (COMEDIA) mechanism, 
        which endpoints can use to negotiate the endpoint that initiates the creation of media transport connection.
        </t>

        <t>
        COMEDIA is especially useful when one of the endpoints is located behind a Network Address Translator (NAT). The endpoint 
        can use the mechanism to indicate that it will create the media
 transport connection, in order for the media to traverse 
        the NAT without the usage of relays and without being required to
 support more complex mechanisms (e.g., "TCP Candidates with 
        Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)" <xref
target="ICE-TCP" />).
    In addition, COMEDIA allows the usage of identical procedures in establishing Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) 
    <xref target="RFC0793" /> connections for different types of media.
    </t>

    <t>
     An example is the Open Mobile Alliance (OMA)-defined
    "Instant Message using SIMPLE" <xref target="OMA-SIMPLE" />,
     where one MSRP UA of every MSRP transport connection represents
     a media server, which is always located in the
     carrier network.  The media server has a globally reachable IP
         address and handles application-specific policy control as well as
         NAT traversal. The OMA IM (Instant Messenger) uses COMEDIA for
         NAT traversal, and all OMA IM MSRP clients support COMEDIA.
        </t>

        <t>
            This document defines how an MSRP UA uses COMEDIA in order to negotiate which UA will create the MSRP 
            transport TCP connection towards the other UA. The document also defines how an MSRP UA that uses 
            COMEDIA can establish an MSRP transport connection with a remote UA that does not support COMEDIA.
        </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Terminology" toc="default">
        <t>
            The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
            "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 
            <xref target="RFC2119" />.
        </t>
    </section>
        
    <section title="Applicability Statement" toc="default">
        <t>
            Support of this specification is OPTIONAL for MSRP UAs in general. UAs that are likely 
            to be deployed in networks with NATs SHOULD support this specification. It will improve the odds of being 
            able to make TCP connections successfully traverse NATs, since UAs behind NATs can be requested to initiate 
            the establishment of the TCP connections.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="COMEDIA for MSRP" toc="default">
        <section title="General" toc="default">
            <t>
                This section defines how an MSRP UA that supports this specification uses the COMEDIA SDP 
                attributes defined in <xref target="RFC4145" />.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="a=setup" toc="default">
          <section title="General" toc="default">
           <t>
                    An MSRP UA uses the SDP a=setup attribute <xref
target="RFC4145" /> in order to negotiate which endpoint will create
the MSRP transport connection towards the other UA.
           </t>

           <t>
            An MSRP UA MUST always include an explicit a=setup attribute in its
            SDP offers and answers, since it might be useful for the other
            endpoint, or for entities in the network, to know whether the UA
            supports COMEDIA or not.
            </t>

            <t>
            An MSRP UA MUST support the a=setup "active", "actpass", and "passive"
            attribute values. An MSRP UA MUST NOT send the "holdconn" attribute
value. If an
            MSRP UA receives the "holdconn" attribute value, it MUST ignore it and process
            the message as if it did not contain an a=setup attribute.
            </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Attribute Usage" toc="default">
            <t>
            When the a=setup attribute value is "actpass" or "passive", the IP address and 
            port values in the MSRP URI of the SDP a=path attribute MUST contain the actual address and 
            port values on which the UA can receive a TCP connection for the MSRP transport connection. 
            </t>

            <t>
            In accordance with <xref target="RFC4145" />, if the a=setup attribute 
            value is "active", the port number value should be 9.
            </t>

            <t>
            If an MSRP UA can provide a globally reachable IP address that the other endpoint
            can use as a destination for a TCP connection, the UA MUST use the
            a=setup "actpass" attribute value in SDP offers. This is in order to
            allow the remote UA to send an SDP answer with an a=setup "active"
            attribute value if the UA is located behind a NAT, and in order to be
            compatible with UAs that do not support COMEDIA and thus always
            will act as passive endpoints. If an MSRP UA cannot provide the
            actual transport address, the UA MUST use the a=setup "active"
            attribute value.
            </t>

            <t>
            The UA MUST NOT use the a=setup "passive" attribute value in an SDP offer.
            </t>

            <t>
            The MSRP UA can determine that it provides a globally reachable IP address in the following scenarios:                
            </t>

           <list style="symbols">
            <t>
            the UA can determine that it is not located behind a NAT;
            </t>

            <t>
            the UA relays its MSRP transport connections via a relay (e.g.,
an MSRP relay or Traversal Using Relay NAT (TURN) server); or
            </t>

            <t>
            the UA has used Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) 
            <xref target="RFC5389" /> signaling to retrieve the NAT address and port 
            through the local port to be used for the eventual transport connection, while also having 
            determined that the NAT has endpoint-independent mapping and filtering behavior
            <xref target="RFC5382" />, e.g., using the mechanism defined in 
            <xref target="RFC5780" />.
             </t>
             </list>

                <t>
                    Some UAs can determine whether the SIP <xref target="RFC3261" />
                    signaling has traversed a NAT by inspecting the SIP Via header field in the 200 (OK) response to the
                    initial SIP REGISTER request, and comparing the IP addresses in the Via sent-by and the received 
                    header field parameters. If the IP addresses are not
the same, then the UA can determine that there is 
                    a NAT in the path. Even though the media transport might not traverse the NAT, it is safe to assume 
                    that it will.  This comparing mechanism does not work in
            all scenarios, though. For example, if SIP a request crosses a SIP proxy before crossing a NAT, 
            the UA will not be able to detect the NAT by comparing the IP
addresses.
            </t>

            <t>
                    If an SDP offer includes an a=setup "actpass" attribute value, the SDP answerer MAY include an a=setup 
                    "active" attribute value in the SDP answer, but SHOULD
 include an a=setup "passive" attribute value if 
                    it knows that it is not located behind a NAT. 
                </t>
                <t>
                    Once the active UA has established the MSRP transport connection, the UA must immediately send an 
                    MSRP SEND request, as defined in <xref target="RFC4975" />.
                </t>

                <t>
                <list style="empty"><t>
                NOTE: According to <xref target="RFC4975" />, the initiating
                UA is 
                always active, but when COMEDIA is used, the a=setup attribute
                is used to negotiate which UA becomes active.</t></list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="TLS" toc="default">
            <t>
                If an MSRP UA conformant to this document uses Transport Layer
Security (TLS), it MUST use the TLS mechanisms defined in 
                <xref target="RFC4975" /> and <xref target="RFC4976" />.
            </t>
            <t>
                According to <xref target="RFC4975" />, the connection can be 
                established with or without TLS mutual authentication. In case mutual authentication is not used, 
                the listening device waits until it receives a request on the connection, at which time it infers 
                the identity of the connecting device from the associated
session description. From the TLS authentication
                point of view, it is thus irrelevant whether an endpoint takes the active or passive role.
            </t>
            <t>
                If an MSRP UA uses a self-signed TLS certificate to
authenticate itself to MSRP peers, it also includes its certificate
fingerprint in the SDP.
            </t>
            <t>
                Note that fingerprints can only be exchanged in peer-to-peer communication, as MSRP relays 
                <xref target="RFC4976" /> will not receive the SDP payloads containing 
                the fingerprint attributes.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="a=connection" toc="default">
            <t>
                MSRP UAs MUST NOT use the SDP a=connection attribute. <xref target="RFC4975" /> defines connection reuse procedures for MSRP, and this document does 
                not modify those procedures.
            </t>

            <t>
                If an MSRP UA receives an a=connection attribute, the UA MUST ignore it.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="MSRP Relay Connection" toc="default">
            <t>
                If an MSRP UA is located behind an MSRP relay <xref target="RFC4976" />, the UA MUST always initiate a transport connection towards the relay, 
                no matter what value the client has provided in the a=setup attribute.
            </t>

            <t>
            <list style="empty"><t>
            NOTE: Even if an MSRP UA initiates the TCP connection towards
            its relay, the UA will only 
            send a SEND request if the UA is active, based on the COMEDIA
            negotiation.</t></list>
            </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Interoperability with the Connection Model Defined in RFC 4975" toc="default">
        <t>
        An MSRP UA conformant to this document can interoperate with
        a UA that follows the connection model defined in 
            <xref target="RFC4975" />. However, if an MSRP UA conformant to
        this document
        is located behind a NAT, does not proxy its MSRP communication
        via an MSRP relay, and receives 
        an SDP offer from a remote UA that follows the connection model
        defined in <xref target="RFC4975" />, then NAT traversal can only be
        achieved if the MSRP UA supports ICE <xref target="ICE-TCP" />
        or if the network supports Session Border Controller (SBC)-assisted
        NAT traversal for TCP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-security" toc="default">
        <t>
        According to the connection model defined in <xref target="RFC4975" />,
        the MSRP UA 
        that sends the SDP offer becomes the active party, and it is responsible for creating the
        MSRP transport connection towards the remote UA if a new connection is required.
        </t>

        <t>
            When COMEDIA is used, either the sender or the receiver of the SDP offer can become the active party. 
            <xref target="RFC4975" /> requires that the active party
            immediately issue an MSRP SEND request once the connection has been established. This allows the
            passive party to bind the inbound TCP connection to the message session identified by the
            session id part of its MSRP URI. The use of COMEDIA does not change this requirement, but
            the sender of the SDP offer is no longer assumed to always become the active party.
        </t>

        <t>
        The active party also takes the role of the TLS client, if TLS is used to protect the MSRP
        messages. However, there are no procedures in <xref target="RFC4975" /> 
        that would break in case the receiver of the SDP offer takes the role
of the TLS client, and the level of security provided by TLS is not affected.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks" toc="default">
        <t>
        Thanks to Ben Campbell, Remi Denis-Courmont, Nancy Greene,
Hadriel Kaplan, Adam Roach, Robert Sparks, Salvatore Loreto, and Shida
Schubert for their guidance and input in producing this document.
        </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
  <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4145"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4975"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4976"?>
  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5382"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5780"?>

   <reference anchor='ICE-TCP'>
   <front>
   <title>TCP Candidates with Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)</title>
   <author initials='J' surname='Rosenberg' fullname='Jonathan Rosenberg'>
   </author>
   <author initials='A' surname='Keranen' fullname='Ari Keranen'>
   </author>
   <author initials='B' surname='Lowekamp' fullname='Bruce Lowekamp'>
   </author>

   <author initials='A' surname='Roach' fullname='Adam Roach'>
   </author>
   <date month='February' year='2011' />
   </front>

   <seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
   </reference>

 <reference anchor="OMA-SIMPLE">
       <front>
           <title>Instant Messaging using SIMPLE</title>
           <author surname="Open Mobile Alliance"></author>
           <date month="September" year="2009" />
       </front>
       <seriesInfo name="OMA-TS-SIMPLE_IM-V1_0" value="20090901-D"/>
 </reference>

  </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
