<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" number="6725" submissionType="IETF"
consensus="yes">

<front>

<title abbrev="IANA Registry Update">DNS Security (DNSSEC) DNSKEY Algorithm IANA Registry Updates</title>
        <author fullname="Scott Rose" initials="S." surname="Rose">
                        <organization> NIST </organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street>100 Bureau Dr.</street>
                                        <city>Gaithersburg</city>
                                        <code>20899</code>
                                        <region>MD</region>
                                        <country>USA</country>
                                </postal>
                                <phone>+1-301-975-8439</phone>
                                <email> scottr.nist@gmail.com </email>
                        </address>
                </author>
        
<date month="August" year="2012"/>
<area> Internet Area </area>
<workgroup> DNS Extensions Working Group </workgroup>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
<keyword>IANA</keyword>
<keyword>DNSKEY</keyword>
<keyword>registry</keyword>

<abstract>
        <t>
        The DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) require the use of
        cryptographic algorithm suites for generating digital signatures over DNS data.  The algorithms specified for
        use with DNSSEC are reflected in an IANA-maintained registry.  This document presents a set of changes for
        some entries of the registry.
        </t>
</abstract>

</front>
<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
        <t>
        The Domain Name System (DNS) Security Extensions (DNSSEC, defined by <xref target="RFC4033" />, <xref target="RFC4034" />,
        <xref target="RFC4035" />, <xref target="RFC4509" />, <xref target="RFC5155" />, and <xref target="RFC5702" />) 
        use digital signatures over DNS data
        to provide source authentication and integrity protection.  DNSSEC uses an IANA registry
        to list codes for digital signature algorithms (consisting of an asymmetric cryptographic
        algorithm and a one-way hash function).   
        </t>
        <t>
    This document updates a set of entries in the IANA registry titled "DNS
         Security (DNSSEC) Algorithm Numbers".  These updated entries are
        given in <xref target="dnssec-algo-number-reg-table"/> below. This list
        includes changes to selected entries originally set aside for future
        algorithm specification that did
    not occur. These three entries are changed to "Reserved" to avoid potential conflicts with older implementations.  This 
    document also brings the list of references for entries up to date.
        </t>
        <t>
        There are auxiliary sub-registries related to the DNS Security (DNSSEC) Algorithm Numbers registry
        that deal with various Diffie-Hellman parameters used with DNSSEC. These registry tables are not altered by
        this document. 
        </t>
</section>
<section title="The DNS Security Algorithm Numbers Sub-registry">
        <t>
        The DNS Security Algorithm Numbers sub-registry (part of the Domain Name
        System Security (DNSSEC) Algorithm Numbers registry) contains a set of entries that contain errors. 
        There are additional differences to entries that are described
        in <xref target="updates-adds"/>, and the complete list of changed
        registry entries is in <xref target="dnssec-algo-number-reg-table"/>.
        </t>
  <section title="Updates and Additions" anchor="updates-adds">
        <t>
        This document updates three entries in the Domain Name System Security (DNSSEC)
        Algorithm Numbers registry:
        </t>
        <t>
        The description for assignment number 4 is changed to "Reserved".
        </t>
        <t>
        The description for assignment number 9 is changed to "Reserved".
        </t>
        <t>
        The description for assignment number 11 is changed to "Reserved".</t> 
    <t>
        The above entries are changed to "Reserved" because they were placeholders for algorithms that
        were not fully specified for use with DNSSEC.  Older implementations may still have these algorithm 
        codes assigned, so these codes are reserved to prevent potential incompatibilities.  
        </t>
  </section>
  <section title="DNS Security Algorithm Numbers Sub-registry
Table" anchor="dnssec-algo-number-reg-table">

        <figure><preamble>
        The list of DNS Security Algorithm Numbers sub-registry entry changes is
        given below. All other existing entries in the sub-registry table are unchanged by this document 
        and are not shown.
        The other two sub-registries in the Domain Name System Security (DNSSEC) Algorithm Numbers registry (DNS KEY Record Diffie-Hellman Prime Lengths and
        DNS KEY Record Diffie-Hellman Well-Known Prime/Generator Pairs) are not changed in any way
        by this document.
        </preamble>
<artwork>  
                                       Zone     Trans.
 Number  Description       Mnemonic   Signing   Sec.      Reference
 ------  -----------       --------   -------   ---------  ---------
   0      Reserved                                         [RFC4034],
                                                           [RFC4398]

   1      RSA/MD5           RSAMD5       N         Y       [RFC3110],
          (deprecated;                                     [RFC4034]
          see 5)                                 
  
   4      Reserved                                         [RFC6725] 

   5      RSA/SHA-1         RSASHA1      Y         Y       [RFC3110],
                                                           [RFC4034]
 
   9      Reserved                                         [RFC6725]

  11      Reserved                                         [RFC6725]

15-122    Unassigned                                       

123-251   Reserved                                         [RFC4034],
                                                           [RFC6014]

  253     private           PRIVATEDNS   Y         Y       [RFC4034]
          algorithm

  254     private           PRIVATEOID   Y         Y       [RFC4034]
          algorithm OID
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>
        This document updates a set of DNS Security Algorithm Numbers sub-registry entries
        as given in <xref target="dnssec-algo-number-reg-table"/>.  The changes include moving three registry entries to "Reserved" and updating the reference list for entries.
    </t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
        This document updates the Domain Name System Security (DNSSEC) Algorithm Numbers registry.  
        
        It is not meant
        to be a discussion on algorithm superiority. No new security considerations are
        raised in this document.
        </t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
        <references title="Informative References">
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3110" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4034" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4035" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4398" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4509" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5155" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5702" ?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6014" ?>
        </references>
</back>
</rfc>
