<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc4677 SYSTEM 
	"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4677.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902"
	number="6722"
	category="info"
	obsoletes="4677"
        submissionType="IETF"
        consensus="yes"
>

<front>
<title abbrev="Tao as Web">Publishing the "Tao of the IETF" as a Web Page</title>
<author initials='P.' surname="Hoffman" fullname='Paul Hoffman' role='editor'>
<organization>VPN Consortium</organization>
<address>
<email>paul.hoffman@vpnc.org</email>
</address>
</author>
<date month="August" year="2012"/>

<abstract>

<t>This document describes how the "Tao of the IETF", which has been published
as a series of RFCs in the past, is instead being published as a web page.
It also contains the procedure for publishing and editing that web page.</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>The "Tao of the IETF" ("Tao") describes the inner workings of IETF meetings
and Working Groups, discusses organizations related to the IETF, and
introduces the standards process.  It is not a formal IETF process document
but instead an informational overview. The Tao has traditionally been
published as an RFC. It has been published as RFCs 1391, 1539, 1718, and 3160;
it is currently <xref target="RFC4677"/>.</t>

<t>At the time this document is published,
there is a strong desire in the IETF community to turn the Tao into a
web page that can be updated more easily. This document describes
that process. At the same time, this document formally obsoletes the
last version of the Tao that was published as an RFC because the last
version, RFC 4677, is no longer considered the "latest" version of the
Tao: the new web page is.</t>

<t>This document contains the procedure agreed to by the IESG. The Tao has
traditionally been an IETF consensus document, which means that the IESG has
had the final say about what the Tao contained before it was sent to the RFC
Editor. Thus, the IESG should have final say regarding what the Tao says when it is
a web page.</t>

</section>

<section title="Procedure for Publishing and Editing the Tao">

<t>The Tao is published at <eref target="http://www.ietf.org/tao.html"/>
and <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/tao.html" />. The initial content for
the Tao web page is based on a draft document that was meant to replace
RFC 4677.</t>

<t>The Tao is edited by one or more people as designated by the IESG. Suggestions
for changes to the Tao are discussed on the tao-discuss@ietf.org
mailing list.</t>

<t>The editor of the Tao decides which proposed changes should be submitted to
the IESG for approval. The editor publishes the proposed changes in a
version at <eref target="http://www.ietf.org/tao-possible-revision.html"/>.
The IESG may accept as many of the proposed changes as it wishes. The IESG
then submits the changed version to the IETF Secretariat for publication
on the IETF web page at the URLs given above.
The Tao editor and the IESG should confirm that the page appears on the web
site as intended. 
</t>

<t>Each version of the Tao has a visible timestamp near the beginning of
the document. All published versions are archived using URLs of the
form &lt;http://www.ietf.org/tao-archive/tao-YYYYMMDD.html&gt;, and a
list of the revisions is available at
<eref target="http://www.ietf.org/tao-archive/"/>.

<!-- [rfced] Should the following URL have a placeholder for the Tao Archive 
instead of returning "404: Page Not Found"? 

http://www.ietf.org/tao-archive/

-->
</t>

<t>From time to time, versions of the Tao are translated into other
languages. These translations do not represent IETF consensus and may be
provided on an "as is" basis. The issues of how translations are recorded,
made available, cross-referenced to versions of the Tao, and archived are
outside the scope of this document and are for future study.</t>

</section>

<section title="Proposals for How the Tao Web Page Should Be Developed">

<t>During the discussion that led to this document, there were many proposals
for how the Tao, as a web page, should be published and edited. Some wanted just
a web page; some wanted a web page and periodic snapshots as RFCs. Some wanted
a wiki that could be easily edited by anyone in the IETF community, with a
master editor who would revert bad edits; some wanted a wiki with a more
limited group of contributors. The procedure in Section 2 above was the
rough consensus of the discussion.</t>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>None.</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>The Tao is available over Transport Layer Security (TLS) at
<eref target="https://www.ietf.org/tao.html" />.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='RFC4677'>

<front>
<title>The Tao of IETF - A Novice's Guide to the Internet Engineering Task Force</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Hoffman' fullname='P. Hoffman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Harris' fullname='S. Harris'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='September' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes the inner workings of IETF meetings and Working Groups, discusses organizations related to the IETF, and introduces the standards process.  It is not a formal IETF process document but instead an informational overview.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='17' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4677' />
<format type='TXT' octets='127383' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4677.txt' />
</reference>

</references>

</back>

</rfc>

  

