<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="std" ipr='pre5378Trust200902' number="6784" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<front>
  <title>Kerberos Options for DHCPv6</title>
  <author initials="S.S." surname="Sakane" fullname="Shoichi Sakane">
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>9-7-1 Akasaka</street>
        <city>Minato-ku</city>
        <code>107-6227</code>
        <region>Tokyo</region>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </postal>
      <email>ssakane@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="M.I." surname="Ishiyama" fullname="Masahiro Ishiyama">
    <organization>Toshiba Corporation</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>1, Komukai-toshiba-cho, Saiwai-ku,</street>
        <city>Kawasaki</city>
        <region>Kanagawa</region>
        <code>212-8582</code>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </postal>
      <email>masahiro.ishiyama@toshiba.co.jp</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date month="November" year="2012"/>

  <area/>
  <workgroup/>

  <keyword>security</keyword>
  <keyword>dhcpv6</keyword>

  <abstract>
  <t>This document defines four new options for the Dynamic Host
   Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6).
   These options are used to carry configuration information for Kerberos.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
  <t>
   Kerberos Version 5 <xref target="RFC4120" /> is a trusted third-party
   authentication system.  Each organization wishing to use Kerberos
   establishes its own "realm", and each client is registered as part of
   that realm.  At least one Key Distribution Center (KDC) is required
   for the operation of a Kerberos realm.
  </t>
  <t>
   When a client wishes to communicate with, and be authenticated to, a
   Kerberos application server (also a client of the KDC), the client
   identifies itself, and its realm, to the KDC and acquires a
   credential from the KDC.  The client then presents the credential to
   the Kerberos application server, which can use the credential to
   authenticate the client.  The client needs to know at least one IP
   address for a KDC in order to initiate this process.
  </t>
  <t>
   One example of the application of this protocol is as follows.  A
   student might want to use a shared, public workstation, one that is
   not configured for Kerberos.  If there is a mechanism for the
   workstation to obtain a realm name and IP address for a KDC, then a
   student need only input a user-id and pass phrase to be able to use
   Kerberos.
  </t>
  <t>
   The Kerberos V5 specification <xref target="RFC4120"/>
   defines the use of DNS SRV
   records <xref target="RFC2782"/> for KDC discovery.  Some systems,
   such as industrial
   systems, do not use DNS.  Such systems already have their own name
   spaces and their own name resolution systems, including preconfigured
   mapping tables for devices, and do not use Fully Qualified Domain Names.
   However, many of these systems do use DHCP.
  </t>
  <t>
   Adding a DNS server to such systems may decrease the reliability of
   the system and increase the management cost.  In
   such an environment, another mechanism is needed to provide an IP
   address for the KDC.  For the PacketCable Architecture <xref target="PCARCH" />,
   <xref target="RFC3634">RFC&nbsp;3634</xref> defines the KDC Server Address sub-option for the
   DHCPv4 CableLabs Client Configuration option.  However, a mechanism
   is still needed to provide a realm name and an IPv6 address -- one
   that does not depend on any external architecture.
  </t>
  <t>
   This document defines a Kerberos option for DHCPv6 that provides a
   realm name and/or a list of KDC IP addresses.  This option does not
   replace or modify any of the existing methods for obtaining this
   information.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
  <t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC&nbsp;2119</xref>.
  </t>
  <t>
   It is assumed that the readers are familiar with the terms and
   concepts described in
   DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315" />,
   Kerberos V5 <xref target="RFC4120" />,
   and DNS SRV <xref target="RFC2782" />.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Kerberos Options">
  <t>
   This document defines four DHCPv6 configuration parameters for
   Kerberos.
  </t>
  <t>
    <list style="empty">
    <t>Kerberos Principal Name Option</t>
    <t>Kerberos Realm Name Option</t>
    <t>Kerberos Default Realm Name Option</t>
    <t>Kerberos KDC Option</t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>
   This section describes the format of each option and the usage of
   each field in that option.
  </t>
  <t>
   These options, except for the Kerberos KDC Option, MUST NOT appear more
   than once in a DHCPv6 message.
  </t>

  <section title="Kerberos Principal Name Option">
    <t>
   The Kerberos Principal Name Option carries the name of a Kerberos
   principal.  This is sent by the client to the DHCPv6 server, which
   MAY use it to select a specific set of configuration parameters, either
   for a client or for a Kerberos application server.
    </t>
    <t>
   The format of the Kerberos Principal Name Option is:
    </t>
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   OPTION_KRB_PRINCIPAL_NAME   |          option-len           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                                                               :
   :                        principal-name                         :
   :                       (variable length)                       :
   :                                                               :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>   </artwork>   </figure>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>option-code (16 bits): OPTION_KRB_PRINCIPAL_NAME (75)</t>
      <t>option-len (16 bits): length of the principal-name field.</t>
      <t>principal-name (variable): a client principal name.  The encoding
      of the principal-name field MUST conform to the definition of
      "PrincipalName" in Section 5.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4120">RFC&nbsp;4120</xref>.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Kerberos Realm Name Option">
    <t>
   The Kerberos Realm Name Option carries a Kerberos realm name.  A
   DHCPv6 client uses this option to specify to a DHCPv6 server which
   realm the client wants to access.
    </t>
    <t>
   The format of the Kerberos Realm Name Option is:
    </t>
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     OPTION_KRB_REALM_NAME     |          option-len           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                                                               :
   :                          realm-name                           :
   :                       (variable length)                       :
   :                                                               :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>   </artwork>   </figure>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>option-code (16 bits): OPTION_KRB_REALM_NAME (76)</t>
      <t>option-len (16 bits): the length of the realm-name field in octets.</t>
      <t>realm-name (variable): a realm-name.  The encoding of the
      realm&nbhy;name field MUST conform to the definition of "Realm" in
      Section&nbsp;5.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4120">RFC&nbsp;4120</xref>.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Kerberos Default Realm Name Option">
    <t>
   The Kerberos Default Realm Name Option is used to specify a default
   realm name for the Kerberos system.
   A DHCPv6 server uses this option to specify the default realm name
   to both clients and Kerberos application servers.
    </t>
    <t>
   The option-code of this option is OPTION_KRB_DEFAULT_REALM_NAME
   (77).
   The format and usage of the option-len and realm-name fields are
   identical to those for the Kerberos Realm Name Option.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Kerberos KDC Option" anchor="kdc-option">
    <t>
   The Kerberos KDC Option is used to provide configuration information
   about a KDC.
    </t>
    <t>
   The format of the Kerberos KDC Option is:
    </t>
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         OPTION_KRB_KDC        |          option-len           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |           Priority            |            Weight             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Transport Type|          Port Number          |               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+               |
   |                                                               |
   |                                                               |
   |                       KDC IPv6 address        +---------------+
   |                                               |               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+               :
   :                                                               :
   :                          realm-name                           :
   :                       (variable length)                       :
   :                                                               :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>  </artwork>   </figure>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>option-code (16 bits): OPTION_KRB_KDC (78)</t>
      <t>option-len (16 bits): 23 + the length of the realm-name field in
      octets.</t>
      <t>Priority (16 bits): see the description of the Weight field.</t>
      <t>Weight (16 bits): the Priority and Weight fields provide a hint to
      the client as to which KDC to select.  The usage of the Priority
      and Weight values MUST follow the specification for DNS SRV
      <xref target="RFC2782" />.</t>
      <t>Transport Type (8 bits): The Transport Type specifies the transport
      protocol used for Kerberos.  Kerberos <xref target="RFC4120" /> defines UDP and
      TCP transports.  Exchanges over TCP are further described in
      <xref target="RFC5021" />, while the transport of Kerberos over
      Transport Layer Security (TLS) is described in
      <xref target="RFC6251" />.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>
      The transport type is defined below.
    </t>
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
     Value    Transport Type
     ----     --------------
     0        Reserved
     1        UDP
     2        TCP
     3        TLS
     4-254    Unassigned
     255      Reserved
]]>  </artwork>  </figure>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>Port Number (16 bits): the port number on which the KDC listens.</t>
      <t>KDC IPv6 address (128 bits): the IPv6 address of the KDC.</t>
      <t>realm-name (variable): the name of the realm for which the
      specified KDC provides service.  The encoding of the
      realm-name field MUST conform to the definition of  "Realm" in
      Section 5.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4120">RFC&nbsp;4120</xref>.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

</section>

<section title="Client and Server Operation">
  <t>
   This section describes the operations of the client and server.  It
   assumes that the client has been configured with a principal name.
  </t>
  <t>
   If a client requires a realm name, the client sends a DHCPv6
   Option Request Option (ORO) specifying the Kerberos Default Realm
   Name Option.  The DHCPv6 server responds with a Reply message
   containing a Kerberos Default Realm Name Option.
  </t>
  <t>
   If a client requires configuration parameters for a KDC, the client
   sends a DHCPv6 ORO specifying the Kerberos KDC Option.  The
   client MAY include a Kerberos Principal Name Option.  The client MAY
   include a Kerberos Realm Name Option.
  </t>
  <t>
   The DHCPv6 server replies with one or more sets of configuration
   parameters for a Kerberos KDC.  If the client has specified either a
   Kerberos Principal Name Option or a Kerberos Realm Name Option, then
   the DHCPv6 server MAY use those parameters to select specific sets
   of configuration parameters.
  </t>
  <t>
   Where the server replies with more than one set of configuration
   parameters, the usage of the Priority and Weight fields by the client MUST
   follow the specification for DNS SRV <xref target="RFC2782" />.
  </t>
  <t>
   The client MAY include other options with data values as hints to the
   DHCPv6 server about parameter values the client would like to have
   returned; this is specified in Section 18.1.5 of <xref target="RFC3315">RFC&nbsp;3315</xref>.
  </t>

  <section title="KDC Discovery for a Client">
    <t>
   When a client implements both the DNS method defined by
   Section&nbsp;7.2.3.2 of <xref target="RFC4120" /> and the DHCP method
   defined by this document,
   the choice of method is determined by local policy.
   The administrator of the realm usually defines the method as part of the
   configuration of the client before the client is installed.
    </t>
    <t>
   When no criteria have been specified and the client could get the
   Kerberos information from either the DNS server or the DHCPv6 server,
   then the information from DNS SHOULD be preferred.
    </t>
  </section>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>
   IANA has assigned four option codes from the DHCPv6
   Option Codes registry for the following:
  </t>
  <t>
    <list style="empty">
    <t>75 OPTION_KRB_PRINCIPAL_NAME</t>
    <t>76 OPTION_KRB_REALM_NAME</t>
    <t>77 OPTION_KRB_DEFAULT_REALM_NAME</t>
    <t>78 OPTION_KRB_KDC</t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>
   IANA has created the Kerberos Message
   Transport Types sub-registry, under the Kerberos Parameters registry.  The initial
   entries are described in <xref target="kdc-option"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
   The assignment of future entries is by "IETF Review" policy as
   described in BCP 26 <xref target="RFC5226" />.  Per that policy, a document
   specifies the symbolic name of such entries, which are assigned
   numeric codes by IANA once publication is approved.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
   The security considerations in <xref target="RFC3315">RFC&nbsp;3315</xref> apply.
  </t>
  <t>
   DHCPv6 messages can be modified in transit.  If an adversary modifies
   the response from a DHCPv6 server or injects its own response, a
   client may be led into contacting a malicious KDC.  Both cases are
   categorized as a Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack.  However, a
   malicious KDC does not know the shared key and so is unable to
   proceed any further with the exchange.  If a client receives a
   response from such a KDC, the client can use the shared key to detect
   that the message originates from a malicious KDC.
  </t>
  <t>
   A shared, unconfigured workstation may obtain its KDC information,
   and default realm, via DHCPv6.  Such a workstation may not have a
   host or other service key, and thus it may be unable to validate the
   Ticket-Granting Ticket issued by the KDC.  A modified DHCPv6 response would
   then result in the workstation talking to a malicious KDC, and the
   workstation would not be able to detect that this has happened.
   This in turn could allow access by unauthorized users.
  </t>
  <t>
   To minimize potential vulnerabilities, a client SHOULD use DHCPv6
   authentication as defined in Section 21 of <xref target="RFC3315">RFC&nbsp;3315</xref>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Kerberos information may be manually configured on the client
   before requesting information from DHCPv6.  Manual configuration of
   the device SHOULD be preferred to configuration via the DHCPv6
   server.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>
   The authors are very grateful to Nobuo Okabe and Shigeya Suzuki.
   They contributed the explanation as to why DNS is inappropriate for
   some industry networks.
   Ted Lemon made many suggestions to improve DHCP aspects of
   this specification.  Ken'ichi Kamada and Yukiyo Akisada contributed
   to the initial work on this document.  Tom Petch helped to improve
   the readability of this document.  The authors also thank Jeffrey
   Hutzelman, Kazunori Miyazawa, Kensuke Hosoya, Nicolas Williams,
   Nobumichi Ozoe, Sam Hartman, and Stephen Farrell.  They made valuable
   comments and suggestions.
  </t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2782" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4120" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5021" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3634" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6251" ?>
  <reference
    anchor="PCARCH"
    target="http://www.packetcable.com/downloads/specs/pkt-tr-arch-v01-991201.pdf">
    <front>
      <title>PacketCable 1.0(TM) Architecture Framework Technical Report</title>
      <author>
        <organization>CableLabs</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="1999" month="December" day="1" />
    </front>
  </reference>
</references>

<section anchor="app-a" title="An Example of the Operation of the Client">
  <t>
   When no criteria have been specified and the client could get the
   Kerberos information from either the DNS server or the DHCPv6 server,
   then the information from DNS SHOULD be preferred.  The following
   is an informational guide for the client in such an environment.
  </t>

  <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
                            No Resp. or
            +------------+  DNS Info. +-----------+ No Resp.
  Start --> | Ask DHCP(1)| ---------> | Ask DNS(3)| ------>
            +------------+            +-----------+     Terminate(4)
             /          \                      \
   Only KRB /            \ DNS and              \ KRB Info.
     Info. /              \ KRB Info.            \
          /                \                      \
         |                  |                       |
         |                  V                       |
         V     No Ans.  +-----------+  KRB Info.    V
    Use Info. <-------- | Ask DNS(6)| ---------> Use Info.
    from DHCP           +-----------+            from DNS
    (2), (7)                                     (5), (8)

     Abbreviations:
       Resp.: Response
       Info.: Information
       KRB  : Kerberos

1) Initially, the client requests both DNS and Kerberos information
   from the DHCPv6 server.

2) If the DHCPv6 server replies with Kerberos information and not
   with DNS information, then the client uses that information.

3) If the DHCPv6 server does not reply or replies with only DNS
   information, then the client requests Kerberos information from
   the DNS server.

4) If the client gets no response or no Kerberos information from
   the DNS server, then the client terminates the process.

5) If the client gets Kerberos information from the DNS server, then
   the client uses that information.

6) If, as the result of (1), the DHCPv6 server replies with both DNS
   and Kerberos information, then the client requests Kerberos
   information from the DNS server.

7) If the client gets no response from the DNS server, then the
   client uses the Kerberos information from the DHCPv6 server.

8) If, as the result of (6), the DNS server replies with Kerberos
   information, then the client uses the information from the DNS
   server and not that from the DHCPv6 server.
]]> </artwork> </figure>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
