<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc submissionType="IRTF" category="exp" consensus="yes" number="6260" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CBHE">Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE)</title>

    <author fullname="Scott Burleigh" initials="S" surname="Burleigh">
      <organization>Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of
      Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4800 Oak Grove Drive, m/s 301-490</street>

          <city>Pasadena</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>91109</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

		<phone>+1 818 393 3353</phone>
        <email>Scott.C.Burleigh@jpl.nasa.gov</email>

      </address>
    </author>

<workgroup>Delay-Tolerant Networking</workgroup>

    <date month="May" year="2011" />


    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a convention by which Delay-Tolerant
      Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP) "convergence-layer" adapters may
      represent endpoint identifiers in a compressed form within the primary
      blocks of bundles, provided those endpoint identifiers conform to the
      structure prescribed by this convention.</t>

      <t>Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE) compression is a convergence-layer adaptation. It is opaque to
      bundle processing. Therefore, it has no impact on the interoperability of
      different Bundle Protocol implementations, but instead affects only the
      interoperability of different convergence-layer adaptation
      implementations.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of the Delay-Tolerant Networking Research
      Group and has been reviewed by that group. No objections to its
      publication as an RFC were raised.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes a convention by which Delay-Tolerant
      Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP) <xref target="RFC5050"></xref>
      "convergence-layer" adapters may represent endpoint identifiers (EIDs) in a
      compressed form within the primary blocks of bundles, provided those
      endpoint identifiers conform to the structure prescribed by this
      convention.</t>

      <t>Each DTN bundle's primary block contains the following four BP
      endpoint identifiers, of which any two, any three, or even all
      four may be lexically identical: the endpoint identifiers of the
      bundle's source, destination, report-to endpoint, and current custodian.
      Each EID is a Uniform Record Identifier (URI) as defined by <xref
      target="RFC3986"></xref>. More specifically, each BP EID is a URI
      consisting of a "scheme name" followed by ":", followed by a sequence of
      characters -- historically, termed the "scheme-specific part" (SSP) in DTN
      specifications -- conforming to URI syntax as defined by RFC 3986.</t>

      <t>A degree of block compression is provided by the design of the
      primary block: the scheme names and scheme-specific parts of the four
      endpoints' IDs &mdash; up to eight NULL-terminated strings &mdash; are
      concatenated at the end of the block in a variable-length character
      array called a "dictionary", enabling each EID to be represented by a
      pair of integers indicating the offsets (within the dictionary) of the
      EID's scheme name and scheme-specific part. Duplicate strings may be
      omitted from the dictionary, so the actual number of concatenated
      NULL-terminated strings in the dictionary may be less than eight, and
      two or more of the scheme name or scheme-specific part offsets in the
      block may have the same value. Moreover, the eight offsets in the
      primary block are encoded as Self-Delimiting Numeric Values (SDNVs),
      which shrink to fit the encoded values; when the total length of the
      dictionary is less than 127 bytes, all eight offsets can be encoded into
      just eight bytes.</t>

      <t>However, these strategems do not prevent the scheme names and
      especially the scheme-specific parts themselves from being lengthy
      strings of ASCII text. It is therefore still possible for the length of
      a bundle's primary header to be a very large fraction of the total
      length of the bundle when the bundle's payload is relatively small, as
      is anticipated for a number of DTN applications such as space flight
      operations (and as is in any case true of bundles carrying BP
      administrative records).</t>

      <t>The Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE) convention was developed
      to improve DTN transmission efficiency for such applications by further
      reducing the number of bytes used by convergence-layer adapters to
      represent EIDs in the primary blocks of bundles.</t>
<section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Compression Convention">
      <section title="Constraints" anchor="constraints">
        <t>The only valid scheme name for BP EIDs identified to date is "dtn".
        Although no specification of valid SSP syntax for URIs composed within
        the "dtn" scheme has yet been formally defined, the syntax on which
        rough agreement has been reached in practice is unsuitable for CBHE's
        compression procedures. For the purposes of CBHE, then, this document
        defines an additional URI scheme named "ipn". As noted in <xref
target="IANA" />, IANA has registered this new URI scheme.</t>

        <t>Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE) is possible only when all
        endpoint IDs in the primary block of a given bundle are
        "CBHE conformant". The following two forms of endpoint ID are
        CBHE conformant: (a) the null endpoint ID "dtn:none" and (b) any
        endpoint ID formed within the "ipn" scheme.</t>

        <t>The SSP of every URI formed within the "ipn" scheme must
        comprise:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>A sequence of ASCII numeric digits representing an integer in
            the range 1 to (2^64 - 1), termed the "node number" of the
            URI.</t>

            <t>An ASCII period ('.') character.</t>

            <t>A sequence of ASCII numeric digits representing an integer in
            the range 0 to (2^64 - 1), termed the "service number" of the
            URI.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The node number notionally identifies a BP node. However, since
        CBHE is not used universally in Delay-Tolerant Networking, it must not
        be assumed that all BP nodes are identified by node numbers.</t>

        <t>Negative integers and integers larger than (2^64 - 1) cannot be
        used as node numbers because they cannot be encoded into the SDNVs
        that are used for representation of scheme name and SSP offsets in the
        primary blocks of bundles and therefore could not be compressed as
        described later in this specification. Node number zero is reserved
        for representation of the null endpoint ID in the compressed form
        described later; decompressing a compressed null EID must always yield
        the standard null endpoint ID URI "dtn:none".</t>

        <t>The service number notionally functions as a de-multiplexing token.
        When the bundle payload is a protocol data unit of some protocol that
        has its own de-multiplexing identifiers, the service number may
        function in a manner similar to that of the protocol number in an IP
        packet, characterizing the encapsulated protocol; alternatively, the
        service number may function in a manner similar to that of the port
        number in a UDP datagram. Service numbers enable inbound bundles'
        application data units to be de-multiplexed to instances of
        application functionality that are designed to process them, so that
        effective communication relationships can be developed between bundle
        producers and consumers.</t>

        <t>A service number must not be negative or exceed (2^64 - 1) for the
        same reason that a node number must not do so.</t>

        <t>For example, "ipn:9.37" would be a CBHE-conformant endpoint ID.</t>

        <t>Conversion of a CBHE-conformant EID to and from a tuple of two
        integers is therefore straightforward: all characters in the EID other
        than the node number and service number are constant (as defined by
        the "ipn" scheme definition), and the node number and service number
        are taken as the two integers of the tuple. This ease of conversion
        enables an array of pairs of integers to serve the same function as a
        dictionary of ASCII string EIDs.</t>

        <t>Note, however, that CBHE decompression cannot faithfully recreate
        the dictionary of a compressed primary block from an array of integer
        pairs unless the order of the scheme names and scheme-specific part
        strings in the dictionary of the original, uncompressed block is
        known. (The Bundle Protocol Specification does not require that the
        strings in the dictionary appear in any particular order and does not
        require that redundant strings be omitted from the dictionary.)
        Therefore, a further precondition to CBHE compression is that the
        strings in the dictionary of the bundle to be compressed must be
        exactly as follows, in this order and without addition:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The scheme name of the destination endpoint ID.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the destination endpoint ID.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the source endpoint ID, if and only if
            different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the source endpoint ID, if and only
            if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the report-to endpoint ID, if and only if
            different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the report-to endpoint ID, if and
            only if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme name of the current custodian endpoint ID, if and
            only if different from any prior string in the dictionary.</t>

            <t>The scheme-specific part of the current custodian endpoint ID,
            if and only if different from any prior string in the
            dictionary.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Note: this constraint implies that a bundle that includes any
        extension blocks containing EID-references to endpoint IDs other than
        the block's destination, source, report-to, and current custodian
        cannot be CBHE compressed since such compression would result in a
        dictionary that would deviate from this structure.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Method" anchor="method">
        <t>When the constraints enumerated above are met, the CBHE block
        compression method can be applied by the convergence-layer adapter
        (CLA) at the time the bundle is transmitted via a convergence-layer
        protocol. In a CBHE-compressed primary block, the eight SDNVs that
        normally contain EIDs' scheme name and SSP offsets within the
        dictionary are instead used to contain the eight integer values listed
        below, in the order shown:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The node number of the destination endpoint ID, or zero if the
            destination endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the destination endpoint ID, or zero if
            the destination endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the source endpoint ID, or zero if the
            source endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the source endpoint ID, or zero if the
            source endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the report-to endpoint ID, or zero if the
            report-to endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the report-to endpoint ID, or zero if the
            report-to endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The node number of the current custodian endpoint ID, or zero
            if the current custodian endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>

            <t>The service number of the current custodian endpoint ID, or
            zero if the current custodian endpoint is the null endpoint.</t>
          </list>Further, the dictionary is omitted from the primary block and
        the primary block's dictionary length is set to zero.</t>

        <t>Upon reception, the receiving convergence-layer adaptation
        de-compresses the block by simply reversing the process so that the
        bundle presented to the bundle protocol agent has the standard form
        (i.e., the dictionary is reconstituted).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Specification">
      <t>CBHE compression is a convergence-layer adaptation. It is opaque to
      bundle processing. Therefore, it has no impact on the interoperability of
      different Bundle Protocol implementations, but instead affects only the
      interoperability of different convergence-layer adaptation
      implementations.</t>

      <t>Bundle Protocol convergence-layer adapters that conform to the CBHE
      specification must implement the following procedures.</t>

      <section title="Transmission">
        <t>When and only when required by the bundle protocol agent to
        transmit a bundle whose primary block's endpoint IDs satisfy the
        constraints identified in <xref target="constraints" />, the CLA MAY encode the
        primary block of the bundle in accordance with the CBHE compression
        convention described in <xref target="method" /> UNLESS the CLA to which the
        bundle is to be transmitted is known not to be CBHE conformant. Note
        that CBHE compression may be applied only if the receiving CLA is
        known or presumed to be CBHE conformant, i.e., able to decode the
        encoded primary block. Knowledge as to whether or not a receiving CLA
        is (or might be) CBHE conformant may be asserted by node
        administration and/or may be inferred from reception of a
        CBHE-compressed bundle as noted in <xref target="reception" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reception" anchor="reception">
        <t>Upon receiving a bundle whose dictionary length is zero (and only
        in this circumstance), a CBHE-conformant convergence-layer
        adapter:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>MAY infer that the CLA from which the bundle was received is
            CBHE conformant.</t>

            <t>MUST decode the primary block of the bundle in accordance with
            the CBHE compression convention described in <xref target="method" />            before delivering it to the bundle protocol agent.</t>
          </list>Note that when a CLA that is not CBHE conformant receives a bundle
        whose dictionary length is zero, it has no choice but to pass it to
        the bundle agent without modification. In this case, the bundle
        protocol agent will be unable to dispatch the received bundle, because
        it will be unable to determine the destination endpoint; the bundle
        will be judged to be malformed. The behavior of the bundle protocol
        agent in this circumstance is an implementation matter.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has registered a provisional registration (per <xref
target="RFC4395"/>) for a URI scheme for CBHE, with the string "ipn" as the
scheme name, as follows:</t>

      <t>URI scheme name: "ipn"</t>

      <t>Status: provisional</t>

      <t>URI scheme syntax:</t>

      <t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
      notation of <xref target="RFC5234"/>, including the core ABNF syntax rule for DIGIT
      defined by that specification.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
ipn-uri = "ipn:" ipn-hier-part
ipn-hier-part = node-nbr nbr-delim service-nbr ; a path-rootless
node-nbr = 1*DIGIT
nbr-delim = "."
service-nbr = 1*DIGIT
          ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>None of the reserved characters defined in the generic URI syntax are
      used as delimiters within URIs of the IPN scheme.</t>

      <t>URI scheme semantics: URIs of the IPN scheme are used as endpoint
      identifiers in the Delay-Tolerant Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP)
      <xref target="RFC5050"></xref> as described in <xref target="constraints" />.</t>

      <t>Encoding considerations: URIs of the IPN scheme are encoded
      exclusively in US-ASCII characters.</t>

      <t>Applications and/or protocols that use this URI scheme name: the
      Delay-Tolerant Networking (DTN) Bundle Protocol (BP) <xref
      target="RFC5050"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Interoperability considerations: as noted above, URIs of the IPN
      scheme are encoded exclusively in US-ASCII characters.</t>

      <t>Security considerations:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Reliability and consistency: none of the BP endpoints identified
          by the URIs of the IPN scheme are guaranteed to be reachable at any
          time, and the identity of the processing entities operating on those
          endpoints is never guaranteed by the Bundle Protocol itself. Bundle
          authentication as defined by the Bundle Security Protocol is
          required for this purpose.</t>

          <t>Malicious construction: malicious construction of a conformant
          IPN-scheme URI is limited to the malicious selection of node numbers and
          the malicious selection of service numbers. That is, a maliciously
          constructed IPN-scheme URI could be used to direct a bundle to an
          endpoint that might be damaged by the arrival of that bundle or,
          alternatively, to declare a false source for a bundle and thereby
          cause incorrect processing at a node that receives the bundle. In
          both cases (and indeed in all bundle processing), the node that
          receives a bundle should verify its authenticity and validity before
          operating on it in any way.</t>

          <t>Back-end transcoding: the limited expressiveness of URIs of the
          IPN scheme effectively eliminates the possibility of threat due to
          errors in back-end transcoding.</t>

          <t>Rare IP address formats: not relevant, as IP addresses do not
          appear anywhere in conformant IPN-scheme URIs.</t>

          <t>Sensitive information: because IPN-scheme URIs are used only to
          represent the identities of Bundle Protocol endpoints, the risk of
          disclosure of sensitive information due to interception of these
          URIs is minimal. Examination of IPN-scheme URIs could be used to
          support traffic analysis; where traffic analysis is a plausible
          danger, bundles should be conveyed by secure convergence-layer
          protocols that do not expose endpoint IDs.</t>

          <t>Semantic attacks: the simplicity of IPN-scheme URI syntax
          minimizes the possibility of misinterpretation of a URI by a human
          user.</t>
        </list></t>
<t>	
<artwork>
Contact: 
   Scott Burleigh
   Jet Propulsion Laboratory, 
   California Institute of Technology
   scott.c.burleigh@jpl.nasa.gov
   +1 (800) 393-3353

Author/Change controller: 
   Scott Burleigh
   Jet Propulsion Laboratory, 
   California Institute of Technology
   scott.c.burleigh@jpl.nasa.gov
   +1 (800) 393-3353
</artwork>
</t>
	<t>References: S. Burleigh, "Compressed Bundle Header Encoding (CBHE)",
		RFC 6260, May 2011. </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The Bundle Security Protocol (BSP) may, under some conditions, insert
      additional endpoint ID strings into the dictionary of a bundle and
      reference those strings in BSP extension blocks. Because a bundle that
      includes any extension blocks containing EID-references to endpoint IDs
      other than the block's destination, source, report-to, and current
      custodian cannot be CBHE compressed, bundles cannot be compressed under
      those conditions.</t>

      <t>Specifically, the specification detailed above implies that a bundle
      cannot be CBHE compressed when the security-source endpoint for the
      Bundle Authentication Block (BAB) is noted in the dictionary (typically,
      because there is no other way for the receiving bundle protocol agent to
      determine the security-source endpoint); when the security-destination
      endpoint for the BAB is noted in the dictionary (in the rare case that
      the receiving endpoint is not the security-destination endpoint); when
      the security-source endpoint for the Payload Integrity Block (PIB),
      Payload Confidentiality Block (PCB), or Extension Security Block (ESB)
      is not the source endpoint; or when the security-destination endpoint
      for the PIB, PCB, or ESB is not the destination endpoint.</t>

      <t>Also, the CBHE-conformance inference mechanism identified in <xref target="reception" /> introduces a possible denial-of-service attack. Malicious code
      could issue a CHBE-compressed bundle whose source EID falsely identifies
      the bundle origin as some node whose CLA is not CBHE conformant; a
      CBHE-conformant CLA receiving this bundle might incorrectly infer that
      the CLA at the purported source node was CBHE conformant and might then
      begin CBHE compressing all bundles that it sends to that node, thus
      preventing those bundles from being dispatched by the node's bundle
      protocol agent. Nodes can defend against such an attack by requiring
      Bundle Authentication Blocks and discarding any inference of CBHE
      conformance for the CLAs at nodes from which inauthentic bundles are
      received.</t>

      <t>These caveats aside, CBHE introduces no new security considerations
      beyond those discussed in the DTN Bundle Protocol <xref target="RFC5050">RFC 5050</xref> and Bundle Security
      Protocol <xref target="RFC6257">RFC 6257</xref> Specifications.

</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5050"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>



<reference anchor='RFC6257'>
<front>
<title>Bundle Security Protocol Specification</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Symington' fullname='Susan Symington'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Farrell' fullname='Stephen Farrell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Weiss' fullname='Howard Weiss'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Lovell' fullname='Peter Lovell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>This document defines the bundle security protocol, which provides data integrity and confidentiality services for the bundle protocol. Separate capabilities are provided to protect the bundle payload and additional data that may be included within the bundle.  We also describe various security considerations including some policy options.  This document is a product of the Delay Tolerant Networking Research Group and has been reviewed by that group.  No objections to its publication as an RFC were raised.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6257' />

</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4395"?>
    </references>
<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>This research was carried out at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, under a contract with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.  Government sponsorship acknowledged.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
