<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc number="6487" category="std" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Resource Certificate Profile">A Profile for X.509 PKIX
    Resource Certificates</title>

    <author fullname="Geoff Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">APNIC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>gih@apnic.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Michaelson" initials="G." surname="Michaelson">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">APNIC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Robert Loomans" initials="R." surname="Loomans">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">APNIC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>robertl@apnic.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2012" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>SIDR</workgroup>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcsearch.html. -->

<keyword>example</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a standard profile for X.509 certificates for
      the purpose of supporting validation of assertions of "right-of-use" of
      Internet Number Resources (INRs). The certificates issued under this
      profile are used to convey the issuer's authorization of the subject to
      be regarded as the current holder of a "right-of-use" of the INRs that
      are described in the certificate. This document contains the normative
      specification of Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL)
      syntax in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI). This document
      also specifies profiles for the format of certificate requests and 
      specifies the Relying Party RPKI certificate path
      validation procedure.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines a standard profile for X.509 certificates <xref
      target="X.509"></xref> for use in the context of certification of
      Internet Number Resources (INRs), i.e., IP Addresses and Autonomous
      System (AS) numbers. Such certificates are termed "resource
      certificates". A resource certificate is a certificate that conforms to
      the PKIX profile <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>, and that conforms to
      the constraints specified in this profile. A resource certificate
      attests that the issuer has granted the subject a "right-of-use" for a
      listed set of IP addresses and/or Autonomous System numbers.</t>

      <t>This document is referenced by Section 7 of the "Certificate Policy
      (CP) for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)" <xref
      target="RFC6484"></xref>. It is an integral part of that policy and
      the normative specification for certificate and Certificate Revocation
      List (CRL) syntax used in the RPKI. The document also specifies profiles
      for the format of certificate requests, and the relying party (RP) RPKI
      certificate path validation procedure.</t>

      <t>Resource certificates are to be used in a manner that is consistent
      with the RPKI Certificate Policy (CP) <xref target="RFC6484"></xref>. They
      are issued by entities that assign and/or allocate public INRs, and thus
      the RPKI is aligned with the public INR distribution function. When an
      INR is allocated or assigned by a number registry to an entity, this
      allocation can be described by an associated resource certificate. This
      certificate is issued by the number registry, and it binds the
      certificate subject's key to the INRs enumerated in the certificate. One
      or two critical extensions, the IP Address Delegation or AS Identifier
      Delegation Extensions <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>, enumerate the INRs
      that were allocated or assigned by the issuer to the subject.</t>

      <t>Relying party (RP) validation of a resource certificate is performed in the manner
      specified in <xref target="resvalid"></xref>. This validation procedure
      differs from that described in Section 6 of <xref
      target="RFC5280"></xref>, such that: <list style="symbols">
          <t>additional validation processing imposed by the INR extensions is
          required,</t>

          <t>a confirmation of a public key match between the CRL issuer and
          the resource certificate issuer is required, and</t>

          <t>the resource certificate is required to conform to this
          profile.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This profile defines those fields that are used in a resource
      certificate that MUST be present for the certificate to be valid. Any
      extensions not explicitly mentioned MUST be absent. The same applies to
      the CRLs used in the RPKI, that are also profiled in this document. A
Certification Authority (CA)
      conforming to the RPKI CP MUST issue certificates and CRLs consistent
      with this profile.</t>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>It is assumed that the reader is familiar with the terms and
        concepts described in "Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure
        Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile" <xref
        target="RFC5280"></xref>, and "X.509 Extensions for IP Addresses and
        AS Identifiers" <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Describing Resources in Certificates">
      <t>The framework for describing an association between the subject of a
      certificate and the INRs currently under the subject's control is
      described in <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>. This profile further
      requires that: 

<list style="symbols">
          <t>Every resource certificate MUST contain either the IP Address
          Delegation or the Autonomous System Identifier Delegation extension,
          or both.</t>

          <t>These extensions MUST be marked as critical.</t>

          <t>The sorted canonical format describing INRs, with maximal
          spanning ranges and maximal spanning prefix masks, as defined in
          <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>, MUST be used for the resource
          extension field, except where the "inherit" construct is used
          instead.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>When validating a resource certificate, an RP MUST verify that the
      INRs described in the issuer's resource certificate encompass the INRs
      of the resource certificate being validated. In this context, "encompass"
      allows for the issuer's INRs to be the same as, or a strict superset of,
      the subject's INRs.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="End-Entity (EE) Certificates and Signing Functions in the RPKI">
      <t>As noted in <xref target="RFC6480"></xref>, the primary function
      of end-entity (EE) certificates in the RPKI is the verification of
      signed objects that relate to the usage of the INRs described in the
      certificate, e.g., Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs) and manifests.</t>

      <t>The private key associated with an EE certificate is used to sign a
      single RPKI signed object, i.e., the EE certificate is used to validate
      only one object. The EE certificate is embedded in the object as part of
      a Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) signed-data structure <xref
      target="RFC6488"></xref>. Because of the one-to-one
      relationship between the EE certificate and the signed object,
      revocation of the certificate effectively revokes the corresponding
      signed object.</t>

      <t>An EE certificate may be used to validate a sequence of signed
      objects, where each signed object in the sequence overwrites the previous
      instance of the signed object in the repository publication point, such
      that only one instance of the signed object is published at any point in
      time (e.g., an EE certificate MAY be used to sign a sequence of
      manifests <xref target="RFC6486"></xref>). Such EE
      certificates are termed "sequential use" EE certificates.</t>

      <t>EE certificates used to validate only one instance of a signed
      object, and are not used thereafter or in any other validation context,
      are termed "one-time-use" EE certificates.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Resource Certificates">
      <t>A resource certificate is a valid X.509 public key certificate,
      consistent with the PKIX profile <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>,
      containing the fields listed in this section. Only the differences from
      <xref target="RFC5280"></xref> are noted below.</t>

      <t>Unless specifically noted as being OPTIONAL, all the fields listed
      here MUST be present, and any other fields MUST NOT appear in a
      conforming resource certificate. Where a field value is specified here,
      this value MUST be used in conforming resource certificates.</t>

      <section title="Version">
        <t>As resource certificates are X.509 version 3 certificates, the
        version MUST be 3 (i.e., the value of this field is 2).</t>

        <t>RPs need not process version 1 or version 2 certificates (in
        contrast to <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Serial Number">
        <t>The serial number value is a positive integer that is unique for
        each certificate issued by a given CA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Signature Algorithm">
        <t>The algorithm used in this profile is specified in <xref
        target="RFC6485"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="issuer" title="Issuer">
        <t>The value of this field is a valid X.501 distinguished name.</t>

        <t>An issuer name MUST contain one instance of the CommonName
        attribute and MAY contain one instance of the serialNumber attribute.
        If both attributes are present, it is RECOMMENDED that they appear as
        a set. The CommonName attribute MUST be encoded using the ASN.1 type
        PrintableString <xref target="X.680"></xref>. Issuer names are not
        intended to be descriptive of the identity of issuer.</t>

        <t>The RPKI does not rely on issuer names being globally unique, for
        reasons of security. However, it is RECOMMENDED that issuer names be
        generated in a fashion that minimizes the likelihood of collisions.
        See <xref target="notes"></xref> for (non-normative) suggested name-generation mechanisms that fulfill this recommendation.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Subject">
        <t>The value of this field is a valid X.501 distinguished name <xref
        target="RFC4514"></xref>, and is subject to the same constraints as
        the issuer name.</t>

        <t>In the RPKI, the subject name is determined by the issuer, not
        proposed by the subject <xref target="RFC6481"></xref>.
        Each distinct subordinate CA and EE certified by the issuer MUST be
        identified using a subject name that is unique per issuer. In this
        context, "distinct" is defined as an entity and a given public key. An
        issuer SHOULD use a different subject name if the subject's key pair
        has changed (i.e., when the CA issues a certificate as part of
        re-keying the subject.) Subject names are not intended to be
        descriptive of the identity of subject.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Validity">
        <t>The certificate validity period is represented as a SEQUENCE of two
        dates: the date on which the certificate validity period begins
        (notBefore) and the date on which the certificate validity period ends
        (notAfter).</t>

        <t>While a CA is typically advised against issuing a
        certificate with a validity period that spans a greater period
        of time than the validity period of the CA's certificate that
        will be used to validate the issued certificate, in the
        context of this profile, a CA MAY have valid grounds to issue
        a subordinate certificate with a validity period that exceeds
        the validity period of the CA's certificate.</t>

        <section title="notBefore">
          <t>The "notBefore" time SHOULD be no earlier than the time of
          certificate generation.</t>

          <t>In the RPKI, it is valid for a certificate to have a value for
          this field that pre-dates the same field value in any superior
          certificate. Relying Parties SHOULD NOT attempt to infer from this
          time information that a certificate was valid at a time in the past,
          or that it will be valid at a time in the future, as the scope of an RP's
          test of validity of a certificate refers specifically to validity at
          the current time.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="notAfter">
          <t>The "notAfter" time represents the anticipated lifetime of the
          current resource allocation or assignment arrangement between the
          issuer and the subject.</t>

          <t>It is valid for a certificate to have a value for this field that
          post-dates the same field value in any superior certificate. The
          same caveats apply to RP's assumptions relating to the certificate's
          validity at any time other than the current time.</t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title="Subject Public Key Info">
        <t>The algorithm used in this profile is specified in <xref
        target="RFC6485"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Resource Certificate Extensions">
        <t>The following X.509 v3 extensions MUST be present in a conforming
        resource certificate, except where explicitly noted otherwise. Each
        extension in a resource certificate is designated as either critical
        or non-critical. A certificate-using system MUST reject the
        certificate if it encounters a critical extension it does not
        recognize; however, a non-critical extension MAY be ignored if it is
        not recognized <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>.</t>

        <section title="Basic Constraints">
          <t>The Basic Constraints extension field is a critical extension in
          the resource certificate profile, and MUST be present when the
          subject is a CA, and MUST NOT be present otherwise.</t>

          <t>The issuer determines whether the "cA" boolean is set.</t>

          <t>The Path Length Constraint is not specified for RPKI
          certificates, and MUST NOT be present.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Subject Key Identifier">
          <t>This extension MUST appear in all resource certificates. This
          extension is non-critical.</t>

          <t>The Key Identifier used for resource certificates is the 160-bit
          SHA-1 hash of the value of the DER-encoded ASN.1 bit string of the
          Subject Public Key, as described in Section 4.2.1.2 of <xref
          target="RFC5280"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authority Key Identifier">
          <t>This extension MUST appear in all resource certificates, with the
          exception of a CA who issues a "self-signed" certificate. In a
          self-signed certificate, a CA MAY include this extension, and set it
          equal to the Subject Key Identifier. The authorityCertIssuer and
          authorityCertSerialNumber fields MUST NOT be present. This extension
          is non-critical.</t>

          <t>The Key Identifier used for resource certificates is the 160-bit
          SHA-1 hash of the value of the DER-encoded ASN.1 bit string of the
          issuer's public key, as described in Section 4.2.1.1 of <xref
          target="RFC5280"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Key Usage">
          <t>This extension is a critical extension and MUST be present.</t>

          <t>In certificates issued to certification authorities only, the
          keyCertSign and CRLSign bits are set to TRUE, and these MUST be the
          only bits set to TRUE.</t>

          <t>In EE certificates, the digitalSignature bit MUST be set to TRUE
          and MUST be the only bit set to TRUE.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Extended Key Usage">
          <t>The Extended Key Usage (EKU) extension MUST NOT appear in any CA
          certificate in the RPKI. This extension also MUST NOT appear in EE
          certificates used to verify RPKI objects (e.g., ROAs or manifests.
          The extension MUST NOT be marked critical.</t>

          <t>The EKU extension MAY appear in EE certificates issued to routers
          or other devices. Permitted values for the EKU OIDs will be
          specified in Standards Track RFCs issued by other IETF working
          groups that adopt the RPKI profile and that identify
          application-specific requirements that motivate the use of such
          EKUs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="CRL Distribution Points">
          <t>This extension MUST be present, except in "self-signed"
          certificates, and it is non-critical. In a self-signed certificate,
          this extension MUST be omitted.</t>

          <t>In this profile, the scope of the CRL is specified to be all
          certificates issued by this CA issuer.</t>

          <t>The CRL Distribution Points (CRLDP) extension identifies the
  location(s) of the CRL(s) associated with certificates issued by this
  issuer.  The RPKI uses the URI <xref target="RFC3986"></xref> form of object identification.  The
  preferred URI access mechanism is a single rsync URI ("rsync://")
  <xref target="RFC5781"></xref> that references a single inclusive CRL for each issuer.
</t>

          <t>In this profile, the certificate issuer is also the CRL issuer,
          implying that the CRLIssuer field MUST be omitted, and the
          distributionPoint field MUST be present. The Reasons field MUST be
          omitted.</t>

          <t>The distributionPoint MUST contain the fullName field, and MUST
          NOT contain a nameRelativeToCRLIssuer. The form of the generalName
          MUST be of type URI.</t>

          <t>The sequence of distributionPoint values MUST contain only a
          single DistributionPoint. The DistributionPoint MAY contain more
          than one URI value. An rsync URI <xref target="RFC5781"></xref> MUST
          be present in the DistributionPoint and MUST reference the most recent
          instance of this issuer's CRL. Other access form URIs MAY be used in
          addition to the rsync URI, representing alternate access mechanisms
          for this CRL.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authority Information Access">
          <t>In the context of the RPKI, this extension identifies the
          publication point of the certificate of the issuer of the
          certificate in which the extension appears. In this profile, a single
          reference to the publication point of the immediate superior
          certificate MUST be present, except for a "self-signed" certificate,
          in which case the extension MUST be omitted. This extension is
          non-critical.</t>

          <t>This profile uses a URI form of object identification. The
          preferred URI access mechanisms is "rsync", and an rsync URI <xref
          target="RFC5781"></xref> MUST be specified with an accessMethod
          value of id-ad-caIssuers. The URI MUST reference the point of
          publication of the certificate where this Issuer is the subject (the
          issuer's immediate superior certificate). Other accessMethod URIs
          referencing the same object MAY also be included in the value
          sequence of this extension.</t>

          <t>A CA MUST use a persistent URL name scheme for CA certificates
          that it issues <xref target="RFC6481"></xref>. This
          implies that a reissued certificate overwrites a previously issued
          certificate (to the same subject) in the publication repository. In
          this way, certificates subordinate to the reissued (CA) certificate
          can maintain a constant Authority Information Access (AIA) extension
          pointer and thus need not be reissued when the parent certificate
          is reissued.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="SIA" title="Subject Information Access">
          <t>In the context of the RPKI, this Subject Information Access (SIA) extension identifies the
          publication point of products signed by the subject of the
          certificate.</t>

          <section title="SIA for CA Certificates">
            <t>This extension MUST be present and MUST be marked non-critical.
</t>

            <t>This extension MUST have an instance of an accessMethod of
            id-ad-caRepository, with an accessLocation form of a URI that MUST
            specify an rsync URI <xref target="RFC5781"></xref>. This URI
            points to the directory containing all published material issued
            by this CA, i.e., all valid CA certificates, published EE
            certificates, the current CRL, manifest, and signed objects
            validated via EE certificates that have been issued by this CA
            <xref target="RFC6481"></xref>. Other
            accessDescription elements with an accessMethod of
            id-ad-caRepository MAY be present. In such cases, the
            accessLocation values describe alternate supported URI access
            mechanisms for the same directory. The ordering of URIs in this
            accessDescription sequence reflect the CA's relative preferences
            for access methods to be used by RPs, with the first element of
            the sequence being the most preferred by the CA.</t>

            <t>This extension MUST have an instance of an AccessDescription
            with an accessMethod of id-ad-rpkiManifest,</t>

            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
      id-ad OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-pkix 48 }

      id-ad-rpkiManifest OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ad 10 }
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>with an rsync URI <xref target="RFC5781"></xref> form of
            accessLocation. The URI points to the CA's manifest of published
            objects <xref target="RFC6486"></xref> as an object
            URL. Other accessDescription elements MAY exist for the
            id-ad-rpkiManifest accessMethod, where the accessLocation value
            indicates alternate access mechanisms for the same manifest
            object.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="SIA for EE Certificates">
            <t>This extension MUST be present and MUST be marked non-critical.</t>

            <t>This extension MUST have an instance of an accessMethod of
            id-ad-signedObject,</t>

            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
      id-ad-signedObject OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ad 11 }
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>with an accessLocation form of a URI that MUST include an rsync
            URI <xref target="RFC5781"></xref>. This URI points to the signed
            object that is verified using this EE certificate <xref
            target="RFC6481"></xref>. Other accessDescription
            elements may exist for the id-ad-signedObject accessMethod, where
            the accessLocation value indicates alternate URI access mechanisms
            for the same object, ordered in terms of the EE's relative
            preference for supported access mechanisms.</t>

            <t>Other AccessMethods MUST NOT be used for an EE certificates's
            SIA.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Certificate Policies">
          <t>This extension MUST be present and MUST be marked critical. It
          MUST include exactly one policy, as specified in the RPKI CP <xref
          target="RFC6484"></xref></t>
        </section>

        <section title="IP Resources">
          <t>Either the IP Resources extension, or the AS Resources extension,
          or both, MUST be present in all RPKI certificates, and if present,
          MUST be marked critical.</t>

          <t>This extension contains the list of IP address resources as per
          <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>. The value may specify the "inherit"
          element for a particular Address Family Identifier (AFI) value. In the context of resource
          certificates describing public number resources for use in the
          public Internet, the Subsequent AFI (SAFI) value MUST NOT be used.</t>

          <t>This extension MUST either specify a non-empty set of IP address
          records, or use the "inherit" setting to indicate that the IP
          address resource set of this certificate is inherited from that of
          the certificate's issuer.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="AS Resources">
          <t>Either the AS Resources extension, or the IP Resources extension,
          or both, MUST be present in all RPKI certificates, and if present,
          MUST be marked critical.</t>

          <t>This extension contains the list of AS number resources as per
          <xref target="RFC3779"></xref>, or it may specify the "inherit"
          element. Routing Domain Identifier (RDI) values are NOT supported in this profile and MUST NOT
          be used.
</t>

          <t>This extension MUST either specify a non-empty set of AS number
          records, or use the "inherit" setting to indicate that the AS number
          resource set of this certificate is inherited from that of the
          certificate's issuer.
</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Resource Certificate Revocation Lists">
      <t>Each CA MUST issue a version 2 CRL that is
      consistent with <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>. RPs are NOT required to
      process version 1 CRLs (in contrast to <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>).
      The CRL issuer is the CA. CRLs conforming to this profile MUST NOT
      include Indirect or Delta CRLs. The scope of each CRL MUST be all
      certificates issued by this CA.</t>

      <t>The issuer name is as in <xref target="issuer"></xref> above.</t>

      <t>Where two or more CRLs are issued by the same CA, the CRL with the
      highest value of the "CRL Number" field supersedes all other CRLs issued
      by this CA.</t>

      <t>The algorithm used in CRLs issued under this profile is specified in
      <xref target="RFC6485"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The contents of the CRL are a list of all non-expired certificates
      that have been revoked by the CA.</t>

      <t>An RPKI CA MUST include the two extensions, Authority Key Identifier
      and CRL Number, in every CRL that it issues. RPs MUST be prepared to
      process CRLs with these extensions. No other CRL extensions are
      allowed.</t>

      <t>For each revoked resource certificate, only the two fields, Serial
      Number and Revocation Date, MUST be present, and all other fields MUST
      NOT be present. No CRL entry extensions are supported in this profile,
      and CRL entry extensions MUST NOT be present in a CRL.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Resource Certificate Requests">
      <t>A resource certificate request MAY use either of PKCS#10 or
      Certificate Request Message Format (CRMF). A CA MUST support certificate
      issuance in PKCS#10 and a CA MAY support CRMF requests.</t>

      <t>Note that there is no certificate response defined in this profile.
      For CA certificate requests, the CA places the resource certificate in
      the repository, as per <xref target="RFC6484"></xref>. No response is
      defined for EE certificate requests.</t>

      <section title="PCKS#10 Profile">
        <t>This profile refines the specification in <xref
        target="RFC2986"></xref>, as it relates to resource certificates. A
        Certificate Request Message object, formatted according to PKCS#10, is
        passed to a CA as the initial step in issuing a certificate.</t>

        <t>With the exception of the SubjectPublicKeyinfo and the SIA
        extension request, the CA is permitted to alter any field in the
        request when issuing a certificate.</t>

        <section title="PKCS#10 Resource Certificate Request Template Fields">
          <t>This profile applies the following additional requirements to
          fields that MAY appear in a CertificationRequestInfo:  

<list>
              <t><list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Version"><vspace />This field is mandatory and
                  MUST have the value 0.</t>

                  <t hangText="Subject"><vspace /> This field MAY be omitted.
                  If present, the value of this field SHOULD be empty (i.e.,
                  NULL), in which case the CA MUST generate a subject name
                  that is unique in the context of certificates issued by this
                  CA. This field is allowed to be non-empty only for a
                  re-key/reissuance request, and only if the CA has adopted a
                  policy (in its Certificate Practice Statement (CPS)) that
                  permits reuse of names in these circumstances. 
                  </t>

                  <t hangText="SubjectPublicKeyInfo"><vspace />This field
                  specifies the subject's public key and the algorithm with
                  which the key is used. The algorithm used in this profile is
                  specified in <xref target="RFC6485"></xref>.
                  </t>

                  <t hangText="Attributes"><vspace /><xref
                  target="RFC2986"></xref> defines the attributes field as
                  key-value pairs where the key is an OID and the value's
                  structure depends on the key.</t>

                  <t>The only attribute used in this profile is the
                  extensionRequest attribute as defined in <xref
                  target="RFC2985"></xref>. This attribute contains
                  certificate extensions. The profile for extensions in
                  certificate requests is specified in <xref
                  target="exts"></xref>.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>This profile applies the following additional constraint to
          fields that MAY appear in a CertificationRequest Object:
 <list>
              <t><list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="signatureAlgorithm"><vspace />The
                  signatureAlgorithm value is specified in <xref
                  target="RFC6485"></xref>.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="CRMF Profile">
        <t>This profile refines the Certificate Request Message Format (CRMF)
        specification in <xref target="RFC4211"></xref>, as it relates to
        resource certificates. A Certificate Request Message object, formatted
        according to the CRMF, is passed to a CA as the initial step in
        certificate issuance.</t>

        <t>With the exception of the SubjectPublicKeyinfo and the SIA
        extension request, the CA is permitted to alter any requested field
        when issuing the certificate.</t>

        <section title="CRMF Resource Certificate Request Template Fields">
          <t>This profile applies the following additional requirements to
          fields that may appear in a Certificate Request Template:  <list>

              <t><list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="version"><vspace />This field SHOULD be
                  omitted. If present, it MUST specify a request for a version
                  3 Certificate.</t>

                  <t hangText="serialNumber"><vspace />This field MUST be
                  omitted. </t>

                  <t hangText="signingAlgorithm"><vspace />This field MUST be
                  omitted. </t>

                  <t hangText="issuer"><vspace /> This MUST be omitted in this
                  profile. </t>

                  <t hangText="Validity"><vspace /> This field MAY be omitted.
                  If omitted, the CA will issue a Certificate with Validity
                  dates as determined by the CA. If specified, then the CA MAY
                  override the requested values with dates as determined by
                  the CA. </t>

                  <t hangText="Subject"><vspace />This field MAY be omitted.
                  If present, the value of this field SHOULD be empty (i.e.,
                  NULL), in which case the CA MUST generate a subject name
                  that is unique in the context of certificates issued by this
                  CA. This field is allowed to be non-empty only for a
                  re-key/reissuance request, and only if the CA has adopted a
                  policy (in its CPS) that permits the reuse of names in these
                  circumstances.</t>

                  <t hangText="PublicKey"><vspace /> This field MUST be
                  present.</t>

                  <t hangText="extensions"><vspace />The profile for
                  extensions in certificate requests is specified in <xref
                  target="exts"></xref>.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Resource Certificate Request Control Fields">
          <t>The following control fields are supported in this profile:
           <list>
              <t><list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Authenticator Control"><vspace />The intended
                  model of authentication of the subject is a "long term"
                  model, and the guidance offered in <xref
                  target="RFC4211"></xref> is that the Authenticator Control
                  field be used. </t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="exts"
               title="Certificate Extension Attributes in Certificate Requests">
        <t>The following extensions MAY appear in a PKCS#10 or CRMF
        Certificate Request. Any other extensions MUST NOT appear in a
        Certificate Request. This profile places the following additional
        constraints on these extensions:  <list>
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="BasicConstraints"><vspace /> If this is omitted,
                then the CA will issue an EE certificate (hence no
                BasicConstraints extension will be included).<vspace
                blankLines="1" />

                The pathLengthConstraint is not supported in this profile,
                and this field MUST be omitted.<vspace blankLines="1" />

                The CA MAY honor the cA boolean if set to TRUE (CA
                Certificate Request). If this bit is set, then it indicates
                that the subject is requesting a CA certificate.<vspace
                blankLines="1" />

                The CA MUST honor the cA bit if set to FALSE (EE
                Certificate Request), in which case the corresponding EE
                certificate will not contain a Basic Constraints extension.
                </t>

                <t hangText="KeyUsage"><vspace />The CA MAY honor KeyUsage
                extensions of keyCertSign and cRLSign if present, as long as
                this is consistent with the BasicConstraints SubjectType sub-field, when specified.</t>

                <t hangText="ExtendedKeyUsage"><vspace />The CA MAY honor
                ExtendedKeyUsage extensions of keyCertSign and cRLSign if
                present, as long as this is consistent with the
                BasicConstraints SubjectType sub-field, when specified.
                </t>

                <t hangText="SubjectInformationAccess"><vspace /> This field
                MUST be present, and the field value SHOULD be honored by the
                CA if it conforms to the requirements set forth in <xref
                target="SIA"></xref>. If the CA is unable to honor the
                requested value for this field, then the CA MUST reject the
                Certificate Request. </t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Resource Certificate Validation">
      <t>This section describes the resource certificate validation procedure.
      This refines the generic procedure described in Section 6 of <xref
      target="RFC5280"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="resvalid" title="Resource Extension Validation">
        <t>The IP Resources and AS Resources extensions <xref
        target="RFC3779"></xref> define critical extensions for INRs. These
        are ASN.1 encoded representations of the IPv4 and IPv6 address range
        and an AS number set.</t>

        <t>Valid resource certificates MUST have a valid IP address and/or AS
        number resource extension. In order to validate a resource certificate,
        the resource extension MUST also be validated. This validation process
        relies on definitions of comparison of resource sets:
 <list>
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="more specific"><vspace />Given two contiguous IP
address ranges or two contiguous AS number ranges, A and B, A is "more
specific" than B if range B includes all IP addresses or AS numbers described
by range A, and if range B is larger than range A.
                </t>

                <t hangText="equal"><vspace />Given two contiguous IP address
ranges or two contiguous AS number ranges, A and B, A is "equal" to B if range
                A describes precisely the same collection of IP addresses or
                AS numbers described by range B. The definition of
                "inheritance" in <xref target="RFC3779"></xref> is equivalent
                to this "equality" comparison.</t>

                <t hangText="encompass"><vspace />Given two IP address and AS
                number sets, X and Y, X "encompasses" Y if, for every
                contiguous range of IP addresses or AS numbers elements in set
                Y, the range element is either "more specific" than or "equal"
                to a contiguous range element within the set X.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Validation of a certificate's resource extension in the context of
        a certification path (see <xref target="Path"></xref> entails that for
        every adjacent pair of certificates in the certification path
        (certificates 'x' and 'x + 1'), the number resources described in
        certificate 'x' "encompass" the number resources described in
        certificate 'x + 1', and the resources described in the trust anchor
        information "encompass" the resources described in the first
        certificate in the certification path.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Path" title="Resource Certification Path Validation">
        <t>Validation of signed resource data using a target resource
        certificate consists of verifying that the digital signature of the
        signed resource data is valid, using the public key of the target
        resource certificate, and also validating the resource certificate in
        the context of the RPKI, using the path validation process. This path
        validation process verifies, among other things, that a prospective
        certification path (a sequence of n certificates) satisfies the
        following conditions:
<list>
            <t><list style="numbers">
                <t>for all 'x' in {1, ..., n-1}, the subject of certificate
                'x' is the issuer of certificate ('x' + 1); 
                </t>

                <t>certificate '1' is issued by a trust anchor;
                </t>

                <t>certificate 'n' is the certificate to be validated; and
                </t>

                <t>for all 'x' in {1, ..., n}, certificate 'x' is valid.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Certificate validation entails verifying that all of the following
        conditions hold, in addition to the certification path validation
        criteria specified in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>:
         <list>
            <t><list style="numbers">
                <t>The certificate can be verified using the issuer's public
                key and the signature algorithm </t>

                <t>The current time lies within the certificate's Validity
                From and To values. </t>

                <t>The certificate contains all fields that MUST be present,
                as defined by this specification, and contains values for
                selected fields that are defined as allowable values by this
                specification.</t>

                <t>No field, or field value, that this specification defines
                as MUST NOT be present is used in the certificate.
                </t>

                <t>The issuer has not revoked the certificate. A revoked
                certificate is identified by the certificate's serial number
                being listed on the issuer's current CRL, as identified by the
                CRLDP of the certificate, the CRL is itself valid, and the
                public key used to verify the signature on the CRL is the same
                public key used to verify the certificate itself.
                </t>

                <t>The resource extension data is "encompassed" by the
                resource extension data contained in a valid certificate where
                this issuer is the subject (the previous certificate in the
                context of the ordered sequence defined by the certification
                path).</t>

                <t>The certification path originates with a certificate issued
                by a trust anchor, and there exists a signing chain across the
                certification path where the subject of Certificate 'x' in the
                certification path matches the issuer in Certificate 'x + 1'
                in the certification path, and the public key in Certificate
                'x' can verify the signature value in Certificate 'x+1'.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>A certificate validation algorithm MAY perform these tests in any
        chosen order.</t>

        <t>Certificates and CRLs used in this process MAY be found in a
        locally maintained cache, maintained by a regular synchronization
        across the distributed publication repository structure <xref
        target="RFC6481"></xref>.</t>

        <t>There exists the possibility of encountering certificate paths that
        are arbitrarily long, or attempting to generate paths with loops as
        means of creating a potential denial-of-service (DOS) attack on an RP. An RP executing this
        procedure MAY apply further heuristics to guide the
        certification path validation process to a halt in order to avoid some of the
        issues associated with attempts to validate such malformed
        certification path structures. Implementations of resource certificate
        validation MAY halt with a validation failure if the certification
        path length exceeds a locally defined configuration parameter.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notes" title="Design Notes">
      <t>The following notes provide some additional commentary on the
      considerations that lie behind some of the design choices that were made
      in the design of this certificate profile. These notes are
      non-normative, i.e., this section of the document does not constitute a
      formal part of the profile specification, and the interpretation of key
      words as defined in RFC 2119 are not applicable in this section of the
      document.

 <list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Certificate Extensions:"><vspace />This profile does
          not permit the use of any other critical or non-critical extensions.
          The rationale for this restriction is that the resource certificate
          profile is intended for a specific defined use. In this context,
having certificates with additional non-critical extensions that RPs may see as
valid certificates without understanding the extensions is inappropriate,
because if the RP were in a position to understand the extensions, it would
contradict or qualify this original judgment of validity in some way.
This profile takes the position of minimalism over
          extensibility. The specific goal for the associated RPKI is to
          precisely match the INR allocation structure through an aligned
          certificate structure that describes the allocation and its context
          within the INR distribution hierarchy. The profile defines a
          resource certificate that is structured to meet these
          requirements.</t>

          <t
          hangText="Certification Authorities and Key Values:"><vspace />This
          profile uses a definition of an instance of a CA as a combination of
          a named entity and a key pair. Within this definition, a CA instance
          cannot rollover a key pair. However, the entity can generate a new
          instance of a CA with a new key pair and roll over all the signed
          subordinate products to the new CA <xref target="RFC6489"></xref>.
</t>

          <t>This has a number of implications in terms of subject name
          management, CRL Scope, and repository publication point
          management.</t>

          <t hangText="CRL Scope and Key Values:"><vspace />For CRL Scope, this
          profile specifies that a CA issues a single CRL at a time, and the
          scope of the CRL is all certificates issued by this CA. Because the
          CA instance is bound to a single key pair, this implies that the CA's
          public key, the key used to validate the CA's CRL, and the key used
          to validate the certificates revoked by that CRL are all the same
          key value.</t>

          <t hangText="Repository Publication Point:"><vspace />The definition
          of a CA affects the design of the repository publication system. In
          order to minimize the amount of forced re-certification on key
          rollover events, a repository publication regime that uses the same
          repository publication point for all CA instances that refers to the
          same entity, but with different key values, will minimize the extent
          of re-generation of certificates to only immediate subordinate
          certificates. This is described in <xref target="RFC6489"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Subject Name:"><vspace />This profile specifies that
          subject names must be unique per issuer, and does not specify that
          subject names must be globally unique (in terms of assured
          uniqueness). This is due to the nature of the RPKI as a distributed
          PKI, implying that there is no ready ability for certification
          authorities to coordinate a simple RPKI-wide unique name space
          without resorting to additional critical external dependencies. CAs
          are advised to use subject name generation procedures that minimize
          the potential for name clashes.</t>

          <t>One way to achieve this is for a CA to use a subject name
          practice that uses the CommonName component of the Distinguished
          Name as a constant value for any given entity that is the subject of
          CA-issued certificates, and set the serialNumber component of the
          Distinguished Name to a value that is derived from the hash of the
          subject public key value. </t>

          <t>If the CA elects not to use the serialNumber component of the
          DistinguishedName, then it is considered beneficial that a CA
          generates CommonNames that have themselves a random component that
          includes significantly more than 40 bits of entropy in the name.
          Some non-normative recommendations to achieve this include:

 <list style="format %d)">
              <t>Hash of the subject public key (encoded as ASCII
              HEX).<vspace /> example:
              cn="999d99d564de366a29cd8468c45ede1848e2cc14"</t>

              <t>A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) <xref
              target="RFC4122"></xref><vspace /> example:
              cn="6437d442-6fb5-49ba-bbdb-19c260652098"</t>

              <t>A randomly generated ASCII HEX encoded string of length 20 or
              greater:<vspace /> example:

              cn="0f8fcc28e3be4869bc5f8fa114db05e1"&gt;<vspace /> (A string of
              20 ASCII HEX digits would have 80-bits of entropy) </t>

              <t>An internal database key or subscriber ID combined with one
              of the above<vspace /> example: cn="&lt;DBkey1&gt;
              (6437d442-6fb5-49ba-bbdb-19c2606520980)"<vspace /> (The issuing
              CA may wish to be able to extract the database key or subscriber
              ID from the commonName. Since only the issuing CA would need to
              be able to parse the commonName, the database key and the source
              of entropy (e.g., a UUID) could be separated in any way that the
              CA wants, as long as it conforms to the rules for
              PrintableString. The separator could be a space character,
              parenthesis, hyphen, slash, question mark, etc.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations for Profile Agility">
      <t>This profile requires that relying parties reject certificates or
      CRLs that do not conform to the profile. (Through the remainder of this
      section, the term "certificate" is used to refer to both certificates and
      CRLs.) This includes certificates that contain extensions that are
      prohibited, but that are otherwise valid as per <xref
      target="RFC5280"></xref>. This means that any change in the profile
      (e.g., extensions, permitted attributes or optional fields, or field
      encodings) for certificates used in the RPKI will not be backward
      compatible. In a general PKI context, this constraint probably would
      cause serious problems. In the RPKI, several factors minimize the
      difficulty of effecting changes of this sort.</t>

      <t>Note that the RPKI is unique in that every relying party (RP)
      requires access to every certificate issued by the CAs in
      this system. An important update of the certificates used in
      the RPKI must be supported by all CAs and RPs in the system, lest views
      of the RPKI data differ across RPs. Thus, incremental changes require
      very careful coordination. It would not be appropriate to introduce a
      new extension, or authorize use of an extant, standard extension, for a
      security-relevant purpose on a piecemeal basis.</t>

      <t>One might imagine that the "critical" flag in X.509 certificate extensions could be used to ameliorate this problem. However, this
      solution is not comprehensive and does not address the problem of
      adding a new, security-critical extension. (This is because such an
      extension needs to be supported universally, by all CAs and RPs.) Also,
      while some standard extensions can be marked either critical or
      non-critical, at the discretion of the issuer, not all have this
      property, i.e., some standard extensions are always non-critical.
      Moreover, there is no notion of criticality for attributes within a name
      or optional fields within a field or an extension. Thus, the critical
      flag is not a solution to this problem.</t>

      <t>In typical PKI deployments, there are few CAs and many RPs. However,
      in the RPKI, essentially every CA in the RPKI is also an RP. Thus the
      set of entities that will need to change in order to issue certificates
      under a new format is the same set of entities that will need to change
      to accept these new certificates. To the extent that this is literally
      true, it says that CA/RP coordination for a change is tightly linked
      anyway. In reality, there is an important exception to this general
      observation. Small ISPs and holders of provider-independent allocations
      are expected to use managed CA services, offered by Regional Internet
      Registries (RIRs) and potentially by wholesale Internet Service
      Providers (ISPs). This reduces the number of distinct CA implementations
      that are needed and makes it easier to effect changes for certificate
      issuance. It seems very likely that these entities also will make use of
      RP software provided by their managed CA service provider, which reduces
      the number of distinct RP software implementations. Also note that many
      small ISPs (and holders of provider-independent allocations) employ
      default routes, and thus need not perform RP validation of RPKI data,
      eliminating these entities as RPs.</t>

      <t>Widely available PKI RP software does not cache large numbers of
      certificates, an essential strategy for the RPKI. It does not
      process manifest or ROA data structures, essential elements of the RPKI
      repository system. Experience shows that such software deals poorly with
      revocation status data. Thus, extant RP software is not adequate for the
      RPKI, although some open source tools (e.g., OpenSSL and cryptlib) can
      be used as building blocks for an RPKI RP implementation. Thus, it is
anticipated that RPs will make use of software that is designed specifically
for the RPKI environment and is available from a limited number of open sources.
Several RIRs and two companies are providing such software
      today. Thus it is feasible to coordinate change to this software among
      the small number of developers/maintainers.</t>

      <t>If the resource certificate profile is changed in the future, e.g.,
      by adding a new extension or changing the allowed set of name attributes
      or encoding of these attributes, the following procedure will be
      employed to effect deployment in the RPKI. The model is analogous to
      that described in <xref target="RPKI-ALG"></xref>, but
      is simpler.</t>

      <t>A new document will be issued as an update to this RFC. The CP for
      the RPKI <xref target="RFC6484"></xref> will be updated to reference
      the new certificate profile. The new CP will define a new policy OID for
      certificates issued under the new certificate profile. The updated CP
      also will define a timeline for transition to the new certificate (CRL)
      format. This timeline will define 3 phases and associated dates: <list>
          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>At the end of phase 1, all RPKI CAs MUST be capable of
              issuing certificates under the new profile, if requested by a
              subject. Any certificate issued under the new format will
              contain the new policy OID.</t>

              <t>During phase 2, CAs MUST issue certificates under the new
              profile, and these certificates MUST coexist with certificates
              issued under the old format. (CAs will continue to issue
              certificates under the old OID/format as well.) The old and new
              certificates MUST be identical, except for the policy OID and
              any new extensions, encodings, etc. The new certificates, and
              associated signed objects, will coexist in the RPKI repository
              system during this phase, analogous to what is required by an
              algorithm transition for the RPKI <xref
              target="RPKI-ALG"></xref>. Relying parties MAY
              make use of the old or the new certificate formats when
              processing signed objects retrieved from the RPKI repository
              system. During this phase, a relying party that elects to
              process both formats will acquire the same values for all
              certificate fields that overlap between the old and new formats.
              Thus if either certificate format is verifiable, the relying
              party accepts the data from that certificate. This allows CAs to
              issue certificates under the new format before all relying
              parties are prepared to process that format.</t>

              <t>At the beginning of phase 3, all relying parties MUST be
              capable of processing certificates under the new format. During
              this phase, CAs will issue new certificates ONLY under the new
              format. Certificates issued under the old OID
              will be replaced with certificates containing the new policy
              OID. The repository system will no longer require matching old
              and new certificates under the different formats.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>At the end of phase 3, all certificates under the old OID will have
      been replaced. The resource certificate profile RFC will be replaced to
      remove support for the old certificate format, and the CP will be
      replaced to remove reference to the old policy OID and to the old
      resource certificate profile RFC. The system will have returned to a
      new, steady state.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The Security Considerations of <xref target="RFC5280"></xref> and
      <xref target="RFC3779"></xref> apply to resource certificates. The
      Security Considerations of <xref target="RFC2986"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC4211"></xref> apply to resource certificate certification
      requests.</t>

      <t>A resource certificate PKI cannot in and of itself resolve any forms
      of ambiguity relating to uniqueness of assertions of rights of use in
      the event that two or more valid certificates encompass the same
      resource. If the issuance of resource certificates is aligned to the
      status of resource allocations and assignments, then the information
      conveyed in a certificate is no better than the information in the
      allocation and assignment databases.</t>

      <t>This profile requires that the key used to sign an issued certificate
      be the same key used to sign the CRL that can revoke the certificate,
      implying that the certification path used to validate the signature on a
      certificate is the same as that used to validate the signature of the
      CRL that can revoke the certificate. It is noted that this is a tighter
      constraint than required in X.509 PKIs, and there may be a risk in using
      a path validation implementation that is capable of using separate
      validation paths for a certificate and the corresponding CRL. If there
      are subject name collisions in the RPKI as a result of CAs not following
      the guidelines provided here relating to ensuring sufficient entropy in
      constructing subject names, and this is combined with the situation that
      an RP uses an implementation of validation path construction that is not
      in conformance with this RPKI profile, then it is possible that the
      subject name collisions can cause an RP to conclude that an otherwise
      valid certificate has been revoked.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to particularly acknowledge the valued
      contribution from Stephen Kent in reviewing this document and proposing
      numerous sections of text that have been incorporated into the document. The
      authors also acknowledge the contributions of Sandy Murphy, Robert
      Kisteleki, Randy Bush, Russ Housley, Ricardo Patara, and Rob Austein in
      the preparation and subsequent review of this document. The document
      also reflects review comments received from Roque Gagliano, Sean Turner,
      and David Cooper.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2986.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3779.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4211.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5280.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5781.xml'?>


      <reference anchor="X.509">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation X.509: The Directory - Authentication
          Framework</title>

          <author fullname="ITU-T" surname="ITU-T">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="X.680">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation X.680 (2002) | ISO/IEC 8824-1:2002,
          Information technology - Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1):
          Specification of basic notation</title>

          <author fullname="ITU-T" surname="ITU-T">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-rpki-algs -->
  <reference anchor="RFC6485">
        <front>
          <title>A Profile for Algorithms and Key Sizes for Use in the
          Resource Public Key Infrastructure</title>

          <author fullname="G. Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6485" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-cp -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6484">
        <front>
          <title>Certificate Policy (CP) for the Resource PKI (RPKI)</title>

          <author fullname="S. Kent" initials="S." surname="Kent">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Kent" initials="D." surname="Kong">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K. Kent" initials="K." surname="Seo">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Kent" initials="R." surname="Watro">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP"
                    value="173" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6484" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2985.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4122.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4514.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3986.xml'?>

<!-- ID.sidr-arch -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6480">
        <front>
          <title>An Infrastructure to Support Secure Internet Routing</title>

          <author fullname="M. Lepinski" initials="M." surname="Lepinski">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kent" initials="S." surname="Kent">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6480" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-rpki-manifests -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6486">
        <front>
          <title>Manifests for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure</title>

          <author fullname="Rob Austein" initials="R." surname="Austein">
            <organization>ISC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Geoff Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kent" initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization>BBN</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Lepinski" initials="M" surname="Lepinski">
            <organization>2BBN</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6486" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-signed-object -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6488">
        <front>
          <title>Signed Object Template for the Resource Public Key
          Infrastructure</title>

          <author fullname="M. Lepinski" initials="M" surname="Lepinski">
            <organization>BBN</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Chi" initials="A" surname="Chi">
            <organization>BBN</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kent" initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization>BBN</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6488" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-repos-struct -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6481">
        <front>
          <title>A Profile for Resource Certificate Repository
          Structure</title>

          <author fullname="G. Huston" initials="G" surname="Huston">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Loomans" initials="R" surname="Loomans">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Michaelson" initials="G" surname="Michaelson">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6481" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-keyroll -->
      <reference anchor="RFC6489">
        <front>
          <title>Certification Authority (CA) Key Rollover in the Resource
Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>

          <author fullname="G. Huston" initials="G" surname="Huston">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Michaelson" initials="G" surname="Michaelson">
            <organization>APNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Stephen Kent" initials="S." surname="Kent">
            <organization abbrev="BBN">BBN Technologies</organization>

            <address>
              <email>kent@bbn.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2012" />
        </front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='174' />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC"
                    value="6489" />
      </reference>

<!-- ID.sidr-algorithm-agility -->
      <reference anchor="RPKI-ALG">
        <front>
          <title>Algorithm Agility Procedure for RPKI</title>

          <author fullname="R. Gagliano" initials="R." surname="Gagliano">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Kent" initials="S." surname="Kent">
            <organization>BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Turner" initials="S." surname="Turner">
            <organization>ICEA, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in"
                    value="Progress" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Example Resource Certificate">
      <t>The following is an example resource certificate.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Certificate Name: 9JfgAEcq7Q-47IwMC5CJIJr6EJs.cer

Data:
  Version: 3 (0x2)
  Serial: 1500 (0x5dc)
  Signature Algorithm: SHA256WithRSAEncryption
  Issuer: CN=APNIC Production-CVPQSgUkLy7pOXdNeVWGvnFX_0s
  Validity 
   Not Before: Oct 25 12:50:00 2008 GMT
    Not After : Jan 31 00:00:00 2010 GMT
  Subject: CN=A91872ED
  Subject Public Key Info:
    Public Key Algorithm: rsaEncryption
    RSA Public Key: (2048 bit)
    Modulus (2048 bit):
      00:bb:fb:4a:af:a4:b9:dc:d0:fa:6f:67:cc:27:39:
      34:d1:80:40:37:de:88:d1:64:a2:f1:b3:fa:c6:7f:
      bb:51:df:e1:c7:13:92:c3:c8:a2:aa:8c:d1:11:b3:
      aa:99:c0:ac:54:d3:65:83:c6:13:bf:0d:9f:33:2d:
      39:9f:ab:5f:cd:a3:e9:a1:fb:80:7d:1d:d0:2b:48:
      a5:55:e6:24:1f:06:41:35:1d:00:da:1f:99:85:13:
      26:39:24:c5:9a:81:15:98:fb:5f:f9:84:38:e5:d6:
      70:ce:5a:02:ca:dd:61:85:b3:43:2d:0b:35:d5:91:
      98:9d:da:1e:0f:c2:f6:97:b7:97:3e:e6:fc:c1:c4:
      3f:30:c4:81:03:25:99:09:4c:e2:4a:85:e7:46:4b:
      60:63:02:43:46:51:4d:ed:fd:a1:06:84:f1:4e:98:
      32:da:27:ee:80:82:d4:6b:cf:31:ea:21:af:6f:bd:
      70:34:e9:3f:d7:e4:24:cd:b8:e0:0f:8e:80:eb:11:
      1f:bc:c5:7e:05:8e:5c:7b:96:26:f8:2c:17:30:7d:
      08:9e:a4:72:66:f5:ca:23:2b:f2:ce:54:ec:4d:d9:
      d9:81:72:80:19:95:57:da:91:00:d9:b1:e8:8c:33:
      4a:9d:3c:4a:94:bf:74:4c:30:72:9b:1e:f5:8b:00:
      4d:e3
    Exponent: 65537 (0x10001)
  X509v3 extensions:
    X509v3 Subject Key Identifier: 
      F4:97:E0:00:47:2A:ED:0F:B8:EC:8C:0C:0B:90:89:
      20:9A:FA:10:9B

    X509v3 Authority Key Identifier: 
      keyid:09:53:D0:4A:05:24:2F:2E:E9:39:77:4D:79:
      55:86:BE:71:57:FF:4B

    X509v3 Key Usage: critical
      Certificate Sign, CRL Sign

    X509v3 Basic Constraints: critical
      CA:TRUE

    X509v3 CRL Distribution Points: 
      URI:rsync://rpki.apnic.net/repository/A3C38A24
          D60311DCAB08F31979BDBE39/CVPQSgUkLy7pOXdNe
          VWGvnFX_0s.crl

    Authority Information Access: 
       CA Issuers - URI:rsync://rpki.apnic.net/repos
          itory/8BDFC7DED5FD11DCB14CF4B1A703F9B7/CVP
          QSgUkLy7pOXdNeVWGvnFX_0s.cer

    X509v3 Certificate Policies: critical
       Policy: 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.14.2

    Subject Information Access: 
       CA Repository - URI:rsync://rpki.apnic.net/mem
           ber_repository/A91872ED/06A83982887911DD81
           3F432B2086D636/
       Manifest - URI:rsync://rpki.apnic.net/member_r
           epository/A91872ED/06A83982887911DD813F432
           B2086D636/9JfgAEcq7Q-47IwMC5CJIJr6EJs.mft

     sbgp-autonomousSysNum: critical
       Autonomous System Numbers:
         24021
         38610
         131072
         131074

     sbgp-ipAddrBlock: critical
       IPv4:
         203.133.248.0/22
         203.147.108.0/23

Signature Algorithm: sha256WithRSAEncryption
    51:4c:77:e4:21:64:80:e9:35:30:20:9f:d8:4b:88:60:b8:1f:
    73:24:9d:b5:17:60:65:6a:28:cc:43:4b:68:97:ca:76:07:eb:
    dc:bd:a2:08:3c:8c:56:38:c6:0a:1e:a8:af:f5:b9:42:02:6b:
    77:e0:b1:1c:4a:88:e6:6f:b6:17:d3:59:41:d7:a0:62:86:59:
    29:79:26:76:34:d1:16:2d:75:05:cb:b2:99:bf:ca:c6:68:1b:
    b6:a9:b0:f4:43:2e:df:e3:7f:3c:b3:72:1a:99:fa:5d:94:a1:
    eb:57:9c:9a:2c:87:d6:40:32:c9:ff:a6:54:b8:91:87:fd:90:
    55:ef:12:3e:1e:2e:cf:c5:ea:c3:4c:09:62:4f:88:00:a0:7f:
    cd:67:83:bc:27:e1:74:2c:18:4e:3f:12:1d:ef:29:0f:e3:27:
    00:ce:14:eb:f0:01:f0:36:25:a2:33:a8:c6:2f:31:18:22:30:
    cf:ca:97:43:ed:84:75:53:ab:b7:6c:75:f7:2f:55:5c:2e:82:
    0a:be:91:59:bf:c9:06:ef:bb:b4:a2:71:9e:03:b1:25:8e:29:
    7a:30:88:66:b4:f2:16:6e:df:ad:78:ff:d3:b2:9c:29:48:e3:
    be:87:5c:fc:20:2b:df:da:ca:30:58:c3:04:c9:63:72:48:8c:
    0a:5f:97:71
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Example Certificate Revocation List">
      <t>The following is an example Certificate Revocation List.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
CRL Name: q66IrWSGuBE7jqx8PAUHAlHCqRw.crl
Data:
  Version: 2
  Signature Algorithm:
    Hash: SHA256, Encryption: RSA
  Issuer: CN=Demo Production APNIC CA - Not for real use,
    E=ca@apnic.net
  This Update: Thu Jul 27 06:30:34 2006 GMT
  Next Update: Fri Jul 28 06:30:34 2006 GMT
  Authority Key Identifier: Key Identifier:
    ab:ae:88:ad:64:86:b8:11:3b:8e:ac:7c:3c:05:
    07:02:51:c2:a9:1c
  CRLNumber: 4
  Revoked Certificates: 1
    Serial Number: 1
    Revocation Date: Mon Jul 17 05:10:19 2006 GMT
    Serial Number: 2
    Revocation Date: Mon Jul 17 05:12:25 2006 GMT
    Serial Number: 4
    Revocation Date: Mon Jul 17 05:40:39 2006 GMT
  Signature:
    b2:5a:e8:7c:bd:a8:00:0f:03:1a:17:fd:40:2c:46:
    0e:d5:64:87:e7:e7:bc:10:7d:b6:3e:39:21:a9:12:
    f4:5a:d8:b8:d4:bd:57:1a:7d:2f:7c:0d:c6:4f:27:
    17:c8:0e:ae:8c:89:ff:00:f7:81:97:c3:a1:6a:0a:
    f7:d2:46:06:9a:d1:d5:4d:78:e1:b7:b0:58:4d:09:
    d6:7c:1e:a0:40:af:86:5d:8c:c9:48:f6:e6:20:2e:
    b9:b6:81:03:0b:51:ac:23:db:9f:c1:8e:d6:94:54:
    66:a5:68:52:ee:dd:0f:10:5d:21:b8:b8:19:ff:29:
    6f:51:2e:c8:74:5c:2a:d2:c5:fa:99:eb:c5:c2:a2:
    d0:96:fc:54:b3:ba:80:4b:92:7f:85:54:76:c9:12:
    cb:32:ea:1d:12:7b:f8:f9:a2:5c:a1:b1:06:8e:d8:
    c5:42:61:00:8c:f6:33:11:29:df:6e:b2:cc:c3:7c:
    d3:f3:0c:8d:5c:49:a5:fb:49:fd:e7:c4:73:68:0a:
    09:0e:6d:68:a9:06:52:3a:36:4f:19:47:83:59:da:
    02:5b:2a:d0:8a:7a:33:0a:d5:ce:be:b5:a2:7d:8d:
    59:a1:9d:ee:60:ce:77:3d:e1:86:9a:84:93:90:9f:
    34:a7:02:40:59:3a:a5:d1:18:fb:6f:fc:af:d4:02:
    d9
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
