<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- used xml2rfc v1 -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1122 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.1122.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2131 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2131.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2464 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2464.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2827 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2827.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3633 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3633.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3646 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3646.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3704 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3704.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3736 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3736.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4191 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4191.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4193 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4193.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4242 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4242.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4443 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4443.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4605 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4605.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4632 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4632.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4779 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4779.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4862 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4862.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5072 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5072.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5075 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5075.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5908 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5908.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5942 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5942.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5969 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5969.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6092 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6092.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6106 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6106.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6144 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6144.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6177 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6177.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6333 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6333.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6334 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6334.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6434 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6434.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6603 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6603.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6887 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6887.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" number="7084" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" obsoletes="6204">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 CE Router Requirements">Basic Requirements for IPv6
    Customer Edge Routers</title>

    <author fullname="Hemant Singh" initials="H." surname="Singh">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 978 936 1622</phone>

        <email>shemant@cisco.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.cisco.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wes Beebee" initials="W." surname="Beebee">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 978 936 2030</phone>

        <email>wbeebee@cisco.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.cisco.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chris Donley" initials="C.D." surname="Donley">
      <organization>CableLabs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>858 Coal Creek Circle</street>

          <city>Louisville</city>

          <region>CO</region>

          <code>80027</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>c.donley@cablelabs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Barbara Stark" initials="B." surname="Stark">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1057 Lenox Park Blvd. NE</street>

          <city>Atlanta</city>

          <region>GA</region>

          <code>30319</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>barbara.stark@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2013" />



    <keyword>IPv6 CE requirements</keyword>


    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies requirements for an IPv6 Customer Edge (CE)
      router. Specifically, the current version of this document focuses on
      the basic provisioning of an IPv6 CE router and the provisioning of IPv6
      hosts attached to it. The document also covers IP transition
      technologies. Two transition technologies in RFC 5969's IPv6 Rapid Deployment on IPv4 Infrastructures (6rd) and RFC
      6333's Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite) are covered in the document. The document obsoletes RFC
      6204.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines basic IPv6 features for a residential or small-
         office router, referred to as an "IPv6 CE router", in order to
         establish an industry baseline for features to be implemented on such
         a router.
      </t>
      <t>These routers typically also support IPv4.
      </t>

      <t>Mixed environments of dual-stack hosts and IPv6-only hosts (behind
      the CE router) can be more complex if the IPv6-only devices are using a
      translator to access IPv4 servers <xref target="RFC6144"></xref>.
      Support for such mixed environments is not in scope of this
      document.</t>

      <t>This document specifies how an IPv6 CE router automatically
      provisions its WAN interface, acquires address space for provisioning of
      its LAN interfaces, and fetches other configuration information from the
      service provider network. Automatic provisioning of more complex
      topology than a single router with multiple LAN interfaces is out of
      scope for this document.</t>

      <t>See <xref target="RFC4779"></xref> for a discussion of options
      available for deploying IPv6 in service provider access networks.</t>

      <t>The document also covers the IP transition technologies that were
      available at the time this document was written. Two transition
      technologies in 6rd <xref target="RFC5969"></xref> and DS-Lite <xref
      target="RFC6333"></xref> are covered in the document.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
           Take careful note: Unlike other IETF documents, the key words "MUST",
           "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
           "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are not used as
           described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>. This document uses 
           these keywords not
           strictly for the purpose of interoperability, but rather for the
           purpose of establishing industry-common baseline functionality.  As
           such, the document points to several other specifications (preferable
           in RFC or stable form) to provide additional guidance to implementers
           regarding any protocol implementation required to produce a
           successful CE router that interoperates successfully with a
           particular subset of currently deploying and planned common IPv6
           access networks.
         </t>

          
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t><list hangIndent="26" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="End-User Network">one or more links attached to the
          IPv6 CE router that connect IPv6 hosts.</t>

          <t hangText="IPv6 Customer Edge Router">a node intended for home or
          small-office use that forwards IPv6 packets not explicitly addressed
          to itself. The IPv6 CE router connects the end-user network to a
          service provider network.</t>

          <t hangText="IPv6 Host">any device implementing an IPv6 stack
          receiving IPv6 connectivity through the IPv6 CE router.</t>

          <t hangText="LAN Interface">an IPv6 CE router's attachment to a link
          in the end-user network. Examples are Ethernet (simple or bridged),
          802.11 wireless, or other LAN technologies. An IPv6 CE router may
          have one or more network-layer LAN interfaces.</t>

          <t hangText="Service Provider">an entity that provides access to the
          Internet. In this document, a service provider specifically offers
          Internet access using IPv6, and it may also offer IPv4 Internet access.
          The service provider can provide such access over a variety of
          different transport methods such as DSL, cable, wireless, and
          others.</t>

          <t hangText="WAN Interface">an IPv6 CE router's attachment to a link
          used to provide connectivity to the service provider network;
          example link technologies include Ethernet (simple or bridged), PPP
          links, Frame Relay, or ATM networks, as well as Internet-layer (or
          higher-layer) "tunnels", such as tunnels over IPv4 or IPv6
          itself.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Architecture">
      <section title="Current IPv4 End-User Network Architecture">
        <t>An end-user network will likely support both IPv4 and IPv6. It is
        not expected that an end user will change their existing network
        topology with the introduction of IPv6. There are some differences in
        how IPv6 works and is provisioned; these differences have implications
        for the network architecture. A typical IPv4 end-user network consists
        of a "plug and play" router with NAT functionality and a single link
        behind it, connected to the service provider network.</t>

        <t>A typical IPv4 NAT deployment by default blocks all incoming
        connections. Opening of ports is typically allowed using a Universal
        Plug and Play Internet Gateway Device (UPnP IGD) <xref
        target="UPnP-IGD"></xref> or some other firewall control protocol.</t>

        <t>Another consequence of using private address space in the end-user
        network is that it provides stable addressing; that is, it never changes
        even when you change service providers, and the addresses are always
        there even when the WAN interface is down or the customer edge router
        has not yet been provisioned.</t>

        <t>Many existing routers support dynamic routing (which learns routes 
           from other routers), and advanced end-users can build arbitrary, complex 
           networks using manual configuration of address prefixes combined with a 
           dynamic routing protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 End-User Network Architecture">
        <t>The end-user network architecture for IPv6 should provide
        equivalent or better capabilities and functionality than the current
        IPv4 architecture.</t>

        <t>The end-user network is a stub network. Figure 1 illustrates the
        model topology for the end-user network.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="sp_architecture"
                title="An Example of a Typical End-User Network">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                  +-------+-------+                      \
                  |   Service     |                       \
                  |   Provider    |                        | Service
                  |    Router     |                        | Provider
                  +-------+-------+                        | Network
                          |                               /
                          | Customer                     /
                          | Internet Connection         /
                          |
                   +------+--------+                    \
                   |     IPv6      |                     \
                   | Customer Edge |                      \
                   |    Router     |                      /
                   +---+-------+-+-+                     /
       Network A       |       |   Network B            | End-User
 ---+-------------+----+-    --+--+-------------+---    | Network(s)
    |             |               |             |        \
+----+-----+ +-----+----+     +----+-----+ +-----+----+   \
|IPv6 Host | |IPv6 Host |     | IPv6 Host| |IPv6 Host |   /
|          | |          |     |          | |          |  /
+----------+ +-----+----+     +----------+ +----------+ /
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>This architecture describes the:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Basic capabilities of an IPv6 CE router</t>

            <t>Provisioning of the WAN interface connecting to the service
            provider</t>

            <t>Provisioning of the LAN interfaces</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>For IPv6 multicast traffic, the IPv6 CE router may act as a
        Multicast Listener Discovery (MLD) proxy <xref
        target="RFC4605"></xref> and may support a dynamic multicast routing
        protocol.</t>

        <t>The IPv6 CE router may be manually configured in an arbitrary
        topology with a dynamic routing protocol. Automatic provisioning and
        configuration are described for a single IPv6 CE router only.</t>

        <section title="Local Communication">
          <t>Link-local IPv6 addresses are used by hosts communicating on a single
  link.  Unique Local IPv6 Unicast Addresses (ULAs) <xref target="RFC4193" /> are used
  by hosts communicating within the end-user network across multiple
  links, but without requiring the application to use a globally
  routable address.  The IPv6 CE router defaults to acting as the
  demarcation point between two networks by providing a ULA boundary, a
  multicast zone boundary, and ingress and egress traffic filters.</t>

          <t>At the time of this writing, several host implementations do not
          handle the case where they have an IPv6 address configured and no
          IPv6 connectivity, either because the address itself has a limited
          topological reachability (e.g., ULA) or because the IPv6 CE router
          is not connected to the IPv6 network on its WAN interface. To
          support host implementations that do not handle multihoming in a
          multi-prefix environment <xref
          target="MULTIHOMING-WITHOUT-NAT"></xref>, the IPv6 CE router should
          not, as detailed in the requirements below, advertise itself as a
          default router on the LAN interface(s) when it does not have IPv6
          connectivity on the WAN interface or when it is not provisioned with
          IPv6 addresses. For local IPv6 communication, the mechanisms
          specified in <xref target="RFC4191"></xref> are used.</t>

          <t>ULA addressing is useful where the IPv6 CE router has multiple
          LAN interfaces with hosts that need to communicate with each other.
          If the IPv6 CE router has only a single LAN interface (IPv6 link),
          then link-local addressing can be used instead.</t>

          <t>Coexistence with IPv4 requires any IPv6 CE router(s) on the LAN
          to conform to these recommendations, especially requirements ULA-5
          and L-4 below.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements">
      <section title="General Requirements">
        <t>The IPv6 CE router is responsible for implementing IPv6 routing;
        that is, the IPv6 CE router must look up the IPv6 destination address
        in its routing table to decide to which interface it should send the
        packet.</t>

        <t>In this role, the IPv6 CE router is responsible for ensuring that
        traffic using its ULA addressing does not go out the WAN interface
        and does not originate from the WAN interface.</t>

        <t><list style="format G-%d:">
            <t>An IPv6 CE router is an IPv6 node according to the <xref
            target="RFC6434"> IPv6 Node Requirements specification</xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST implement ICMPv6 according to <xref
            target="RFC4443"></xref>. In particular, point-to-point links MUST
            be handled as described in Section 3.1 of <xref
            target="RFC4443"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST NOT forward any IPv6 traffic between
            its LAN interface(s) and its WAN interface until the router has
            successfully completed the IPv6 address and the delegated prefix
            acquisition process.</t>

            <t>By default, an IPv6 CE router that has no default router(s) on
            its WAN interface MUST NOT advertise itself as an IPv6 default
            router on its LAN interfaces. That is, the "Router Lifetime" field
            is set to zero in all Router Advertisement messages it originates
            <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>

            <t>By default, if the IPv6 CE router is an advertising router and
            loses its IPv6 default router(s) and/or detects loss of
            connectivity on the WAN interface, it MUST explicitly invalidate
            itself as an IPv6 default router on each of its advertising
            interfaces by immediately transmitting one or more Router
            Advertisement messages with the "Router Lifetime" field set to
            zero <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="WAN-Side Configuration">
        <t>The IPv6 CE router will need to support connectivity to one or more
        access network architectures. This document describes an IPv6 CE
        router that is not specific to any particular architecture or service
        provider and that supports all commonly used architectures.</t>

        <t>IPv6 Neighbor Discovery and DHCPv6 protocols operate over any type
        of IPv6-supported link layer, and there is no need for a
        link-layer-specific configuration protocol for IPv6 network-layer
        configuration options as in, e.g., PPP IP Control Protocol (IPCP) for
        IPv4. This section makes the assumption that the same mechanism will
        work for any link layer, be it Ethernet, the Data Over Cable Service
        Interface Specification (DOCSIS), PPP, or others.</t>

        <t>WAN-side requirements: <list style="format W-%d:">
            <t>When the router is attached to the WAN interface link, it MUST
            act as an IPv6 host for the purposes of stateless <xref
            target="RFC4862"></xref> or stateful <xref
            target="RFC3315"></xref> interface address assignment.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST generate a link-local address and
            finish Duplicate Address Detection according to <xref
            target="RFC4862"></xref> prior to sending any Router Solicitations
            on the interface. The source address used in the subsequent Router
            Solicitation MUST be the link-local address on the WAN
            interface.</t>

            <t>Absent other routing information, the IPv6 CE router MUST use
            Router Discovery as specified in <xref target="RFC4861"></xref> to
            discover a default router(s) and install a default route(s) in its
            routing table with the discovered router's address as the next
            hop.</t>

            <t>The router MUST act as a requesting router for the purposes of
            DHCPv6 prefix delegation (<xref target="RFC3633"></xref>).</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST use a persistent DHCP Unique Identifier
            (DUID) for DHCPv6 messages. The DUID MUST NOT change between
            network-interface resets or IPv6 CE router reboots.</t>

            <t>The WAN interface of the CE router SHOULD support a Port Control Protocol (PCP) client
            as specified in <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> for use
            by applications on the CE router. The PCP client SHOULD follow the
            procedure specified in Section 8.1 of <xref
            target="RFC6887"></xref> to discover its PCP server.
            This document takes no position on whether such functionality is
            enabled by default or mechanisms by which users would configure
            the functionality. Handling PCP requests from PCP clients in the
            LAN side of the CE router is out of scope.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Link-layer requirements: <list style="format WLL-%d:">
            <t>If the WAN interface supports Ethernet encapsulation, then the
            IPv6 CE router MUST support IPv6 over Ethernet <xref
            target="RFC2464"></xref>.</t>

            <t>If the WAN interface supports PPP encapsulation, the IPv6 CE
            router MUST support IPv6 over PPP <xref
            target="RFC5072"></xref>.</t>

            <t>If the WAN interface supports PPP encapsulation, in a
            dual-stack environment with IPCP and IPV6CP running over one PPP
            logical channel, the Network Control Protocols (NCPs) MUST be
            treated as independent of each other and start and terminate
            independently.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Address assignment requirements:<list style="format WAA-%d:">
            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support Stateless Address
            Autoconfiguration (SLAAC) <xref target="RFC4862"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST follow the recommendations in Section 4
            of <xref target="RFC5942"></xref>, and in particular the handling
            of the L flag in the Router Advertisement Prefix Information
            option.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support DHCPv6 <xref
            target="RFC3315"></xref> client behavior.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST be able to support the following DHCPv6
            options: Identity Association for Non-temporary Address (IA_NA), Reconfigure Accept <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>,
            and DNS_SERVERS <xref target="RFC3646"></xref>. The IPv6 CE router
            SHOULD be able to support the DNS Search List (DNSSL) option as
            specified in <xref target="RFC3646"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD implement the Network Time
            Protocol (NTP) as specified in <xref target="RFC5905"></xref> to provide 
            a time reference common to the service provider for other protocols, such 
            as DHCPv6, to use.  If the CE router implements NTP, it requests the NTP 
            Server DHCPv6 option <xref target="RFC5908"></xref> and uses the received 
            list of servers as primary time reference, unless explicitly configured
            otherwise. LAN side support of NTP is out of scope for this document.</t>

            <t>If the IPv6 CE router receives a Router Advertisement message
            (described in <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>) with the M flag set
            to 1, the IPv6 CE router MUST do DHCPv6 address assignment
            (request an IA_NA option).</t>

            <t>If the IPv6 CE router does not acquire a global IPv6 address(es)
            from either SLAAC or DHCPv6, then it MUST create a global IPv6
            address(es) from its delegated prefix(es) and configure those on
            one of its internal virtual network interfaces, unless configured
            to require a global IPv6 address on the WAN interface.</t>

            <t>The CE router MUST support the SOL_MAX_RT 
               option <xref target="RFC7083"></xref>
               and request the SOL_MAX_RT option in an Option Request Option (ORO).</t>

            <t>As a router, the IPv6 CE router MUST follow the weak host (Weak
            End System) model <xref target="RFC1122"></xref>. When originating packets
            from an interface, it will use a source address from another one
            of its interfaces if the outgoing interface does not have an
            address of suitable scope.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD implement the Information Refresh
            Time option and associated client behavior as specified in <xref
            target="RFC4242"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Prefix delegation requirements: <list style="format WPD-%d:">
            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support DHCPv6 prefix delegation
            requesting router behavior as specified in <xref
            target="RFC3633"></xref> (Identity Association for Prefix Delegation (IA_PD) option).</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MAY indicate as a hint to the delegating
            router the size of the prefix it requires. If so, it MUST ask for
            a prefix large enough to assign one /64 for each of its
            interfaces, rounded up to the nearest nibble, and SHOULD be
            configurable to ask for more.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST be prepared to accept a delegated
            prefix size different from what is given in the hint. If the
            delegated prefix is too small to address all of its interfaces,
            the IPv6 CE router SHOULD log a system management error. <xref
            target="RFC6177"></xref> covers the recommendations for service
            providers for prefix allocation sizes.</t>

            <t>By default, the IPv6 CE router MUST initiate DHCPv6 prefix
            delegation when either the M or O flags are set to 1 in a received
            Router Advertisement (RA) message.  Behavior of the CE router to 
            use DHCPv6 prefix delegation when the CE router has not received 
            any RA or received an RA with the M and the O bits set to zero is 
            out of scope for this document.</t>

            <t>Any packet received by the CE router with a destination
               address in the prefix(es) delegated to the CE router but
               not in the set of prefixes assigned by the CE router to the
               LAN must be dropped.  In other words, the next hop for the
               prefix(es) delegated to the CE router should be the null
               destination.  This is necessary to prevent forwarding loops
               when some addresses covered by the aggregate are not
               reachable <xref target="RFC4632"></xref>.<list
                style="format (%c)">
                <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD send an ICMPv6 Destination
                Unreachable message in accordance with <xref target="RFC4443">
                Section 3.1 of</xref> back to the source of the packet, if the
                packet is to be dropped due to this rule.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>If the IPv6 CE router requests both an IA_NA and an IA_PD
            option in DHCPv6, it MUST accept an IA_PD option in DHCPv6
            Advertise/Reply messages, even if the message does not contain any
            addresses, unless configured to only obtain its WAN IPv6 address
            via DHCPv6; see <xref target="DHCPV6-STATEFUL-ISSUES"></xref>.</t>

            <t>By default, an IPv6 CE router MUST NOT initiate any dynamic
            routing protocol on its WAN interface.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD support the <xref
            target="RFC6603"></xref> Prefix Exclude option.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="LAN-Side Configuration">
        <t>The IPv6 CE router distributes configuration information obtained
        during WAN interface provisioning to IPv6 hosts and assists IPv6 hosts
        in obtaining IPv6 addresses. It also supports connectivity of these
        devices in the absence of any working WAN interface.</t>

        <t>An IPv6 CE router is expected to support an IPv6 end-user network
        and IPv6 hosts that exhibit the following characteristics:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Link-local addresses may be insufficient for allowing IPv6
            applications to communicate with each other in the end-user
            network. The IPv6 CE router will need to enable this communication
            by providing globally scoped unicast addresses or ULAs <xref
            target="RFC4193"></xref>, whether or not WAN connectivity
            exists.</t>

            <t>IPv6 hosts should be capable of using SLAAC and may be capable
            of using DHCPv6 for acquiring their addresses.</t>

            <t>IPv6 hosts may use DHCPv6 for other configuration information,
            such as the DNS_SERVERS option for acquiring DNS information.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Unless otherwise specified, the following requirements apply to the
        IPv6 CE router's LAN interfaces only.</t>

        <t>ULA requirements:<list style="format ULA-%d:">
            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD be capable of generating a ULA prefix
            <xref target="RFC4193"></xref>.</t>

            <t>An IPv6 CE router with a ULA prefix MUST maintain this prefix
            consistently across reboots.</t>

            <t>The value of the ULA prefix SHOULD be configurable.</t>

            <t>By default, the IPv6 CE router MUST act as a site border router
            according to Section 4.3 of <xref target="RFC4193"></xref> and
            filter packets with local IPv6 source or destination addresses
            accordingly.</t>

            <t>An IPv6 CE router MUST NOT advertise itself as a default router
            with a Router Lifetime greater than zero whenever all of its
            configured and delegated prefixes are ULA prefixes.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>LAN requirements:<list style="format L-%d:">
            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support router behavior according to
            Neighbor Discovery for IPv6 <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST assign a separate /64 from its
            delegated prefix(es) (and ULA prefix if configured to provide ULA
            addressing) for each of its LAN interfaces.</t>

            <t>An IPv6 CE router MUST advertise itself as a router for the
            delegated prefix(es) (and ULA prefix if configured to provide ULA
            addressing) using the "Route Information Option" specified in
            Section 2.3 of <xref target="RFC4191"></xref>. This advertisement
            is independent of having or not having IPv6 connectivity on the
            WAN interface.</t>

            <t>An IPv6 CE router MUST NOT advertise itself as a default router
            with a Router Lifetime <xref target="RFC4861"></xref> greater than
            zero if it has no prefixes configured or delegated to it.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST make each LAN interface an advertising
            interface according to <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>

            <t>In Router Advertisement messages (<xref target="RFC4861"></xref>), the Prefix Information
            option's A and L flags MUST be set to 1 by default.</t>

            <t>The A and L flags' (<xref target="RFC4861"></xref>) settings SHOULD be user configurable.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support a DHCPv6 server capable of IPv6
            address assignment according to <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> OR
            a stateless DHCPv6 server according to <xref
            target="RFC3736"></xref> on its LAN interfaces.</t>

            <t>Unless the IPv6 CE router is configured to support the DHCPv6
            IA_NA option, it SHOULD set the M flag to zero and the O flag to 1 in
            its Router Advertisement messages <xref
            target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support providing DNS information in
            the DHCPv6 DNS_SERVERS and DOMAIN_LIST options <xref
            target="RFC3646"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support providing DNS information in
            the Router Advertisement Recursive DNS Server (RDNSS)
            and DNS Search List options. Both options are specified 
            in <xref target="RFC6106"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD make available a subset of DHCPv6
            options (as listed in Section 5.3 of <xref
            target="RFC3736"></xref>) received from the DHCPv6 client on its
            WAN interface to its LAN-side DHCPv6 server.</t>

            <t>If the delegated prefix changes, i.e., the current prefix is
            replaced with a new prefix without any overlapping time period,
            then the IPv6 CE router MUST immediately advertise the old prefix
            with a Preferred Lifetime of zero and a Valid Lifetime of either
            a) zero or b) the lower of the current Valid Lifetime and two
            hours (which must be decremented in real time) in a Router
            Advertisement message as described in Section 5.5.3, (e) of <xref
            target="RFC4862"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST send an ICMPv6 Destination Unreachable
            message, code 5 (Source address failed ingress/egress policy) for
            packets forwarded to it that use an address from a prefix that has
            been invalidated.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transition Technologies Support">

        <section title="6rd">
          <t>6rd <xref target="RFC5969"></xref> specifies an automatic
          tunneling mechanism tailored to advance deployment of IPv6 to end users
          via a service provider's IPv4 network infrastructure. Key
          aspects include automatic IPv6 prefix delegation to sites, stateless
          operation, simple provisioning, and service that is equivalent to
          native IPv6 at the sites that are served by the mechanism. It is
          expected that such traffic is forwarded over the CE router's native
          IPv4 WAN interface and not encapsulated in another tunnel.</t>

          <t>The CE router SHOULD support 6rd functionality. If 6rd is
          supported, it MUST be implemented according to <xref
          target="RFC5969"> </xref>. The following CE Requirements also
          apply:</t>

          <t>6rd requirements: <list style="format 6RD-%d:">
              <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST support 6rd configuration via the 6rd
              DHCPv4 Option 212. If the CE router has obtained an IPv4
              network address through some other means such as PPP, it SHOULD
              use the DHCPINFORM request message <xref
              target="RFC2131"></xref> to request the 6rd DHCPv4 Option. The
              IPv6 CE router MAY use other mechanisms to configure 6rd
              parameters. Such mechanisms are outside the scope of this
              document.</t>

              <t>If the IPv6 CE router is capable of automated configuration
              of IPv4 through IPCP (i.e., over a PPP connection), it MUST
              support user-entered configuration of 6rd.</t>

              <t>If the CE router supports configuration
mechanisms other than the 6rd DHCPv4 Option 212 (user-entered,
TR-069 <xref target="TR-069" />, etc.), the CE router MUST support 6rd in "hub and spoke"
mode. 6rd in "hub and
              spoke" requires all IPv6 traffic to go to the 6rd Border Relay.
              In effect, this requirement removes the "direct connect to 6rd"
              route defined in Section 7.1.1 of <xref
              target="RFC5969"></xref>.</t>

              <t>A CE router MUST allow 6rd and native IPv6 WAN interfaces 
                 to be active alone as well as simultaneously in order to support 
                 coexistence of the two technologies during an incremental migration 
                 period such as a migration from 6rd to native IPv6.
              </t>

              <t>Each packet sent on a 6rd or native WAN interface MUST be directed 
                 such that its source IP address is derived from the delegated prefix 
                 associated with the particular interface from which the packet 
                 is being sent (Section 4.3 of <xref target="RFC3704"></xref>).</t>
              
              <t>The CE router MUST allow different as well as identical delegated prefixes 
                 to be configured via each (6rd or native) WAN interface.
              </t>

              <t>In the event that forwarding rules produce a tie between 6rd and 
                 native IPv6, by default, the IPv6 CE router MUST prefer native IPv6.
              </t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite)">
          <t>Dual-Stack Lite <xref target="RFC6333"></xref> enables both
          continued support for IPv4 services and incentives for the
          deployment of IPv6. It also de&nbhy;couples IPv6 deployment in the
          service provider network from the rest of the Internet, making
          incremental deployment easier. Dual-Stack Lite enables a broadband
          service provider to share IPv4 addresses among customers by
          combining two well-known technologies: IP in IP (IPv4-in-IPv6) and
          Network Address Translation (NAT). It is expected that DS-Lite
          traffic is forwarded over the CE router's native IPv6 WAN interface,
          and not encapsulated in another tunnel.</t>

          <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD implement DS-Lite functionality. If
          DS&nbhy;Lite is supported, it MUST be implemented according to <xref
          target="RFC6333"></xref>. This document takes no position on
          simultaneous operation of Dual-Stack Lite and native IPv4. The
          following CE router requirements also apply:</t>

          <t>WAN requirements: <list style="format DLW-%d:">
              <t>The CE router MUST support configuration of DS-Lite via the 
                 DS-Lite DHCPv6 option <xref target="RFC6334"></xref>. 
                 The IPv6 CE router MAY use other mechanisms to configure 
                 DS-Lite parameters. Such mechanisms are outside the scope 
                 of this document.</t>

              <t>The IPv6 CE router MUST NOT perform IPv4 Network Address
              Translation (NAT) on IPv4 traffic encapsulated using
              DS-Lite.</t>

              <t>If the IPv6 CE router is configured with an IPv4 address on
              its WAN interface, then the IPv6 CE router SHOULD disable the
              DS-Lite Basic Bridging BroadBand (B4) element.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>It is considered a best practice to filter obviously malicious
        traffic (e.g., spoofed packets, "Martian" addresses, etc.). Thus, the
        IPv6 CE router ought to support basic stateless egress and ingress
        filters. The CE router is also expected to offer mechanisms to filter
        traffic entering the customer network; however, the method by which
        vendors implement configurable packet filtering is beyond the scope of
        this document.</t>

        <t>Security requirements:<list style="format S-%d:">
            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD support <xref
            target="RFC6092"></xref>. In particular, the IPv6 CE router SHOULD
            support functionality sufficient for implementing the set of
            recommendations in <xref target="RFC6092"></xref>, Section&nbsp;4.
            This document takes no position on whether such functionality is
            enabled by default or mechanisms by which users would configure
            it.</t>

            <t>The IPv6 CE router SHOULD support ingress filtering in
            accordance with BCP 38 <xref target="RFC2827"></xref>.  Note that
            this requirement was downgraded from a MUST from RFC 6204 due
            to the difficulty of implementation in the CE router and the feature's 
            redundancy with upstream router ingress filtering.</t>

            <t>If the IPv6 CE router firewall is configured to filter incoming
            tunneled data, the firewall SHOULD provide the capability to
            filter decapsulated packets from a tunnel.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to the following people (in alphabetical order) for their
      guidance and feedback:</t>

      <t>Mikael Abrahamsson, Tore Anderson, Merete Asak, Rajiv Asati, Scott
      Beuker, Mohamed Boucadair, Rex Bullinger, Brian Carpenter, Tassos
      Chatzithomaoglou, Lorenzo Colitti, Remi Denis-Courmont, Gert Doering,
      Alain Durand, Katsunori Fukuoka, Brian Haberman, Tony Hain, Thomas Herbst, 
      Ray Hunter, Joel Jaeggli, Kevin Johns, Erik Kline, Stephen Kramer, Victor Kuarsingh,
      Francois-Xavier Le Bail, Arifumi Matsumoto, David Miles, Shin Miyakawa,
      Jean-Francois Mule, Michael Newbery, Carlos Pignataro, John Pomeroy,
      Antonio Querubin, Daniel Roesen, Hiroki Sato, Teemu Savolainen, Matt
      Schmitt, David Thaler, Mark Townsley, Sean Turner, Bernie Volz, Dan Wing, 
      Timothy Winters, James Woodyatt, Carl Wuyts, and Cor Zwart.</t>

      <t>This document is based in part on CableLabs' eRouter specification.
      The authors wish to acknowledge the additional contributors from the
      eRouter team:</t>

      <t>Ben Bekele, Amol Bhagwat, Ralph Brown, Eduardo Cardona, Margo Dolas,
      Toerless Eckert, Doc Evans, Roger Fish, Michelle Kuska, Diego Mazzola,
      John McQueen, Harsh Parandekar, Michael Patrick, Saifur Rahman, Lakshmi
      Raman, Ryan Ross, Ron da Silva, Madhu Sudan, Dan Torbet, and Greg
      White.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors">
      <t>The following people have participated as co-authors or provided
      substantial contributions to this document: Ralph Droms, Kirk Erichsen,
      Fred Baker, Jason Weil, Lee Howard, Jean-Francois Tremblay, Yiu Lee,
      John Jason Brzozowski, and Heather Kirksey. Thanks to Ole Troan for
      editorship in the original RFC 6204 document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
  
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1122;

      &RFC2119;

      &RFC2131;

      &RFC2464;

      &RFC2827;

      &RFC3315;

      &RFC3633;

      &RFC3646;


      &RFC3704;

      &RFC3736;

      &RFC5905;

      &RFC5908;

      &RFC4191;

      &RFC4193;

      &RFC4242;

      &RFC4443;

      &RFC4605;

      &RFC4632;

      &RFC4779;

      &RFC4861;

      &RFC4862;

      &RFC5072;

      &RFC5942;

      &RFC5969;

      &RFC6177;

      &RFC6092;

      &RFC6106;

      &RFC6333;

      &RFC6334;

      &RFC6434;

      &RFC6603;

      &RFC6887;


<!-- I-D.droms-dhc-dhcpv6-solmaxrt-update.xml, Companion Document-->
<reference anchor='RFC7083'>
<front>
<title>Modification to Default Value of SOL_MAX_RT</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Droms' fullname='Ralph Droms'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2013' />

<abstract><t>This document updates RFC 3315 by redefining the default value for SOL_MAX_RT and defining an option through which a DHCPv6 server can override the client's default value for SOL_MAX_RT with a new value.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7083' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">


<reference anchor='TR-069' target="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/trlist.php">
<front>
<title>CPE WAN Management Protocol</title>

<author initials='' surname='' fullname=''>
    <organization> Broadband Forum</organization>
</author>

<date month='July' year='2011' />


</front>

<seriesInfo name='TR-069 Amendment' value='4' />
</reference>





       
     &RFC6144;

<!--ietf-dhc-dhcpv6-stateful-issues-00, Active -->
<reference anchor='DHCPV6-STATEFUL-ISSUES'>
<front>
<title>Issues with multiple stateful DHCPv6 options</title>

<author initials='O' surname='Troan' fullname='Ole Troan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Volz' fullname='Bernie Volz'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' year='2013' />

<abstract><t>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6) was not written with the expectation that additional stateful DHCPv6 options would be developed.  IPv6 Prefix Options for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) version 6 shoe-horned the new options for Prefix Delegation into DHCPv6.  Implementation experience of the CPE model described in [RFC6204] has shown multiple issues with the DHCPv6 protocol in supporting multiple stateful options.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in' value='Progress' />
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-v6ops-multihoming-without-nat66-00.txt, Expired -->
      <reference anchor="MULTIHOMING-WITHOUT-NAT">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Multihoming without Network Address Translation</title>

          <author fullname="Ole Troan" initials="O" role="editor"
                  surname="Troan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="David Miles" initials="D" surname="Miles">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Satoru Matsushima" initials="S"
                  surname="Matsushima">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Tadahisa Okimoto" initials="T" surname="Okimoto">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D" surname="Wing">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />


      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UPnP-IGD" target="http://upnp.org/specs/gw/igd2/">
        <front>
          <title>InternetGatewayDevice:2 Device Template Version 1.01</title>

          <author fullname="UPnP Forum" surname="UPnP Forum">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
  </back>
</rfc>
