<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2328 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.2328.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5015 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.5015.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6513 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.6513.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6514 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.6514.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7582 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.7582.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6388 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.6388.xml'>
]>


<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="7740" ipr="trust200902" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

<front>
    <title abbrev='C-BIDIR Support with IR'>
    Simulating Partial Mesh of Multipoint-to-Multipoint (MP2MP) Provider Tunnels with Ingress Replication
    </title>

    <author initials="Z." surname="Zhang" fullname="Zhaohui Zhang">
	<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street>10 Technology Park Dr.</street>
		<city>Westford</city>
		<region>MA</region>
		<code>01886</code>
		<country>United States</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>zzhang@juniper.net</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter" fullname="Yakov Rekhter">
	<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
    </author>

    <author initials="A." surname="Dolganow" fullname="Andrew Dolganow">
	<organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street>600 March Rd.</street>
		<city>Ottawa</city>
		<region>ON</region>
		<code>K2K 2E6</code>
		<country>Canada</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>andrew.dolganow@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2016"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <keyword>MVPN</keyword>
    <keyword>P-tunnel</keyword>
    <keyword>Ingress Replication</keyword>
    <keyword>Bidirectional C-flow</keyword>

    <abstract>
	<t>
    RFC 6513 ("Multicast in MPLS/BGP IP VPNs") describes a method to support
    bidirectional customer multicast flows using a partial mesh of
    Multipoint-to-Multipoint (MP2MP) tunnels.  This document specifies how
    a partial mesh of MP2MP tunnels can be simulated using Ingress
    Replication.  This solution enables a service provider to use Ingress
    Replication to offer transparent bidirectional multicast service to its
    VPN customers.
	</t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction" anchor='intro'>
    <t>
    Section 11.2 of RFC 6513 ("Partitioned Sets of PEs") describes two methods
    of carrying Bidirectional PIM (BIDIR-PIM) <xref target="RFC5015"/> C-flow traffic over a
    provider core without using the core as the Rendezvous Point Link (RPL) or
    requiring Designated Forwarder election.
	</t>

	<t>
    With these two methods, all Provider Edges (PEs) of a particular VPN are separated into
    partitions, with each partition being all the PEs that elect the same
    PE as the Upstream PE with respect to the C-RPA (the Rendezvous Point
    Address in the customer's address space). A PE must discard
    bidirectional C-flow
    traffic from PEs that are not in the same partition as the PE itself.
	</t>
	<t>
    In particular, Section 11.2.3 of RFC 6513
    ("Partial Mesh of MP2MP P-Tunnels") guarantees the above discard behavior
    without using an extra PE Distinguisher Label
    by having all PEs in the same partition join a single MP2MP tunnel
    dedicated to that partition and use it to transmit traffic.
    All traffic arriving on the tunnel
    will be from PEs in the same partition, so it will be always accepted.
	</t>
	<t>
    RFC 6514 specifies BGP encodings and procedures used to implement
    Multicast VPN (MVPN)
    as specified in RFC 6513, while the details related to MP2MP tunnels
    are specified in <xref target="RFC7582"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
    RFC 7582 assumes that an MP2MP P-tunnel
    is realized either via BIDIR-PIM <xref target="RFC5015"/>
    or via MP2MP mLDP (Multipoint extensions for LDP) <xref target="RFC6388"/>. Each 
    would require signaling and state not just on PEs, but on the
    P routers as well. This document describes how the MP2MP tunnel can be
    simulated with a mesh of P2MP tunnels, each of which is instantiated by
    Ingress Replication (IR) <xref target="RFC6513"/> <xref target="RFC6514"/>.
    The procedures in this document are different from the procedures
    that are used to set up the mesh of Ingress Replication
    tunnels as described in RFC 6514; the procedures in this document
    do not require each PE on the MP2MP tunnel to
    send a Selective P-Multicast Service Interface (S-PMSI) auto-discovery
    route (A-D route) for the
    P2MP tunnel that the PE is the root
    for, nor do they require each PE to send a Leaf A-D route to the root
    of each P2MP tunnel in the mesh.
    </t>

<!--     <t>
    This document assumes that segmented provider tunnels are not used.
    Use of segmented provider tunnels is for further study and out of the
    scope of this document.
	</t>
-->
	<t>
    Because it uses Ingress Replication, this scheme has both the advantages
    and the disadvantages of Ingress Replication in general.
	</t>
<section title="Terminology">
    <t>
    This document uses terminology from <xref target="RFC5015"/>,
    <xref target="RFC6513"/>,
    <xref target="RFC6514"/>, and <xref target="RFC7582"/>.
    </t>
</section>


<section title="Requirements Language">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section title="Operation">
    <t>
In the following sections, the originator of an S-PMSI A-D route or Leaf A-D
route is determined from the "originating router's IP address" field
of the corresponding route.
    </t>

<section title="Control State">
    <t>
If a PE, say PEx, is connected to a site of a given VPN and PEx's next-hop
interface to some C-RPA is a VPN Routing
   and Forwarding (VRF) interface,
then PEx MUST advertise a (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route, regardless of
whether it has any local BIDIR-PIM join states corresponding to the C-RPA
learned from its Customer Edges (CEs). It MAY also advertise one or more (C-*,C-G-BIDIR)
S-PMSI A-D routes, if selective distribution trees are needed for those
C-G-BIDIR groups and the corresponding C-RPA is in the site that the PEx connects to.
For example, the (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D routes could be triggered when the
(C-*,C-G-BIDIR) traffic rate goes above a threshold (this may require
measuring the traffic in both directions, due to the nature of BIDIR-PIM),
and fan-out could also be taken into account.
    </t>
    <t>
The S-PMSI A-D routes include a PMSI Tunnel Attribute (PTA) with tunnel type
set to Ingress Replication, with the Leaf Information Required flag set, with a
downstream allocated MPLS label that other PEs in the same partition MUST use
when sending relevant C-BIDIR flows to this PE,
and with the Tunnel Identifier field in the PTA set to a routable
address of the originator.
This specification does not prevent sharing of labels between P-tunnels,
such as a label being shared by a (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) and a (C-*,C-G-BIDIR)
S-PMSI A-D route originated by a given PE (note that other specifications put
constraints on how that can be done, e.g., <xref target="MVPN-EXTRANET"/>).
	</t>
    <t>
If some other PE, PEy, receives and imports into one of its VRFs any
(C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route whose PTA specifies an IR P-tunnel and the
VRF has any local BIDIR-PIM join state that PEy has received from its CEs
and if PEy chooses PEx as its Upstream PE with respect to the C-RPA for those states,
PEy MUST advertise a Leaf A-D route in response. Or, if PEy has received and
imported into one of its VRFs a
(C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route from PEx before, then upon receiving in the VRF
any local
BIDIR-PIM join state from its CEs with PEx being the Upstream PE for those states'
C-RPA, PEy MUST advertise a Leaf A-D route.
	</t>
    <t>
The encoding of the Leaf A-D route is as specified in RFC 6514, except that
the Route Targets are set to the same value as in the corresponding S-PMSI
A-D route so that the Leaf A-D route will be imported by all VRFs that import
the corresponding S-PMSI A-D route.
This is irrespective of whether or not the originator of the S-PMSI A-D route is the
Upstream PE from a receiving PE's perspective.
The label in the PTA of the Leaf A-D route originated by PEy MUST be allocated
specifically for PEx, so that when traffic arrives with that label,
the traffic can associate with the partition (represented
by the PEx).
This specification does not prevent sharing of labels between P-tunnels,
such as a label being shared by a (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) and a (C-*,C-G-BIDIR)
Leaf A-D route originated by a given PE (note that other specifications put
constraints on how that can be done, e.g., <xref target="MVPN-EXTRANET"/>).
	</t>
    <t>
Note that RFC 6514 requires that a PE or an ASBR (Autonomous System Border Router) take
no action with regard to a
Leaf A-D route unless that Leaf A-D route carries an IP-address-specific Route Target
identifying the PE/ASBR.  This document removes that requirement
when the route key of a Leaf A-D route identifies a (C-*,C-*-BIDIR)
or a (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI.
	</t>
    <t>
To speed up convergence (so that PEy starts receiving traffic
from its new Upstream PE immediately instead of waiting until the new
Leaf A-D route corresponding to the new Upstream PE is received by sending PEs),
PEy MAY advertise a Leaf A-D
route even if it does not choose PEx as its Upstream PE with respect to the C-RPA. With that,
it will receive traffic from all PEs, but some will arrive with the label
corresponding to its choice of Upstream PE while some will arrive with a different
label; the traffic in the latter case will be discarded.
    </t>
    <t>
Similar to the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) case, if PEy receives and imports into one of
its VRFs any (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route whose PTA specifies an IR
P-tunnel, PEy chooses PEx as its Upstream PE with respect to the C-RPA, and it has
corresponding local (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) join state that it has received from its
CEs in the VRF, PEy MUST
advertise a Leaf A-D route in response. Or, if PEy has received and imported
into one of its VRFs a
(C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route before, then upon receiving its local
(C-*,C-G-BIDIR) join state from its CEs in the VRF, it MUST advertise a Leaf
A-D route.
	</t>
    <t>
The encoding of the Leaf A-D route is similar to the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) case.
Similarly, PEy MAY advertise a Leaf A-D route even if it does not choose PEx
as its Upstream PE with respect to the C-RPA.
    </t>
    <t>
PEy MUST withdraw the corresponding Leaf A-D route if any of the following
conditions are true:
<list style="symbols">
<t>the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) or (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route is withdrawn.</t>
<t>PEy no longer chooses the originator PEx as its Upstream PE with
      respect to C-RPA and PEy only advertises Leaf A-D routes in
      response to its Upstream PE's S-PMSI A-D route.</t>
<t>if relevant local join state is pruned.</t>
</list> 
    </t>
</section>
<section title="Forwarding State">

<t>
   The specification regarding forwarding state in this section matches the
   "When an S-PMSI is a 'Match for Transmission'" and "When an S-PMSI is
   a 'Match for Reception'" rules for the "Flat Partitioning" method in
   <xref target="RFC7582"/>, except that the rules about (C-*,C-*) are not applicable,
   because this document requires that (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D routes
   are always originated for a VPN that supports C-BIDIR flows.
    </t>

<t>
   For the (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route that a PEy receives and
   imports into one of its VRFs from its Upstream PE with respect to the
   C-RPA, if PEy itself advertises the S-PMSI A-D route in the VRF,
   PEy maintains a (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) forwarding state in the VRF, with the
   Ingress Replication provider tunnel leaves being the originators of
   the S-PMSI A-D route and all relevant Leaf A-D routes. 
The relevant Leaf A-D routes are the routes whose Route Key field contains the
same information as the MCAST-VPN Network Layer Reachability Information
(NLRI) of the (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route advertised by the Upstream PE.   
</t>

<t>
   For the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route that a PEy receives and
   imports into one of its VRFs from its Upstream PE with respect to a
   C-RPA, if PEy itself advertises the S-PMSI A-D route in the VRF,
   it maintains appropriate forwarding states in the VRF for the ranges
   of bidirectional groups for which the C-RPA is responsible. 
The provider tunnel
leaves are the originators of the S-PMSI A-D route and all
relevant Leaf A-D routes. The relevant Leaf A-D routes are the routes whose
Route Key field contains the same information as the MCAST-VPN NLRI of the
(C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route advertised by the Upstream PE. This is for the so-called "Sender Only
Branches" where a router only has data to send upstream towards C-RPA but no
explicit join state for a particular bidirectional group. Note that the traffic
must be sent to all PEs (not just the Upstream PE) in the partition, because they may
have specific (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) join states that this PEy is not aware of,
while there are no corresponding (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D and Leaf A-D routes.
    </t>

    <t>
For a (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) join state that a PEy has received from its CEs in a VRF,
if there is no corresponding (C-*,C-G-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route from its Upstream PE in
the VRF, PEy maintains a corresponding forwarding state in the VRF,
with the provider tunnel leaves
being the originators of the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route and all relevant
Leaf A-D routes (same as the "Sender Only Branches" case above).  The relevant
Leaf A-D routes are the routes whose Route Key field contains the
same information as the MCAST-VPN NLRI of the (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI
A-D route originated by the Upstream PE. If there is also no (C-*,C-*-BIDIR) S-PMSI A-D route
from its Upstream PE, then the provider tunnel has an empty set of leaves, and
PEy does not forward relevant traffic across the provider network.
    </t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor='sec-security'>

    <t>
    This document raises no new security issues. Security
    considerations for the base protocol are covered in
    <xref target="RFC6513"/> and <xref target="RFC6514"/>.
    </t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title='Normative References'>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6513'?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6514'?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7582'?>
</references>

<references title='Informative References'>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5015'?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6388'?>

<!-- draft-ietf-bess-mvpn-extranet IESG EVAL -->

<reference anchor='MVPN-EXTRANET'>
<front>
<title>Extranet Multicast in BGP/IP MPLS VPNs</title>

<author initials='Y' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Yakov Rekhter' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E' surname='Rosen' fullname='Eric Rosen' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Aggarwal' fullname='Rahul Aggarwal'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Cai' fullname='Yiqun Cai'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='T' surname='Morin' fullname='Thomas Morin'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2015' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-bess-mvpn-extranet-05' />

</reference>


</references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor='sec-ack' numbered="no">
    <t>We would like to thank Eric Rosen for his comments and suggestions for
    some text used in the document.
    </t>
</section>


</back>

</rfc>
