<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>


<rfc number="7389"
     category="std" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902"> 
     
<front>


<title abbrev="PMIPv6 CP-UP Split">
Separation of Control and User Plane for Proxy Mobile IPv6
</title>


<author initials="R." surname="Wakikawa" fullname="Ryuji Wakikawa">
<organization>Softbank Mobile</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1-9-1, Higashi-Shimbashi, Minato-Ku</street>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<code>105-7322</code>
<country>Japan</country>

</postal>
<email>ryuji.wakikawa@gmail.com</email>
</address>
</author>
        

<author fullname="Rajesh S. Pazhyannur" initials="R.P" surname="Pazhyannur">
<organization>Cisco</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134</code>
<country>United States</country>
</postal>
<email>rpazhyan@cisco.com</email>
</address>
</author>


<author initials="S" surname="Gundavelli" fullname="Sri Gundavelli">
<organization abbrev="">Cisco</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<city>San Jose</city> 
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134</code>
<country>United States</country>
</postal>
<email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>
</address>
</author>


<author fullname="Charles E. Perkins" initials="C.P" surname="Perkins">
<organization>Futurewei Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
<city>Santa Clara</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95050</code>
<country>United States</country>
</postal>
<email>charliep@computer.org</email>
</address>
</author>


<date month="October" year="2014" />
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>NETEXT WG</workgroup>

<keyword>Control and User Plane Split</keyword>
<keyword>Control and User Plane Separation</keyword>
<keyword>LMA User-Plane Address Mobility Option</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>
        This document specifies a method to split the control plane (CP) and
	user plane (UP) for a network                                 
        infrastructure based on Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6).
        Existing specifications allow a mobile access
	gateway (MAG) to separate its control and user
	plane using the Alternate Care-of Address mobility option for
	IPv6 or Alternate IPv4 Care-of Address option for
	IPv4. However, the current specification does not
	provide any mechanism allowing the local mobility anchor (LMA) to
	perform an analogous functional split. To remedy that shortcoming,
	this document specifies a mobility option enabling an
	LMA to provide an alternate LMA address to
	be used for the bidirectional user-plane traffic between the
	MAG and LMA. With this new option, an LMA will be able to use an
	IP address for its user plane that is different than the IP
	address used for the control plane.
</t>
   
   
</abstract>

</front>


<middle>

<section anchor="sec:introduction"  title="Introduction">
<t>
	A Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) infrastructure comprises two primary entities: LMA
	(local mobility anchor) and MAG (mobile access gateway).
	The interface between the MAG and LMA consists of the control plane
	and user plane. The control plane is responsible for signaling
	messages between the MAG and LMA, such as the Proxy Binding Update (PBU)
	and Proxy Binding Acknowledgement (PBA) messages to
	establish a mobility binding. In addition, the control-plane components
	in the MAG and LMA  are also responsible
	for setting up and tearing down a bidirectional tunnel between
	the MAG and LMA.  The user plane is used
	for carrying the mobile node's IP traffic between the MAG and the
	LMA over the bidirectional tunnel. 
</t>	

<t>
    Widely deployed mobility management systems for wireless
	communications require separation of IP transport for forwarding user-plane
    and control-plane traffic.  This separation offers more flexible deployment options
    for LMA and MAG entities in Proxy Mobile IPv6, as described
	in <xref target="MOBILE-SEPARATION"/>.
	To meet this requirement would also require that the
	control-plane functions of the LMA
	be addressable at a different IP address than
	the IP address assigned for the user plane. However, PMIPv6
	does not currently specify a mechanism for allowing the LMA to
	separate the control plane from the user plane. The LMA is currently
	required to associate the IP address of the tunnel source with the
	target IP address for the control messages received from the MAG. 
</t>


      
<t> 
	The control-plane and user-plane components of a MAG or LMA are
	typically co-located in the same
	physical entity.  However, there are situations where it is desirable
	to have the control and user plane of
	a MAG or LMA in separate physical entities. For example, in a WLAN
	(Wireless LAN) network, it may be desirable to have the
	control-plane component of the MAG reside on the Access Controller (also
	sometimes referred to as Wireless LAN Controller (WLC))
	while the user-plane component of the MAG resides on the WLAN
	Access Point.  This enables all the control-plane messages to
	the LMA to be centralized while the user plane would be distributed
	across the multiple Access Points. Similarly, there is a need for
	either the control-plane or user-plane component of the LMA to be
	separated according to different scaling requirements or, in other
	cases, the need to centralize the control plane in one geographical location 
    while distributing the user-plane
	component across multiple locations.
	For example, as illustrated in <xref target="fig1"/>,
	the LMA and MAG could have one control session established
	for PMIPv6 control signaling while maintaining separate connectivity
	via Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) or IP-in-IP tunneling for forwarding user-plane traffic.
</t>
<figure anchor="fig1"
	title="Functional Separation of the Control and User Plane">
<artwork>  <![CDATA[
                  MAG                    LMA    
              +--------+              +--------+ 
+------+      | MAG-CP |--------------| LMA-CP |        _----_      
|  MN  |      |        |    PMIPv6    |        |      _(      )_   
|      |----  +--------+              +--------+  ===( Internet )
+------+          :                       :           (_      _)   
              +--------+              +--------+        '----'
              | MAG-UP |--------------| LMA-UP |   
              |        | GRE/IP-in-IP |        |    
              +--------+    /UDP      +--------+ 

MN: Mobile Node
CP: Control Plane
UP: User Plane      ]]> 
</artwork>
</figure>
      
<t>
	<xref target="RFC6463"/> and <xref target ="RFC6275"/>
	enable separating the control and user plane in the MAG. In particular,
	<xref target="RFC6463"/> defines the Alternate IPv4 Care-of
	Address option, and  <xref target ="RFC6275"/> defines an Alternate
	Care-of Address option for IPv6. The MAG may provide an Alternate
	Care-of Address in the PBU, and if the
	LMA supports this option, then a bidirectional tunnel is set up 
	between the LMA address and the MAG's Alternate Care-of Address.
	However, these documents do not specify a corresponding option for
	the LMA to provide an alternate tunnel endpoint address to the MAG. 
</t>
      
<t>
	This specification therefore defines a new mobility option
	that enables a local mobility anchor to provide an alternate
	LMA address to be used for the bidirectional tunnel between
	the MAG and LMA, as shown in <xref target="fig1"/>.
</t>

<t>
The LMA control-plane and the LMA user-plane functions are typically deployed on the same IP 
node, and in such a scenario, the interface between these functions is internal to the implementation.
Deployments may also choose to deploy the LMA control-plane and the LMA user-plane functions on 
separate IP nodes. In such deployment models, there needs to be a protocol interface between these
two functions, but that is outside the scope of this document. Possible options
for such an interface 
include OpenFlow <xref target="OpenFlow-Spec-v1.4.0"/>,
Forwarding and Control Element Separation (ForCES) <xref target="RFC5810"/>, use of routing infrastructure <xref target="STATELESS-UPLANE"/>, 
and vendor-specific approaches. This specification does not mandate a specific protocol interface and
views this interface as a generic interface relevant more broadly for
many other protocol systems in addition to Proxy Mobile IPv6.
When the LMA control-plane and the LMA user-plane functions are deployed
on separate IP nodes, the requirement related to user-plane address
anchoring (specified in Section 5.6.2 of <xref target="RFC5213"/> and Section 3.1.3 of <xref target="RFC5844"/>) must 
be met by the node hosting the LMA user-plane functionality. The
LMA user-plane node must be a topological anchor point for the IP
address/prefixes allocated to the mobile node. 
</t>


</section>

<section anchor="sec:conv_and_term" title="Conventions and Terminology">

<section anchor="sec:conventions" title="Conventions">
<t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in
	RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec:terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>
	3GPP terms can be found in <xref target="RFC6459"/>.
	Other mobility-related terms used in this document are to be interpreted
	as defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/> and <xref target="RFC5844"/>.
	Additionally, this document uses the following terms:
</t>
<t>
	IP-in-IP
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
		IP-within-IP Encapsulation <xref target="RFC2473"/> <xref target="RFC4213"/>.
</t> </list> </t>

<t>
	GRE
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
		Generic Routing Encapsulation <xref target="RFC1701"/>.
</t> </list> </t>


<t>
	UDP Encapsulation
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
		Encapsulation mode based on UDP transport specified in  <xref target="RFC5844"/>.
</t> </list> </t>


<t>
	LMA Control-Plane Address (LMA-CPA)
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
		The IP address on the LMA that is used for sending and
		receiving control-plane traffic from the MAG.
        
</t> </list> </t>

<t>
	LMA User-Plane Address (LMA-UPA)
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
		The IP address on the LMA that is used for sending and
		receiving user-plane traffic from the MAG.
</t> </list> </t>

<t>
	MAG Control-Plane Address (MAG-CPA)
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
        The IP address on the MAG that is used for sending and receiving 
	control-plane traffic from the LMA.
</t> </list> </t>

<t>
	MAG User-Plane Address (MAG-UPA)
	<list style="hanging"> <t>
        The IP address on the MAG that is used for sending and receiving 
	user-plane traffic from the LMA. This address is also referred 
	to as the Alternate Care-of Address. 
</t> </list> </t>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec:conceptual"
	title="Additional Fields in Conceptual Data Structures">

<t>
	To support the capability specified in this document, the conceptual
	Binding Update List entry data structure maintained by the LMA and the
	MAG is extended with the following additional fields:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>The IP address of the LMA that carries user-plane traffic.</t>
	<t>The IP address of the LMA that handles control-plane traffic.</t>
	</list>
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="sec:dmnp_format"
	title="LMA User-Plane Address Mobility Option">
<t>    
   The LMA User-Plane Address mobility option is a new mobility header
   option defined for use with PBU and PBA messages exchanged between
   the LMA and the MAG.  This option is used for notifying the MAG about
   the LMA's user-plane IPv6 or IPv4 address. There can be zero, one, or
   two instances of the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option present in
   the message. When two instances of the option are present, one instance
   of the option must be for IPv4 transport, and the other instance must be
   for IPv6 transport.
</t>

<t>
	The LMA User-Plane Address mobility option has an alignment
	requirement of 8n+2.  Its format is as shown in <xref target="fig2"/>:
</t>

<figure anchor="fig2"  title="LMA User-Plane Address Mobility Option Format">
<artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |   Length      |           Reserved            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                                                               +
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
+                     LMA User-Plane Address                    +
|                                                               |
+                                                               +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>


<t>
	Type
<list>
<t>
        59
</t>
</list>

</t>
<t>
	Length
<list>
<t>
	An 8-bit, unsigned integer indicating the length of the option in octets,
	excluding the Type and Length fields. 
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
	Reserved
<list>
<t>
	This field is unused in this specification. The value MUST be set
	to zero (0) by the sender and MUST be ignored by the receiver.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
	LMA User-Plane Address
<list>
<t>
	Contains the 32-bit IPv4 address or the 128-bit IPv6 address of the
	LMA user plane. When the LMA User-Plane Address mobility
	option is included in a PBU message, this
	field can be a zero-length field, or it can have a value of
	ALL_ZERO, with all bits in the 32-bit IPv4 address or the 128-bit
	IPv6 address set to zero.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
	When including the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option
	in the PBU, the MAG must apply the following rules:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>         
    When using IPv4 transport for the user plane, the IP address field
    in the option MUST be either a zero-length field or a 4-octet
    field with ALL_ZERO value.
	</t>
	<t>         
    When using IPv6 transport for the user plane, the IP address field
    in the option MUST be either a zero-length field or a 16-octet
    field with ALL_ZERO value.
	</t>
	</list>
</t>

	<t>
	When the LMA includes the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in
	the PBA, the IP address field in the option MUST
	be set to the LMA's IPv4 or IPv6 address carrying user-plane traffic.
	<list style="symbols">

	<t>
      When using IPv4 transport for the user plane, the IP address field
      in the option is the IPv4 address carrying user-plane
      traffic.
	</t>

	<t>
      When using IPv6 transport for the user plane, the IP address field
      in the option is the IPv6 address carrying user-plane
      traffic.
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>
    
    
    <t>
	The encapsulation mode that will be chosen for the user plane between the MAG and the LMA has to
    based on the considerations specified in <xref target="RFC5213"/> and <xref target="RFC5844"/>. 
    </t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Configuration Variable" anchor="sec-pvars">
<t>
	This specification defines the following configuration variable,
	which must be configurable (e.g., by the system management)
	on the LMA and MAG mobility entities.  The configured value for
	this protocol variable MUST survive server reboots and service
	restarts and MUST be the same for every LMA and MAG in the
	network domain supporting PMIPv6.
</t>


<t>
<list style='hanging'>

<t hangText="Domain-wide-LMA-UPA-Support">
<list>
<t>
	This variable indicates whether or not all the mobility entities in
	the PMIPv6 domain support the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option.
</t>

<t>
	When this variable on the MAG is set to zero (0), the MAG MUST
	indicate whether or not it supports this feature by
	including the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in the PBU.
	If the option is not present in the PBU,
	the LMA SHALL disable this feature
	for the mobility session corresponding to the PBU. 
</t>

<t>
	Setting this variable to one (1) on the MAG indicates that
	there is domain-wide support for this feature and the MAG is not
	required to include the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in
	the PBA.  In this case, the MAG MAY choose not to include the
	LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in the PBU.
</t>

<t>
	When this variable on the LMA is set to zero (0), the LMA MUST NOT
	include the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in the PBA
	unless the MAG has indicated support for this feature by including
	the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in the PBU message.
</t>

<t>
	Setting this variable to one (1) on the LMA indicates that
	there is domain-wide support for this feature and the LMA SHOULD
	choose to include this LMA User-Plane Address mobility option in
	the PBA even if the option is not present in the PBU message.
</t>

<t>
	On both the LMA and the MAG, the default value for this variable
	is zero (0).  This implies that
        the default behavior of a MAG is to include this option in the	
        PBU, and the default behavior of an LMA is to include this option	
        in a PBA only if the option is present in the PBU.</t>
</list>
</t>
</list>
</t>


</section>

<section anchor="sec:iana"  title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This specification defines a new mobility header option -- the
LMA User-Plane Address mobility option.  The format of this option
is described in <xref target="sec:dmnp_format"/>.  The Type value
59 for this mobility option has been allocated by IANA in the
"Mobility Options" registry at
&lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/mobility-parameters&gt;. 
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="sec:secons"  title="Security Considerations">

<t>
The Proxy Mobile IPv6 specification <xref target="RFC5213"/> requires the
signaling messages between the MAG and the LMA to be protected using end-to-end
security association(s) offering integrity and data origin authentication.
The Proxy Mobile IPv6 specification also requires IPsec <xref
target="RFC4301"/> to be a mandatory-to-implement security mechanism.
</t>

<t>
This document specifies an approach where the control-plane and user-plane functions of the 
MAG and LMA are separated and hosted on different IP nodes. In such deployment models,
the nodes hosting those respective control-plane functions still have to meet
the <xref target="RFC5213"/> security requirement listed above; specifically, the Proxy Mobile IPv6 signaling messages exchanged between these
entities MUST be protected using end-to-end security association(s) offering integrity and
data origin authentication. Furthermore, IPsec is a mandatory-to-implement security mechanism
for the nodes hosting the control-plane function of the MAG and
LMA. Additional documents may specify alternative security mechanisms for
securing Proxy Mobile IPv6 signaling messages. The mobility entities
in a Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain can enable a specific security mechanism
based on either (1) static configuration or (2) dynamic negotiation
(using any standard security negotiation protocols).
</t>

<t>
As per the Proxy Mobile IPv6 specification, the use of IPsec for protecting the mobile node's
user-plane traffic is optional. This specification keeps the same requirement and therefore
requires the nodes hosting the user-plane functions of the MAG and the LMA to have IPsec as a
mandatory-to-implement security mechanism but make the use of IPsec optional for user-plane
traffic protection.
</t>

<t>
	The LMA User-Plane Address mobility option defined in this
	specification is for use in PBU and PBA messages.  This option is
	carried like any other mobility header
	option as specified in <xref target="RFC5213"/>.  Therefore,
	it inherits security guidelines from <xref target="RFC5213"/>.
</t>

<t>
	The IP address of the LMA user plane (the LMA-UPA), provided
        within the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option, MUST be a
        valid address under the administrative control associated with
        the LMA functional block. 
</t>

<t>
	If the LMA user-plane and the LMA control-plane functions are hosted in different
	entities, any control messages between these two entities containing
	the LMA User-Plane Address mobility option MUST be
	protected using end-to-end security association(s) offering
        integrity and data origin authentication.
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor='RFC2119' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17970' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5213' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5213">
<front>
<title>Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Gundavelli' fullname='S. Gundavelli'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Leung' fullname='K. Leung'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Devarapalli' fullname='V. Devarapalli'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Chowdhury' fullname='K. Chowdhury'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Patil' fullname='B. Patil'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='August' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5213' />
<format type='TXT' octets='226902' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5213.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5844' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5844">
<front>
<title>IPv4 Support for Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Wakikawa' fullname='R. Wakikawa'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Gundavelli' fullname='S. Gundavelli'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5844' />
<format type='TXT' octets='116102' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5844.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4301' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4301">
<front>
<title>Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Kent' fullname='S. Kent'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Seo' fullname='K. Seo'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='December' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4301' />
<format type='TXT' octets='262123' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4301.txt' />
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='RFC1701' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1701">
<front>
<title>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE)</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Hanks' fullname='Stan Hanks'>
<organization>NetSmiths, Ltd.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2025 Lincoln Highway</street>
<city>Edison</city>
<region>NJ</region>
<code>08817</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<email>stan@netsmiths.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Li' fullname='Tony Li'>
<organization>cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1525 O'Brien Drive</street>
<city>Menlo Park</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94025</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<email>tli@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Farinacci' fullname='Dino Farinacci'>
<organization>cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1525 O'Brien Drive</street>
<city>Menlo Park</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94025</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<email>dino@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Traina' fullname='Paul Traina'>
<organization>cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1525 O'Brien Drive</street>
<city>Menlo Park</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94025</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<email>pst@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1994' month='October' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1701' />
<format type='TXT' octets='15460' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1701.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC2473' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2473">
<front>
<title abbrev='Generic Packet Tunneling in IPv6'>Generic Packet Tunneling in IPv6 Specification</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Conta' fullname='Alex Conta'>
<organization>Lucent Technologies Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>300 Baker Ave</street>
<city>Concord</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>01742-2168</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 978 287 2842</phone>
<email>aconta@lucent.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Deering' fullname='Stephen Deering'>
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Dr</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95132-1706</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-408-527-8213</phone>
<email>deering@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1998' month='December' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2473' />
<format type='TXT' octets='77956' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2473.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='103157' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2473.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='85049' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2473.xml' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6275' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6275">
<front>
<title>Mobility Support in IPv6</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Perkins' fullname='C. Perkins'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Johnson' fullname='D. Johnson'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Arkko' fullname='J. Arkko'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6275' />
<format type='TXT' octets='405488' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6275.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC6463' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6463">
<front>
<title>Runtime Local Mobility Anchor (LMA) Assignment Support for Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Korhonen' fullname='J. Korhonen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Gundavelli' fullname='S. Gundavelli'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Yokota' fullname='H. Yokota'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='X.' surname='Cui' fullname='X. Cui'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='February' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6463' />
<format type='TXT' octets='50702' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6463.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='RFC6459' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6459">
<front>
<title>IPv6 in 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) Evolved Packet System (EPS)</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Korhonen' fullname='J. Korhonen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Soininen' fullname='J. Soininen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Patil' fullname='B. Patil'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Savolainen' fullname='T. Savolainen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Bajko' fullname='G. Bajko'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Iisakkila' fullname='K. Iisakkila'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6459' />
<format type='TXT' octets='84769' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6459.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC5810' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5810">
<front>
<title>Forwarding and Control Element Separation (ForCES) Protocol Specification</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Doria' fullname='A. Doria'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Hadi Salim' fullname='J. Hadi Salim'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Haas' fullname='R. Haas'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Khosravi' fullname='H. Khosravi'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='W.' surname='Wang' fullname='W. Wang'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Dong' fullname='L. Dong'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Gopal' fullname='R. Gopal'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Halpern' fullname='J. Halpern'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5810' />
<format type='TXT' octets='239754' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5810.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4213' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4213">
<front>
<title>Basic Transition Mechanisms for IPv6 Hosts and Routers</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Nordmark' fullname='E. Nordmark'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Gilligan' fullname='R. Gilligan'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='October' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4213' />
<format type='TXT' octets='58575' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4213.txt' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-matsushima-stateless-uplane-vepc-03: I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='STATELESS-UPLANE'>
<front>
<title>Stateless user-plane architecture for virtualized EPC (vEPC)</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Matsushima' fullname='Satoru Matsushima'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Wakikawa' fullname='Ryuji Wakikawa'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2014' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-matsushima-stateless-uplane-vepc-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-matsushima-stateless-uplane-vepc-03.txt' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-wakikawa-req-mobile-cp-separation-00: Expired -->

<reference anchor='MOBILE-SEPARATION'>
<front>
<title>Requirements and use cases for separating control and user planes in mobile network architectures</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Wakikawa' fullname='Ryuji Wakikawa'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Matsushima' fullname='Satoru Matsushima'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Patil' fullname='Basavaraj Patil'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Chen' fullname='Bonnie Chen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Joachimpillai' fullname='Damascene Joachimpillai'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Deng' fullname='Hui Deng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2013' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-wakikawa-req-mobile-cp-separation-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-wakikawa-req-mobile-cp-separation-00.txt' />
</reference>


      <reference anchor="OpenFlow-Spec-v1.4.0">
        <front>
          <title>OpenFlow Switch Specification, Version 1.4.0</title>

          <author fullname="OpenFlow-Spec-v1.4.0">
            <organization>Open Networking Foundation</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


</references>

<section anchor="sec:ack" title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>   The authors of this document thank the NetExt Working Group for the
   valuable feedback on different versions of this specification.  In
   particular, the authors want to thank John Kaippallimalil, Sridhar
   Bhaskaran, Nirav Salot, Bruno Landais, Brian Carpenter, Pete Resnick,
   Stephen Farrell, and Brian Haberman for their valuable comments and
   suggestions to improve this specification.</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
