<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  ]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc number="7684"
     category="std" 
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">

<front>
<title abbrev="OSPFv2 Prefix/Link Attributes ">OSPFv2 Prefix/Link Attribute Advertisement</title> 
  <author initials='P.' surname="Psenak" fullname='Peter Psenak'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Apollo Business Center</street>
        <street>Mlynske nivy 43</street>
        <city>Bratislava</city> <region>821 09</region> 
        <country>Slovakia</country>
        <code></code> 
       </postal>
       <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='H.' surname="Gredler" fullname='Hannes Gredler'>
    <organization>Independent</organization>
    <address>
       <email>hannes@gredler.at</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='R.' surname="Shakir" fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization>Jive Communications, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>1275 W 1600 N, Suite 100</street>
        <city>Orem</city>
        <region>UT</region>
        <code>84057</code>
        <country>United States</country>
       </postal>
       <email>rjs@rob.sh</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='W.' surname="Henderickx" fullname='Wim Henderickx'>
    <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Copernicuslaan</street>
        <city>Antwerp</city><region>2018</region>
        <country>Belgium</country>
        <code>94089</code> 
       </postal>
       <email>wim.henderickx@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='J.' surname="Tantsura" fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization>Ericsson</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>300 Holger Way</street>
        <city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region> 
        <country>United States</country>
        <code>95134</code> 
       </postal>
       <email>jeff.tantsura@ericsson.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>
        <city>Cary</city> <region>NC</region> 
        <country>United States</country>
        <code>27513</code> 
       </postal>
       <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

<date month="November" year="2015"/>



  <abstract>
  <t>OSPFv2 requires functional extension beyond what can readily be done with the
   fixed-format Link State Advertisements (LSAs) as described in RFC 2328.
   This document defines OSPFv2 Opaque LSAs based on Type-Length-Value (TLV) tuples that can
   be used to associate additional attributes with prefixes or links. Depending on the 
   application, these prefixes and links may or may not be advertised in 
   the fixed-format LSAs. The 
   OSPFv2 Opaque LSAs are optional and fully backward compatible.</t> 
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
  <t>OSPFv2 requires functional extension beyond what can readily be done with the
   fixed-format Link State Advertisements (LSAs) as described in RFC 2328 <xref target="OSPFV2"/>.
   This document defines OSPFv2 Opaque LSAs based on Type-Length-Value (TLV) tuples that can
   be used to associate additional attributes with prefixes or links. Depending on the 
   application, these prefixes and links may or may not be advertised in 
   the fixed-format LSAs. The OSPFv2 Opaque LSAs are optional and fully backward compatible. 
   This is in contrast to the 
   approach taken in OSPFv3  <xref target="OSPFv3-EXTEND"/> where the 
   existing LSAs will be replaced by TLV-based extended LSAs.</t>
  <t>New requirements such as source/destination routing, route tagging, and segment routing 
     necessitate this extension.</t>
   <t>This specification defines the following OSPFv2 Opaque LSAs:
    <list style="numbers"> 


      <t>OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA - Allows advertisement of additional attributes
         for prefixes advertised in Router-LSAs, Network-LSAs, 
         Summary-LSAs (IP network), NSSA-LSAs, and AS-external-LSAs <xref
	 target="OSPFV2"/><xref target="RFC3101"/>.</t> 
      <t>OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA - Allows advertisement of additional attributes
         for links advertised in Router-LSAs.</t>
   </list></t>
  <t>Additionally, the following TLVs are defined:
   <list style="numbers"> 
      <t>OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV - Top-level TLV advertising attributes for a prefix in
         the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA.</t>
      <t>OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV - Top-level TLV advertising attributes for a link in
         the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA.</t>
   </list></t>
  <section title="Requirements Notation">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
       and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
       described in <xref target="KEYWORDS"/>.</t>
   </section>
</section>

<section anchor="EXTENDED-PREFIX-LSA" title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA">
   <t>The OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is used to advertise additional 
   prefix attributes. Opaque LSAs are described in <xref target="OPAQUE"/>.</t>
   <t>Multiple OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs can be advertised by an
   OSPFv2 router.  The flooding scope of the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix
   Opaque LSA depends on the scope of the advertised prefixes and is
   under the control of the advertising router.  In some cases (e.g.,
   mapping server deployment <xref target="SEGMENT-ROUTING"/>), the LSA 
   flooding scope may be greater
   than the scope of the corresponding prefixes.</t>
   <t>The format of the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is as follows:</t>


   <t><figure title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |            LS age             |     Options   |   LS Type     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Opaque Type  |                 Opaque ID                     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                     Advertising Router                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                     LS sequence number                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         LS checksum           |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +-                            TLVs                             -+
   |                             ...                               |
      </artwork>
   </figure></t>
   <t>The Opaque Type used by the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is 7. 
      The Opaque Type is used to differentiate the various types of OSPFv2
      Opaque LSAs and is described in Section 3 of <xref target="OPAQUE"/>.
      The LS Type may be 10 or 11, indicating that the Opaque LSA flooding
      scope is area-local (10) or AS-wide (11) <xref target="OPAQUE"/>. 
      The LSA Length field <xref target="OSPFV2"/> represents the 
      total length (in octets) of the Opaque LSA, including the LSA header
      and all TLVs (including padding). </t>

   <t>The Opaque ID field is an arbitrary value used to maintain multiple
      OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs.  For OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs, 
      the Opaque ID has no semantic significance other than to differentiate 
      OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs originated by the same OSPFv2 router.
      If multiple OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs include the same prefix, the
      attributes from the Opaque LSA with the lowest Opaque ID SHOULD be 
      used.</t> 
     
    <t>The format of the TLVs within the body of the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is the same as
       the format used by the Traffic Engineering Extensions to OSPFv2 <xref target="TE"/>.
       The variable TLV section consists of one or more nested
       TLV tuples.  Nested TLVs are also referred to as sub-TLVs. 
       The format of each TLV is:</t>
   <t><figure title="TLV Format">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              Type             |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                            Value                              |
                                  o
                                  o
                                  o
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      </artwork>
   </figure></t>
   <t>The Length field defines the length of the value portion in octets
   (thus, a TLV with no value portion would have a length of 0).  The TLV
   is padded to 4-octet alignment; padding is not included
   in the Length field (so a 3-octet value would have a length of 3, but
   the total size of the TLV would be 8 octets).  Nested TLVs are also 32-bit
   aligned.  For example, a 1-byte value would have the Length field set
   to 1, and 3 octets of padding would be added to the end of the value
   portion of the TLV. The padding is composed of zeros.</t>
 <section anchor="EXTENDED-PREFIX-TLV" title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV">
  <t>The OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV is used to advertise additional
   attributes associated with the prefix.  Multiple OSPFv2 Extended Prefix
   TLVs MAY be advertised in each OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA. However,
   since the Opaque LSA type defines the flooding scope, the LSA flooding 
   scope MUST satisfy the application-specific requirements for all
   the prefixes included in a single OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA.
   The OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV has the following format:</t> 
   <t><figure title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV">
     <artwork>
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |              Type             |             Length            |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  Route Type   | Prefix Length |     AF        |     Flags     |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                     Address Prefix (variable)                 |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                      Sub-TLVs (variable)                      |
 +-                                                             -+
 |                             ...                               | 
</artwork>
</figure></t>
<t><vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="hanging">  
   <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     The TLV type. The value is 1 for this TLV type.</t>
   <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     Variable, dependent on sub-TLVs.</t>
   <t hangText="Route Type"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     The type of the OSPFv2 route. 
     If the route type is 0 (Unspecified), the information inside
     the OSPFv2 External Prefix TLV applies to the prefix regardless
     of prefix's route type.  This is useful when prefix-specific
     attributes are advertised by an external entity that
     is not aware of the route type associated with the 
     prefix. Supported types are:
    <list>
      <t>0 - Unspecified</t>
      <t>1 - Intra-Area</t>
      <t>3 - Inter-Area</t>
      <t>5 - Autonomous System (AS) External</t>
      <t>7 - Not-So-Stubby Area (NSSA) External</t>
    </list>

    These route types correspond directly to the OSPFv2 LSAs types as defined
    in the "OSPFv2 Link State (LS) Type" registry in 
    &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/ospfv2-parameters&gt;.
    Specification of route types other than those defined will prevent correlation with existing 
    OSPFv2 LSAs and is beyond the scope of this specification.</t> 
   <t hangText="Prefix Length"><vspace blankLines="0" />


      Length of prefix in bits.
    </t>
   <t hangText="AF"><vspace blankLines="0" />
    Address family for the prefix. Currently, the only supported value
    is 0 for IPv4 unicast. The inclusion of address family
    in this TLV allows for future extension.</t>
   <t hangText="Flags"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     This one-octet field contains flags applicable to the prefix. Supported Flags include:


     <list style="hanging">
     <t>0x80 - A-Flag (Attach Flag): An Area Border Router (ABR) generating 
        an OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV for an inter-area prefix that is locally connected or attached
        in another connected area SHOULD set this flag.</t> 
     <t>0x40 - N-Flag (Node Flag): Set when the prefix identifies the advertising router, i.e., the
  	prefix is a host prefix advertising a globally reachable address typically
  	associated with a loopback address.
  	The advertising router MAY choose to not set this flag even when the above
  	conditions are met. If the flag is set and the prefix length is not a host
  	prefix, then the flag MUST be ignored. The flag is preserved when the OSPFv2 
  	Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is propagated between areas.</t>
     </list></t>
   <t hangText="Address Prefix"><vspace blankLines="0" />
    For the address family IPv4 unicast, the prefix itself is encoded as a
    32-bit value. The default route is represented by a prefix of length 0.
    Prefix encoding for other address families is beyond the scope of this 
    specification.</t>
 </list></t>
 <t>If this TLV is advertised multiple times for the same prefix 
   in the same OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA, only the first 
   instance of the TLV is used by receiving OSPFv2 routers. This situation 
   SHOULD be logged as an error.</t>
 <t>If this TLV is advertised multiple times for the same prefix 
   in different OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs originated by the
   same OSPFv2 router, the OSPFv2 advertising router is re-originating
   OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs for multiple prefixes and is most likely
   repacking Extended-Prefix-TLVs in OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs. 
   In this case, the Extended-Prefix-TLV in the OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque 
   LSA with the smallest Opaque ID is used by receiving OSPFv2 routers.
   This situation may be logged as a warning.</t> 
 <t>It is RECOMMENDED that OSPFv2 routers advertising OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLVs 
    in different OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs re-originate these LSAs
    in ascending order of Opaque ID to minimize the disruption.</t> 
 <t>If this TLV is advertised multiple times for the same prefix 
   in different OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs originated by
   different OSPFv2 routers, the application using the information is required
   to determine which OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA is used. For 
   example, the application could prefer the LSA providing the best 
   path to the prefix.</t>
 <t>This document creates a registry for OSPFv2 Extended Prefix sub-TLVs 
    in <xref target="IANA"/>.</t> 
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="EXTENDED-LINK-LSA" title="OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA">
 <t>The OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA is used to advertise additional 
   link attributes. Opaque LSAs are described in <xref target="OPAQUE"/>.</t>
   <t>The OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA has an area flooding scope.
   Multiple OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs can be advertised by a
   single router in an area.</t>
   <t>The format of the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA is as follows:</t>
   <t><figure title="OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |            LS age             |     Options   |   LS Type     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Opaque Type  |                   Opaque ID                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                     Advertising Router                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                     LS sequence number                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         LS checksum           |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +-                            TLVs                             -+
   |                             ...                               |
     </artwork>
  </figure></t>
  <t>The Opaque Type used by the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA is 8.
      The LS Type is 10, indicating that the Opaque LSA flooding scope 
      is area-local <xref target="OPAQUE"/>. 
      The Opaque Type is used to differentiate the various types of OSPFv2
      Opaque LSAs and is described in Section 3 of <xref target="OPAQUE"/>.
      The LSA Length field <xref target="OSPFV2"/> represents the 
      total length (in octets) of the Opaque LSA, including the LSA header
      and all TLVs (including padding). </t>
  
   <t>The Opaque ID field is an arbitrary value used to maintain multiple
      OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs.  For OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs, 
      the Opaque ID has no semantic significance other than to differentiate 
      OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs originated by the same OSPFv2 router.
      If multiple OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs include the same link, the
      attributes from the Opaque LSA with the lowest Opaque ID will be used.</t> 
     
  <t>The format of the TLVs within the body of the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA
     is the same as described in <xref target="EXTENDED-PREFIX-LSA"/>.</t>
<section anchor="EXTENDED-LINK-TLV" title="OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV">
<t>The OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV is used to advertise various
   attributes of the link.  It describes a single link and is
   constructed of a set of sub-TLVs.  There are no ordering requirements
   for the sub-TLVs.  Only one OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV SHALL be advertised in
   each OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA, allowing for fine granularity changes
   in the topology.</t>

<t>The OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV has following format:</t>
   <t><figure title="OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              Type             |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Link Type |                  Reserved                     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                            Link ID                            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                           Link Data                           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                      Sub-TLVs (variable)                      |
   +-                                                             -+
   |                             ...                               |
     </artwork>
  </figure></t>
  <t><vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="hanging">  
   <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     The TLV type. The value is 1 for this TLV type.</t>
 <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="0" />
     Variable, dependent on sub-TLVs.</t>

   <t hangText="Link Type"><vspace blankLines="0" />
      Link Type is defined in Section A.4.2 of <xref target="OSPFV2"/> and in
      the "OSPFv2
      Router LSA Link Type (Value 1)" registry at 
      &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/ospfv2-parameters&gt;.
      Specification of link types other than those defined will prevent correlation with existing 
      OSPFv2 Router-LSA links and is beyond the scope this specification.</t> 
   <t hangText="Link ID"><vspace blankLines="0" />
      Link ID is defined in Section A.4.2 of <xref target="OSPFV2"/>.</t>
   <t hangText="Link Data"><vspace blankLines="0" />
      Link Data is defined in Section A.4.2 of <xref target="OSPFV2"/>.</t>
 </list></t>
 
 <t>If this TLV is advertised multiple times 
    in the same OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA, only the first 
    instance of the TLV is used by receiving OSPFv2 routers. This situation 
    SHOULD be logged as an error.</t>
 <t>If this TLV is advertised multiple times for the same link 
    in different OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs originated by the
    same OSPFv2 router, the OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV in the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque 
    LSA with the smallest Opaque ID is used by receiving OSPFv2 routers.
    This situation may be logged as a warning.</t> 
 <t>It is RECOMMENDED that OSPFv2 routers advertising OSPFv2 Extended Link TLVs 
    in different OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs re-originate these LSAs
    in ascending order of Opaque ID to minimize the disruption.</t>
 
 <t>This document creates a registry for OSPFv2 Extended Link sub-TLVs 
    in <xref target="IANA"/>.</t> 
</section>
</section>
<section title="Backward Compatibility">
<t>Since Opaque OSPFv2 LSAs are optional and backward compatible 
<xref target="OPAQUE"/>, the extensions described herein are fully backward
compatible. However, future OSPFv2 applications utilizing these extensions
MUST address backward compatibility of the corresponding functionality.</t>
</section>


<section title="Security Considerations">                        
<t>In general, new LSAs defined in this document are subject to the same
   security concerns as those described in <xref target="OSPFV2"/> and 
   <xref target="OPAQUE"/>.</t>

  <t>OSPFv2 applications utilizing these OSPFv2 extensions must define the
  security considerations relating to those applications in
  the specifications corresponding to those applications.</t>
  <t>Additionally, implementations must assure that malformed TLV and sub-
  TLV permutations are detected and do not provide a vulnerability for
  attackers to crash the OSPFv2 router or routing process. 


Malformed
  LSAs MUST NOT be stored in the Link State Database (LSDB),
  acknowledged, or reflooded. Reception of malformed LSAs SHOULD be
  counted and/or logged for further analysis. In this context, a 
  malformed LSA is one that cannot be parsed due to a
  TLV or sub-TLV overrunning the end of the subsuming LSA, TLV, or
  sub-TLV or where there is data remaining to be parsed but the length
  of the remaining data is less than the size of a TLV header.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">                        

  <t>This specification updates the
     "Opaque Link-State Advertisements (LSA) Option Types" registry with the following values:
    <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>7 - OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA</t>
     <t>8 - OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA</t>
    </list></t>
   <t>This specification also creates five new registries:
    <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA TLVs</t>
     <t>OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs</t>
     <t>OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Flags</t>
     <t>OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA TLVs</t>
     <t>OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV Sub-TLVs</t>
    </list></t>

<section title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSA TLVs Registry">                        

   <t>The "OSPFv2 Extend Prefix Opaque LSA TLVs" registry defines
   top-level TLVs for OSPFv2 Extended Prefix Opaque LSAs and has been added
   to the "Open Shortest Path First v2 (OSPFv2) Parameters"
   registry. New values can be allocated via IETF Review or IESG
   Approval <xref target="RFC5226"/>.</t>
   <t>The following initial values have been allocated:

    <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>0 - Reserved</t>
     <t>1 - OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV</t>
    </list></t>
   <t>Types in the range 32768-33023 are for Experimental Use; these will
   not be registered with IANA and MUST NOT be mentioned by RFCs.</t>
   <t>Types in the range 33024-65535 are not to be assigned at this time.
   Before any assignments can be made in the 33024-65535 range, there MUST
   be an IETF specification that specifies IANA considerations covering
   the range being assigned.</t>
</section>  

<section title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs Registry">
   <t>The "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Sub-TLVs" registry defines
   sub-TLVs at any level of nesting for OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLVs and has been added
   to the "Open Shortest Path First v2 (OSPFv2) Parameters"
   registry. New values can be allocated via IETF Review or IESG
   Approval.</t>
  <t>The following initial value has been allocated:
    <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>0 - Reserved</t>
   </list></t>
   <t>Types in the range 32768-33023 are for Experimental Use; these will
   not be registered with IANA and MUST NOT be mentioned by RFCs.</t>
   <t>Types in the range 33024-65535 are not to be assigned at this time.
   Before any assignments can be made in the 33024-65535 range, there MUST
   be an IETF specification that specifies IANA considerations covering
   the range being assigned.</t>
</section>

<section title="OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Flags Registry">
   <t>The "OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Flags" registry defines
   the bits in the 8-bit OSPFv2 Extended Prefix TLV Flags (<xref target="EXTENDED-PREFIX-TLV"/>). 
   This specification defines the A (0x80) and N (0x40) bits. 
   This registry has been
   added to the "Open Shortest Path First v2 (OSPFv2) Parameters"
   registry. New values can be allocated via IETF Review or IESG
   Approval.</t>
</section>

<section title="OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA TLVs Registry">                        
  <t> The "OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA TLVs" registry defines
   top-level TLVs for OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSAs and has been added
   to the "Open Shortest Path First v2 (OSPFv2) Parameters" 
   registry. New values can be allocated via IETF Review or IESG
   Approval.</t>
   <t>The following initial values have been allocated:
    <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>0 - Reserved</t>
      <t>1 - OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV</t>
   </list></t>
   <t>Types in the range 32768-33023 are for Experimental Use; these will
   not be registered with IANA and MUST NOT be mentioned by RFCs.</t>
   <t>Types in the range 33024-65535 are not to be assigned at this time.
   Before any assignments can be made in the 33024-65535 range, there MUST
   be an IETF specification that specifies IANA considerations covering
   the range being assigned.</t>
</section>

<section title="OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV Sub-TLVs Registry">
   <t>The "OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV Sub-TLVs" registry defines
   sub-TLVs at any level of nesting for OSPFv2 Extended Link TLVs and has been
   added to the "Open Shortest Path First v2 (OSPFv2) Parameters"
   registry. New values can be allocated via IETF Review or IESG
   Approval.</t>
  <t>The following initial value has been allocated:
    <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>0 - Reserved</t>
   </list></t>
  <t>Types in the range 32768-33023 are for Experimental Use; these will
   not be registered with IANA and MUST NOT be mentioned by RFCs.</t>
<t>
   Types in the range 33024-65535 are not to be assigned at this time.
   Before any assignments can be made in the 33024-65535 range, there MUST
   be an IETF specification that specifies IANA considerations covering
   the range being assigned.</t>
</section> 
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<reference anchor="KEYWORDS" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="TE" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3630'>
<front>
<title>Traffic Engineering (TE) Extensions to OSPF Version 2</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Katz' fullname='D. Katz'><organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Kompella' fullname='K. Kompella'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Yeung' fullname='D. Yeung'><organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3630'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3630'/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="OPAQUE" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5250'>
<front>
<title>The OSPF Opaque LSA Option</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Berger' fullname='L. Berger'><organization /></author>
<author initials='I.' surname='Bryskin' fullname='I. Bryskin'><organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Zinin' fullname='A. Zinin'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Coltun' fullname='R. Coltun'><organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5250'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5250'/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="OSPFV2" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2328'>
<front>
<title>OSPF Version 2</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Moy' fullname='J. Moy'><organization /></author>
<date year='1998' month='April' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='54'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2328'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2328'/>
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">


<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3101"?>

<!--draft-ietf-ospf-segment-routing-extensions: I-D Exists-->

<reference anchor="SEGMENT-ROUTING">
<front>
<title>OSPF Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
<author initials="P." surname="Psenak" fullname="Peter Psenak">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="C." surname="Filsfils" fullname="Clarence Filsfils">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="H." surname="Gredler" fullname="Hannes Gredler">
<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
</author>
<author initials="R." surname="Shakir" fullname="Rob Shakir">
<organization>Individual Contributor</organization>
</author>
<author initials="W." surname="Henderickx" fullname="Wim Henderickx">
<organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
</author>
<author initials="J." surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
<organization>Ericsson</organization>
</author>
<date month="June" year="2015" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-ietf-ospf-segment-routing-extensions-05"/>
</reference>


<!--draft-ietf-ospf-ospfv3-lsa-extend-06: I-D Updated -->

<reference anchor='OSPFv3-EXTEND'>
<front>
<title>OSPFv3 LSA Extendibility</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Lindem' fullname='Acee Lindem'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Mirtorabi' fullname='Sina Mirtorabi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Roy' fullname='Abhay Roy'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='F' surname='Baker' fullname='Fred Baker'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2015' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ospf-ospfv3-lsa-extend-08' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-ospf-ospfv3-lsa-extend-08.txt' />
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>


</references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>We would like to thank Anton Smirnov for his contribution.</t>

<t>Thanks to Tony Przygienda for his review and comments.</t>

<t>Thanks to Wim Henderickx, Greg Harkins, Peter Psenak, Eric Wu,
Shraddha Hegde, and Csaba Mate for their responses to the
implementation survey.</t>

<t>Thanks to Tom Petch and Chris Bowers for review and comments.</t>

<t>Thanks to Alia Atlas and Alvaro Retana for their AD review and comments.</t>

<t>Thanks to Carlos Pignataro and Ron Bonica for Operations Directorate
review and comments.</t>

<t>Thanks to Suresh Krishnan for the Gen-ART review and comments.</t>

<t> Thanks to Ben Campbell, Kathleen Moriarty, and Barry Leiba for IESG
review and comments.</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
