<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="7503" category="std" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" updates="5340" submissionType="IETF">

<front>
<title abbrev="OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration">OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration</title>


  <author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>
        <city>Cary</city> <region>NC</region> 
        <country>United States</country>
        <code>27513</code> 
       </postal>
       <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <author initials='J.' surname="Arkko" fullname='Jari Arkko'>
    <organization>Ericsson</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Jorvas</city> <region>02420</region> 
        <country>Finland</country>
       </postal>
       <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
    </address>
    </author>

<date month="April" year="2015"/>
  <abstract><t>OSPFv3 is a candidate for deployments in environments where autoconfiguration
   is a requirement. One such environment is the IPv6 home network where users expect to 
   simply plug in a router and have it automatically use OSPFv3 for intra-domain routing. 
   This document describes the necessary mechanisms for OSPFv3 to be self-configuring.
   This document updates RFC 5340 by relaxing the HelloInterval/RouterDeadInterval checking during OSPFv3
   adjacency formation and adding hysteresis to the update of self-originated Link State 
   Advertisements (LSAs).</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
  <t>OSPFv3 <xref target="OSPFV3"/> is a candidate for deployments in environments where 
   autoconfiguration is a requirement. This document describes 
   extensions to OSPFv3 to enable it to operate in these environments.
   In this mode of operation, the protocol is largely unchanged from the
   base OSPFv3 protocol specification <xref target="OSPFV3"/>.
   Since the goals of autoconfiguration and security can be conflicting,
   operators and network administrators should carefully consider their
   security requirements before deploying the solution described in this
   document. Refer to <xref target="SECURITY"/> for more information.
</t>
   <t>The following aspects of OSPFv3 autoconfiguration are described in this
   document:

   <list style="numbers"> 
      <t>Default OSPFv3 Configuration</t> 
      <t>HelloInterval/RouterDeadInterval Flexibility</t>
      <t>OSPFv3 Minimal Authentication Configuration</t>
      <t>Unique OSPFv3 Router ID Generation</t>
      <t>OSPFv3 Adjacency Formation</t>
      <t>Duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID Resolution</t>
      <t>Self-Originated LSA Processing</t>
   </list></t>
  <t>OSPFv3 <xref target="OSPFV3" /> is updated by allowing OSPFv3 adjacencies to be formed
     between OSPFv3 routers with differing HelloIntervals or RouterDeadIntervals
     (refer to <xref target="FLEX-INTERVAL"/>). Additionally, hysteresis has been added to the processing of
     stale self-originated LSAs to mitigate the flooding overhead created by an OSPFv3 Router with
     a duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID in the OSPFv3 routing domain (refer to 
     <xref target="UPDATE-BACKOFF"/>). Both updates are fully backward compatible.</t>
  <section title="Requirements Notation">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
       and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
       described in <xref target="RFC-KEYWORDS"/>.</t>
   </section>
</section>

<section anchor="DEFAULT" title="OSPFv3 Default Configuration">
<t>For complete autoconfiguration, OSPFv3 will need to choose suitable configuration defaults. These include:
   <list style="numbers"> 
      <t>Area 0 Only - All autoconfigured OSPFv3 interfaces MUST be in area 0.</t> 
      <t>OSPFv3 SHOULD be autoconfigured on all IPv6-capable interfaces on the router. 
         An interface MAY be excluded if it is clear that running OSPFv3 on the interface is not required. 
         For example, if manual configuration or another condition indicates that an interface is connected to an
         Internet Service Provider (ISP), there is typically no need to employ OSPFv3. In fact, <xref target="IPv6-CPE"/> 
         specifically requires that 
         IPv6 Customer Premise Equipment (CPE) routers not initiate any dynamic routing protocol by default on the 
         router's WAN, i.e., ISP-facing, interface. In home networking environments, an interface where no
         OSPFv3 neighbors are found, but a DHCP IPv6 prefix can be acquired, may be considered an ISP-facing interface,
         and running OSPFv3 is unnecessary.</t>
      <t>OSPFv3 interfaces will be autoconfigured to an interface type
      corresponding to their Layer 2 capability. 
         For example, Ethernet interfaces and Wi-Fi interfaces will be autoconfigured as OSPFv3 
         broadcast networks 
         and Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP) interfaces will be autoconfigured as OSPFv3 Point-to-Point interfaces. 
         Most extant OSPFv3 implementations do this already. autoconfigured operation over wireless networks 
         requiring a point-to-multipoint (P2MP) topology and dynamic metrics based on wireless feedback is 
         not within the scope of this document. However, autoconfiguration is not precluded in these environments.</t>
      <t>OSPFv3 interfaces MAY use an arbitrary HelloInterval and RouterDeadInterval as specified in 
         <xref target="FLEX-INTERVAL"/>. Of course, an identical HelloInterval and RouterDeadInterval will still 
         be required to form an adjacency with an OSPFv3 router not supporting autoconfiguration
         <xref target="OSPFV3"/>.</t>
      <t>All OSPFv3 interfaces SHOULD be autoconfigured to use an Interface Instance ID of 0 that corresponds to the 
         base IPv6 unicast address family instance ID as defined in <xref target="OSPFV3-AF"/>. Similarly, if IPv4 
         unicast addresses are advertised in a separate autoconfigured OSPFv3 instance, the base IPv4 unicast address family 
         instance ID value, i.e., 64, SHOULD be autoconfigured as the Interface Instance ID for all interfaces corresponding
         to the IPv4 unicast OSPFv3 instance <xref target="OSPFV3-AF"/>.</t> 
   </list></t>
</section> 
   <section anchor="FLEX-INTERVAL" title="OSPFv3 HelloInterval/RouterDeadInterval Flexibility">
     <t>autoconfigured OSPFv3 routers will not require an identical HelloInterval and RouterDeadInterval to form
        adjacencies. Rather, the received HelloInterval will be ignored and the received RouterDeadInterval will be used
        to determine OSPFv3 liveliness with the sending router. In other words, the Neighbor Inactivity Timer 
        (Section 10 of <xref target="OSPFV2"/>) for each neighbor
        will reflect that neighbor's advertised RouterDeadInterval and MAY be different from other OSPFv3 routers on 
        the link without impacting adjacency formation. A similar mechanism requiring additional 
        signaling is proposed for all OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 routers <xref target="ASYNC-HELLO"/>.</t> 
   <section title="Wait Timer Reduction">
     <t>In many situations, autoconfigured OSPFv3 routers will be deployed in environments where back-to-back ethernet
        connections are utilized. When this is the case, an OSPFv3 broadcast interface will not come up until the 
        other OSPFv3 router is connected, and the routers will wait RouterDeadInterval seconds before forming an
        adjacency <xref target="OSPFV2"/>. In order to reduce this delay, an autoconfigured OSPFv3 router MAY reduce the
        wait interval to a value no less than (HelloInterval + 1). Reducing the setting will slightly 
        increase the likelihood of the Designated Router (DR) flapping but is preferable to the long adjacency formation
        delay. Note that this value is not included in OSPFv3 Hello packets and does not impact interoperability.</t>
   </section>
 </section>
<section anchor="AUTH-CONFIG" title="OSPFv3 Minimal Authentication Configuration">
<t>In many deployments, the requirement for OSPFv3 authentication overrides the goal 
  of complete OSPFv3 autoconfiguration. Therefore, it is RECOMMENDED that OSPFv3 routers 
  supporting this specification minimally offer an option to explicitly configure a 
  single password for HMAC-SHA authentication as described in <xref
  target="OSPFV3-AUTH-TRAILER"/>.


  It is RECOMMENDED that the password be entered as ASCII hexadecimal 
  digits and that 32 or more digits be accepted to facilitate a password 
  with a high degree of entropy. 

  When configured, the password will be used on all autoconfigured interfaces with
  the Security Association Identifier (SA ID) set to 1 and HMAC-SHA-256 used
  as the authentication algorithm.</t>                        
</section>
<section title="OSPFv3 Router ID Selection">
 <t>An OSPFv3 router requires a unique Router ID within the OSPFv3 routing domain
    for correct protocol operation. Existing Router ID selection algorithms (Appendix C.1 in
    <xref target="OSPFV2"/> and <xref target="OSPFV3"/>) are not viable since they are
    dependent on a unique IPv4 interface address that is not likely to be available in
    autoconfigured deployments.
    An OSPFv3 router implementing 
    this specification will select a Router ID that has a high probability of uniqueness. 
    A pseudorandom number SHOULD be used for the OSPFv3 Router ID. The generation SHOULD be seeded
    with a variable that is likely to be unique in 
    the applicable OSPFv3 router deployment. A good choice of seed would be some portion or hash of the
    Router-Hardware-Fingerprint as described in <xref target="FINGER"/>.</t>
  <t>Since there is a possibility of a Router ID collision, duplicate Router ID detection and resolution
     are required as described in Sections <xref target="DUPLICATE"
     format="counter"/> and <xref target="RESOLUTION" format="counter"/>. OSPFv3 routers 
     SHOULD maintain the last successfully chosen Router ID in nonvolatile storage to avoid collisions 
     subsequent to when an autoconfigured OSPFv3 router is first added to the OSPFv3 routing domain.</t>
</section> 
<section anchor="ADJACENCY" title="OSPFv3 Adjacency Formation">
 <t>Since OSPFv3 uses IPv6 link-local addresses for all protocol messages other than messages sent on virtual
    links (which are  not applicable to autoconfiguration), OSPFv3 adjacency formation can proceed as soon as
    a Router ID has been selected and the IPv6 link-local address has completed Duplicate Address Detection (DAD)
    as specified in IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration <xref target="SLAAC"/>. Otherwise, the only changes
    to the OSPFv3 base specification are supporting HelloInterval/RouterDeadInterval flexibility as described in 
    <xref target="FLEX-INTERVAL"/> and duplicate Router ID detection and resolution as described in Sections
   <xref target="DUPLICATE" format="counter"/> and <xref target="RESOLUTION" format="counter"/>.</t> 
</section> 
<section anchor="DUPLICATE" title="OSPFv3 Duplicate Router ID Detection and Resolution">
  <t>There are two cases of duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID detection. One where the OSPFv3 router with the
     duplicate Router ID is directly connected and one where it is not. In both cases, the duplicate resolution is
     for one of the routers to select a new OSPFv3 Router ID.</t>
  <section anchor="CONNNETED-DETECT" title="Duplicate Router ID Detection for Neighbors">
  <t>In this case, a duplicate Router ID is detected if any valid OSPFv3 packet is received with the same OSPFv3 Router ID 
     but a different IPv6 link-local source address. Once this occurs, the OSPFv3 router with the numerically smaller
     IPv6 link-local address will need to select a new Router ID as described in <xref target="RESOLUTION"/>.
     Note that the fact that the OSPFv3 router is a neighbor on a non-virtual interface implies that the 
     router is directly connected. An OSPFv3 router implementing this specification should ensure that the inadvertent
     connection of multiple router interfaces to the same physical link is not misconstrued as 
     detection of an OSPFv3 neighbor with a duplicate Router ID.</t> 
  </section> 
  <section anchor="INDIRECT-DETECT" title="Duplicate Router ID Detection for Non-neighbors"> 
  <t>OSPFv3 routers implementing autoconfiguration, as specified herein, MUST originate an Autoconfiguration (AC)
  Link State Advertisement (LSA) including the Router-Hardware-Fingerprint Type-Length-Value (TLV). 
  The Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV contains a variable-length value that has a very high probability of 
  uniquely identifying the advertising OSPFv3 router. An OSPFv3 router implementing this specification MUST detect
  received Autoconfiguration LSAs with its Router ID specified in the LSA header. LSAs received with the local 
  OSPFv3 Router's Router ID in the LSA header are perceived as self-originated (see 
  Section 4.6 of <xref target="OSPFV3"/>).
  In these received Autoconfiguration LSAs, the Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV is compared against the OSPFv3 Router's
  own router hardware fingerprint. If the fingerprints are not equal, there is a duplicate Router ID conflict
  and the OSPFv3 router with the numerically smaller router hardware fingerprint MUST select a new Router ID 
  as described in <xref target="RESOLUTION"/>.</t> 
  <t>This new LSA is designated for information related to OSPFv3 autoconfiguration and, in the future, could 
     be used for other autoconfiguration information, e.g., global IPv6 prefixes. However, this is beyond the
     scope of this document.</t>  
  <section anchor="AC-LSA" title="OSPFv3 Router Autoconfiguration LSA">
   <t>The OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA has a function code of 15 and the
   S2/S1 bits set to 01 indicating Area Flooding Scope. 
   The U bit will be set indicating that the OSPFv3 AC LSA should be
   flooded even if it is not understood.  The Link State ID (LSID) value
   will be an integer index used to discriminate between multiple AC LSAs 
   originated by the same OSPFv3 router. This specification only describes the
   contents of an AC LSA with an LSID of 0.</t>
   <t><figure title="OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA">
     <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |            LS age             |1|0|1|           15            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                       Link State ID                           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                       Advertising Router                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                       LS sequence number                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        LS checksum            |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    +-                            TLVs                             -+
    |                             ...                               |
      </artwork>
   </figure></t>

   <t>The format of the TLVs within the body of an AC LSA is the same as
       the format used by the Traffic Engineering Extensions to OSPFv2 <xref target="TE"/>.
       The LSA payload consists of one or more nested TLV triplets.  The format of each TLV is:</t>


   <t><figure title="TLV Format">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              Type             |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                            Value...                           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      </artwork>
   </figure></t>

   <t>The Length field defines the length of the value portion in octets
   (thus a TLV with no value portion would have a length of 0).  The TLV
   is padded to 4-octet alignment; padding is not included in the length
   field (so a 3-octet value would have a length of 3, but the total
   size of the TLV would be 8 octets).  Nested TLVs are also 32-bit
   aligned.  For example, a 1-byte value would have the length field set
   to 1, and 3 octets of padding would be added to the end of the value
   portion of the TLV.  Unrecognized types are ignored.</t>
  <t>The new LSA is designated for information related to OSPFv3 
     autoconfiguration and, in the future, can be used other 
     autoconfiguration information.</t>  
  </section>
  <section anchor="FINGER" title="Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV">
   <t>The Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV is the first TLV defined
      for the OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA. It will have type 1
      and MUST be advertised in the LSID OSPFv3 AC LSA with an LSID of 0. 
      It SHOULD occur, at most, once and the first instance of the
      TLV will take precedence over subsequent TLV instances. The 
      length of the Router-Hardware-Fingerprint is variable but must
      be 32 octets or greater. If the Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV is 
      not present as the first TLV, the AC LSA is considered malformed and
      is ignored for the purposes of duplicate Router ID detection. 
      Additionally, the event SHOULD be logged.</t>
   <t>The contents of the hardware fingerprint MUST have an extremely high
      probability of uniqueness.  It SHOULD be constructed from the 
      concatenation of a number of local values that themselves have a high
      likelihood of uniqueness, such as Media Access Control (MAC) addresses, CPU ID, or serial 
      numbers.  It is RECOMMENDED that one or more available universal 
      tokens (e.g., IEEE 802 48-bit MAC addresses or IEEE EUI-64 
      Identifiers <xref target="EUI64"/>) associated with the OSPFv3 router
      be included in the hardware fingerprint.  It MUST be based on
      hardware attributes that will not change across hard and soft
      restarts.</t>


   <t><figure title="Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV Format">
     <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              1                |             >32               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                    Router Hardware Fingerprint                |
                                   o
                                   o
                                   o
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      </artwork>
   </figure></t>
  </section>
  </section> 


  <section anchor="RESOLUTION" title="Duplicate Router ID Resolution"> 
   <t>The OSPFv3 router selected to resolve the duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID condition must select a new OSPFv3
      Router ID. The OSPFv3 router SHOULD reduce the possibility of a subsequent Router ID collision by 
      checking the Link State Database (LSDB) for an OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration LSA with the newly selected Router ID
      and a different Router-Hardware-Fingerprint. If one is detected, a new Router ID should be selected without
      going through the resolution process (<xref target="DUPLICATE"/>). 
      After selecting a new Router ID, all self-originated LSAs MUST be reoriginated, and any OSPFv3
      neighbor adjacencies MUST be reestablished. The OSPFv3 router retaining the Router ID causing the conflict
      will reoriginate or flush any stale self-originated LSAs as described in Section 13.4 of
   <xref target="OSPFV2"/>.</t>


  </section> 
  <section anchor="UPDATE-BACKOFF" title="Change to RFC 2328, Section 13.4 (&quot;Receiving Self-Originated LSAs&quot;)">
   <t>RFC 2328 <xref target="OSPFV2"/>, Section 13.4, describes the processing of received 
      self-originated LSAs. If the received LSA doesn't exist, the receiving router will flush
      it from the OSPF routing domain.  If the LSA is newer than the version in the LSDB, the receiving router will originate a newer version by advancing the 
      LSA sequence number and reoriginating.  Since it is possible for an autoconfigured OSPFv3 router
      to choose a duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID, OSPFv3 routers implementing this specification should
      detect when multiple instances of the same self-originated LSA are flushed or reoriginated since this
      is indicative of an OSPFv3 router with a duplicate Router ID in the OSPFv3 routing domain. When this
      condition is detected, the OSPFv3 router SHOULD delay self-originated LSA processing for LSAs 
      that have recently been flushed or reoriginated. This specification recommends 10 seconds as the interval
      defining recent self-originated LSA processing and an exponential back-off of 1 to 8 seconds for the
      processing delay. This additional delay should allow for the mechanisms described in 
      <xref target="DUPLICATE"/> to resolve the duplicate OSPFv3 Router ID conflict.</t>
    <t>Since this mechanism is useful in mitigating the flooding overhead associated with the
       inadvertent or malicious introduction of an OSPFv3 router with a duplicate Router ID into
       an OSPFv3 routing domain, it MAY be deployed outside of autoconfigured deployments. 
       The detection of a self-originated LSA that is being repeatedly
       reoriginated or flushed
       SHOULD be logged.</t> 
  </section> 
</section> 
<section anchor="SECURITY" title="Security Considerations">                        

<t> The goals of security and complete OSPFv3 autoconfiguration are
  somewhat contradictory. When no explicit security configuration takes
  place, autoconfiguration implies that additional devices placed in the network
  are automatically adopted as a part of the network. However,
  autoconfiguration can also be combined with password configuration (see <xref target="AUTH-CONFIG"/>) or
  future extensions for automatic pairing between devices. These mechanisms can
  help provide an automatically configured, securely routed network.</t>

<t>In deployments where a different authentication algorithm or encryption is
   required (or different per-interface keys are required), OSPFv3 IPsec <xref target="OSPFV3-IPSEC"/> or alternate OSPFv3 Authentication Trailer
   <xref target="OSPFV3-AUTH-TRAILER"/> algorithms MAY be used at the expense of additional 
   configuration. The configuration and operational description of such deployments 
   are beyond the scope of this document. However, a deployment could always revert to 
   explicit configuration as described in <xref target="MANAGEMENT"/> for features 
   such as IPsec, per-interface keys, or alternate authentication algorithms.</t>

<t>The introduction, either malicious or accidental, of an OSPFv3 router with a duplicate Router ID 
   is an attack point for OSPFv3 routing domains. This is due to the fact that OSPFv3 routers will
   interpret LSAs advertised by the router with the same Router ID as self-originated LSAs and attempt
   to flush them from the routing domain. The mechanisms in <xref target="UPDATE-BACKOFF"/> 
   will mitigate the effects of duplication.</t>

</section>


<section anchor="MANAGEMENT" title="Management Considerations">
<t>It is RECOMMENDED that OSPFv3 routers supporting this specification
  also support explicit configuration of OSPFv3 parameters as specified
  in Appendix C of <xref target="OSPFV3"/>. 
  This would allow explicit override of autoconfigured parameters in situations 
  where it is required (e.g., if the deployment requires multiple OSPFv3 areas).    
  This is in addition to the authentication key configuration recommended in 
  <xref target="AUTH-CONFIG"/>. Additionally, it is RECOMMENDED that OSPFv3
  routers supporting this specification allow autoconfiguration to be 
  completely disabled.</t>
<t>Since there is a small possibility of OSPFv3 Router ID collisions, manual
   configuration of OSPFv3 Router IDs is RECOMMENDED in OSPFv3 routing domains
   where route convergence due to a Router ID change is intolerable.</t>
<t>OSPFv3 routers supporting this specification MUST augment mechanisms for displaying 
   or otherwise conveying OSPFv3 operational state to indicate whether or not 
   the OSPFv3 router was autoconfigured and whether or not its OSPFv3 interfaces
   have been autoconfigured.</t>
</section>
<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This specification defines an OSPFv3 LSA Type for the 
   OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA, as described in <xref target="AC-LSA"/>. The value 15
   has been allocated from the existing "OSPFv3 LSA Function Codes" registry for the OSPFv3
   Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA.</t>
<t>This specification also creates a registry for OSPFv3 Autoconfiguration (AC) LSA TLVs. 
This registry has been placed in the existing OSPFv3 IANA registry, and new
values will be
allocated via IETF Review or, under exceptional circumstances, IESG Approval. 
<xref target="IANA-GUIDELINES"/></t>
<t>Three initial values are allocated:
   <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>0 is marked as Reserved.</t> 
     <t>1 is Router-Hardware-Fingerprint TLV (<xref target="FINGER"/>).</t>
    <t>65535 is an Autoconfiguration-Experiment-TLV, a common value that can be 
       used for experimental purposes.</t>
   </list></t>
 </section>
</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">

    <reference  anchor='RFC-KEYWORDS' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
    <front>
    <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1997' month='March' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='4723'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='OSPFV3' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5340'>
    <front>
    <title>OSPF for IPv6</title>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Coltun' fullname='R. Coltun'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Ferguson' fullname='D. Ferguson'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Moy' fullname='J. Moy'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='A.' surname='Lindem' fullname='A. Lindem'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2008' month='July' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5340'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='225664'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='OSPFV2' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2328'>
    <front>
    <title>OSPF Version 2</title>
    <author initials='J.' surname='Moy' fullname='J. Moy'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1998' month='April' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='STD' value='54'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2328'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='447367'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='SLAAC' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4862'>
    <front>
    <title>IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Thomson' fullname='S. Thomson'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Jinmei' fullname='T. Jinmei'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2007' month='September' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4862'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='72482'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='TE' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3630'>
    <front>
    <title>Traffic Engineering (TE) Extensions to OSPF Version 2</title>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Katz' fullname='D. Katz'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='K.' surname='Kompella' fullname='K. Kompella'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Yeung' fullname='D. Yeung'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2003' month='September' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3630'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='27717'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='OSPFV3-AF' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5838'>
    <front>
    <title>Support of Address Families in OSPFv3</title>
    <author initials='A.' surname='Lindem' fullname='A. Lindem' role='editor'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Mirtorabi' fullname='S. Mirtorabi'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='A.' surname='Roy' fullname='A. Roy'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Barnes' fullname='M. Barnes'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='R.' surname='Aggarwal' fullname='R. Aggarwal'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2010' month='April' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5838'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='26193'/>
    </reference>



    <reference  anchor='OSPFV3-AUTH-TRAILER' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7166'>
    <front>
    <title>Supporting Authentication Trailer for OSPFv3</title>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Bhatia' fullname='M. Bhatia'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='V.' surname='Manral' fullname='V. Manral'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='A.' surname='Lindem' fullname='A. Lindem'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2014' month='March' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7166'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='49533'/>
    </reference>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">


    <reference  anchor='IPv6-CPE' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7084'>
    <front>
    <title>Basic Requirements for IPv6 Customer Edge Routers</title>
    <author initials='H.' surname='Singh' fullname='H. Singh'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='W.' surname='Beebee' fullname='W. Beebee'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='C.' surname='Donley' fullname='C. Donley'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='B.' surname='Stark' fullname='B. Stark'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2013' month='November' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7084'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='46569'/>
    </reference>


    <reference  anchor='OSPFV3-IPSEC' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4552'>
    <front>
    <title>Authentication/Confidentiality for OSPFv3</title>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Gupta' fullname='M. Gupta'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='N.' surname='Melam' fullname='N. Melam'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2006' month='June' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4552'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='31540'/>
    </reference>

<!-- draft-madhukar-ospf-agr-asymmetric: Expired -->
<reference anchor="ASYNC-HELLO">

<front>
<title>Asymmetric OSPF Hold Timer</title>
<author initials="M" surname="Anand" fullname="Madhukar Anand">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="H." surname="Grover" fullname="Hasmit Grover">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Roy" fullname="Abhay Roy">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<date year='2013' month='June'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-madhukar-ospf-agr-asymmetric-01"/>
</reference>


    <reference  anchor='IANA-GUIDELINES' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5226'>
    <front>
    <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='H.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='H. Alvestrand'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2008' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='26'/>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5226'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='66160'/>
    </reference>

<reference anchor="EUI64" target="http://standards.ieee.org/regauth/oui/tutorials/EUI64.html">
<front>
<title>Guidelines for 64-bit Global Identifier (EUI-64)</title>
<author>
<organization>IEEE</organization>
</author>
<date year='1997' month='March'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Registration Authority" value="Tutorial"/>
</reference>
</references>

  <section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
   <t>This specification was inspired by the work presented in the HOMENET working group 
     meeting in October 2011 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. In particular, we would like
     to thank Fred Baker, Lorenzo Colitti, Ole Troan, Mark Townsley, and Michael Richardson.</t> 
    <t>Arthur Dimitrelis and Aidan Williams did prior work in OSPFv3 autoconfiguration in the 
       expired Internet-Draft titled "Autoconfiguration of routers using a link state routing protocol". 
       There are many similarities between the concepts and techniques in this document.</t>
    <t>Thanks for Abhay Roy and Manav Bhatia for comments regarding duplicate
    Router ID 
       processing.</t>
   <t>Thanks for Alvaro Retana and Michael Barnes for comments regarding OSPFv3 Instance
      ID autoconfiguration.</t>
   <t>Thanks to Faraz Shamim for review and comments.</t>
   <t>Thanks to Mark Smith for the requirement to reduce the adjacency formation delay in 
      the back-to-back ethernet topologies that are prevalent in home networks.</t>
   <t>Thanks to Les Ginsberg for document review and recommendations on OSPFv3 hardware
      fingerprint content.</t>
   <t>Thanks to Curtis Villamizar for document review and analysis of duplicate
      Router ID resolution nuances.</t> 
   <t>Thanks to Uma Chunduri for comments during OSPF WG last call.</t> 
   <t>Thanks to Martin Vigoureux for Routing Area Directorate review and comments.</t> 
   <t>Thanks to Adam Montville for Security Area Directorate review and comments.</t> 
   <t>Thanks to Qin Wu for Operations &amp; Management Area Directorate review and comments.</t> 
   <t>Thanks to Robert Sparks for General Area (GEN-ART) review and comments.</t>
   <t>Thanks to Rama Darbha for review and comments.</t>
   <t>Special thanks to Adrian Farrel for his in-depth review, copious comments, and suggested text.</t>
   <t>Special thanks go to Markus Stenberg for his implementation of this specification in Bird.</t> 
   <t>Special thanks also go to David Lamparter for his implementation of this specification in Quagga.</t> 
   <t>This document was initially produced using the xml2rfc tool.</t>
  </section>

</back>

</rfc>
