<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="7982" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
    <title abbrev="RTT and Fractional Loss">Measurement of Round-Trip
    Time and Fractional Loss Using&nbsp;Session&nbsp;Traversal&nbsp;Utilities&nbsp;for&nbsp;NAT&nbsp;(STUN)</title>
   
   <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 22</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1325</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>
          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="V." surname="Singh" fullname="Varun Singh">
      <organization abbrev="callstats.io">
        CALLSTATS I/O Oy
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Runeberginkatu 4c A 4</street>
          <code>00100</code> <city>Helsinki</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>varun@callstats.io</email>
        <uri>
          https://www.callstats.io/about
        </uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="September" year="2016" />

    <workgroup>TRAM</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        A host with multiple interfaces needs to choose the best
        interface for communication. Oftentimes, this decision is
        based on a static configuration and does not consider the path
        characteristics, which may affect the user experience.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document describes a mechanism for an endpoint to
        measure the path characteristics fractional loss and RTT
        using Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) messages.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        This document extends STUN <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> to
        make it possible to correlate STUN responses to specific
        requests when retransmits occur. This assists the client in
        determining path characteristics like round-trip time
        (RTT) and fractional packet loss.
      </t>
      <t>
        The TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute introduced in
        <xref target="new_attribute"/> can be used in <xref
        target="RFC5245">Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)</xref> connectivity checks (STUN Binding
        request and response). It can also be used with <xref
        target="RFC5766">Traversal Using Relays around NAT (TURN)</xref> by adding this attribute to
        Allocate requests and responses to measure loss and RTT
        between the client and the respective TURN server.
      </t>
      <t>
        ICE is a mechanism commonly used in Voice over IP (VoIP) applications to
        traverse NATs, and it uses a static prioritization formula to
        order the candidate pairs and perform connectivity checks, in
        which the most preferred address pairs are tested first, and
        when a sufficiently good pair is discovered, that pair is used
        for communications and then further connectivity tests are stopped.
      </t>
      <t>
        When multiple paths are available for communication, the
        endpoint sends ICE connectivity checks across each path
        (candidate pair). Choosing the path with the lowest round-trip
        time is a reasonable approach, but retransmits can cause an
        otherwise good path to appear flawed. However, STUN's
        retransmission algorithm <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> cannot
        determine the round-trip time (RTT) if a STUN request packet
        is retransmitted because each request and retransmission
        packet is identical. Further, several STUN requests may be
        sent before the connectivity between candidate pairs are
        ascertained (see Section 16 of <xref
        target="RFC5245"></xref>). 

   To resolve the issue of identical request and
   response packets in a STUN transaction, this document changes the
   retransmission behavior for idempotent packets.  Using the 
   mechanism described herein, a client can determine RTT as well as
   get a hint regarding which path direction caused packet loss.
   This is achieved by defining a new STUN attribute and requires 
   compliant STUN (TURN and ICE) endpoints to count request packets.

      </t>
      <t>
        The mechanisms described in this document can  be used by
        the controlling agent to influence the ICE candidate pair
        selection. How ICE will actually use this information to
        improve the active candidate pair selection is outside the
        scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification uses terminology defined in <xref
        target="RFC5245">ICE</xref> and STUN <xref
        target="RFC5389"></xref>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="alg_over"
             title="Measuring RTT and Fractional Loss">
      
      <t>
        This document defines a new comprehension-optional STUN
        attribute TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER with a STUN Type
        0x8025.  This type is in the comprehension-optional range,
        which means that STUN agents can safely ignore the
        attribute. If ICE is in use, it will fall back to normal
        procedures.
      </t>
      <t>
        If a client wishes to measure RTT, it inserts the
        TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute in a STUN request. In
        this attribute, the client sends the number of times the STUN
        request is transmitted with the same transaction ID. The
        server would echo back the transmission count in the response
        so that the client can distinguish between STUN responses coming
        from retransmitted requests. Hence, the endpoint can use the
        STUN requests and responses to determine the round-trip time
        (RTT). The server may also convey the number of responses it
        has sent for the STUN request to the client. Further, this
        information enables the client to get a hint regarding in which
        direction the packet loss occurred. In some cases, it is
        impossible to distinguish between packet reordering and packet
        loss. However, if this information is collected as network
        metrics from several clients over a longer time period, it will
        be easier to detect a pattern that can provide useful
        information.
      </t>

      <section anchor="new_attribute" 
               title="TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER Attribute">
        <t>
          The TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute in a STUN request
          takes a 32-bit value. This document updates one of the STUN
          message structuring rules explained in Section 6 of <xref
          target="RFC5389"></xref> wherein retransmission of the same request
          reuses the same transaction ID and is bit-wise identical to
          the previous request. For idempotent packets, the Req and
          Resp fields in the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute
          will be incremented by 1 by the client or server for every
          transmission with the same transaction ID. Any
          retransmitted STUN request MUST be bit-wise identical to
          the previous request except for the values in the
          TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute.
        </t>
        <t>
          The IANA-assigned STUN type for the new attribute is 0x8025.
        </t>
        <t>
          The format of the value in the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER
          attribute in the request is:
        </t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="att_in_request"
                  title=" TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER Attribute in Request">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Reserved (Padding)     |    Req        |     Resp      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>
          The fields are described below:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Req:">Number of times the request is
            transmitted with the same transaction ID to the
            server.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Resp:">Number of times a response with the same
            transaction ID is sent from the server. MUST be set to
            zero in requests and ignored by the receiver.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The padding is necessary to hit the 32-bit boundary needed
          for STUN attributes. The padding bits are ignored, but to
          allow for future reuse of these bits, they MUST be set to zero.
        </t>
      </section>
        
      <section title="Usage in Requests">
        <t>
          When sending a STUN request, the
          TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER Attribute allows a client to
          indicate to the server that it wants to measure RTT and get
          a hint about the direction of any packet loss. 
        </t>
        <t>
          The client MUST populate the Req value in the
          TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER. This value MUST reflect the
          number of requests that have been transmitted to the
          server. Therefore, the initial value for the first request sent is 1. The first retransmit will set the value to 2
          and so on. 
        </t>
        <t>
          The Resp field in the attribute MUST be set to zero in the
          request.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Usage in Responses">
        <t>
          When a server receives a STUN request that includes a
          TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute, it processes the
          request as per the <xref target="RFC5389">STUN
          protocol</xref> plus the specific rules mentioned here. The
          server checks the following:
        </t>

        <t><list style="symbols">


            <t>
              If the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute is not
              recognized, ignore the attribute because its type
              indicates that it is comprehension-optional. This
              should be the existing behavior as explained in Section
              7.3 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              The server that supports the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER
              attribute MUST echo back the Req field in the response
              using a TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute.
            </t>
            <t>
              If the server is stateless or does not want to remember
              the transaction ID, then it populates value 0 for
              the Resp field in the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute
              sent in the response. If the server is stateful, then it
              populates the Resp field with the number of responses it
              has sent for the STUN request.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          A client that receives a STUN response with a
          TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER can check the values in the Req
          field to accurately calculate the RTT if retransmits are
          occurring.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the server sending the STUN response is stateless, the
          value of the Resp field will always be 0. If the server
          keeps state of the numbers of STUN requests with that same
          transaction ID, the value will reflect how many packets the
          server has seen and responded to. This gives the client a
          hint about in which direction loss occurred. See <xref
          target="example_operation"/> for more details.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="example_operation" title="Example Operation">
        <t>
          An example operation, when a server is stateful, is described
          in <xref target="retransmit_op"></xref>. In the first case, all
          the requests and responses are received correctly. 
        </t>
        <t>
          In the case of upstream loss, the first request is lost, but
          the second one is received correctly. The client, upon
          receiving the response, notes that while two requests were
          sent, only one was received by the server. The server also
          realizes that the value in the Req field does not match the
          number of received requests, therefore one request was
          lost. This may also occur at startup in the presence of
          firewalls or NATs that block unsolicited incoming traffic.
        </t>
        <t>
          In the case of downstream loss, the responses get
          lost, the client expecting multiple responses notes that, while
          the server responded to three requests, only one response was
          received. 
        </t>
        <t>
          In the case of loss in both directions, requests and responses get
          lost in tandem, the server notes that one request packet was not
          received, while the client expecting three responses received
          only one, and then it notes that one request and response packet
          were lost.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure anchor="retransmit_op"
            title="Retransmit Operation between Client and Server">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
|     Normal    |  Upstream loss | Downstream loss | Both upstream &|
|               |                |                 | downstream loss|
| Client Server |  Client Server |  Client  Server |  Client Server |
|+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+|
| 1        1,1  |  1        x    |  1         1,1  |  1        x    |
|   1,1         |                |    x            |                |
|               |  2        2,1  |  2         2,2  |  2        2,1  |
|               |    2,1         |    x            |    x           |
|               |                |  3         3,3  |  3        3,2  |
|               |                |    3,3          |    3,2         |
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
        <t>
          Another example is when the client sends two requests but
          the second request arrives at the server before the first
          request because of out-of-order delivery. In this case, the
          stateful server populates value 1 for the Resp field
          in the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute sent in response
          to the second request and value 2 for the Resp field
          in the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute sent in response
          to the first request.
        </t>
        <t>
          The intention with this mechanism is not to carry out
          comprehensive and accurate measurements regarding in what
          direction loss is occurring. In some cases, it might not be
          able to distinguish the difference between downstream loss and
          packet reordering.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>This document defines the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER STUN attribute,
      described in <xref target="alg_over"></xref>. IANA has allocated
      the comprehension-optional codepoint 0x8025 for this
      attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Security considerations discussed in <xref
        target="RFC5389"></xref> are to be taken into account. STUN
        requires that the 96-bit transaction ID be uniformly and
        randomly chosen from the interval 0 .. 2**96-1, and be
        cryptographically strong. This is good enough security against
        an off-path attacker. An on-path attacker can either inject a
        fake response or modify the values in the
        TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute to mislead the client
        and server. This attack can be mitigated using STUN
        authentication. As the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER is expected to
        be used between peers using ICE, and ICE uses a STUN short-term
        credential mechanism, the risk of an on-path attack influencing
        the messages is minimal. 

   If the TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER is used with an Allocate request,
   one of the following mechanisms can be used to prevent attackers from 
   trying to impersonate a TURN server and sending a bogus
   TRANSACTION_TRANSMIT_COUNTER attribute in the Allocate response:
   1)&nbsp;the STUN long-term credential mechanism, 2) the STUN Extension for
   Third-Party Authorization <xref target="RFC7635"/>, or 3) a TLS or DTLS connection 
   between the TURN client and the TURN server.


 However, an attacker could corrupt, remove, or delay
        an ICE request or response, in order to discourage that path
        from being used.
      </t>
      <t>
        If not encrypted, the information sent in any STUN packet can
	potentially be observed passively and used for reconnaissance and later attacks.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"  ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5766"  ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7635"  ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>Thanks to Brandon Williams, Simon Perreault, Aijun Wang,
      Martin Thomson, Oleg Moskalenko, Ram Mohan Ravindranath, Spencer Dawkins,
      Suresh Krishnan, Ben Campbell, Mirja Kuehlewind, Lionel Morand, Kathleen Moriarty,
      and Alissa Cooper for their valuable input and comments.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
