<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

]>


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
	
<rfc number="7908"
     category="info" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Route-Leak Problem Definition">Problem Definition and Classification of BGP Route Leaks</title>

       <author fullname="Kotikalapudi Sriram" initials="K." surname="Sriram">
      <organization>US NIST</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ksriram@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>
        <author fullname="Doug Montgomery" initials="D." surname="Montgomery">
      <organization>US NIST</organization>

      <address>
        <email>dougm@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>

      <author fullname="Danny McPherson" initials="D." surname="McPherson">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>dmcpherson@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
        <author fullname="Eric Osterweil" initials="E." surname="Osterweil">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>eosterweil@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Brian Dickson" initials="B." surname="Dickson">
       <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>brian.peter.dickson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 

    <date month="June" year="2016" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>

    <keyword>BGP, BGPSEC, Route Leak, Route Leak Detection, Route Leak Mitigation, BGP Security</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
A systemic vulnerability of the Border Gateway Protocol routing system, known
as "route leaks", has received significant attention in recent years. Frequent
incidents that result in significant disruptions to Internet routing are
labeled route leaks, but to date a common definition of the term has been
lacking. This document provides a working definition of route leaks while
keeping in mind the real occurrences that have received significant
attention. Further, this document attempts to enumerate (though not
exhaustively) different types of route leaks based on observed events on the
Internet. The aim is to provide a taxonomy that covers several forms of route
leaks that have been observed and are of concern to the Internet user community as well as the network operator community.
   </t>
 
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      
       <t>
 </t>

 <t>

Frequent incidents <xref target="Huston2012"></xref> <xref target="Cowie2013"></xref> <xref target="Toonk2015-A"></xref> <xref target="Toonk2015-B"></xref> <xref target="Cowie2010"></xref> <xref target="Madory"></xref> <xref target="Zmijewski"></xref> <xref target="Paseka"></xref> <xref target="LRL"></xref> <xref target="Khare"></xref> that result in significant disruptions to Internet routing are commonly called "route leaks". Examination of the details of some of these incidents reveals that they vary in their form and technical details. In order to pursue solutions to "the route-leak problem" it is important to first provide a clear, technical definition of the problem and enumerate its most common forms.  
<xref target="definition"></xref> provides a working definition of route
leaks, keeping in view many recent incidents that have received significant
attention. <xref target="types"></xref> attempts to enumerate (though not
exhaustively) different types of route leaks based on observed events on the
Internet. Further, <xref target="types"></xref> provides a taxonomy that
covers several forms of route leaks that have been observed and are of concern
to the Internet user community as well as the network operator community. This document builds on and extends earlier work in the IETF <xref target="ROUTE-LEAK-DEF"></xref> <xref target="ROUTE-LEAK-REQ"></xref>.     

	 </t>
 
	
</section>


<section anchor="definition" title="Working Definition of Route Leaks">

<t>
A proposed working definition of "route leak" is as follows: 
 </t>
<!-- A route leak occurs when an offending AS propagates a route to a neighbor AS in violation of its own or neighbor AS's routing policy, where the route in question was learned from another neighbor AS or it may be internal (i.e., meant for only internal use within the offending AS). The routing policy (that is violated) may be implicit (i.e. commonly understood practice) or explicitly agreed to between the ASes involved. --> 
<t>

A route leak is the propagation of routing announcement(s) beyond their
intended scope. That is, an announcement from an Autonomous System (AS) of a
learned BGP route to another AS is in violation of the intended policies of
the receiver, the sender, and/or one of the ASes along the preceding AS
path. The intended scope is usually defined by a set of local
redistribution/filtering policies distributed among the ASes involved. Often,
these intended policies are defined in terms of the pair-wise peering business
relationship between ASes (e.g., customer, transit provider, peer). For
literature related to AS relationships and routing policies, see <xref
target="Gao"></xref>, <xref target="Luckie"></xref>, and <xref
target="Gill"></xref>. For measurements of valley-free violations in Internet
routing, see <xref target="Anwar"></xref>, <xref target="Giotsas"></xref>, and <xref target="Wijchers"></xref>.
</t>
<t>

The result of a route leak can be redirection of traffic through an unintended
path that may enable eavesdropping or traffic analysis and may or may not
result in an overload or black hole. Route leaks can be accidental or malicious but most often arise from accidental misconfigurations.
 </t>
<t>

The above definition is not intended to be all encompassing. Our aim here is to have a working definition that fits enough observed incidents so that the IETF community has a basis for developing solutions for route-leak detection and mitigation. 
</t>

</section>
	  <section anchor="types" title="Classification of Route Leaks Based on Documented Events">
<t>

As illustrated in <xref target="fig1"></xref>, a common form of route leak occurs when a multihomed customer AS (such as AS3 in <xref target="fig1"></xref>) learns a prefix update from one transit provider (ISP1) and leaks the update to another transit provider (ISP2) in violation of intended routing policies, and further, the second transit provider does not detect the leak and propagates the leaked update to its customers, peers, and transit ISPs. 
</t>

<t>

<figure align="center" anchor="fig1" title="Basic Notion of a Route Leak">
  <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                                   /\              /\
                                    \ route leak(P)/
                                     \ propagated / 
                                      \          /  
           +------------+    peer    +------------+
     ______| ISP1 (AS1) |----------->|  ISP2 (AS2)|---------->
    /       ------------+  prefix(P) +------------+ route leak(P)
   | prefix |          \   update      /\        \  propagated
    \  (P)  /           \              /          \
     -------   prefix(P) \            /            \   
                  update  \          /              \          
                           \        /route leak(P)  \/
                           \/      /
                        +---------------+
                        | customer(AS3) |
                        +---------------+

]]></artwork>
 </figure>

</t>

<t>


This document proposes the following taxonomy to cover several types of observed route leaks while acknowledging that the list is not meant to be exhaustive. In what follows, the AS that announces a route that is in violation of the intended policies is referred to as the "offending AS". 

<!-- In the following descriptions, when we use the term "U-turn", it basically means a hairpin-like turn, i.e., an update goes down towards a customer AS from a transit-provider AS and goes back up from the customer AS via another transit-provider AS. -->   
</t>


  <section anchor="type1" title="Type 1: Hairpin Turn with Full Prefix">


<t>
Description: A multihomed AS learns a route from one upstream ISP and simply
propagates it to another upstream ISP (the turn essentially resembling a
hairpin). Neither the prefix nor the AS path in the update is altered. This is
similar to a straightforward path-poisoning attack <xref
target="Kapela-Pilosov"></xref>, but with full prefix. It should be noted that
leaks of this type are often accidental (i.e., not malicious). The update
basically makes a hairpin turn at the offending AS's multihomed AS. The leak
often succeeds (i.e., the leaked update is accepted and propagated) because the second ISP prefers customer announcement over peer announcement of the same prefix. Data packets would reach the legitimate destination, albeit via the offending AS, unless they are dropped at the offending AS due to its inability to handle resulting large volumes of traffic.
</t>

<t> <list style="symbols">

<t>
 
Example incidents: Examples of Type 1 route-leak incidents are (1) the Dodo-Telstra incident in March 2012 <xref target="Huston2012"></xref>, (2) the VolumeDrive-Atrato incident in September 2014 <xref target="Madory"></xref>, and (3) the massive Telekom Malaysia route leak of about 179,000 prefixes, which in turn Level3 accepted and propagated <xref target="Toonk2015-B"></xref>. 
</t>
</list> </t>
</section>


<section anchor="type2" title="Type 2: Lateral ISP-ISP-ISP Leak">
<t>
Description: The term "lateral" here is synonymous with "non-transit" or "peer-to-peer". This type of route leak typically occurs when, for example, three sequential ISP peers (e.g., ISP-A, ISP-B, and ISP&nbhy;C) are involved, and ISP-B receives a route from ISP-A and in turn leaks it to ISP-C. The typical routing policy between laterally (i.e., non-transit) peering ISPs is that they should only propagate to each other their respective customer prefixes.
</t>
<t> <list style="symbols">
<t>
Example incidents: In <xref target="Mauch-nanog"></xref> and <xref
target="Mauch"></xref>, route leaks of this type are reported by monitoring
updates in the global BGP system and finding three or more very large ISPs'
Autonomous System Numbers (ASNs) in a sequence in a BGP update's AS path. <xref target="Mauch"></xref> observes that its detection algorithm detects for these anomalies and potentially route leaks because very large ISPs do not, in general, buy transit services from each other. However, it also notes that there are exceptions when one very large ISP does indeed buy transit from another very large ISP, and 
accordingly, exceptions are made in its detection algorithm for known cases. 
</t>
</list> </t>
</section>

<section anchor="type3" title="Type 3: Leak of Transit-Provider Prefixes to Peer">
<t>
Description: This type of route leak occurs when an offending AS leaks routes learned from its transit provider to a lateral (i.e., non-transit) peer.
</t>
<t> <list style="symbols">
<t>
Example incidents: The incidents reported in <xref target="Mauch"></xref> include Type&nbsp;3 leaks.     
</t>
</list> </t>   
 </section>

<section anchor="type4" title="Type 4: Leak of Peer Prefixes to Transit Provider">
<t>
Description: This type of route leak occurs when an offending AS leaks routes learned from a lateral (i.e., non-transit) peer to its (the AS's) own transit provider. These leaked routes typically originate from the customer cone of the lateral peer.
</t>
<t> <list style="symbols">
<t>
Example incidents: Examples of Type 4 route-leak incidents are (1) the
Axcelx-Hibernia route leak of Amazon Web Services (AWS) prefixes causing
disruption of AWS and a variety of services that run on AWS <xref
target="Kephart"></xref>, (2) the Hathway-Airtel route leak of 336 Google prefixes causing widespread interruption of Google services in Europe and Asia <xref target="Toonk2015-A"></xref>, (3) the Moratel-PCCW route leak of Google prefixes causing Google's services to go offline <xref target="Paseka"></xref>, and (4) some of the example incidents cited for Type 1 route leaks above are also inclusive of Type 4 route leaks. For instance, in the Dodo-Telstra incident <xref target="Huston2012"></xref>, the leaked routes from Dodo to Telstra included routes that Dodo learned from its transit providers as well as lateral peers.      
</t>
</list> </t>

 </section>

<section anchor="type5" title="Type 5: Prefix Re-origination with Data Path to Legitimate Origin">

<t>
Description: A multihomed AS learns a route from one upstream ISP and
announces the prefix to another upstream ISP as if it is being originated by
it (i.e., strips the received AS path and re-originates the prefix). This can
be called re-origination or mis-origination. However, somehow a reverse path
to the legitimate origination AS may be present and data packets reach the
legitimate destination albeit via the offending AS. (Note: The presence of a
reverse path here is not attributable to the use of a path-poisoning trick by the offending AS.) But sometimes the reverse path may not be present, and data packets destined for the leaked prefix may be simply discarded at the offending AS.
 
</t>
<t> <list style="symbols">
<t>
Example incidents: Examples of Type 5 route leak include (1) the China Telecom incident in April 2010 <xref target="Hiran"></xref> <xref target="Cowie2010"></xref> <xref target="Labovitz"></xref>, (2) the Belarusian GlobalOneBel route-leak incidents in February-March 2013 and May 2013 <xref target="Cowie2013"></xref>, (3) the Icelandic Opin Kerfi-Simmin route-leak incidents in July-August 2013 <xref target="Cowie2013"></xref>, and (4) the Indosat route-leak incident in April 2014 <xref target="Zmijewski"></xref>. The reverse paths (i.e., data paths from the offending AS to the legitimate destinations) were present in incidents #1, #2, and #3 cited above, but not in incident #4. In incident #4, the misrouted data packets were dropped at Indosat's AS.  
</t>
</list> </t>
</section>

<section anchor="type6" title="Type 6: Accidental Leak of Internal Prefixes and More-Specific Prefixes">

<t>
Description: An offending AS simply leaks its internal prefixes to one or more
of its transit-provider ASes and/or ISP peers. The leaked internal prefixes
are often more-specific prefixes subsumed by an already announced, less-specific
prefix. The more-specific prefixes were not intended to be routed in
External BGP (eBGP). Further, the AS receiving those leaks fails to filter them. Typically, these leaked announcements are due to some transient failures within the AS; they are short-lived and typically withdrawn quickly following the announcements. However, these more-specific prefixes may momentarily cause the routes to be preferred over other aggregate (i.e., less specific) route announcements, thus redirecting traffic from its normal best path. 
</t> 
<t> <list style="symbols">

<t>
Example incidents: Leaks of internal routes occur frequently (e.g., multiple
times in a week), and the number of prefixes leaked range from hundreds to
thousands per incident. One highly conspicuous and widely disruptive leak of
internal routes happened in August 2014 
when AS701 and AS705 leaked about 22,000 more-specific prefixes of already-announced aggregates <xref target="Huston2014"></xref> <xref target="Toonk2014"></xref>.
</t>
</list> </t>
</section>
</section>


<section anchor="Comments" title="Additional Comments about the Classification">

<t>
It is worth noting that Types 1 through 4 are similar in that a route is leaked in violation of policy in each case, but what varies is the context of the leaked-route source AS and destination AS roles.
</t>

<t>
A Type 5 route leak (i.e., prefix mis-origination with data path to legitimate origin) can also happen in conjunction with the AS relationship contexts in Types 2, 3, and 4. While these possibilities are acknowledged, simply enumerating more types to consider all such special cases does not add value as far as solution development for route leaks is concerned. Hence, the special cases mentioned here are not included in enumerating route-leak types.
</t>


</section>
<!--
<section anchor="Summary" title="Summary">
<t>
We attempted to provide a working definition of route leak. We also presented a taxonomy for categorizing route leaks. It covers not all but at least several forms of route leaks that have been observed and are of concern to Internet user and network operator communities. We hope that this work provides the IETF community a basis for pursuing possible BGP enhancements for route leak detection and mitigation. 
</t>
    </section>
-->

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    	<t>No security considerations apply since this is a problem definition document.

	</t>
      
    </section>
	</middle> 
  

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>


    <references title="Informative References">


<reference anchor="Huston2012" target="http://labs.apnic.net/blabs/?p=139/">
        <front>
        <title>Leaking Routes</title>

         <author initials="G." surname="Huston">
 <organization></organization>
  </author>
<date month='March' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Asia Pacific Network Information Centre (APNIC)"
	    value="Blog" />
     </reference> 

<reference anchor="Huston2014" target="http://labs.apnic.net/blabs/?p=520/">
        <front>
        <title>What's so special about 512?</title>

<author initials="G." surname="Huston">
 <organization></organization>
  </author>
<date month='September' year='2014' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Asia Pacific Network Information Centre (APNIC)" value="Blog"/>
     </reference> 

<reference anchor="Toonk2014" target="http://www.bgpmon.net/what-caused-todays-internet-hiccup/">
        <front>
        <title>What caused today's Internet hiccup</title>
	<author initials="A." surname="Toonk">
 <organization></organization>
  </author>
<date month='August' year='2014' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BGPMON" value="Blog"/>
     </reference> 

<reference anchor="Toonk2015-A" target="http://www.bgpmon.net/what-caused-the-google-service-interruption/">
        <front>
       <title>What caused the Google service interruption</title>
<author initials="A." surname="Toonk">
 <organization></organization>
  </author>
<date month='March' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BGPMON" value="Blog"/>
     </reference>

<reference anchor="Toonk2015-B" target="http://www.bgpmon.net/massive-route-leak-cause-internet-slowdown/">
        <front>
        <title>Massive route leak causes Internet slowdown</title>
<author initials="A." surname="Toonk">
 <organization></organization>
  </author>
<date month='June' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BGPMON" value="Blog"/>
     </reference> 


  <reference anchor="Paseka" target="http://blog.cloudflare.com/why-google-went-offline-today-and-a-bit-about/">
        <front>
          <title>Why Google Went Offline Today and a Bit about How the Internet Works</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Paseka">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='November' year='2012' />
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="CloudFlare" value="Blog"/>
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Cowie2010" target="http://research.dyn.com/2010/11/chinas-18-minute-mystery/">
        <front>
          <title>China's 18 Minute Mystery</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Cowie">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
     <date month='November' year='2010' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo  name='Dyn Research: The New Home of Renesys' value="Blog"/> 
      </reference>

  <reference anchor="Hiran" target="http://www3.cs.stonybrook.edu/~phillipa/papers/CTelecom.html">
        <front>
          <title>Characterizing Large-Scale Routing Anomalies: A Case Study of the China Telecom Incident</title>
          
<author initials="R." surname="Hiran">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="N." surname="Carlsson">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="P." surname="Gill">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <date month='March' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='In Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on
			  Passive and Active Measurement (PAM)' value='2013'/>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-642-36516-4_23"/>
	
      </reference>

 <reference anchor="Anwar" target="http://www.cs.usc.edu/assets/007/94928.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Investigating Interdomain Routing Policies in the Wild</title>
<author initials="R." surname="Anwar">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="H." surname="Niaz">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="D." surname="Choffnes">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="I." surname="Cunha">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="P." surname="Gill">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
<author initials="N." surname="Katz-Bassett">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='October' year='2015' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='In Proceedings of the 2015 ACM' value='Internet Measurement Conference (IMC)' /> 
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2815675.2815712"/>
      </reference>


 <reference anchor="Cowie2013" target="http://research.dyn.com/2013/11/mitm-internet-hijacking/">
        <front>
          <title>The New Threat: Targeted Internet Traffic Misdirection</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Cowie">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
        <date month='November' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Dyn Research: The New Home of Renesys' value='Blog' /> 
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Labovitz" target="http://www.arbornetworks.com/asert/2010/11/additional-discussion-of-the-april-china-bgp-hijack-incident/">
        <front>
          <title>Additional Discussion of the April China BGP Hijack Incident</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Labovitz">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='November' year='2010' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Arbor Networks IT Security' value='Blog' /> 
      </reference>





      <reference anchor="Khare" target="http://www.cs.arizona.edu/~bzhang/paper/12-imc-hijack.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Concurrent Prefix Hijacks: Occurrence and Impacts</title>
          <author initials="V." surname="Khare">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Q." surname="Ju">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Zhang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <date month='November' year='2012' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='In Proceedings of the 2013 ACM' 
		    value='Internet Measurement Conference (IMC)' /> 
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2398776.2398780" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="LRL" target="http://nrl.cs.arizona.edu/projects/lsrl-events-from-2003-to-2009/">
        <front>
          <title>Large Route Leaks</title>
          <author initials="V." surname="Khare">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Q." surname="Ju">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Zhang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <date year='2012' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='University of Arizona (UA) Network Research Lab:' value='Projects Webpage' /> 
      </reference>


    <reference anchor="Mauch" target="http://puck.nether.net/bgp/leakinfo.cgi/">
        <front>
          <title>BGP Routing Leak Detection System</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mauch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
   <date year='2014' />

        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='' value='Project web page' /> 
      </reference>


<reference anchor="Mauch-nanog" target="https://www.nanog.org/meetings/nanog41/presentations/mauch-lightning.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Detecting Routing Leaks by Counting</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mauch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
 <date month='October' year='2007' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='41st NANOG' value='Conference' /> 
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Kapela-Pilosov" target="https://www.defcon.org/images/defcon-16/dc16-presentations/defcon-16-pilosov-kapela.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Stealing the Internet: An Internet-Scale Man in the Middle Attack</title>
          <author initials="A." surname="Pilosov">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="T." surname="Kapela">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <date month='August' year='2008' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='16th Defcon' value='Conference' /> 
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Kephart" target="https://blog.thousandeyes.com/route-leak-causes-amazon-and-aws-outage">
        <front>
          <title>Route Leak Causes Amazon and AWS Outage</title>
          <author initials="N." surname="Kephart">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <date month='June' year='2015' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='ThousandEyes' value='Blog' /> 
      </reference>


<reference anchor="Madory" target="http://research.dyn.com/2014/09/why-the-internet-broke-today/">
        <front>
          <title>Why Far-Flung Parts of the Internet Broke Today</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Madory">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <date month='September' year='2014' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Dyn Research: The New Home of Renesys' value='Blog' /> 
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Zmijewski" target="http://research.dyn.com/2014/04/indonesia-hijacks-world/">
        <front>
          <title>Indonesia Hijacks the World</title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Zmijewski">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <date month='April' year='2014' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Dyn Research: The New Home of Renesys' value='Blog' /> 
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Wijchers" target="http://ripe69.ripe.net/presentations/157-RIPE-69-Routing-WG.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Quantitative Analysis of BGP Route Leaks </title>
          
	  <author initials="B." surname="Wijchers">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="B." surname="Overeinder">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='November' year='2014' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Reseaux IP Europeens (RIPE)' value='69th Meeting' /> 
      </reference> 


 <reference anchor="Giotsas" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Valley-free violation in Internet routing - Analysis based on BGP Community data</title>
          <author initials="V." surname="Giotsas">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="S." surname="Zhou">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='June' year='2012' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='2012 IEEE International Conference on Communications' value='(ICC)' /> 
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/ICC.2012.6363987"/>
      </reference> 


  <reference anchor="Luckie" target="http://www.caida.org/~amogh/papers/asrank-IMC13.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>AS Relationships, Customer Cones, and Validation</title>
      	  <author initials="M." surname="Luckie">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="B." surname="Huffaker">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="A." surname="Dhamdhere">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="V." surname="Giotsas">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="kc" surname="claffy">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='October' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='In Proceedings of the 2013 ACM Internet
			  Measurement Conference' value='(IMC)' />
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2504730.2504735" />
      </reference> 

<reference anchor="Gao" target="http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~jrex/papers/sigmetrics00.long.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Stable Internet Routing Without Global Coordination</title>
          <author initials="L." surname="Gao">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="J." surname="Rexford">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='December' year='2001' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (TON),'
		    value='Volume 9, Issue 6, pp 689-692' /> 
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/90.974523" />
      </reference> 


<reference anchor="Gill" target="http://www.cs.bu.edu/~goldbe/papers/survey.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>A Survey of Interdomain Routing Policies</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Gill">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="M." surname="Schapira">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="S." surname="Goldberg">
          <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month='January' year='2014' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review,'
		    value='Volume 44, Issue 1, pp 28-34'/>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2567561.2567566" />
      </reference>

<!-- draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-def-03: I-D Expired -->

<reference anchor='ROUTE-LEAK-DEF'>
<front>
<title>Route Leaks -- Definitions</title>

<author initials='B' surname='Dickson' fullname='Brian Dickson'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-def-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-def-03.txt' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-reqts-02: I-D Expired -->

<reference anchor='ROUTE-LEAK-REQ'>
<front>
<title>Route Leaks -- Requirements for Detection and Prevention thereof</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Dickson' fullname='Brian Dickson'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2012' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-reqts-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-dickson-sidr-route-leak-reqts-02.txt' />
</reference>
       
</references>
       
<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>The authors wish to thank Jared Mauch, Jeff Haas, Warren Kumari, Amogh
Dhamdhere, Jakob Heitz, Geoff Huston, Randy Bush, Job Snijders, Ruediger Volk, 
Andrei Robachevsky, Charles van Niman, Chris Morrow, and Sandy Murphy
for comments, suggestions, and critique. The authors are also thankful to Padma Krishnaswamy, Oliver Borchert, and Okhee Kim for their
comments and review.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>


