<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="7972" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
     category="info" obsoletes="7302">

	<front>
		<title  abbrev='EIDR URN Namespace Definition'>Entertainment Identifier Registry (EIDR) URN Namespace Definition</title>
		<author initials='P.-A.' surname='Lemieux' fullname='Pierre-Anthony Lemieux'>
			<organization>Sandflow Consulting LLC</organization>
			<address>
				<email>pal@sandflow.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date month='September' year='2016' />

		<area>General</area>

		<keyword>EIDR</keyword>
		<keyword>Entertainment Identifier Registry</keyword>
		<keyword>URN</keyword>

		<abstract>
			<t>Entertainment Identifier Registry (EIDR) Identifiers are used for the globally unique identification of motion picture and television content. This document defines the formal Uniform Resource Name (URN) Namespace Identifier (NID) for EIDR Identifiers.</t>
			<t>This document obsoletes RFC
			7302.</t>
<!-- [rfced] Please note that we have moved the reference to the Appendix from
the Abstract to the Introduction.  The Abstract will appear separately from
the document (e.g., search results), so it should be self-contained.  The
updates are described below.  Please let us know if you have any concerns. 

Original in the Abstract:
   This document obsoletes Request For Comments (RFC) 7302 - see
   Appendix A for a summary of changes.

Current in the Abstract:
   This document obsoletes Request For Comments (RFC) 7302.

Current in the Introduction:
   This document defines the formal Uniform Resource Name (URN)
   Namespace Identifier (NID) for EIDR Identifiers.  This document
   obsoletes RFC 7302.  See Appendix A for a summary of changes.

-->

		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section anchor='intro' title='Introduction'>
			<t>This document defines the formal Uniform Resource
			Name (URN) Namespace Identifier (NID) for EIDR
			Identifiers.</t>
			<t>EIDR Identifiers are centrally registered, globally unique identifiers for audiovisual works and their variants, primarily film and television. A unique set of metadata parameters describing the associated work is bound to the EIDR Identifier at the time of registration.</t>

			<t>EIDR Identifiers are a special kind of
			DOI Name
			allocated by EIDR Association specifically for
			audiovisual works. The Digital Object Identifier (DOI)
			system provides an infrastructure for persistent
			unique identification of objects of any type and is
			specified in <xref target='ISO26234' />. A DOI Name is
			the identifier that is permanently assigned to an
			object. The use of DOI Names ensures persistence,
			global uniqueness, and an open resolution
			infrastructure.</t>


			<t>As a DOI Name, an EIDR Identifier has two
			components: a prefix assigned exclusively to EIDR
			Association by the DOI Registration Authority and a
			suffix defined by EIDR Association. Currently, EIDR Identifiers use the prefix "10.5240", but additional prefixes might be introduced in the future.</t>

			<t>The following is an example of an EIDR Identifier in its canonical representation:
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
                10.5240/7791-8534-2C23-9030-8610-5]]>
</artwork></figure>
						 where "10.5240" is the prefix and "7791-8534-2C23-9030-8610-5" is the suffix. The canonical URN representation of the same EIDR Identifier is:
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
                urn:eidr:10.5240:7791-8534-2C23-9030-8610-5]]>
</artwork></figure>
						 Note that ":" is used as
			separator between the prefix and the suffix since "/"
			is a URN reserved character.</t>


			<t>
				<xref target='EIDR-OVERVIEW'/> and <xref target='EIDR-INTRO'/> provide additional background information.</t>
                
            <t>This document obsoletes RFC 7302. See <xref target="changes"/> for a summary of changes.</t>

		</section>
		<section title='Completed URN Namespace Definition Template' anchor="reg_template">
			<t> The namespace definition according to the template in <xref target='RFC3406'/> is as follows:</t>
			<t>Namespace ID:
				<list>
					<t>eidr</t>
				</list>		
			</t>

			<t>Registration Information:
				<list>
					<t>Version 1</t>
					<t>2014-03-03</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>Declared registrant of the namespace:
				<list>
					<t>Name:<list>
							<t>Entertainment Identifier Registry Association</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>Address:<list>
							<t>c/o Alliances Management<vspace/>544 Hillside Road<vspace/>Redwood City, CA 94062<vspace/>USA</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>Contact:<list>
							<t>URL: http://eidr.org/contact/<vspace/>Email: info@eidr.org</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Declaration of syntactic structure:
				<list>
					<t>An EIDR Identifier is a special
					kind of DOI Name (see <xref
					target='ISO26234' />) and, as such,
					consists of two components: a prefix
					denoted EIDR-PREFIX and a
					suffix denoted EIDR-SUFFIX. The URN
					representation URN-EIDR of an EIDR
					Identifier conforms to the syntax
					(expressed using <xref
					target='RFC5234'/>): 
<figure>
<artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
                URN-EIDR = "urn:eidr:" EIDR-NSS
                EIDR-NSS = EIDR-PREFIX ":" EIDR-SUFFIX
                EIDR-PREFIX = 1*EIDR-CHARS
                EIDR-SUFFIX = 1*EIDR-CHARS
                EIDR-CHARS = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "." / "_"
]]></artwork></figure>
					</t>

					<t>The only value of EIDR-PREFIX currently in use is "10.5240".
Additional prefix values conforming to the EIDR-PREFIX syntax might be
introduced by EIDR Association in the future. In all cases, each of these
additional prefix values will be associated with suffix
values that conform to a subset of the EIDR-SUFFIX syntax. These
additional prefixes and their corresponding suffixes will be
documented in future revisions to this registration.</t>

<t>An implementation
can process an EIDR-NSS with an unknown prefix as an opaque string per
the "Rules of Lexical Equivalence" below, and resolve it as a
generic DOI Name per the "Process for identifier resolution" below.</t>

<t>When EIDR-PREFIX is equal to "10.5240", the syntax of EIDR-SUFFIX is
further constrained according to the RP2079-SUFFIX syntax specified in
<xref target='SMPTERP2079'/>:<figure><artwork><![CDATA[

                RP2079-SUFFIX = 5(4HEXDIG "-") CHECK
                CHECK         = DIGIT / ALPHA
]]></artwork></figure>
							where CHECK is the Mod 37,36 check character as specified in <xref target='ISO7064'/>, computed over the 20 hexadecimal digits HEXDIG of RP2079-SUFFIX.</t>

					<t>EXAMPLE: urn:eidr:10.5240:7791-8534-2C23-9030-8610-5</t>

				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>Relevant ancillary documentation:
				<list>
					<t>
						<xref target='ISO26234' /> specifies DOI Name syntax and registration.</t>
					<t>
						<xref target='SMPTERP2079' />
					specifies the syntax of the EIDR Identifier with the prefix "10.5240".</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Identifier uniqueness considerations:

				<list>
					<t>An EIDR Identifier is a DOI Name. The ISO 26324 Registration Authority ensures
					DOI Name uniqueness; therefore, the URN-EIDR derived from an EIDR
					Identifier is guaranteed to be unique and never reassigned.</t>
					<t>Furthermore, an EIDR Identifier is associated with a single URN-EIDR.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Identifier persistence considerations:

				<list>
					<t>An EIDR Identifier is a DOI Name. The ISO 26324 Registration Authority ensures that a DOI Name remains valid indefinitely;
					therefore, the URN-EIDR derived from an EIDR Identifier remains valid indefinitely.</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>Process of identifier assignment:

				<list>
					<t>EIDR Association registers each EIDR Identifier with the ISO 26324 Registration Authority.</t>

					<t>Entities involved in the motion picture and television industry, either directly in the production of content or in its distribution and related services, are eligible to apply for registrant status. Registrants pay an annual membership fee that depends on the size of the company.</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>Process for identifier resolution:

				<list>
					<t>As a DOI Name, the resolution of the EIDR Identifier associated with an EIDR-NSS is handled by the ISO 26324 Registration Authority.</t>

					<t>The ISO 26324 Registration Authority operates a web service that allows the EIDR Identifier associated with an EIDR-NSS to be resolved by issuing an HTTP GET request to the following URI (see <xref target='RFC7231' /> and <xref target='RFC2818' />):
<figure><artwork>
                        "https://doi.org/" URN-EIDR</artwork></figure>

						If the EIDR Identifier exists, then an XML Schema instance document (see <xref target='XMLSchema' />) containing metadata associated with the EIDR Identifier is returned; otherwise, the HTTP status code "404 Not Found" is returned.

<figure><artwork>
EXAMPLE: https://doi.org/urn:eidr:10.5240:7791-8534-2C23-9030-8610-5
</artwork></figure>     
				</t>
					
					<t>NOTE: The web service uses the HTTP Accept header to determine the format of the response. When using a web browser to access the resource above, the query string "?locatt=type:Full" is appended to the URI to explicitly request an XML response.</t>
					
					<t>EIDR Association operates additional services specifically tailored to EIDR users (see <xref target='EIDR-SERVICES'/> and <xref target='DOI-EIDR-PROXY'/>). These services include additional features, e.g., the ability to register EIDR Identifiers and web-based GUI tools.</t>
				</list>
			</t>

			<t>Rules for Lexical Equivalence:

				<list>
					<t>Lexical equivalence of the URN-EIDR is defined by case-insensitive string match.</t>
                    <t>NOTE: The URN-EIDR includes the "urn:eidr:" string, as specified under "Declaration of syntactic structure".</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Conformance with URN Syntax:

				<list>
					<t>As specified above, the syntax of
					the URN-EIDR is a subset of the URN syntax specified in <xref target='RFC2141' />.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Validation mechanism:

				<list>
					<t>The validity of an EIDR-NSS can only be guaranteed by completing the resolution process.</t>

					<t>For EIDR-NSS with an EIDR-PREFIX equal to "10.5240", the CHECK value can be used for integrity checking, as specified above.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Scope:

				<list>
					<t>EIDR Identifiers are centrally registered, globally unique identifiers for use with audiovisual works worldwide.</t>
				</list>
			</t>

		</section>
		<section title='Namespace Considerations'>
			<t>	

EIDR Identifiers are intended for use in Internet applications, where URNs are routinely used to identify audiovisual resources. There is no direct mapping from EIDR Identifiers to existing URN namespaces. 

			</t>
		</section>
		<section title='Community Considerations'>
			<t>	

The primary registrants of EIDR Identifiers are producers and distributors of audiovisual works, metadata aggregators, and audiovisual archives. Any bona fide member of the ecosystem can become an EIDR member and register any work. EIDR Identifiers can be used by anyone to unambiguously identify an audiovisual asset and retrieve underlying metadata.  The primary benefits of their use are associated with works in wide distribution, management of long or complex distribution chains, and aggregation of information from multiple sources.

			</t>
		</section>
		<section title='IANA Considerations'>
			<t>	
IANA has registered the
   Formal URN Namespace 'eidr' in the "Uniform Resource Names (URN)
   Namespaces" registry, using the registration template in <xref target="reg_template"/> of this document.

			</t>
		</section>
		<section title='Security Considerations'>
			<t>This document specifies the syntax of the URN-EIDR
			namespace and makes no security
			representations. Furthermore, the details of
			assignment and resolution processes are defined
			external to this document by EIDR Association and
			the ISO 26324 Registration Authority, and are
			thus outside the scope of this document. Note, however, that failure to conform to the syntactic and lexical equivalence rules in this specification when using an EIDR Identifier as a criteria for accessing restricted resources can result in granting unauthorized access to these resources.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title='Normative References'>
<!-- [rfced] Would you like the references to be alphabetized
or left in their current order?
-->

<reference anchor='ISO26234'>
       <front>
          <title>ISO 26324:2012                                                                             
             Information and documentation -- Digital object identifier
	  system</title>
          <author><organization>International Organization for Standardization
	  (ISO)</organization></author>
          <date month="June" year='2012' />
       </front>
<seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 26324"/>
</reference>

			<reference anchor="ISO7064">
				<front>
					<title>Information technology -- Security techniques -- Check character systems</title>
					<author>
						<organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="February" year="2003"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 7064"/>
			</reference>
                        
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2141"?>
			            
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

			<reference anchor="SMPTERP2079">
				<front>
					<title>Digital Object Identifier (DOI) Name and Entertainment ID Registry (EIDR) Identifier Representations</title>
					<author>
						<organization>Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers</organization>
					</author>
					<date year="2014"/>
				</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.5594/SMPTE.RP2079.2013"/> 
<seriesInfo name="SMPTE" value="RP 2079"/>
			</reference>

            
		</references>
        
		<references title='Informative References'>
        
			<reference anchor="EIDR-INTRO" target="http://eidr.org/documents/EIDR_ID_Format_v1.1.pdf">
				<front>
					<title>EIDR: ID Format Ver. 1.1</title>
					<author>
						<organization>Entertainment Identifier Registry Association</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="August" year="2013"/>
				</front>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="EIDR-OVERVIEW" target="http://eidr.org/documents/2013-11-01_EIDR_Overview_FINAL.pdf" >
				<front>
					<title>EIDR Overview</title>
					<author>
						<organization>Entertainment Identifier Registry Association</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="November" year="2013"/>
				</front>
			</reference>

			
            <reference anchor="EIDR-SERVICES" target="http://eidr.org/documents/EIDR_2.0_Registry_User_Guide.pdf">
				<front>
					<title>EIDR System Version 2.0: Registry User's Guide</title>
					<author>
						<organization>Entertainment Identifier Registry Association</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="August" year="2013"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			
			<reference anchor="DOI-EIDR-PROXY" target="http://eidr.org/documents/EIDR_and_the_DOI_Proxy.pdf">
				<front>
					<title>EIDR and the DOI Proxy</title>
					<author>
						<organization>Entertainment Identifier Registry Association</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="May" year="2015"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
            
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2818"?>

            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3406"?>
            
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7231"?>
			
            <reference anchor="XMLSchema" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/CR-xmlschema-ref-20100119">
				<front>
					<title>
W3C XML Schema Definition Language (XSD): Component Designators
					</title>
					<author initials="M." surname="Holstege" fullname="Mary Holstege">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="A." surname="Vedamuthu" fullname="Asir Vedamuthu">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="January" day="19" year="2010"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="W3C Candidate Recommendation" value="CR-xmlschema-ref-20100119"/>
				<format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/CR-xmlschema-ref-20100119"/>
			</reference>
            
            <reference anchor="rfcdiff" target="https://tools.ietf.org/tools/rfcdiff/">
				<front>
					<title>Rfcdiff Tool</title>
					<author/>
					<date/>
				</front>
			</reference>
            
		</references>

		<section title='Summary of Changes (Informative)' anchor="changes">
		
			<section title="Introduction">

			<t>This Appendix summarizes changes across revisions of this specification. This
			summary is informative and not intended to be exhaustive. Readers seeking a definitive
			list of changes are instead encouraged to use tools such
			as <xref target="rfcdiff"/>.</t>
			
			</section>
			
			<section title="Changes from RFC 7302">
				<t>
				<list style="symbols">
				<t>"Process for identifier resolution" paragraph: The syntax for the URI supplied to the web service is modified to use (a) the 'https' scheme and (b) the URN-EIDR representation of the EIDR Identifier.</t>
				</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
