<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="7709" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Very Fast Setup of GMPLS LSPs">Requirements for Very Fast
    Setup of GMPLS Label Switched Paths (LSPs)</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Andrew G. Malis" initials="A.G." role="editor"
            surname="Malis">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>agmalis@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brian J. Wilson" initials="B.J."
            surname="Wilson">
      <organization>Applied Communication Sciences</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>bwilson@appcomsci.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Clapp" initials="G."
            surname="Clapp">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs Research</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>clapp@research.att.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vishnu Shukla" initials="V."
            surname="Shukla">
      <organization>Verizon Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>vishnu.shukla@verizon.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

   <date month="November" year="2015" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</workgroup>

    <abstract>
<t>Establishment and control of Label Switch Paths (LSPs) have become
mainstream tools of commercial and government network providers. One of the
elements of further evolving such networks is scaling their performance in
terms of LSP bandwidth and traffic loads, LSP intensity (e.g., rate of LSP
creation, deletion, and modification), LSP set up delay, quality-of-service differentiation, and different levels of resilience. </t>

<t>The goal of this document is to present target scaling objectives and the related protocol requirements for Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
<t>Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) <xref target="RFC3471"/> <xref target="RFC3945"/> includes an architecture and a set of control-plane protocols that can be used to operate data networks ranging from packet-switch-capable networks, through those networks that use Time Division Multiplexing, to WDM networks.  The Path Computation Element (PCE) architecture <xref target="RFC4655"/> defines functional components that can be used to compute and suggest appropriate paths in connection-oriented traffic-engineered networks. Additional wavelength switched optical networks (WSON) considerations were defined in <xref target="RFC6163"/>.</t>

<t>This document refers to the same general framework and technologies, but it
adds requirements related to expediting LSP setup under heavy connection churn
scenarios, while achieving low blocking under an overall distributed control
plane. This document focuses on a specific problem space -- high-capacity and
highly dynamic connection request scenarios -- that may require clarification
and or extensions to current GMPLS protocols and procedures. In particular,
the purpose of this document is to address the potential need for protocols
and procedures that enable expediting the setup of LSPs in high-churn
scenarios. Both single-domain and multi-domain network scenarios are
considered.</t> 

<t>This document focuses on the following two topics: 1) the driving
applications and main characteristics and requirements of this problem space,
and 2) the key requirements that may be novel with respect to current GMPLS
protocols.</t> 

<t>This document presents the objectives and related requirements for GMPLS to
provide the control for networks operating with such performance
requirements. While specific deployment scenarios are considered part of the
presentation of objectives, the stated requirements are aimed at ensuring the
control protocols are not the limiting factor in achieving a particular
network's performance. Implementation dependencies are out of scope of this
document.   </t> 

<t>Other documents may be needed to define how GMPLS protocols meet the
requirements laid out in this document. Such future documents may define
extensions or simply clarify how existing mechanisms may be used to address
the key requirements of highly dynamic networks.</t> 
</section>

    <section title="Background">
<t>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) Core Optical Networks
(CORONET) program <xref target="Chiu"/> is an example target environment that
includes IP and optical commercial and government networks, with 
a focus on highly dynamic and resilient multi-terabit core networks.
It anticipates the need for rapid (sub-second) setup and SONET/SDH-like
restoration times for high-churn (up to tens of requests per second network
wide and holding times as short as one second) on-demand wavelength,
sub-wavelength, and packet services for a variety of applications (e.g., grid
computing, cloud computing, data visualization, fast data transfer, etc.).
This must be done while meeting stringent call-blocking requirements and while
minimizing the use of resources such as time slots, switch ports, wavelength
conversion, etc. 
</t>

</section>

    <section title="Motivation">

    <t>The motivation for this document, and envisioned related future documents, is two-fold:

<list style="numbers">
<t>The anticipated need for rapid setup, while maintaining low
blocking, of large bandwidth and highly churned on-demand connections (in the form of sub-wavelengths, e.g., OTN ODUx, and wavelengths, e.g., OTN OCh) for a variety of applications including grid computing, cloud computing, data visualization, and intra- and inter-datacenter communications.</t>
<t>The ability to set up circuit-like LSPs for large bandwidth flows with low setup delays provides an alternative to packet-based solutions implemented over static circuits that may require tying up more expensive and power-consuming resources (e.g., router ports). Reducing the LSP setup delay will reduce the minimum bandwidth threshold at which a GMPLS circuit approach is preferred over a layer 3 (e.g., IP) approach. Dynamic circuit and virtual circuit switching intrinsically provide guaranteed bandwidth, guaranteed low-latency and jitter, and faster restoration, all of which are very hard to provide in  packet-only networks. Again, a key element in achieving these benefits is enabling the fastest possible circuit setup times.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Future applications are expected to require setup times that are as fast as
100 ms in highly dynamic, national-scale network environments while meeting
stringent blocking requirements and minimizing the use of resources such as
switch ports, wavelength converters/regenerators, and other network design
parameters.  Of course, the benefits of low setup delay diminish for
connections with long holding times. For some specific applications, a
trade-off may be required, as the need for rapid setup may be more important
than their requirements for other features currently provided in GMPLS (e.g.,
robustness against setup errors).
</t>

<t>With the advent of data centers, cloud computing, video, gaming, mobile and other broadband applications, it is anticipated that connection request rates may increase, even for connections with longer holding times, either during limited time periods (such as during the restoration from a data center failure) or over the longer term, to the point where the current GMPLS procedures of path computation/selection and resource allocation may not be timely, thus leading to increased blocking or increased resource cost. Thus, extensions of GMPLS signaling and routing protocols (e.g., OSPF-TE) may also be needed to address heavy churn of connection requests (i.e., high-connection-request arrival rate) in networks with high-traffic loads, even for connections with relatively longer holding times.</t>
     </section>
    <section title="Driving Applications and Their Requirements">
<t>
There are several emerging applications that fall under the problem space
addressed here in several service areas such as provided by telecommunication
carriers, government networks, enterprise networks, content providers, and
cloud providers. Such applications include research and education networks / grid computing, and cloud computing. Detailing and standardizing protocols to address these applications will expedite the transition to commercial deployment.
</t>
<t>
In the target environment, there are multiple Bandwidth-on-Demand service
requests per second, such as might arise as cloud services proliferate.  It
includes dynamic services with connection setup requirements that range from
seconds to milliseconds.  The aggregate traffic demand, which is composed of
both packet (IP) and circuit (wavelength and sub-wavelength) services,
represents a five to twenty-fold increase over today's traffic levels for the
largest of any individual carrier.   Thus, the aggressive requirements must be
met with solutions that are scalable, cost effective, and power efficient,
while providing the desired quality of service (QoS). 
</t>
<section title="Key Application Requirements">
<t>
There are two key performance-scaling requirements in the target environment that are the main drivers behind this document:
<list style="numbers">
<t>
Connection request rates ranging from a few requests per second for high-capacity (e.g., 40 Gb/s , 100 Gb/s) wavelength-based LSPs to around 100 requests per second for sub-wavelength LSPs (e.g., OTN ODU0, ODU1, and ODU2).
</t>
<t>
Connection setup delay of around 100 ms across a national or regional
network. To meet this target, assuming pipelined cross-connection and
worst-case propagation delay and hop count, it is estimated that the maximum processing delay per hop is around 700 microseconds <xref target="Lehmen"/>. Optimal path selection and resource allocation may require somewhat longer processing (up to 5 milliseconds) in either the destination or source nodes and possibly tighter processing delays (around 500 microseconds) in intermediate nodes.
</t>
</list> </t>
<t>
The model for a national network is that of the continental US with up to 100
nodes and LSPs with distances up to ~3000 km and up to 15 hops.
</t>
<t>
A connection setup delay is defined here as the time between the arrival of a
connection request at an ingress edge switch -- or more generally a Label
Switch Router (LSR) -- and the time at which information can start flowing
from that ingress switch over that connection.  Note that this definition is
more inclusive than the LSP setup time defined in <xref target="RFC5814"/> and
<xref target="RFC6777"/>, which do not include PCE path computation delays. 
</t>
     </section>
     </section>

    <section anchor="Requirements" title="Requirements for Very Fast Setup of GMPLS LSPs">
<t>This section lists the protocol requirements for very fast setup of GMPLS LSPs in order to adequately support the service characteristics described in the previous sections.
These requirements may be the basis for future documents, some of which may be simply informational, while others may describe specific GMPLS protocol extensions. While some of these requirements may have implications on implementations, the intent is for the requirements to apply to GMPLS protocols and their standardized mechanisms.
</t>


<section anchor="ControlPlaneRequirements" title="Protocol and Procedure Requirements">
<t><list counter="reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format R%d">
<t>
The portion of the LSP establishment time related to protocol processing should
scale linearly based on the number of traversed nodes.
</t>
<t>
End-to-end LSP data path availability should be bounded by the worst-case
single-node data path establishment time. In other words, pipelined
cross-connect processing as discussed in <xref target="RFC6383"/> should be
enabled. 
</t>
<t>
LSP establishment time shall depend on the number of nodes supporting an LSP
and link propagation delays and not on any off (control) path transactions, e.g., PCC-PCE and PCC-PCC communications at the time of connection setup, even when PCE-based approaches are used.
</t>
<t>
LSP holding times as short as one second must be supported.
</t>
<t>
The protocol aspects of LSP signaling must not preclude LSP request rates of tens per second.
</t>
<t>
The above requirements should be met even when there are failures in connection establishment, i.e., LSPs should be established faster than when crank-back is used.
</t>
<t>
These requirements are applicable even when an LSP crosses one or more administrative domains/boundaries.
</t>
<t>
The above are additional requirements and do not replace existing requirements, e.g., alarm-free setup and teardown, recovery, or inter-domain confidentiality.
</t>
</list>
</t>

    </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
Being able to support very fast setup and a high-churn rate of GMPLS LSPs is
not expected to adversely affect the underlying security issues associated
with existing GMPLS signaling. If encryption that requires key exchange is
intended to be used on the signaled LSPs, then this requirement needs to be
included as a part of the protocol design process, as the usual extra
round-trip time (RTT) for key exchange will have an effect on the setup and
churn rate of the GMPLS LSPs. It is possible to amortize the costs of key
exchange over multiple exchanges (if those occur between the same peers) so
that some exchanges need not cost a full RTT and operate in so-called zero-RTT
mode. 
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Ann Von Lehmen, Joe Gannett, Ron Skoog, and
   Haim Kobrinski of Applied Communication Sciences for their comments and
   assistance on this document. Lou Berger provided editorial comments on this document.
</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3471.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3945.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4655.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5814.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6163.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6383.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6777.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="Chiu" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1364/JOCN.4.000001">

        <front>
          <title>Architectures and Protocols for Capacity Efficient, Highly Dynamic and Highly Resilient Core Networks</title>

          <author>

            <organization>Chiu, A., et al.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012" />
        </front>
<seriesInfo name="Journal of Optical Communications and Networking" value="vol. 4, No. 1, pp. 1-14"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Lehmen" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1364/JOCN.7.00A447">
        <front>
          <title>CORONET: Testbeds, Demonstration, and Lessons Learned</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Von Lehmen, A., et al.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2015" />
        </front>
<seriesInfo name="Journal of Optical Communications and Networking" value="Vol. 7, Issue 3, pp. A447-A458"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
