<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[ 
        <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC2865 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2865.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC2866 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2866.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3268 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3268.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3588 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3588.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5176 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5176.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3539 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3539.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3748 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3748.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC3958 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3958.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC4017 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4017.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC4107 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4107.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC4279 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4279.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC4346 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4346.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC4372 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4372.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC4953 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4953.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5246 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5246.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5247 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5247.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5280.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5580 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5580.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC5997 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5997.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6066 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6066.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6125 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6125.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6421 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6421.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6613 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6613.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6614 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6614.xml">		
	<!ENTITY RFC6733 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6733.xml">		
	<!ENTITY RFC6929 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6929.xml">		
        <!ENTITY RFC6973 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6973.xml">
     <!ENTITY RFC7170 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7170.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC7360 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7360.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC7542 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7542.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?> 

<rfc number="7593" ipr="trust200902" category="info" submissionType="independent">
<front> 
	<title abbrev="eduroam">The eduroam Architecture for Network Roaming</title> 
	<author fullname="Klaas Wierenga" initials="K." surname="Wierenga"> 
		<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
  		<address> 
   			<postal> 
    			<street>Haarlerbergweg 13-17</street>
    			<city>Amsterdam</city> 
    			<code>1101 CH</code>
    			<country>The Netherlands</country> 
   			</postal>
   			<phone>+31 20 357 1752</phone> 
   			<email>klaas@cisco.com</email> 
  		</address>
 	</author> 
 	<author fullname="Stefan Winter" initials="S." surname="Winter" >
  		<organization abbrev="RESTENA" >Fondation RESTENA</organization>
  		<address>
  			<postal>
				<street>Maison du Savoir</street>
				<street>2, avenue de l'Universite</street>
				<city>L-4365 Esch-sur-Alzette</city>
				<country>Luxembourg</country>
			</postal>
    		<phone>+352 424409 1</phone>
			<facsimile>+352 422473</facsimile>
			<email>stefan.winter@restena.lu</email>
			<uri>http://www.restena.lu.</uri>
		</address>
    </author>
	<author initials="T." surname="Wolniewicz" fullname="Tomasz Wolniewicz">
	    <organization>Nicolaus Copernicus University</organization>
	    <address>
			<postal>
		    	<street>pl. Rapackiego 1</street>
		    	<city>Torun</city>
		    	<country>Poland</country>
			</postal>
			<phone>+48-56-611-2750</phone>
			<facsimile>+48-56-622-1850</facsimile>
			<email>twoln@umk.pl</email>
			<uri>http://www.home.umk.pl/~twoln/</uri>
	    </address>
	</author>
 <date month="September" year="2015"/>

    <keyword>Federated Authentication</keyword>
    <keyword>AAA</keyword>
    <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
    <keyword>IEEE 802.1X</keyword>
    <keyword>roaming</keyword>
    <keyword>EAP</keyword>
    <keyword>eduroam</keyword>

 <abstract> 
  <t>
   This document describes the architecture of the eduroam service for federated 
   (wireless) network access in academia. 
   The combination of IEEE 802.1X, the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP), and RADIUS that is used in eduroam provides a secure, 
   scalable, and deployable service for roaming network access. The successful 
   deployment of eduroam over the last decade in the educational sector may serve as an 
   example for other sectors, hence this document. In particular, the initial
   architectural choices 
   and selection of standards are described, along with the changes that were prompted by operational 
   experience.
  </t> 
 </abstract> 
</front>
 <!---->
<middle>
 <section title="Introduction"> 
   <t>In 2002, the European Research and Education community set out to create a
   network roaming service for students and employees in academia 
   <xref target="eduroam-start" />. Now, over 10 years later, this  service has grown to 
   more than 10,000 service locations, serving millions of users on all continents with 
   the exception of Antarctica.
   </t>


   <t>
   This memo serves to explain the considerations for the design of
   eduroam as well as to document operational experience and resulting
   changes that led to IETF specifications such as
   RADIUS over TCP <xref target="RFC6613" /> and RADIUS with TLS <xref target="RFC6614" /> 
   and that promoted alternative uses of RADIUS like in Application
   Bridging for Federated Access Beyond web (ABFAB) 
   <xref target="ABFAB-ARCH"/>. Whereas the eduroam service is limited to
   academia, the eduroam architecture can easily be reused in other environments.
   </t>
   <t>First, this memo describes the original architecture of eduroam <xref target="eduroam-homepage"/>. Then, a number of 
   operational problems are presented that surfaced when eduroam gained wide-scale deployment.
   Lastly, enhancements to the eduroam architecture that mitigate the aforementioned issues 
   are discussed.
   </t>
  <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology"> 
   <t>This document uses identity management and privacy terminology from
   <xref target="RFC6973"/>.  In particular, this
   document uses the terms "Identity Provider", "Service Provider", and "identity
   management".
   </t>
  </section>  <!-- Terminology -->
  <section anchor="Notational" title="Notational Conventions"> 
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
   are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
   </t>
   <t>Note: Also, the policy to which eduroam participants subscribe expresses the 
   requirements for participation in RFC 2119 language.
   </t> 
  </section>  <!-- Notational Conventions -->
  <section anchor="DesignGoals" title="Design Goals">
   <t>The guiding design considerations for eduroam were as follows:

<list style="hanging">
   <t hangText="-">Unique identification of users at the edge of the network
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The access Service Provider (SP) needs to be able to determine whether a user is 
   authorized to use the network resources. Furthermore, in case of abuse of the resources, 
   there is a requirement to be able to identify the user uniquely (with the cooperation 
   of the user's Identity Provider (IdP) operator).
   </t>
   <t hangText="-">Enable (trusted) guest use
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   In order to enable roaming, it should be possible for users of participating
   institutions to get seamless access to the networks of other institutions.
   </t>
   <t>
   Note: Traffic separation between guest users and normal users is possible (for example, 
   through the use of VLANs), and indeed widely used in eduroam.
   </t> 
   <t hangText="-">Scalable
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The infrastructure that is created should scale to a large number of users
   and organizations without requiring a lot of coordination and other
   administrative procedures (possibly with the exception of an initial setup). Specifically, 
   it should not be necessary for a user that visits another organization to go through an 
   administrative process.
   </t>
   <t hangText="-">Easy to install and use
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   It should be easy for both organizations and users to participate in 
   the roaming infrastructure; otherwise, it may inhibit wide-scale adoption. In 
   particular, there should be no client installation (or it should be easy) and only one-time configuration.
   </t> 
   <t hangText="-">Secure
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   An important design criterion has been that there needs to be a security association 
   between the end user and their Identity Provider, eliminating the possibility of 
   credential theft. The minimal requirements for security are specified in the eduroam 
   policy and subject to change over time. As an additional protection against user errors 
   and negligence,  it should be possible for participating Identity Providers
   to add their own 
   requirements for the quality of authentication of their own users without the need for 
   the infrastructure as a whole to implement the same requirements.
   </t> 

   <t hangText="-">Privacy preserving
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
    The design of the system should provide for user anonymization, i.e.,
    a possibility to hide the user's identity from any third parties,
    including Service Providers.
   </t>

   <t hangText="-">Standards based
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   In an infrastructure in which many thousands of organizations participate, it
   is obvious that it should be possible to use equipment from different
   vendors; therefore, it is important to build the infrastructure using open
   standards.
   </t>
</list>
   </t>
   </section>  <!-- Design Goals-->
   <section anchor="ConsideredSolutions" title="Solutions That Were Considered"> 
   <t>Three architectures were trialed: one based on the use of VPN technology (deemed 
   secure but not scalable), one based on Web captive-portals (scalable but
   not secure), and one based on
   IEEE 802.1X, the latter being the basis of what is now the eduroam architecture. 
   An overview of the candidate architectures and their relative merits can be found in 
   <xref target="nrenroaming-select" />. 
</t>  
   <t>
   The chosen architecture is based on:
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>IEEE 802.1X <xref target="IEEE.802.1X" /> as the port-based authentication framework using</t> 
     <t>EAP <xref target="RFC3748" /> for integrity-protected and confidential 
     transport of credentials and</t>
     <t>a RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865" /> hierarchy as the trust fabric.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>  <!-- Considered Solutions -->
 </section>  <!-- Introduction-->
 <section anchor="ClassicArchitecture" title="Classic Architecture"> 
  <t>Federations, like eduroam, implement essentially two types of direct trust relations 
  (and one indirect). The trust relation between an end user and the IdP 
  (operated by the home organization of the user) and between the IdP and the SP (in eduroam, 
  the operator of the network at the visited location). In eduroam,
  the trust relation between the user and IdP is through mutual
  authentication. IdPs and the SP 
  establish trust through the use of a RADIUS hierarchy.
  </t>
  <t>These two forms of trust relations in turn provide the transitive trust relation that 
  makes the SP trust the user to use its network resources.
  </t>		
 <section title="Authentication" anchor="Authentication"> 
  <t>Authentication in eduroam is achieved by using a combination of IEEE 802.1X 
  <xref target="IEEE.802.1X" /> and EAP <xref target="RFC4372" /> (the latter carried 
  over RADIUS for guest access; see <xref target="Federation"/>).
  </t>
  <section title="IEEE 802.1X" anchor="Dot1X"> 
   <t>By using the IEEE 802.1X <xref target="IEEE.802.1X" /> framework for port-based 
   network authentication, organizations
   that offer network access (SPs) for visiting (and local) eduroam users can
   make sure that only authorized users get access. The user (or rather the
   user's supplicant) sends an access request to the authenticator (Wi-Fi
   Access Point or switch) at the SP, the authenticator forwards the access
   request to the authentication server of the SP, that in turn proxies the
   request through the RADIUS hierarchy to the authentication server of the
   user's home organization (the IdP).
   </t> 
   <t>Note: The security of the connections between local wireless infrastructure and 
   local RADIUS servers is a part of the local network of each SP; therefore, it is out of 
   scope for this document. For completeness, it should be stated that security between 
   access points and their controllers is vendor specific, and security between 
   controllers (or standalone access points) and local RADIUS servers is based on the 
   typical RADIUS shared secret mechanism.
   </t>
   <t>In order for users to be aware of the availability of the eduroam service,
   an SP that offers wireless network access MUST broadcast the Service Set
   Identifier (SSID) 'eduroam',
   unless that conflicts with the SSID of another eduroam SP, in which case, an
   SSID starting with "eduroam-" MAY be used. The downside of the latter is that clients 
   will not automatically connect to that SSID, thus losing the seamless connection 
   experience.
   </t>
   <t>Note: A direct implication of the common eduroam SSID is that the users cannot 
   distinguish between a connection to the home network and a guest network at another 
   eduroam institution (IEEE 802.11-2012 does have the so-called "Interworking" to 
   make that distinction, but it is not widely implemented yet). Furthermore, without proper 
   server verification, users may even be tricked into joining a rogue eduroam network. Therefore,
   users should be made aware that they should not assume data confidentiality in the 
   eduroam infrastructure.
   </t>
   <t>
   To protect over-the-air confidentiality of user data, IEEE 802.11 wireless networks of eduroam SPs 
   MUST deploy WPA2+AES, and they MAY additionally support Wi-Fi Protected
   Access with the Temporal Key
   Integrity Protocol (WPA/TKIP) as a
   courtesy to users of legacy hardware.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- Dot1X -->
  <section title="EAP" anchor="EAP"> 
   <t>The use of the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) <xref target="RFC4372" /> 
   serves two purposes. In the first place, a properly chosen EAP method allows for integrity-protected
   and confidential transport of the user credentials to the home
   organization. Secondly, by having all RADIUS servers transparently proxy
   access requests, regardless of the EAP method inside the RADIUS packet, the
   choice of EAP method is between the 'home' organization of the user and the
   user. In other words, in principle, every authentication form that can be carried 
   inside EAP can be used in eduroam, as long as they adhere to minimal requirements as
   set forth in the eduroam Policy Service Definition <xref target="eduroam-service-definition"/>.
   </t>
   <t>
    <figure anchor="tunneled-eap" title="Tunneled EAP"><artwork>
     <![CDATA[ 
                            +-----+
                           /       \
                          /         \
                         /           \
                        /             \
       ,----------\    |               |   ,---------\
       |    SP    |    |    eduroam    |   |    IdP  |
       |          +----+  trust fabric +---+         |
       `------+---'    |               |   '-----+---'
              |        |               |         |
              |         \             /          |
              |          \           /           |
              |           \         /            |
              |            \       /             |
         +----+             +-----+              +----+
         |                                            |
         |                                            |
     +---+--+                                      +--+---+
     |      |                                      |      |
   +-+------+-+    ___________________________     |      |
   |          |   O__________________________ )    +------+
   +----------+     
   Host (supplicant)      EAP tunnel       Authentication server
]]></artwork></figure> 
   </t> 
   <t>Proxying of access requests is based on the outer identity in the
   EAP-Message. Those outer identities MUST be a valid user identifier with a mandatory realm as per <xref target="RFC7542"/>, i.e., be of the form something@realm or just @realm,
   where the realm part is the domain name of the institution that the IdP belongs
   to.

   In order to preserve credential protection, participating organizations MUST deploy 
   EAP methods that provide mutual authentication. For EAP methods that support outer 
   identity, anonymous outer identities are recommended. Most commonly used in eduroam 
   are the so-called tunneled EAP methods that first create a
   server-authenticated TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>
   tunnel through which the user credentials are transmitted. 
   As depicted in <xref target= "tunneled-eap"/>, the use of a tunneled EAP method creates 
   a direct logical connection between the supplicant and the authentication 
   server, even though the actual traffic flows through the RADIUS hierarchy. 
   </t>
  </section> <!-- EAP -->
 </section> <!-- Authentication-->
 <section title="Federation Trust Fabric" anchor="Federation"> 
  <t>The eduroam federation trust fabric is based on RADIUS. RADIUS trust is based on 
  shared secrets between RADIUS peers. In eduroam, any RADIUS message originating from a 
  trusted peer is implicitly assumed to originate from a member of the roaming consortium.
  </t>
  <t>Note: See also the security considerations for a discussion on RADIUS
  security that motivated the work on RADIUS with TLS <xref target="RFC6614" />.
   </t>
  <section title="RADIUS" anchor="RADIUS"> 
   <t>The eduroam trust fabric consists of a proxy hierarchy of RADIUS servers 
   (organizational, national, global) that is
   loosely based on the DNS hierarchy. That is, typically an organizational RADIUS
   server agrees on a shared secret with a national server, and the national
   server in turn agrees on a shared secret with the root server. Access requests are
   routed through a chain of RADIUS proxies towards the Identity Provider of the
   user, and the access accept (or reject) follows the same path back.
   </t>
   <t>Note: In some circumstances, there are more levels of RADIUS servers (for 
   example, regional or continental servers), but that doesn't change the general model. Also,
   the packet exchange that is described below requires, in reality, several 
   round-trips.
   </t>
   <t>


    <figure anchor="radius-hierarchy" title="eduroam RADIUS Hierarchy"><artwork>
     <![CDATA[ 
                               +-------+
                               |       |
                               |   .   |
                               |       |
                               +---+---+
                                 / | \
               +----------------/  |  \---------------------+
               |                   |                        |
               |                   |                        |            
               |                   |                        |
            +--+---+            +--+--+                +----+---+                        
            |      |            |     |                |        |                       
            | .edu |    . . .   | .nl |      . . .     | .ac.uk |
            |      |            |     |                |        |
            +--+---+            +--+--+                +----+---+
             / | \                 | \                      | 
            /  |  \                |  \                     |
           /   |   \               |   \                    |
    +-----+    |    +-----+        |    +------+            |
    |          |          |        |           |            |
    |          |          |        |           |            |
+---+---+ +----+---+ +----+---+ +--+---+ +-----+----+ +-----+-----+
|       | |        | |        | |      | |          | |           |
|utk.edu| |utah.edu| |case.edu| |hva.nl| |surfnet.nl| |soton.ac.uk|
|       | |        | |        | |      | |          | |           |
+----+--+ +--------+ +--------+ +------+ +----+-----+ +-----------+
     |                                        |
     |                                        |
  +--+--+                                  +--+--+
  |     |                                  |     |
+-+-----+-+                                |     |                          
|         |                                +-----+
+---------+
user: paul@surfnet.nl             surfnet.nl Authentication server 
]]></artwork> </figure> 
    </t> 
    <t>Routing of access requests to the home IdP is done based on the realm
    part of the outer identity. For example (as in <xref target= "radius-hierarchy"/>), 
    when user paul@surfnet.nl of
    SURFnet (surfnet.nl) tries to gain wireless network access at the University
    of Tennessee at Knoxville (utk.edu) the following happens:
    </t>
    <t>
     <list style="symbols">
      <t>Paul's supplicant transmits an EAP access request to the Access Point
      (Authenticator) at UTK with outer identity of anonymous@surfnet.nl.
      </t>
      <t>The Access Point forwards the EAP message to its Authentication Server
      (the UTK RADIUS server).
      </t>
      <t>The UTK RADIUS server checks the realm to see if it is a local realm;
      since it isn't, the request is proxied to the .edu RADIUS server.
      </t>
      <t>The .edu RADIUS server verifies the realm; since it is not in a
      .edu subdomain, it proxies the request to the root server.
      </t>
      <t>The root RADIUS server proxies the request to the .nl RADIUS server, 
      since the ".nl" domain is known to the root server.
      </t>
      <t>The .nl RADIUS server proxies the request to the surfnet.nl server, 
      since it knows the SURFnet server.
      </t>
      <t>The surfnet.nl RADIUS server decapsulates the EAP message and verifies
      the user credentials, since the user is known to SURFnet.
      </t>
      <t>The surfnet.nl RADIUS server informs the utk.edu server of the outcome
      of the authentication request (Access-Accept or Access-Reject) by proxying the outcome
      through the RADIUS hierarchy in reverse order.
      </t>
      <t>The UTK RADIUS server instructs the UTK Access Point to either accept
      or reject access based on the outcome of the authentication.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
   <t>Note: The depiction of the root RADIUS server is a simplification. In reality, the 
   root server is distributed over three continents and each maintains a list of the top-level 
   realms that a specific root server is responsible for. This also means that, for 
   intercontinental roaming, there is an extra proxy step from one root server to the other.
   Also, the physical distribution of nodes doesn't need to mirror the
   logical distribution of nodes. This helps with stability and scalability.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- RADIUS -->
 </section> <!-- Federation --> 
 </section> <!-- Classic Architecture -->
 <section title="Issues with Initial Trust Fabric" anchor="IssuesClassic">
  <t>While the hierarchical RADIUS architecture described in the previous section has
  served as the basis for eduroam operations for an entire decade, the
  exponential growth of authentications is expected to lead to, and has in fact in 
  some cases already led to, performance and
  operations bottlenecks on the aggregation proxies. The following sections describe 
  some of the shortcomings and the resulting remedies.</t>
  <section title="Server Failure Handling" anchor="IssuesClassicFailure">
   <t>In eduroam, authentication requests for roaming users are statically
   routed through preconfigured proxies. The number of proxies varies: in a
   national roaming case, the number of proxies is typically 1 or 2 (some
   countries deploy regional proxies, which are in turn aggregated by a national
   proxy); in international roaming, 3 or 4 proxy servers are typically involved
   (the number may be higher along some routes).
   </t>
   <t>RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865" /> does not define a failover algorithm. In
   particular, the failure of a server needs to be deduced from the absence of
   a reply. Operational experience has shown that this has detrimental effects
   on the infrastructure and end-user experience:
    <list style="numbers">
     <t>Authentication failure: the first user whose authentication path is
     along a newly failed server will experience a long delay and possibly
     timeout
     </t>
     <t>Wrongly deduced states: since the proxy chain is longer than one hop, a
     failure further along in the authentication path is indistinguishable from a
     failure in the next hop.
     </t>
     <t>Inability to determine recovery of a server: only a "live"
     authentication request sent to a server that is believed to be inoperable 
     can
     lead to the discovery that the server is in working order again. This issue
     has been resolved with RFC 5997 <xref target="RFC5997" />.
     </t>
    </list>
   </t>
   <t>The second point can have significant impact on the operational state of
   the system in a worst-case scenario: imagine one realm's home server being
   inoperable. A user from that realm is trying to roam internationally and
   tries to authenticate. The RADIUS server on the hotspot location may assume
   its own national proxy is down because it does not reply. That national
   server, being perfectly alive, in turn will assume that the international
   aggregation proxy is down, which in turn will believe the home country proxy
   national server is down. None of these assumptions are true. 

Worse yet: in case of failover to a back-up next-hop RADIUS server, also that
server will be marked as being defunct, since through that server no reply will be
received from the defunct home server either.

 Within a short time, all redundant
   aggregation proxies might be considered defunct by their preceding hop.
   </t>
   <t>In the absence of proper next-hop state derivation, some interesting
   concepts have been introduced by eduroam participants -- the most
   noteworthy being a failover logic that considers up/down states not per
   next-hop RADIUS peer, but instead per realm (See <xref target="dead-realm"/> for details).
   Recently, implementations of RFC 5997 <xref target="RFC5997" /> and cautious failover
   parameters make false "downs" unlikely to happen, as long as every hop
   implements RFC 5997. 
    In that case, dead realm detection serves mainly to prevent proxying of large numbers of 
   requests to known dead realms.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- ISSUES-CLASSIC-FAILURE -->
  <section title="No Signaling of Error Conditions" anchor="IssuesClassicErrors">
   <t>The RADIUS protocol lacks signaling of error conditions, and the IEEE
   802.1X standard does not allow conveying of extended failure reasons to the
   end user's device. For eduroam, this creates two issues:
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>The home server may have an operational problem, for example, its
     authentication decisions may depend on an external data source such as a SQL server or Microsoft's Active Directory, and the external data source is unavailable. 
     If the RADIUS interface is still functional, there are two
     options for how to reply to an Access-Request that can't be serviced due to
     such error conditions:
	  <list style="numbers">
	   <t>Do Not Reply: The inability to reach a conclusion can be handled by
	   not replying to the request. The upside of this approach is that the
	   end user's software doesn't come to wrong conclusions and won't give
	   unhelpful hints such as "maybe your password is wrong". The downside is
	   that intermediate proxies may come to wrong conclusions because their
	   downstream RADIUS server isn't responding.
	   </t>
	   <t>Reply with Reject: In this option, the inability to reach a conclusion
	   is treated like an authentication failure. The upside of this approach is
	   that intermediate proxies maintain a correct view on the reachability
	   state of their RADIUS peer. The downside is that EAP supplicants on
	   end-user devices often react with either false advice ("your password is
	   wrong") or even trigger permanent configuration changes (e.g., the Windows
	   built-in supplicant will delete the credential set from its registry,
	   prompting the user for their password on the next connection attempt). The
	   latter case of Windows is a source of significant help-desk activity;
	   users may have forgotten their password after initially storing it but
	   are suddenly prompted again.
	   </t>
	  </list>
	  </t>
	</list>  



	 </t>

     <t>There have been epic discussions in the eduroam community as well as in the IETF RADEXT Working Group 
     as to which of the
     two approaches is more appropriate, but they were not conclusive.
     </t>
     <t>Similar considerations apply when an intermediate proxy does
     not receive a reply from a downstream RADIUS server. The proxy may either
     choose not to reply to the original request, leading to retries and its
     upstream peers coming to wrong conclusions about its own availability; or,
     it may decide to reply with Access-Reject to indicate its own liveliness,
     but again with implications for the end user.
     </t> 

    <t>The ability to send Status-Server watchdog requests is only of use
    after the fact, in case a downstream server doesn't reply (or hasn't been contacted 
    in a long while, so that its previous working state is stale). The active link-state
    monitoring of the TCP connection with, e.g., RADIUS/TLS (see <xref target="RadSec"/>), gives a clearer
    indication whether there is an alive RADIUS peer, but it does not solve the
    defunct back-end problem. An explicit ability to send Error-Replies, on the
    RADIUS level (for other RADIUS peer information) and EAP level (for end-user
    supplicant information), would alleviate these problems but is currently not
    available. 
    </t>
  </section> <!-- ISSUES-CLASSIC-ERRORS -->
  <section title="Routing Table Complexity" anchor="IssuesClassicRouting">
   <t>The aggregation of RADIUS requests based on the structure of the user's
   realm implies that realms ending with the same top-level domain are
   routed to the same server, i.e., to a common administrative domain. While
   this is true for country code Top-Level Domains (ccTLDs), which map into national 
   eduroam federations, it is not true for realms residing in generic Top-Level 
   Domains (gTLDs).
   Realms in gTLDs were historically discouraged because the automatic
   mapping "realm ending" -> "eduroam federation's server" could not be
   applied. However, with growing demand from eduroam realm administrators,
   it became necessary to create exception entries in the forwarding
   rules; such realms need to be mapped on a realm-by-realm basis to their
   eduroam federations. Example: "kit.edu" (Karlsruher Institut fuer Technologie) needs to 
   be routed to the German federation server, whereas "iu.edu" (Indiana University) needs 
   to be routed to the USA federation server.
   </t>
   <t>
   While the ccTLDs occupy only approximately 50 routing entries in total (and
   have an upper bound of approximately 200), the potential size of the routing
   table becomes virtually unlimited if it needs to accommodate all
   individual entries in .edu, .org, etc.
   </t>
   <t>
   In addition to that, all these routes need to be synchronized between
   three international root servers, and the updates need to be applied
   manually to RADIUS server configuration files. The frequency of the
   required updates makes this approach fragile and error-prone as the
   number of entries grows.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- ISSUES-CLASSIC-ROUTING -->
  <section title="UDP Issues" anchor="IssuesClassicUDP">

   <t>RADIUS is based on UDP, which was a reasonable choice when its main use
   was with simple Password Authentication Protocol (PAP) requests that required only exactly one packet
   exchange in each direction.
   </t>
   <t>When transporting EAP over RADIUS, the EAP conversations require
   multiple round-trips; depending on the total payload size, 8-10
   round-trips are not uncommon. The loss of a single UDP packet will lead
   to user-visible delays and might result in servers being marked as dead
   due to the absence of a reply. The proxy path in eduroam consists of
   several proxies, all of which introduce a very small packet loss probability;
   that is, the more proxies needed, the higher the failure rate is going
   to be.
   </t>
   <t>For some EAP types, depending on the exact payload size they carry,
   RADIUS servers and/or supplicants may choose to put as much EAP data
   into a single RADIUS packet as the supplicant's Layer 2 medium allows -- typically 1500 bytes. 
In that case, the RADIUS encapsulation around the EAP-Message will add
more bytes to the overall RADIUS payload size and in the end exceed the
1500-byte limit, leading to fragmentation of the UDP datagram on the IP
layer.
While in theory this is not a problem, in practice there is evidence of misbehaving firewalls that erroneously
   discard non-first UDP fragments; this ultimately leads to a denial of
   service for users with such EAP types and that specific configuration.
   </t>
   <t>One EAP type proved to be particularly problematic: EAP-TLS. While it is
   possible to configure the EAP server to send smaller chunks of EAP
   payload to the supplicant (e.g., 1200 bytes, to allow for another 300
   bytes of RADIUS overhead without fragmentation), very often the
   supplicants that send the client certificate do not expose such a
   configuration detail to the user. Consequently, when the client
   certificate is over 1500 bytes in size, the EAP-Message will always
   make use of the maximum possible Layer 2 chunk size, and this introduces
   fragmentation on the path from EAP peer to EAP server.
   </t>
   <t>Both of the previously mentioned sources of errors (packet loss and fragment discard) 
   lead to significant frustration for the affected users. Operational experience of 
   eduroam shows that such cases are hard to debug since they require coordinated 
   cooperation of all eduroam administrators on the authentication path. For that reason, 
   the eduroam community is developing monitoring tools that help to locate fragmentation 
   problems.
   </t>
   <t>Note: For more detailed discussion of these issues, please refer to Section 1.1 of <xref target="RFC6613"/>.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- ISSUES-CLASSIC-UDP -->
  <section title="Insufficient Payload Encryption and EAP Server Validation" anchor="Crypto">
   <t>The RADIUS protocol's design foresaw only the encryption of select
   RADIUS attributes, most notably User-Password. With EAP methods
   conforming to the requirements of <xref target="RFC4017"/>, the user's credential is not
   transmitted using the User-Password attribute, and stronger encryption
   than the one for RADIUS User-Password is in use (typically TLS).
   </t>
   <t>Still, the use of EAP does not encrypt all personally identifiable
   details of the user session, as some are carried inside cleartext RADIUS attributes. In particular, the user's device
   can be identified by inspecting the Calling-Station-ID attribute; and
   the user's location may be derived from observing NAS-IP-Address,
   NAS-Identifier, or Operator-Name attributes. Since these attributes are
   not encrypted, even IP-layer third parties can harvest the corresponding
   data. In a worst-case scenario, this enables the creation of mobility
   profiles. Pervasive passive surveillance using this connection metadata such as
the recently uncovered incidents in the US National Security
   Agency (NSA) and the UK Government Communications Headquarters
   (GCHQ) becomes possible by tapping
RADIUS traffic from an IP hop near a RADIUS aggregation proxy. While
this is possible, the authors are not aware whether this has actually
been done.
   </t>
   <t>These profiles are not necessarily linkable to an actual user because
   EAP allows for the use of anonymous outer identities and
   protected credential exchanges. However, practical experience has shown
   that many users neglect to configure their supplicants in a
   privacy-preserving way or their supplicants don't support that. In particular, for 
   EAP-TLS users, the use of EAP-TLS identity protection is not usually implemented and 
   cannot be used. In eduroam, concerned individuals and IdPs that use EAP-TLS are using
   pseudonymous client certificates to provide for better privacy.
   </t>
     <t>One way out, at least for EAP types involving a username, is to pursue
   the creation and deployment of preconfigured supplicant configurations
   that make all the required settings in user devices prior to their first
   connection attempt; this depends heavily on the remote configuration 
   possibilities of the supplicants though.
   </t>
   <t>
   A further threat involves the verification of the EAP server's identity.
   Even though the cryptographic foundation, TLS tunnels, is sound, there
   is a weakness in the supplicant configuration: many users do not understand
   or are not willing to invest time into the inspection of server certificates 
   or the installation of a trusted certification authority (CA). As a result, users may easily be tricked
   into connecting to an unauthorized EAP server, ultimately leading to
   a leak of their credentials to that unauthorized third party.
   </t>
   <t>
   Again, one way out of this particular threat is to pursue the creation
   and deployment of preconfigured supplicant configurations that make all
   the required settings in user devices prior to their first connection attempt.
   </t>
   <t>Note: There are many different and vendor-proprietary ways to 
   preconfigure a device with the necessary EAP parameters (examples include
   Apple, Inc.'s "mobileconfig" and Microsoft's "EAPHost" XML schema). Some 
   manufacturers even completely lack any means to distribute EAP configuration
   data. We believe there is value in defining a common EAP configuration metadata 
   format that could be used across manufacturers, ideally leading to
   a situation where IEEE 802.1X network end users merely need to apply
   this configuration file to configure any of their devices securely with the 
   required connection properties.
   </t>
   <t>Another possible privacy threat involves transport of user-specific attributes
   in a Reply-Message. If, for example, a RADIUS server sends back a
   hypothetical RADIUS Vendor-Specific-Attribute "User-Role = Student of
   Computer Science" (e.g., for consumption of an SP RADIUS server and
   subsequent assignment into a "student" VLAN), this information would
   also be visible for third parties and could be added to the mobility
   profile.
   </t>
   <t>The only way to mitigate all information leakage to third parties is
   by protecting the entire RADIUS packet payload so that IP-layer third
   parties cannot extract privacy-relevant information. RADIUS as
   specified in RFC 2865
   does not offer this possibility though. This motivated <xref
   target="RFC6614" />; see <xref target="RadSec"/>.
   </t>
  </section> <!-- CRYPTO -->
 </section> <!-- ISSUES-CLASSIC -->  
<section anchor="NewFederation" title="New Trust Fabric"> 
  <t>The operational difficulties with an ever-increasing number of
  participants (as 
  	documented in the previous section) have led to a number of changes to the eduroam
  	architecture that in turn have led to 
  	IETF specifications (as mentioned in the introduction).
  </t>
  <t>Note: The enhanced architecture components are fully backwards compatible with the
  	existing installed base and are, in fact, gradually replacing those parts of it where 
  	problems may arise.  
  </t>
   <t>Whereas the user authentication using IEEE 802.1X and EAP has remained unchanged (i.e., 
   no need for end users to change any configurations), the issues as reported
   in <xref target="IssuesClassic"/> have
   resulted in a major overhaul of the way EAP messages are transported from the RADIUS
   server of the SP to that of the IdP and back. The two fundamental changes are the use
   of TCP instead of UDP and reliance on TLS instead of shared secrets between RADIUS
   peers, as outlined in <xref target="radsec-whitepaper"/>.
   </t>
  <section title="RADIUS with TLS" anchor="RadSec"> 
	   <t>The deficiencies of RADIUS over UDP as described in 
		<xref target= "IssuesClassicUDP"/> warranted a search for a replacement of 
		RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865" /> for the transport of EAP. 

   By the time this need was understood, the
   designated successor protocol to RADIUS, Diameter, was
   already specified by the IETF in its intial version <xref target="RFC3588"/>.

 However, within the operational constraints of eduroam (listed below), no
 single combination of software could be found (and that is believed to still
 be true, more than ten years and one revision of Diameter <xref
 target="RFC6733"/> later). The constraints are:

		<list style="symbols">
		 <t>reasonably cheap to deploy on many administrative domains
		 </t>
		 <t>supporting the application of Network Access Server
		 Requirements (NASREQ)</t>
		 <t>supporting EAP application</t>
		 <t>supporting Diameter Redirect</t>
		 <t>supporting validation of authentication requests of the most popular
		 EAP types (EAP Tunneled Transport Layer Security (EAP&nbhy;TTLS), Protected EAP (PEAP), and EAP-TLS)</t>
		 <t>possibility to retrieve these credentials from popular back-ends such
		 as MySQL or Microsoft's Active Directory. </t>
		</list>
	   </t>
	   <t> In addition, no
	   Wi-Fi Access Points at the disposal of eduroam participants supported
	   Diameter, nor did any of the manufacturers have a roadmap towards Diameter 
	   support (and that is believed to still be true, more than 10 years later). This 
	   led to the open question of lossless translation from RADIUS 
	   to Diameter and vice versa -- a question not satisfactorily answered by NASREQ.
       </t>
       <t>After monitoring the Diameter implementation landscape for a while, it
       became clear that a solution with better compatibility and a plausible upgrade 
       path from the existing RADIUS hierarchy was needed. The eduroam community
       actively engaged in the IETF towards the specification of several enhancements to 
       RADIUS to overcome  the limitations mentioned in <xref target= "IssuesClassic"/>. 
       The outcome of this process was <xref target="RFC6614" /> and 
       <xref target="DYN-DISC" />.
       </t>
       <t>With its use of TCP instead of UDP, and with its full packet encryption,
       while maintaining full packet format compatibility with RADIUS/UDP, RADIUS/TLS 
       <xref target="RFC6614" /> allows any given RADIUS link in
       eduroam to be upgraded
       without the need of a "flag day".
       </t>
       <t>In a first upgrade phase, the classic eduroam hierarchy (forwarding
       decision made by inspecting the realm) remains intact. That way, 
       RADIUS/TLS merely enhances the underlying transport of the RADIUS datagrams. But, 
       this already provides some key advantages:
        <list style="symbols">
         <t>explicit peer reachability detection using long-lived TCP sessions
         </t>
         <t>protection of user credentials and all privacy-relevant RADIUS attributes
         </t>
        </list>
       </t>
       <t>RADIUS/TLS connections for the static hierarchy could be realized with
       the TLS-PSK <xref target="RFC4279"/> operation mode (which effectively provides a 1:1 replacement
       for RADIUS/UDP's "shared secrets"), but since this operation mode is not
       widely supported as of yet, all RADIUS/TLS links in eduroam are secured
       by TLS with X.509 certificates from a set of accredited CAs.
       </t>
       <t>This first deployment phase does not yet solve the routing table
       complexity problem (see <xref target="IssuesClassicRouting" />); this aspect is 
       covered by introducing dynamic discovery for RADIUS/TLS servers.
       </t>
  </section>  <!-- RadSec -->
  <section title="Dynamic Discovery" anchor="DynamicDiscovery"> 
   <t>When introducing peer discovery, two separate issues had to be addressed:
    <list style="numbers">
     <t>how to find the network address of a responsible RADIUS server for a given realm
     </t>
     <t>how to verify that this realm is an authorized eduroam participant
     </t>
    </list> 
   </t>
   <section title="Discovery of Responsible Server" anchor="ServerDiscovery">
    <t>Issue 1 can relatively simply be addressed by putting eduroam-specific service 
    discovery information into the global DNS tree. In eduroam, this is done by using NAPTR records as per the S-NAPTR specification <xref target="RFC3958"/> with a 
    private-use NAPTR service tag ("x-eduroam:radius.tls"). The usage profile of that 
    NAPTR resource record is that exclusively "S" type delegations are allowed and that 
    no regular expressions are allowed.
    </t>
    <t>A subsequent lookup of the resulting SRV records will eventually yield hostnames 
    and IP addresses of the authoritative server(s) of a given realm.
    </t>
    <t>Example (wrapped for readability):
    </t>
    <t>
     <figure anchor="NAPTR" title="SRV Record Lookup">
      <artwork>
       <![CDATA[ 
> dig -t naptr education.example.

;; ANSWER SECTION:
education.example.            43200   IN      NAPTR   100 10 "s" 
                                  "x-eduroam:radius.tls" "" 
                                  _radsec._tcp.eduroam.example.

        
> dig -t srv _radsec._tcp.eduroam.example.

;; ANSWER SECTION:
_radsec._tcp.eduroam.example. 43200  IN      SRV     0 0 2083 
                                             tld1.eduroam.example.

> dig -t aaaa tld1.eduroam.example.

;; ANSWER SECTION:
tld1.eduroam.example.         21751  IN      AAAA    2001:db8:1::2
       ]]></artwork>
     </figure> 
    </t> 
    <t>From the operational experience with this mode of operation, eduroam is pursuing 
    standardization of this approach for generic AAA use cases. The current RADEXT working 
    group document for this is <xref target="DYN-DISC" />.
    </t>
    <t>Note: It is worth mentioning that this move to a more complex, flexible system may 
    make the system as a whole more fragile, as compared to the static set up.
    </t>
   </section>  <!-- ServerDiscovery -->
   <section title="Verifying Server Authorization" anchor="ServerVerification">
    <t>Any organization can put "x-eduroam" NAPTR entries into their Domain Name Server, 
    pretending to be the eduroam Identity Provider for the corresponding realm. Since eduroam 
    is a service for a heterogeneous, but closed, user group, additional sources of 
    information need to be consulted to verify that a realm with its discovered server is
    actually an eduroam participant.
    </t>
    <t>The eduroam consortium has chosen to deploy a separate PKI that issues 
    certificates only to authorized eduroam Identity Providers and eduroam Service Providers. Since 
    certificates are needed for RADIUS/TLS anyway, it was a straightforward solution to reuse the PKI for that. 
    The PKI fabric allows multiple CAs as trust roots (overseen by a Policy Management 
    Authority) and requires that certificates that were issued to verified eduroam 
    participants are marked with corresponding "X509v3 Policy OID" fields; eduroam RADIUS 
    servers and clients need to verify the existence of these OIDs in the incoming 
    certificates. 
    </t>
    <t>The policies and OIDs can be retrieved from the "eduPKI Trust Profile for 
    eduroam Certificates" <xref target="eduPKI" />.
    </t>
   </section> <!-- ServerVerification -->
   <section title="Operational Experience" anchor="OperationalExperienceDynamic"> 

    <t>The discovery model is currently deployed in approximately 10 
    countries that participate in eduroam, making more than 100 realms discoverable via their 
    NAPTR records. Experience has shown that the model works and scales as expected, the 
    only drawback being that the additional burden of operating a PKI that is not local 
    to the national eduroam administrators creates significant administrative complexities. 
    Also, the presence of multiple CAs and regular updates of Certificate Revocation Lists 
    makes the operation of RADIUS servers more complex.
    </t>
   </section> <!-- OperationalExperienceDiscovery -->
   <section title="Possible Alternatives" anchor="DiscoveryAlternatives">
    <t>There are two alternatives to this approach to dynamic server discovery
    that are monitored by the eduroam 
    community:
       <list style="numbers">
        <t>DNSSEC + DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE) TLSA records</t>
        <t>ABFAB Trust Router</t>
       </list> 
     For DNSSEC+DANE TLSA, the biggest advantage is that the certificate data itself 
     can be stored in the DNS -- possibly obsoleting the PKI infrastructure *if* a new 
     place for the server authorization checks can be found. Its most significant 
     downside is that the DANE specifications only include client-to-server certificate 
     checks, while RADIUS/TLS requires also server-to-client verification.
    </t>
    <t>For the ABFAB Trust Router, the biggest advantage is that it would work without 
     certificates altogether (by negotiating TLS-PSK keys ad hoc). The downside is 
     that it is currently not formally specified and not as thoroughly understood as any 
     of the other solutions. 
    </t>
   </section> <!-- DiscoveryAlternatives -->
  </section> <!-- dynamic-discovery -->
</section> <!-- NewFederation -->
<section title="Abuse Prevention and Incident Handling" anchor="AbuseIncident"> 
   <t>Since the eduroam service is a confederation of autonomous networks, there
   is little justification for transferring accounting information from
   the Service Provider to any other (in general) or to the Identity Provider 
   of the user (in particular). Accounting in eduroam is therefore considered to be a 
   local matter of the Service Provider. The eduroam compliance statement 
   <xref target="eduroam-compliance" /> in fact specifies that accounting
   traffic <xref target="RFC5280"/>
   SHOULD NOT be forwarded.
   </t>
   <t>The static routing infrastructure of eduroam acts as a filtering system 
   blocking accounting traffic from misconfigured local RADIUS
   servers. Proxy servers are configured to terminate accounting
   request traffic by answering to Accounting-Requests with an Accounting-Response
   in order to prevent the retransmission of orphaned Accounting-Request
   messages. With dynamic discovery, Identity Providers that are discoverable via
DNS will need to apply these filtering measures themselves. This is an
increase in complexity of the Identity Provider RADIUS
configuration.
   </t>
   <t>Roaming creates accountability problems, as identified by <xref target="RFC4372" /> (Chargeable
   User Identity). Since the NAS can only see the (likely anonymous) outer identity of 
   the user, it is impossible to correlate usage with a specific user (who may
   use multiple devices). 


A NAS that supports <xref target="RFC4372"/> can request
   the Chargeable-User-Identity and, if supplied
   by the authenticating RADIUS server in the Access-Accept message, add
   this value to corresponding Access-Request packets. While
   eduroam does not have any charging mechanisms, it may still be desirable
   to identify traffic originating from one particular user. One of the reasons is to
   prevent abuse of guest access by users living near university
   campuses. Chargeable User Identity (see <xref target="CUI"/>) supplies the perfect answer to
   this problem; however, at the time of writing, to our knowledge, only one hardware 
   vendor (Meru Networks) implements RFC 4372 on their access points. For all other 
   vendors, requesting the Chargeable-User-Identity attribute needs to happen on the 
   RADIUS server to which the access point is connected to. FreeRADIUS supports this ability 
   in the latest distribution, and Radiator can be retrofitted to do the same.
   </t>
   <section title="Incident Handling" anchor="IncidentHandling"> 
    <t>10 years of experience with eduroam have not exposed any serious
    incident. This may be taken as evidence for proper security design as well as suggest 
    that users' awareness that they are identifiable acts as an effective
    deterrent. It could of course also mean that eduroam operations lack the proper tools 
    or insight into the actual use and potential abuse of the service. In any case, many 
    of the attack vectors that exist in open networks or networks where access control is 
    based on shared secrets are not present, arguably leading to a much more secure system.
    </t>
    <t>Below is a discussion of countermeasures that are taken in eduroam.
    </t>
    <t>
    The European eduroam Policy Service Definition <xref target="eduroam-service-definition" />, as an example, describes 
    incident scenarios and actions to be taken; in this document, we present the relevant 
    technical issues.
    </t>
    <t>The initial implementation has been lacking reliable tools for an SP
   to make its own decision or for an IdP to introduce a conditional
   rule applying only to a given SP.  The introduction of support for
   Operator-Name and Chargeable-User-Identity (see <xref target="CUI"/>) to eduroam
   makes both of these scenarios possible.
    </t>


	<section title="Blocking Users on the SP Side" anchor="blocking-sp">
	<t>The first action in the case of an incident is to block the user's
   access to eduroam at the Service Provider.  Since the roaming user's
   true identity is likely hidden behind an anonymous/fake outer
   identity, the Service Provider can only rely on the realm of the
   user and his MAC address; if the Identity Provider has already sent
   a Chargeable-User-Identity (see <xref target="CUI"/> for details), then this
   extra information can be used to identify the user more reliably.
</t><t>
   A first attempt at the SP side may be to block based on the MAC
   address or outer identity. This blocking can be executed before the
   EAP authentication occurs -- typically in the first datagram, acting
   on the RADIUS attributes EAP-Message/EAP-Response/Identity and
   Calling-Station-ID. The datagram can either be dropped (supplicant
   notices a time-out) or replied to with a RADIUS Access-Reject
   containing an EAP-Failure. Since malicious users can change both
   their MAC addresses and the local part of their outer identity
   between connection attempts, this first attempt is not sufficient to
   lock out a determined user.
</t><t>
   As a second measure, the SP can let the EAP authentication proceed
   as normal, and verify whether the final Access-Accept response from
   the RADIUS server contains a Chargeable-User-Identity (CUI). If so,
   the SP RADIUS server can be configured to turn all future Access-Accepts for this CUI into an Access-Reject/EAP-Failure. This measure
   is effective and efficient: it locks out exactly the one user that
   is supposed to be locked out, and it has no side-effects on other
   users, even from the same realm.
</t><t>
   If the EAP authentication does not reveal a CUI, the SP cannot
   reliably determine the user in question. The only reliable
   information to act upon is then the realm portion of the outer
   identity of the user. The SP will need to resort to blocking the
   entire realm that the offending user belongs to. 
   This is effective, but not efficient: it locks out the user in
   question, but has a DoS side-effect on all other visiting users from
   the same realm.
</t><t>
   In the absence of a CUI handle, SPs that are not willing to take
   the drastic step of blocking an entire realm will be forced to
   contact the Identity Provider in question and demand that the user
   be blocked at the IdP side. 


This involves human interaction between
   SP and IdP and is not possible in real-time.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Blocking Users on the IdP Side" anchor="blocking-idp">
	<t>
The IdP has the power to disable a user account altogether, thus
   blocking this user from accessing eduroam in all sites. If blocking
   the user is done due a request of an SP (as per the previous section),
   there may be a more fine-grained possibility to block access to a
   specific SP -- if the SP in question sends the Operator-Name
   attribute along with his Access-Requests (see <xref target="OperatorName"/> for
   details).
</t><t>
   If the IdP decides to block the user globally, this is typically
   done by treating the login attempt as if the credentials were wrong:
   the entire EAP conversation needs to be executed to the point where
   the true inner identity is revealed (before that, the IdP does not
   know yet which user is attempting to authenticate). This typically
   coincides with the point in time where credentials are exchanged.
   Instead of, or in addition to, checking the credential for validity,
   the Identity Provider also checks whether the user's account is
   (still) eligible for eduroam use and will return an Access-Reject/EAP-Failure if not.
</t><t>
   There may well be cases where opinions between the SP desiring a
   user lockout and the IdP of the user differ. For example, an SP might
   consider massive amounts of up-/downloads with file sharing protocols unacceptable as per local policy, and desire
   blocking of users that create too much traffic -- but the IdP does not
   take offense on such actions and would not want to lock his user out
   of eduroam globally because of this one SP's opinion.
</t><t>
   In the absence of the Operator-Name attribute, there is no way to
   apply a login restriction only for a given SP and not eduroam as a
   whole; eduroam eligibility is an all-or-nothing decision for the IdP.
</t><t>
   If the Operator-Name attribute is present, the IdP can use this
   information to fail the authentication attempt only if the attempt
   originated from SPs that desire such blocking. Even though the
   Operator-Name attribute is available from the first RADIUS Access-
   Request datagram onwards, the EAP authentication needs to be carried
   out until the true inner identity is known just as in the global
   blocking case above. The Operator-Name is simply an additional piece
   of information that the IdP can use to make its decision.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Communicating Account Blocking to the End User" anchor="blocking-communicate">
<t>
 The measures described in Sections <xref target="blocking-sp" format="counter"/> and <xref
 target="blocking-idp" format="counter"/>  alter the EAP conversation. They either
   create a premature rejection or timeout at the start of the
   conversation or change the outcome of the authentication attempt at
   the very end of the conversation.
</t><t>
   On the supplicant side, these alterations are indistinguishable from
   an infrastructure failure: a premature rejection or timeout could be
   due to a RADIUS server being unresponsive, and a rejection at the
   end of the conversation could be either user error (wrong password)
   or server error (credential lookup failed). For the supplicant, it
   is thus difficult to communicate a meaningful error to the user. 
   The newly specified EAP type TEAP, Tunnel Extensible Authentication Protocol <xref target="RFC7170"/>, 
   has a means to transport fine-grained error reason codes to the supplicant;
   this has the potential to improve the situation in the future.
</t><t>
   The EAP protocol foresees one mechanism to provide such
   user-interactive communication: the EAP state machine contains
   states that allow user-visible communication. An extra round of
   EAP-Request/Notification and the corresponding acknowledgement can
   be injected before the final EAP-Failure.
</t><t>
   However, anecdotal evidence suggests that supplicants typically do
   not implement this part of the EAP state machine at all. One
   supplicant is reported to support it, but only logs the contents of
   the notification in a log file -- which is not at all helpful for the
   end user.
</t><t>
   The discovery of reasons and scope of account blocking are thus left
   as an out-of-band action. The eduroam user support process requires
   that users with authentication problems contact their Identity
   Provider as a first measure (via unspecified means, e.g., they could
   phone their IdP or send an email via a 3G backup link). If the
   Identity Provider is the one that blocked their access, the user
   will immediately be informed by them. If the reason for blocking is
   at the SP side, the Identity Provider will instead inform the user
   that the account is in working order and that the user needs to
   contact the SP IT support to get further insight. In that case, that
   SP-side IT support will notify the users about the reasons for
   blocking.
</t>
	</section>
   </section> <!-- IncidentHandling -->
   <section title="Operator Name" anchor="OperatorName"> 
	<t>
	The Operator-Name attribute is defined in <xref target="RFC5580" /> as a means of unique
	identification of the access site.
	</t>
	<t>The Proxy infrastructure of eduroam makes it impossible for home sites to tell
	where their users roam. While this may be seen as a positive aspect
	enhancing user's privacy, it also makes user support, roaming statistics,
	and blocking offending user's access to eduroam significantly harder.
	</t>
	<t>Sites participating in eduroam are encouraged to add the Operator-Name attribute 
	using the REALM namespace, i.e., sending a realm name under control of the
	given site.
	</t>
	<t>The introduction of Operator-Name in eduroam has led to the
	identification of one operational
	problem -- the identifier 126 assigned to this attribute has been
	previously used by some vendors for their specific purposes and
	has been included in attribute dictionaries of several RADIUS server
	distributions.

   Since the syntax of this hijacked attribute
   had been set to Integer, this introduces a syntax clash with the 
   RFC definition (which defines it as Text).

 Operational tests in eduroam have shown that servers using
	the Integer syntax for attribute 126 may either truncate the value to 4
	octets or even drop the entire RADIUS packet (thus making authentication
	impossible). The eduroam monitoring and eduroam test tools try to locate
	problematic sites. Section 2.8 of <xref target="RFC6929" /> clarifies the handling of these packets.
	</t>
	<t>When a Service Provider sends its Operator-Name value, it creates a
	possibility for the home sites to set up conditional blocking rules,
	depriving certain users of access to selected sites. Such action will
	cause much less concern than blocking users from all of eduroam.
	</t>
	<t>In eduroam, the Operator Name is also used for the generation of Chargeable User
	Identity values.
	</t>
	<t>The addition of Operator-Name is a straightforward configuration of the RADIUS
	server and may be easily introduced on a large scale.
	</t>
   </section> <!-- OperatorName -->
   <section title="Chargeable User Identity" anchor="CUI"> 
	<t>The Chargeable-User-Identity (CUI) attribute is defined by 
	RFC 4372 <xref target="RFC4372" /> as an answer to accounting problems caused by the use of 
	anonymous identity in some EAP methods. In eduroam, the primary use of CUI is in 
	incident handling, but it can also enhance local accounting.
	</t>
	<t>The eduroam policy requires that a given user's CUI generated for requests
	originating from different sites should be different (to prevent collusion attacks). 
	The eduroam policy thus mandates that a CUI request be accompanied by the 
	Operator-Name attribute, which is used as one of the inputs for the CUI generation 
	algorithm. The Operator-Name requirement is considered to be the "business requirement"
	described in Section 2.1 of RFC 4372 <xref target="RFC4372" /> and hence conforms to the RFC.
	</t>
	<t>When eduroam started considering using CUI, there were
	no NAS implementations; therefore, the only solution was moving all CUI
	support to the RADIUS server.</t>
	<t>CUI request generation requires only the addition of NUL CUI attributes
	to outgoing Access-Requests; however, the real strength of CUI comes
	with accounting. Implementation of CUI-based accounting in the server
	requires that the authentication and accounting RADIUS servers used
	directly by the NAS are actually the same or at least have access to a
	common source of information. Upon processing of an Access-Accept, the
	authenticating RADIUS server must store the received CUI value together with
	the device's Calling-Station-Id in a temporary database. Upon receipt
	of an Accounting-Request, the server needs to update the packet with
	the CUI value read from the database.
	</t>
	<t>A wide introduction of CUI support in eduroam will significantly simplify
	incident handling at Service Providers. Introducing local, per-user access
	restriction will be possible. Visited sites will also be able to notify
	the home site about the introduction of such a restriction, pointing to
	the CUI value and thus making it possible for the home site to identify
	the user. When the user reports the problem at his home support, the
	reason will be already known.
	</t>
  </section> <!--CUI -->
</section> <!-- AbuseIncident -->
<section title="Privacy Considerations" anchor="PrivacyConsiderations"> 
	<t>
   	 The eduroam architecture has been designed with protection of user credentials in 
   	 mind, as may be clear from reading this far. However, operational experience has
   	 revealed some more subtle points with regards to privacy.
	</t>
	<section title="Collusion of Service Providers" anchor="Collusion">
		<t>If users use anonymous outer identities, SPs cannot easily 
		collude by linking 
		outer identities to users that are visiting their
		campus. However, this poses 
		problems with remediation of abuse or misconfiguration. It is impossible to find
		the user that exhibits unwanted behaviour or whose system has been compromised.
		</t>
		<t>For that reason, the Chargeable-User-Identity has been introduced in eduroam, 
		constructed so that only the IdP of the user can uniquely identify the user. In 
		order to prevent collusion attacks, that CUI is
		required to be unique per user and per 
		Service Provider.
		</t>
	</section> <!-- collusion -->
	<section title="Exposing User Credentials" anchor="UserCreds">
		<t>Through the use of EAP, user credentials are not visible to anyone but the IdP
		of the user. That is, if a sufficiently secure EAP method is chosen and EAP is not terminated prematurely.
		</t>
		<t>There is one privacy sensitive user attribute that is necessarily exposed to 
		third parties and that is the realm the user belongs to. Routing in eduroam is
		based on the realm part of the user identifier, so even though the outer identity
		in a tunneled EAP method may be set to an anonymous identifier, it MUST contain the
		realm of the user, and may thus lead to identifying the user if the realm in question contains few users. This is considered 
		a reasonable trade-off between user privacy and usability. 
		</t>
	</section> <!-- user-creds -->


	<section title="Track Location of Users" anchor="Track">
		<t>Due to the fact that access requests (potentially) travel through a number of 
		proxy RADIUS servers, the home IdP of the user typically cannot tell where a 
		user roams.</t>
		<t>However, the introduction of Operator-Name and dynamic lookups (i.e., direct connections 
		between IdP and SP) gives the home IdP insight into the location of the user. 
		</t>
	</section> <!-- track -->	
</section> <!-- privacy-considerations -->
<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="SecurityConsiderations"> 
	<t>
 		This section addresses only security considerations associated
   		with the use of eduroam.  For considerations relating to IEEE 802.1X, RADIUS, and EAP 
   		in general, the reader is referred to the respective specification and to other 
   		literature.  
	</t>
	<section title="Man-in-the-Middle and Tunneling Attacks" anchor="MitM">
		<t>The security of user credentials in eduroam ultimately lies within the
        EAP server verification during the EAP conversation. Therefore, the
        eduroam policy mandates that only EAP types capable of mutual
        authentication are allowed in the infrastructure, and requires that
        IdPs publish all information that is required to uniquely
        identify the server (i.e., usually the EAP server's CA certificate and
        its Common Name or subjectAltName:dNSName).
        </t>
        <t>
        While in principle this makes man-in-the-middle attacks impossible,
	in practice several attack vectors exist nonetheless. Most of
        these deficiencies are due to implementation shortcomings in EAP
        supplicants. Examples:</t>
        <section title="Verification of Server Name Not Supported" anchor="ServerVerificationNotSupported">
          <t>
          Some supplicants only allow specifying which CA issues the EAP server
          certificate; its name is not checked. As a result, any entity that is
          able to get a server certificate from the same CA can create its own EAP
          server and trick the end user to submit his credentials to that fake server.
          </t>
          <t>
          As a mitigation to that problem, eduroam Operations suggests the use of
          a private CA that exclusively issues certificates to the organization's
          EAP servers. In that case, no other entity will get a certificate from
          the CA and this supplicant shortcoming does not present a security
          threat any more.
          </t>
        </section> <!-- ServerVerificationNotSupported -->
        <section title="Neither Specification of CA nor Server Name Checks during Bootstrap" anchor="NoNameCheck">
          <t>
          Some supplicants allow for insecure bootstrapping in that
	  they allow the simple selection of a network the acceptance of the incoming server certificate,
          identified by its fingerprint. The certificate is then saved as trusted
          for later reconnection attempts. If users are near a fake hotspot
          during initial provisioning, they may be tricked to submit their
          credentials to a fake server; furthermore, they will be branded to trust
          only that fake server in the future.
          </t>
          <t>
          eduroam Identity Providers are advised to provide their users with
          complete documentation for setup of their supplicants without the
          shortcut of insecure bootstrapping. In addition, eduroam Operations has created a
          tool that makes correct, complete, and secure settings on many
          supplicants: eduroam CAT <xref target="eduroam-CAT"/>.
          </t>
        </section> <!-- NoNameCheck -->
        <section title="User Does Not Configure CA or Server Name Checks" anchor="UserNoNameCheck">
          <t>
          Unless automatic provisioning tools such as eduroam CAT are used, it is
          cumbersome for users to initially configure an EAP supplicant securely.
          User interfaces of supplicants often invite the users to take shortcuts
          ("Don't check server certificate") that are easier to set up or hide
          important security settings in badly accessible sub-menus. Such
          shortcuts or security parameter omissions make the user subject to
          man-in-the-middle attacks.
          </t>
          <t>
          eduroam IdPs are advised to educate their users regarding
          the necessary steps towards a secure setup. eduroam Research and Development is 
          in touch with supplicant developers to improve their user interfaces.
          </t>
        </section> <!-- UserNoNameCheck -->
        <section title="Tunneling Authentication Traffic to Obfuscate User Origin" anchor="TunnelingAuthN">
          <t>
          There is no link between the EAP outer ("anonymous") identity and the
          EAP inner ("real") identity. In particular, they can both contain a
          realm name, and the realms need not be identical. It is possible to
          craft packets with an outer identity of user@RealmB, and an inner
          identity of user@realmA. With the eduroam request routing, a Service
          Provider would assume that the user is from realmB and send the request
          there. The server at realmB inspects the inner user name, and if
          proxying is not explicitly disabled for tunneled request content, may
          decide to send the tunneled EAP payload to realmA, where the  user
          authenticates. A CUI value would likely be generated by the server at
          realmB, even though this is not its user.
          </t>
          <t>
          Users can craft such packets to make their identification harder;
          usually, the eduroam SP would assume that the troublesome user originates
          from realmB and demand there that the user be
	  blocked. However, the operator of
          realmB has no control over the user and can only trace back the
          user to his real origin if  logging of proxied requests is also enabled
          for EAP tunnel data.
          </t>
          <t>
          eduroam Identity Providers are advised to explicitly disable proxying on
          the parts of their RADIUS server configuration that process EAP
          tunnel data.
          </t>
        </section> <!-- TunnelingAuthN -->
	</section> <!-- MitM  -->		
	<section title="Denial-of-Service Attacks" anchor="DoS">
	  <t>
	  Since eduroam's roaming infrastructure is based on IP and RADIUS, it
      suffers from the usual DoS attack vectors that apply to these protocols.
      </t>

      <t>
      The eduroam hotspots are susceptible to typical attacks on edge
      networks, such as rogue Router Advertisements (RAs), rogue DHCP servers, and others. Notably,
      eduroam hotspots
      are more robust against malign users' DHCP pool exhaustion than typical
      open or "captive portal" hotspots, because a DHCP address is only leased
      after a successful authentication, thereby reducing the pool of possible
      attackers to eduroam account holders (as opposed to the general public).
      Furthermore, attacks involving ARP spoofing or ARP flooding are also
      reduced to authenticated users, because an attacker needs to be in
      possession of a valid WPA2 session key to be able to send traffic on
      the network.
      </t>
      <t>
      This section does not discuss standard threats to edge networks
      and IP networks in general. The following sections describe attack
      vectors specific to eduroam.
	  </t> 
       <section title="Intentional DoS by Malign Individuals" anchor="MalignDoS">   
       <t>
       The eduroam infrastructure is more robust against Distributed DoS
       attacks than typical services
 that are reachable on the Internet because triggering authentication
       traffic can only be done when physically in proximity of an
       eduroam hotspot (be it a wired socket that is IEEE 802.1X enabled or 
a Wi-Fi Access Point).
       </t>



       <t>
       However, when in the vicinity, an attacker can easily craft authentication
       attempts that traverse the entire international eduroam infrastructure;
       an attacker merely needs to choose a realm from another world region
       than his physical location to trigger Access-Requests that need to be
       processed by the SP, then SP-side national, then world region, then
       target world region, then target national, then target IdP server. So
       long as the realm actually exists, this will be followed by an entire
       EAP conversation on that path. Not having actual credentials, the
       request will ultimately be rejected, but it consumed processing power
       and bandwidth across the entire infrastructure, possibly affecting all
       international authentication traffic.
       </t>
       <t>
       EAP is a lock-step protocol. A single attacker at an eduroam hotspot can
       only execute one EAP conversation after another and is thus
       rate-limited by round-trip times of the RADIUS chain.
       </t>
       <t>
       Currently, eduroam processes several hundred thousands of successful
       international roaming authentications per day (and, incidentally,
       approximately 1.5 times as many Access-Rejects). With the requirement of
       physical proximity, and the rate-limiting induced by EAP's lock-step
       nature, it requires a significant amount of attackers and a
       time-coordinated attack to produce significant load. So far, eduroam Operations
       has not yet observed critical load conditions that could reasonably be
       attributed to such an attack.
       </t>
       <t>
       The introduction of dynamic discovery further eases this problem, as
       authentications will then not traverse all infrastructure servers,
       removing the world-region aggregation servers as obvious bottlenecks.
       Any attack would then be limited between an SP and IdP directly.
       </t>
	  </section> <!-- MalignDoS  -->	
	  <section title="DoS as a Side-Effect of Expired Credentials" anchor="ExpiredCredsDoS"> 
	    <t>  
        In eduroam Operations, it is observed that a significant portion of (failed)
        eduroam authentications is due to user accounts that were once valid
        but have in the meantime been de-provisioned (e.g., if a student has left
        the university after graduation). Configured eduroam accounts are often
        retained on the user devices, and when in the vicinity of an eduroam
        hotspot, the user device's operating system will attempt to connect to
        this network.
        </t>
        <t>
        As operation of eduroam continues, the amount of devices with leftover
        configurations is growing, effectively creating a pool of devices that
        produce unwanted network traffic whenever they can.
        </t>
        <t>
        Until recently, this problem did not emerge with much prominence,
        because there is also a natural shrinking of that pool of devices due to
        users finally decommissioning their old computing hardware.
        </t>
        <t>
        Recently, smartphones are programmed to make use of
        cloud storage and online backup mechanisms that save most, or all,
        configuration details of the device with a third party. When renewing
        their personal computing hardware, users can restore the old settings
        onto the new device. It has been observed that expired eduroam accounts
        can survive perpetually on user devices that way. If this trend
        continues, it can be pictured that an always-growing pool of devices
        will clog up eduroam infrastructure with doomed-to-fail authentication
        requests.
        </t>
        <t>
        There is not currently a useful remedy to this problem, other than
        instructing users to manually delete their configuration in due time.
        Possible approaches to this problem are:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Creating a culture of device provisioning where the provisioning
            profile contains a "ValidUntil" property, after which the configuration
            needs to be re-validated or disabled. This requires a data format for
            provisioning as well as implementation support.</t>
            <t>Improvements to supplicant software so that it maintains state over
            failed authentications. For example, if a previously known
	    working configuration
            failed to authenticate consistently for 30 calendar days, it should be
            considered stale and be disabled.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section> <!-- ExpiredCredsDoS  -->	
	 </section>  <!-- DoS -->		
</section> <!-- security-considerations -->

</middle> 
<back> 
<references title="Normative References"> 

	&RFC2119; &RFC2865; &RFC3748; &RFC4279; &RFC4372; &RFC5280;
	&RFC5246;  &RFC5580; &RFC5997; &RFC6613; &RFC6614; 
	&RFC6973; 
</references>
<references title="Informative References">

&RFC3588;
&RFC3958;
&RFC4017; 
&RFC6929;
&RFC7170;
&RFC6733;
&RFC7542;

<!--  draft-ietf-radext-dynamic-discovery-15: in Queue in REF -->
<reference anchor='DYN-DISC'>
<front>
<title>NAI-based Dynamic Peer Discovery for RADIUS/TLS and RADIUS/DTLS</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Winter' fullname='Stefan Winter'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='McCauley' fullname='Mike McCauley'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='29' year='2015' />

<abstract><t>This document specifies a means to find authoritative RADIUS servers for a given realm.  It is used in conjunction with either RADIUS/TLS and RADIUS/DTLS.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-radext-dynamic-discovery-15' />

</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-abfab-arch-13: In queue in MISSREF -->
<reference anchor='ABFAB-ARCH'>
<front>
<title>Application Bridging for Federated Access Beyond Web (ABFAB) Architecture</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Howlett' fullname='Josh Howlett'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Hartman' fullname='Sam Hartman'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E' surname='Lear' fullname='Eliot Lear'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Schaad' fullname='Jim Schaad'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='21' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>Over the last decade a substantial amount of work has occurred in the space of federated access management.  Most of this effort has focused on two use cases: network access and web-based access. However, the solutions to these use cases that have been proposed and deployed tend to have few building blocks in common.  This memo describes an architecture that makes use of extensions to the commonly used security mechanisms for both federated and non- federated access management, including the Remote Authentication Dial In User Service (RADIUS) the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API), the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) and the Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML).  The architecture addresses the problem of federated access management to primarily non-web-based services, in a manner that will scale to large numbers of identity providers, relying parties, and federations.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-abfab-arch-13' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='IEEE.802.1X'
	   target='http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=5409757'>
 <front>
  <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Port-Based
  Network Access Control</title>
  <author>
   <organization>IEEE</organization>
  </author>
  <date/>
  <abstract><t>Port-based network access control allows a network
  administrator to restrict the use of IEEE 802 LAN service access points
  (ports) to secure communication between authenticated and authorized
  devices. This standard specifies a common architecture, functional elements,
  and protocols that support mutual authentication between the clients of
  ports attached to the same LAN and that secure communication between the
  ports, including the media access method independent protocols that are used
  to discover and establish the security associations used by IEEE 802.1AETM
  MAC Security.</t>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name='IEEE' value='802.1X-2010' />
 <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.1109/ieeestd.2010.5409813' />
</reference>
	
	
	<reference anchor="radsec-whitepaper"
		target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/radsec-whitepaper.pdf">
		<front>
			<title>RadSec: a secure, reliable RADIUS Protocol</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="OSC">Open System Consultants</organization>
			</author>
			<date month="October" year="2012"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/radsec-whitepaper.pdf"/>
	</reference>
	

<reference anchor="eduroam-start"
                        target="http://www.terena.org/activities/tf-mobility/start-of-eduroam.pdf">
                        <front>
    <title>Subject: proposal for inter NREN roaming</title>

                                <author initials="K." surname="Wierenga"
					fullname="Klaas Wierenga">
                                        <organization abbrev="SURFnet">SURFnet  
                                        </organization>
				</author>
				<date month="30 May" year="2002"/>
			</front>
<seriesInfo name="message to the mobility@terena.nl mailing list," value="initial proposal for what is now called eduroam"/>
			<format type="PDF" 
				target="http://www.terena.org/activities/tf-mobility/start-of-eduroam.pdf"/>
		</reference>
		
		<reference anchor="eduroam-homepage" target="http://www.eduroam.org/">
			<front>
				<title>eduroam Homepage</title>
				<author>
					<organization abbrev="TERENA">Trans-European
						Research and Education Networking Association
					</organization>
				</author>
				<date year="2007"/>
			</front>
			<format type="TXT" target="http://www.eduroam.org/"/>
		</reference>	
		


		<reference anchor="nrenroaming-select" target="http://www.terena.org/activities/tf-mobility/deliverables/delG/DelG-final.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>Preliminary selection for inter-NREN roaming</title>
				<author>
					<organization abbrev="TERENA">Trans-European
						Research and Education Networking Association
					</organization>
				</author>
				<date month="December" year="2003"/>
			</front>
			<format type="PDF" target="http://www.terena.org/activities/tf-mobility/deliverables/delG/DelG-final.pdf"/>
		</reference>	
		
		<reference anchor="eduroam-compliance"
		 target="http://www.eduroam.org/downloads/docs/eduroam_Compliance_Statement_v1_0.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>eduroam Compliance Statement</title>
				<author>
					<organization abbrev="TERENA">Trans-European
						Research and Education Networking Association
					</organization>
				</author>
				<date month="October" year="2011"/>
			</front>

		</reference>
		

                <reference anchor="eduroam-service-definition"
                 target="https://www.eduroam.org/downloads/docs/GN3-12-192_eduroam-policy-service-definition_ver28_26072012.pdf">
                        <front>
                                <title>eduroam Policy Service Definition</title>
                                <author>
                                        <organization>GEANT</organization>
                                </author>
                                <date month="July" year="2012"/>
                        </front>
<seriesInfo name="Version" value="2.8"/>
                </reference>

		
		<reference anchor="eduroam-CAT"
		 target="https://cat.eduroam.org">
			<front>
				<title>eduroam CAT</title>
				<author>
					<organization abbrev="Dante">Delivery of Advanced Network Technology to Europe
					</organization>
				</author>
				<date year="2012"/>
			</front>
			<format type="TXT" 
			 target="https://cat.eduroam.org"/>
		</reference>
		


		<reference anchor="dead-realm" target="http://www.eduroam.cz/dead-realm/docs/dead-realm.html">
			<front>
				<title>Dead-realm marking feature for Radiator RADIUS servers</title>
				<author initials="J." surname="Tomasek" fullname="Jan Tomasek">
					<organization abbrev="CESnet">CESnet
					</organization>
				</author>
				<date year="2006"/>
			</front>

		</reference>
		

		<reference anchor="eduPKI" target="https://www.edupki.org/edupki-pma/edupki-trust-profiles/">
		<front>
			<title>eduPKI Trust Profiles</title>
			<author>
			 <organization abbrev="Dante">Delivery of Advanced Network Technology to Europe
			 </organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2012"/>
		</front>
		</reference>
		
</references>
<section title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no"> 
<t>The authors would like to thank the participants in the 
Geant Association Task Force on Mobility and Network Middleware as well as the Geant project for 
their reviews and contributions. Special thanks go to Jim Schaad for doing an excellent 
review of the first version and to him and Alan DeKok for additional reviews.
</t>
<t>The eduroam trademark is registered by TERENA.
</t> 
</section>  <!-- Acknowledgments -->
</back> 
</rfc>
