<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3629 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6949 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6949.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7322 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7749 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7749.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7841 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7841.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" number="7994" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IAB" consensus="yes">

<front>

  <title abbrev="Plain-Text RFCs">Requirements for Plain-Text RFCs</title>
  <author fullname="Heather Flanagan" initials="H." surname="Flanagan">
    <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
    <address>
      <email>rse@rfc-editor.org</email>
      <uri>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2647-2220</uri>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date month="December" year="2016" />

  <keyword>RFC</keyword>
  <keyword>ASCII</keyword>
  <keyword>format</keyword>
  <keyword>plain-text</keyword>
  <keyword>plain text</keyword>

  <abstract>
      <t>In 2013, after a great deal of community discussion, the decision 
      was made to shift from the plain-text, ASCII-only canonical format for
      RFCs to XML as the canonical format with more human-readable formats 
      rendered from that XML.  The high-level requirements that
      informed this change were defined in RFC 6949, "RFC Series Format 
      Requirements and Future Development".  Plain text remains an important
      format for many in the IETF community, and it will be one of the 
      publication formats rendered from the XML.  This document outlines
      the rendering requirements for the plain-text RFC publication format.  
      These requirements do not apply to plain-text RFCs published before
      the format transition.</t>
  </abstract>

</front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In 2013, after a great deal of community discussion, the decision 
      was made to shift from the plain-text, ASCII-only canonical format for
      RFCs to XML as the canonical format <xref target="XML-ANNOUNCE"/>.  
      The high-level requirements that informed this change were defined in 
      <xref target="RFC6949"/>, "RFC Series Format Requirements and Future 
      Development".  Plain text remains an important format for many in the 
      IETF community, and it will be one of the publication formats 
      rendered from the XML. This document outlines the rendering requirements 
      for the plain-text RFC publication format. These requirements do not 
      apply to plain-text RFCs published before the format transition.</t>

      <t>The Unicode Consortium defines "plain text"
      as
      "Computer-encoded text that consists only of a sequence of
      code points from a given standard, with no other formatting or
      structural information.  Plain&nbhy;text interchange is commonly used
      between computer systems that do not share higher-level
      protocols."&nbsp;<xref target="UNICODE-GLOSSARY"></xref>.  In other
      words, plain-text files cannot include embedded character formatting
      or style information.  The actual character encoding, however, is not
      limited to any particular sequence of code points.</t>

      <t>A plain-text output for RFCs will continue to be required
      for the foreseeable future. The process of converting xml2rfc version 2
      (xml2rfc v2) into text documents is well understood 
      <xref target="RFC7749"/>. We plan to rely on the practice 
      to date to inform the requirements for converting xml2rfc version 3
      (xml2rfc v3) to text <xref target="RFC7991"/>. This document 
      calls out those requirements that are changed from v2 or otherwise 
      deserve special attention, such as the requirements around the character 
      encoding that may be used; changes in the page layout; and changes in
      how figures, artwork, and pagination may be handled. For more details
      on general style, see "RFC Style Guide" <xref target="RFC7322"/>.</t>

      <t>The following assumptions drive the changes in the plain-text
      output for RFCs:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>The existing tools used by the RFC Editor and many members
              of the author community to create the text file are complicated
              to change and support; manual manipulation is often required 
              for the final output.  In particular, handling page breaks and 
              associated widows and orphans for paginated output is tricky
              <xref target="WIDOWS"/>.</t>
              <t>Additional publication formats -- for example, PDF,
              HTML -- will be available that will offer features such as
              markup and pretty printing. </t> 
              <t>There is an extensive tool chain in existence among the 
              community to work with plain-text documents.  Similar 
              functionality may be possible with other publication formats, 
              but the workflow that uses the existing tool chain should be 
              supported as much as is considered practical.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
      <t>Where practical, the original guidance for the structure of a 
      plain&nbhy;text RFC has been kept (e.g., with line lengths, with lines
      per&nbsp;page <xref target="INS2AUTH"/>).  Other publication formats, 
      such as HTML and PDF, will include additional features that will not
      be present in the plain text (e.g., paragraph numbering, typographical
      emphasis).</t>

<t>The details described in this document are expected to change based on
experience gained in implementing the new publication toolsets. Revised
documents will be published capturing those changes as the toolsets are
completed. Other implementers must not expect those changes to remain
backwards-compatible with the details described in this document.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Character Encoding">
      <t>Plain-text files for RFCs will use the 
      <xref target="RFC3629">UTF-8</xref> character encoding.  That said, 
      the use of non-ASCII characters will be only allowed in a limited and
      controlled fashion.</t>

      <t>Many elements within the xml2rfc v3 vocabulary have an attribute for 
      the ASCII equivalent to a non-ASCII character string. The ASCII 
      equivalent will be rendered within the plain text as per the guidance in
      <xref target="RFC7997">"The Use of Non-ASCII Characters in
      RFCs"</xref>; please view the PDF version of that document.
      </t>

      <t>The plain-text file will include a Byte Order Mark (BOM) to provide 
      text reader software with in-band information about the character 
      encoding scheme used. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Figures and Artwork">
      <t>Artwork, such as network diagrams or performance graphs, must be 
      tagged by the XML &lt;artwork&gt; element (see Section 2.5 
      of <xref target="RFC7991">"The 'xml2rfc' Version 3 Vocabulary"
      </xref>. Where this artwork is comprised of an ASCII art diagram, it
      must be tagged as "type='ascii&nbhy;art'". The plain-text format will
      only include ASCII&nbsp;art. If the canonical format includes figures or 
      artwork other than ASCII art, then the plain-text output must include a 
      pointer to the relevant figure in the HTML version of the RFC to allow 
      readers to see the relevant artwork.</t>

      <t>Authors who wish to include ASCII art for the plain-text file and 
      SVG&nbsp;art for the other outputs may do so, but they should be aware
      of the potential for confusion to individuals reading the RFC with two
      unique diagrams describing the same content.  If there is conflicting 
      information between the publication formats, please review the XML and 
      PDF files to resolve the conflict.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="General Page Format Layout">
       <t>One plain-text output will be created during the publication
       process with basic pagination that includes a form feed instruction 
       every 58&nbsp;lines at most, including blank lines.  Instructions or a 
       script will be made available by and for the community to strip out 
       pagination as per individual preference. </t>

        <section title="Headers and Footers">
          <t>The front matter on the front page (such as the RFC number 
          and category) and the back matter on the last page (the authors'
          full names and contact information) will continue with the 
          structure described in <xref target="RFC7841">RFC 7841</xref>, 
          "RFC Streams, Headers, and Boilerplates".  Running headers and 
          footers will no longer be added.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Table of Contents">
          <t>In order to retain similar content wherever possible between
          the various publication formats, the table of contents will list 
          section and subsection numbers and titles but will not include 
          page numbers.

</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Line Width">
          <t>Each line must be limited to 72 characters followed by the
          character sequence that denotes an end-of-line (EOL).  The EOL
          sequence used by the RFC Editor will be the two-character sequence
          CR LF (Carriage Return followed by Line Feed).  This
          limit includes any left-side indentation.</t>

          <t>Note that the EOL used by the RFC Editor may change with different
          transports and as displayed in different display software.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Line Spacing">
          <t>Use single-spaced text within a paragraph, and one blank line
           between paragraphs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Hyphenation">
          <t>Hyphenated words (e.g., "Internet-Draft") should not be split 
          across successive lines. 
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="elements" title="Elements from the xml2rfc v3 Vocabulary">
        <t>The plain-text formatter uses the relevant tags from the
        xml2rfc&nbsp;v3 source file to build a document conforming to the
        layout and structure described by the full RFC Style Guide
        <xref target="RFC7322"/> (including the updates in the web portion
        of the Style Guide) <xref target="STYLEWEB"/>.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The requirements of the plain-text format involve no significant
      security considerations. As part of the larger format project, however,
      unintended changes to the text as a result of the transformation from
      the base XML file could in turn corrupt a standard, practice, or
      critical piece of information about a protocol.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC3629;
      &RFC7841;
      &RFC6949;
      &RFC7322;
      &RFC7749;

<!-- draft-iab-xml2rfc (RFC 7991) -->
<reference anchor='RFC7991' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7991">
<front>
<title>The "xml2rfc" Version 3 Vocabulary</title>
<author initials='P' surname='Hoffman' fullname='Paul E. Hoffman'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' year='2016' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7991"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7991"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-iab-rfc-nonascii (RFC 7997) -->
<reference anchor='RFC7997' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7997">
<front>
<title>The Use of Non-ASCII Characters in RFCs</title>
<author initials='H' surname='Flanagan' fullname='Heather Flanagan' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' year='2016' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7997"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7997"/>
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="UNICODE-GLOSSARY"
                 target="http://www.unicode.org/glossary/">
        <front>
          <title>Glossary of Unicode Terms</title>
          <author>
            <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2016" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="INS2AUTH"
                 target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/materials/instructions2authors.txt">
         <front>
           <title>Instructions to Request for Comments (RFC) Authors</title>
           <author>
             <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
           </author>
           <date month="August" year="2004" />
         </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="STYLEWEB"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/styleguide/part2/">
         <front>
           <title>Web Portion of the Style Guide</title>
           <author>
             <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
           </author>
           <date month="February" year="2016" />
         </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="XML-ANNOUNCE"
       target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/pipermail/rfc-interest/2013-May/005584.html">
        <front>
          <title>Subject: Direction of the RFC Format Development effort</title>
          <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan">
             <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="May" day="2" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="WIDOWS"
             target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Widows_and_orphans&amp;oldid=738356204">
         <front>
          <title>Widows and orphans</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Wikipedia</organization>
          </author>
          <date month='September' year='2016' />
         </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

<section title="IAB Members at the Time of Approval" numbered="no">

   <t>
     The IAB members at the time this memo was approved
     were (in&nbsp;alphabetical order):

<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<list>
<t>Jari Arkko</t>
<t>Ralph Droms</t>
<t>Ted Hardie</t>
<t>Joe Hildebrand</t>
<t>Russ Housley</t>
<t>Lee Howard</t>
<t>Erik Nordmark</t>
<t>Robert Sparks</t>
<t>Andrew Sullivan</t>
<t>Dave Thaler</t>
<t>Martin Thomson</t>
<t>Brian Trammell</t>
<t>Suzanne Woolf</t>
</list>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
   </t>
</section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>This document owes a great deal of thanks to the efforts of the RFC 
      Format Design Team: Nevil Brownlee, Tony Hansen, Joe Hildebrand, Paul 
      Hoffman, Ted Lemon, Julian Reschke, Adam Roach, Alice Russo, Robert 
      Sparks, and David Thaler.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>

