<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC3927 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3927.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4291.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4862 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4862.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4903 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4903.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4944 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.4944.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6550 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6550.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7346 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7346.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7368 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7368.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="1"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc number="7558" 
     category="info" 
     ipr="trust200902" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Scalable DNS-SD Requirements"> Requirements for Scalable
    DNS-Based Service Discovery (DNS-SD) / Multicast DNS (mDNS) Extensions </title>

    <author fullname="Kerry Lynn" initials="K." surname="Lynn">
      <organization>Verizon Labs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>50 Sylvan Road</street>
          <city>Waltham</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 781 296 9722</phone>
        <email>kerry.lynn@verizon.com</email>
      </address>

    </author>

    <author fullname="Stuart Cheshire" initials="S." surname="Cheshire">
      <organization>Apple, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 974 3207</phone>
        <email>cheshire@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="M." surname="Blanchet">
      <organization>Viagenie</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>246 Aberdeen</street>
          <city>Quebec</city>
          <region>QC</region>
          <code>G1R 2E1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Marc.Blanchet@viagenie.ca</email>
        <uri>http://viagenie.ca</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Daniel Migault" initials="D." surname="Migault">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 Boulevard Decarie</street>
          <city>Montreal</city>
          <region>QC</region>
          <code>H4P 2N2</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 514 452 2160</phone>
        <email>daniel.migault@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2015"/>
    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>DNS-SD/mDNS Extensions</workgroup>


    <abstract>
      <t>
      DNS-based Service Discovery (DNS-SD) over Multicast DNS (mDNS) is
      widely used today for discovery and resolution of services and names
      on a local link, but there are use cases to extend DNS-SD/mDNS to
      enable service discovery beyond the local link.  This document
      provides a problem statement and a list of requirements for scalable DNS-SD.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- section anchor="sec-1" title="Introduction" -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
      DNS-based Service Discovery <xref target="DNS-SD"/> in combination with its
      companion technology Multicast DNS <xref target="mDNS"/> is widely used today for
      discovery and resolution of services and names on a local link.
      As users move to multi-link home or campus networks, however, they
      find that mDNS (by design) does not work across routers.  DNS-SD can also be used
      in conjunction with conventional unicast DNS to enable wide&nbhy;area
      service discovery, but this capability is not yet widely deployed.
      This disconnect between customer needs and current practice has led
      to calls for improvement, such as the <xref target="EP">Educause petition</xref>.
      </t><t>
      In response to this and similar evidence of market demand, several
      products now enable service discovery beyond the local link using
      different ad hoc techniques.  As of yet, no consensus has emerged regarding
      which approach represents the best long-term direction for DNS-based
      Service Discovery protocol development.
      </t><t>
      Multicast DNS in its present form is also not optimized for network
      technologies where multicast transmissions are relatively expensive.
      Wireless networks such as <xref target="IEEE.802.11">Wi-Fi</xref> may be adversely affected by
      excessive mDNS traffic due to the higher network overhead of
      multicast transmissions.  Wireless mesh networks such as IPv6 over
      Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Network (6LoWPAN) <xref target="RFC4944"/>
      are effectively multi-link subnets <xref target="RFC4903"/> where multicasts must be
      forwarded by intermediate nodes.
      </t><t>
      It is in the best interests of end users, network administrators, and
      vendors for all interested parties to cooperate within the context of
      the IETF to develop an efficient, scalable, and interoperable
      standards-based solution.
      </t><t>
      This document defines the problem statement and gathers requirements
      for scalable DNS-SD/mDNS extensions.
      </t>

      <section title="Terminology and Acronyms">
        <t>
        Service: A listening endpoint (host and port) for a given application
        protocol.  Services are identified by Service Instance Names.
        </t><t>
        DNS-SD: DNS-based Service Discovery <xref target="DNS-SD"/> is a
        conventional application of DNS resource records and messages to
        facilitate the naming, discovery, and location of services.  When
        used alone, the term generally refers to the wide-area unicast protocol.
        </t><t>
        mDNS: Multicast DNS <xref target="mDNS"/> is a mechanism that
        facilitates distributed DNS-like capabilities (including DNS-SD)
        on a local link without need of traditional DNS infrastructure.
        </t><t>
        SSD: Scalable Service Discovery (or Scalable DNS-SD)
        is a future extension of DNS-SD (and perhaps mDNS)
        that meets the requirements set forth in this document.
        </t><t>
        Scope of Discovery: A subset of a local or global namespace, e.g.,
        a DNS subdomain, that is the target of a given SSD query.
        </t><t>
        Zero Configuration: A deployment of SSD that requires no
        administration (although some administration may be optional).
        </t><t>
        Incremental Deployment: An orderly transition, as a network
        installation evolves, from DNS-SD/mDNS to SSD.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>
      Service discovery beyond the local link is perhaps the most important
      feature currently missing from the DNS-SD-over-mDNS framework
      (also written as "DNS-SD over mDNS" or "DNS-SD/mDNS").
      Other issues and requirements are summarized below.
      </t>

      <section title="Multi-link Naming and Discovery">
        <t>
        A list of desired DNS-SD/mDNS improvements from network
        administrators in the research and education community was issued in
        the form of the <xref target="EP">Educause petition</xref>.  The following is a summary
        of their technical issues:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
          It is common practice for enterprises and institutions to
          use wireless links for client access and wired links for
          server infrastructure; typically, they are on different subnets.
          Products that advertise services such as printing and
          multimedia streaming via DNS-SD over mDNS are not
          currently discoverable by client devices on other links.
          DNS-SD used with conventional unicast DNS does work when servers and clients
          are on different links, but the resource records that describe
          the services must somehow be entered into the unicast DNS namespace.
          </t><t>
          DNS-SD resource records may be entered manually into a unicast DNS
          zone file <xref target="STATIC"/>, but this task must be performed by a DNS administrator.
          It is labor intensive and brittle when IP addresses of devices
          change dynamically, as is common when DHCP is used.
          </t><t>
      Automatically adding DNS-SD records using DNS Update works, but it
      requires that the DNS server be configured to allow DNS Updates and 
      that devices be configured with the DNS Update
      credentials to permit such updates, which has proven to be
      onerous.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>
        Therefore, a mechanism is desired that populates the DNS namespace
        with the appropriate DNS-SD records with less manual administration
        than is typically needed for a conventional unicast DNS server.
        </t>
        <t>
        The following is a summary of technical requirements:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
          It must scale to a range of hundreds to thousands of
          DNS-SD/mDNS-enabled devices in a given environment.
          </t><t>
          It must simultaneously operate over a variety of network link
          technologies, such as wired and wireless networks.
          </t><t>
          It must not significantly increase network traffic (wired or
          wireless).
          </t><t>
          It must be cost-effective to manage at up to enterprise scale.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="IEEE 802.11 Wireless LANs">
        <t>
        Multicast DNS was originally designed to run on Ethernet - the
        dominant link layer at the time.  In shared-medium Ethernet networks,
        multicast frames place little additional demand on the shared network
        medium compared to unicast frames.  In IEEE 802.11 networks, however,
        multicast frames are transmitted at a low data rate supported by all
        receivers.  In practice, this data rate leads to a larger fraction
        of airtime being devoted to multicast transmission.  Some network
        administrators block multicast traffic or use access points that
        transmit multicast frames using a series of link-layer unicast frames.
        </t><t>
        Wireless links may be orders of magnitude less reliable than their
        wired counterparts.  To improve transmission reliability, the IEEE
        802.11 Medium Access Control (MAC) requires positive acknowledgement of unicast frames.  It
        does not, however, support positive acknowledgement of multicast
        frames.  
   As a result, it is common to observe higher loss rates of
   multicast frames on wireless network technologies than on wired 
   network technologies.
        </t><t>
        Enabling service discovery on IEEE 802.11 networks requires that the
        number of multicast frames be restricted to a suitably low value or
        replaced with unicast frames to use the MAC's reliability features.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Low-Power and Lossy Networks (LLNs)">
        <t>
		Emerging wireless mesh networking technologies such as the Routing
		Protocol for LLNs (RPL) <xref target="RFC6550"/>
		and 6LoWPAN present several challenges for the current DNS-SD/mDNS
		design.  


		First, link-local multicast scope <xref target="RFC4291"/>
		is defined as a single-hop neighborhood.  A wireless mesh network representing a
		single logical subnet may often extend to multiple hops <xref target="RFC4903"/>; therefore,
		a larger multicast scope is required to span it <xref target="RFC7346"/>.
		Multicast DNS was intentionally not specified for
		greater than link-local scope because of the additional off-link
		multicast traffic that it would generate.
        </t><t>
        Additionally, low-power nodes may be offline for significant periods
        either because they are "sleeping" or due to connectivity problems.
        In such cases, LLN nodes might fail to respond to queries or defend
        their names using the current design.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section title="Basic Use Cases">
      <t>
      The following use cases are defined with different characteristics to
      help motivate, distinguish, and classify the target requirements.  They
      cover a spectrum of increasing deployment and administrative complexity.
      <list>
        <t>
        (A) Personal Area Networks (PANs): The simplest example of a network
        may consist of a single client and server, e.g., one laptop and one
        printer, on a common link.  PANs that do not contain a router may use
        Zero Configuration Networking <xref target="ZC"/> to
        self-assign link-local addresses <xref target="RFC3927"/> <xref target="RFC4862"/>
        and Multicast DNS <xref target="mDNS"/> to provide naming and service discovery,
        as is currently implemented and deployed in Mac OS X, iOS,
        Windows <xref target="B4W"/>, and Android <xref target="NSD"/>.
        </t><t>
        (B) Classic home or 'hotspot' networks, with the following properties:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
          Single exit router: The network may have one or more upstream
          providers or networks, but all outgoing and incoming traffic goes
          through a single router.
          </t><t>
          One-level depth: A single physical link, or
          multiple physical links bridged to form a single logical link,
          that is connected to the default router.
          The single logical link provides a single broadcast domain,
          facilitating use of link-local Multicast DNS, and also ARP,
          which enables the home or 'hotspot' network to consist of just
          a single IPv4 subnet.

          </t><t>
          Single administrative domain: All nodes under the same administrative authority.
          Note that this does not necessarily imply a network administrator.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t><t>
        (C) Advanced home and small business networks <xref target="RFC7368"/>:
        </t><t>
          Like B, but consists of multiple wired and/or wireless links, connected
          by routers, generally behind a single exit router.  However, the forwarding
          nodes are largely self-configuring and do not require routing protocol
          administration.  Such networks should also not require DNS administration.
        </t><t>
        (D) Enterprise networks:
        </t><t>
          Consists of arbitrary network diameter under a single administrative
          authority.  A large majority of the forwarding and security devices are
          configured, and multiple exit routers are more common.
          Large-scale conference-style networks, which are predominantly
          wireless access, e.g., as available at IETF
          meetings, also fall within this category.
        </t><t>
        (E) Higher-Education networks:
        </t><t>
          Like D, but the core network may be under a central administrative authority
          while leaf networks are under local administrative authorities.
        </t><t>
          (F) Mesh networks such as RPL/6LoWPAN:
        </t><t>
          Multi-link subnets with prefixes defined by one or more border
          routers.  May comprise any part of networks C, D, or E.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements">
      <t>
      Any successful SSD solution(s) will have to strike the proper balance
      between competing goals such as scalability, deployability, and
      usability.  With that in mind, none of the requirements listed below
      should be considered in isolation.
      </t><t>
      <list style="format REQ%d:">
        <t>
        For use cases A, B, and C, there should be a Zero Configuration
        mode of operation.  This implies that servers and clients should
        be able to automatically determine a default scope of discovery
        in which to advertise and discover services, respectively.
        </t><t>
        For use cases C, D, and E, there should be a way to configure
        scopes of discovery that support a range of topologically
        independent zones (e.g., from department to campus wide).
        This capability must exist in the protocol; individual
        operators are not required to use this capability in all cases
        -- in particular, use case C should support Zero Configuration
        operation where that is desired.
        If multiple scopes are available, there must be a way to enumerate
        the choices from which a selection can be made.  In use case C,
        either Zero Configuration (one flat list of resources) or configured
        (e.g., resources sorted by room) modes of operation should be available.
        </t><t>
        As stated in REQ2 above, the discovery scope need not be aligned
        to network topology.  For example, it may instead be aligned to
        physical proximity (e.g., building) or organizational structure
        (e.g., "Sales" vs. "Engineering").
        </t><t>
        For use cases C, D, and E, there should be an incremental way to
        deploy the solution.
        </t><t>
        SSD should leverage and build upon current link scope DNS-SD/mDNS
        protocols and deployments.
        </t><t>
        SSD must not adversely affect or break any other current protocols
        or deployments.
        </t><t>
        SSD must be capable of operating across networks that are
        not limited to a single link or network technology,
        including clients and services on non-adjacent links.
        </t><t>
        It is desirable that a user or device be able to discover services
        within the sites or networks to which the user or device is
        connected.
        </t><t>
        SSD should operate efficiently on common link layers and link
        types.
        </t><t>
   SSD should be considerate of networks where power consumption  
   is a critical factor; for example, nodes may be in a low-power or sleeping state.  
        </t><t>
        SSD must be scalable to thousands of nodes with minimal
        configuration and without degrading network performance.  A
        possible figure of merit is that, as the number of services
        increases, the amount of traffic due to SSD on a given link
        remains relatively constant.
        </t><t>
        SSD should enable a way to provide a consistent user
        experience whether local or remote services are being
        discovered.
        </t><t>
        The information presented by SSD should closely reflect
        the current state of discoverable services on the network.
        That is, new information should be available within a few seconds
        and stale information should not persist indefinitely.
        In networking, all information is necessarily somewhat
        out of date by the time it reaches the receiver,
        even if only by a few microseconds or less.
        Thus, timeliness is always an engineering trade-off against
        efficiency. The engineering decisions for SSD should appropriately
        balance timeliness against network efficiency.
        </t><t>
        SSD should operate over existing networks (as described by
        use cases A through F above) without requiring changes to the network
        at the physical, link, or internetworking layers.
        </t><t>
        The administrator of an advertised service should be able to
        control whether the service is advertised beyond the local
        link.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- section anchor="sec-5" title="Namespace Considerations" -->
    <section title="Namespace Considerations">
      <t>
      The traditional unicast DNS namespace contains,
      for the most part, globally unique names.
      Multicast DNS provides every link with its own separate link-local
      namespace, where names are unique only within the context of
      that link. Clients discovering services may need to differentiate
      between local and global names and may need to determine
      when names in different namespaces identify the same service.
      </t><t>
      Devices on different links may have the same mDNS name (perhaps due
      to vendor defaults) because link-local mDNS names are only
      guaranteed to be unique on a per-link basis.  This may lead to a
      local label disambiguation problem when results are aggregated (e.g.,
      for presentation).
      </t><t>
      SSD should support rich internationalized labels within Service
      Instance Names, as DNS-SD/mDNS does today.  SSD must not negatively
      impact the global DNS namespace or infrastructure.
      </t><t>
      The problem of publishing local services in the global DNS namespace
      may be generally viewed as exporting local resource records and their
      associated labels into some DNS zone.  The issues related to defining
      labels that are interoperable between local and global namespaces are
      discussed in a separate document <xref target="INTEROP-LABELS"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
      Insofar as SSD may automatically gather DNS-SD resource records and
      publish them over a wide area, the security issues are likely to include
      the union of those discussed in the <xref target="mDNS">Multicast DNS</xref>
      and <xref target="DNS-SD">DNS-based Service Discovery</xref> specifications.
      The following sections highlight potential threats that are posed by
      deploying DNS-SD over multiple links or by automating DNS-SD
      administration.
      </t>

      <section title="Scope of Discovery">
        <t>
        In some scenarios, the owner of the advertised service may
        not have a clear indication of the scope of its advertisement.
        </t><t>
        For example, since mDNS is currently restricted to a single link,
        the scope of the advertisement is limited, by design, to the
        shared link between client and server. If the advertisement
        propagates to a larger set of links than expected, this may
        result in unauthorized clients (from the perspective of the owner)
        discovering and then potentially attempting to connect to the
        advertised service. It also discloses information (about the
        host and service) to a larger set of potential attackers.
        </t><t>
        Note that discovery of a service does not necessarily imply that the service
        is reachable by, or can be connected to, or can be used by, a given client.
        Specific access-control mechanisms are out of scope of this document.
        </t><t>
        If the scope of the discovery is not properly set up or constrained,
        then information leaks will happen outside the appropriate network.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multiple Namespaces">
        <t>
        There is a possibility of conflicts between the local and global
        DNS namespaces.  Without adequate feedback, a discovering client
        may not know if the advertised  service is the correct one,
        therefore enabling potential attacks.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Authorization">
        <t>
        DNSSEC can assert the validity but not the accuracy of records in
        a zone file.  The trust model of the global DNS relies on the fact
        that human administrators either (a) manually enter resource records
        into a zone file or (b) configure the DNS server to authenticate a
        trusted device (e.g., a DHCP server) that can automatically maintain
        such records.
        </t><t>
        An impostor may register on the local link and appear as a
        legitimate service.  Such "rogue" services may then be automatically
        registered in unicast DNS-SD.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Authentication">
        <t>
        Up to now, the "plug-and-play" nature of mDNS devices has relied
        only on physical connectivity.  If a device is visible via mDNS, then
        it is assumed to be trusted.  This is not likely to be the case in
        foreign networks.
        </t><t>
        If there is a risk that clients may be fooled by the deployment
        of rogue services, then application-layer authentication should
        be considered as part of any security solution.  Authentication of
        any particular service is outside the scope of this document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Access Control">
        <t>
        Access Control refers to the ability to restrict which users are able
        to use a particular service that might be advertised via DNS-SD.  In
        this case, "use" of a service is different from the ability to
        "discover" or "reach" a service.
        </t><t>
        While controlling access to an advertised service is outside the scope of
        DNS-SD, we note that access control today often is provided by
        existing site infrastructure (e.g., router access-control lists,
        firewalls) and/or by service-specific mechanisms (e.g., user
        authentication to the service).
        For example, networked printers can control access via a user ID and password.
        Apple's software supports such access control for USB printers shared
        via Mac OS X Printer Sharing, as do many networked printers themselves.
        So the reliance on existing service-specific
        security mechanisms (i.e., outside the scope of DNS-SD) does not
        create new security considerations.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Privacy Considerations">
        <t>
        Mobile devices such as smart phones or laptops that can expose the location
        of their owners by registering services in arbitrary zones pose a
        risk to privacy.  Such devices must not register their services in
        arbitrary zones without the approval ("opt-in") of their users.
        However, it should be possible to configure one or more "safe"
        zones in which mobile devices may automatically register their
        services.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC3927;
      &RFC4291;
      &RFC4862;
      &RFC4903;
      &RFC4944;
      &RFC6550;
      &RFC7346;
      &RFC7368;




    <reference  anchor='DNS-SD' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6763'>
    <front>
    <title>DNS-Based Service Discovery</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Cheshire' fullname='S. Cheshire'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Krochmal' fullname='M. Krochmal'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2013' month='February' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6763'/>
    <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6763'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='125192'/>
    </reference>



    <reference  anchor='mDNS' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6762'>
    <front>
    <title>Multicast DNS</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Cheshire' fullname='S. Cheshire'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Krochmal' fullname='M. Krochmal'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2013' month='February' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6762'/>
    <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6762'/>
    <format type='ASCII' octets='184992'/>
    </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="B4W" target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonjour_(software)">
        <front>
          <title>Bonjour (software)</title>
          <author/>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

<!--draft-sullivan-dnssd-mdns-dns-interop-01: I-D Exists-->
<reference anchor='INTEROP-LABELS'>
<front>
<title>On Interoperation of Labels Between mDNS and DNS</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Sullivan' fullname='Andrew Sullivan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2014' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress' value='draft-sullivan-dnssd-mdns-dns-interop-01' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-sullivan-dnssd-mdns-dns-interop-01.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="EP" target="https://www.change.org/p/from-educause-higher-ed-wireless-networking-admin-group">
 <front>
  <title>Petitioning Apple: From Educause Higher Ed Wireless Networking Admin Group</title>
   <author initials="L." surname="Badman" fullname="Lee Badman"/>
   <date month="July" year="2012"/>
 </front>
</reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE.802.11"
		 target="http://standards.ieee.org/about/get/802/802.11.html">


        <front>
          <title>
          IEEE Standard for Information technology - Telecommunications and
	  information exchange between systems
          Local and metropolitan area networks - Specific requirements Part
	  11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE Computer Society</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="" year=""/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="Std 802.11"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NSD" target="http://developer.android.com/reference/android/net/nsd/NsdManager.html">
        <front>
          <title>NsdManager</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Android</organization>
	  </author>
	    <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="STATIC" target="http://www.dns-sd.org/ServerStaticSetup.html">
        <front>
          <title>Manually Adding DNS-SD Service Discovery Records to an Existing Name Server</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="July" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ZC">
        <front>
          <title>Zero Configuration Networking: The Definitive Guide</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Cheshire" fullname="Stuart Cheshire"/>
          <author initials="D.H." surname="Steinberg" fullname="Daniel H. Steinberg"/>
          <date year="2005" month="December"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="O'Reilly Media," value="Inc."/>
        <seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="0-596-10100-7"/>
      </reference>

    </references>
<section title="Acknowedgements" numbered="no">
<t>We gratefully acknowledge contributions and review comments made by
   RJ Atkinson, Tim Chown, Guangqing Deng, Ralph Droms, Educause, David
   Farmer, Matthew Gast, Thomas Narten, Doug Otis, David Thaler, and
   Peter Van Der Stok.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
