<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1918 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.1918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6598 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6598.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6887 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6887.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6970 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6970.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6674 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6674.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6619 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6619.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3931 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3931.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7652 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7652.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="7843" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" updates="6887">
        
        <front>

                <title abbrev="Third-Party ID">Port Control Protocol (PCP) Third-Party ID Option</title>

                <author fullname="Andreas Ripke" initials="A.R." surname="Ripke">
                        <organization>NEC</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street></street>
                                        <code></code>
                                        <city>Heidelberg</city>
                                        <country>Germany</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>ripke@neclab.eu</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author fullname="Rolf Winter" initials="R.W." surname="Winter">
                        <organization>NEC</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street></street>
                                        <code></code>
                                        <city>Heidelberg</city>
                                        <country>Germany</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>winter@neclab.eu</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author fullname="Thomas Dietz" initials="T.D." surname="Dietz">
                        <organization>NEC</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street></street>
                                        <code></code>
                                        <city>Heidelberg</city>
                                        <country>Germany</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>dietz@neclab.eu</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author fullname="Juergen Quittek" initials="J.Q." surname="Quittek">
                        <organization>NEC</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street></street>
                                        <code></code>
                                        <city>Heidelberg</city>
                                        <country>Germany</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>quittek@neclab.eu</email>
                        </address>
                </author>
                <author fullname="Rafael Lopez da Silva" initials="R.L.S." surname="da Silva">
                        <organization>Telefonica I+D</organization>
                        <address>
                                <postal>
                                        <street></street>
                                        <code></code>
                                        <city>Madrid</city>
                                        <country>Spain</country>
                                </postal>
                                <email>rafaelalejandro.lopezdasilva@telefonica.com</email>
                        </address>
                </author>

                <date month="April" year="2016" />

                <area>General</area>

                <keyword>PCP, option, third party, ID</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>
	      This document describes a new Port Control Protocol (PCP)
	      option called the THIRD_PARTY_ID option. It is designed to be used
	      together with the THIRD_PARTY option specified in
	      RFC 6887.
			</t>
			<t>
	      The THIRD_PARTY_ID option serves to identify a third party in situations
	      where a third party's IP address contained in the THIRD_PARTY
	      option does not provide sufficient information
	      to create requested mappings in a PCP-controlled device.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <middle>
          <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
            <t>
              The IETF has specified the Port Control Protocol (PCP) 
              <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> to control how packets 
              are translated and/or forwarded by a PCP-controlled device
              such as a Network Address Translator (NAT) or a firewall.
            </t> <t>
              This document focuses on scenarios where
	      the PCP client sends requests 
              that concern internal addresses other than the address of the PCP
              client itself.
            </t> <t>
	      There is already an option defined for this purpose in
	      <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> 
	      called the THIRD_PARTY option. The THIRD_PARTY option 
	      carries the IP address of a host for which a PCP client requests an 
	      action at the PCP server. 


   For example, the THIRD_PARTY option can be used if
   port mapping requests for a Carrier-Grade NAT (CGN) are not sent from
   PCP clients at subscriber terminals but instead from a PCP
   Interworking Function (IWF), which requests port mappings.

            </t> <t>
	      In some cases, the THIRD_PARTY option alone is not sufficient and further 
	      means are needed for identifying the third party. Such
	      cases are addressed by the THIRD_PARTY_ID option, which is specified in 
	      this document.
            </t> <t>
              The primary issue addressed by the THIRD_PARTY_ID option is 
              that there are CGN deployments that do not distinguish 
              internal hosts by their IP address alone, but use further 
              identifiers (IDs) for unique subscriber identification. For
	      example, this 
              is the case if a CGN supports overlapping 
              private or shared IP address spaces 
              <xref target="RFC1918"></xref> <xref target="RFC6598"></xref>
	      for internal hosts of 
              different subscribers. In such cases, different internal hosts are
	      identified and mapped at the CGN by their IP address and/or
              another ID, for example, the ID of a tunnel between
              the CGN and the subscriber. In these scenarios (and similar ones), the internal IP address
              contained in the THIRD_PARTY option is not sufficient to demultiplex connections from internal hosts.
              An additional identifier needs to be present in the PCP
              message in order to uniquely identify an internal host.
              The THIRD_PARTY_ID option is used to carry this ID.
            </t> <t>
              This applies to some of the PCP deployment scenarios that 
              are listed in Section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>,
              in particular to a L2-aware NAT, which is described 
              in more detail in <xref target="sec-scenario"></xref>,
	      as well as in other scenarios where overlapping address spaces occur
	      like in <xref target="RFC6674"></xref> or
	      <xref target="RFC6619"></xref>.
	    </t> <t>
	      The THIRD_PARTY_ID option is defined for the PCP opcodes MAP and PEER 
	      to be used together with the
	      THIRD_PARTY option, which is specified in <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>.
            </t>
          </section> 

          <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
            <t>
              The terminology defined in the specification of PCP 
              <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> applies.
            </t> <t>
              The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
              "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", 
              and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described 
              in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
            </t> 
          </section> 

          <section anchor="sec-scenario" title="Target Scenarios">
            <t>
              This section describes two scenarios that illustrate the use 
			  of the THIRD_PARTY_ID option: 
			  <list style="numbers">
			    <t>
				  A UPnP IGD-PCP IWF (Universal Plug and Play Internet Gateway 
				  Device - Port Control Protocol Interworking Function <xref target="RFC6970"/>). 
				</t>
				<t>A carrier web portal for port mapping.</t>
			  </list>
			  These are just two examples that illustrate the use and applicability
			  of the THIRD_PARTY_ID option. While these are just two examples, there
			  might be other conceivable use cases. However, the use 
			  of the THIRD_PARTY_ID option as specified in this document is restricted 
              to scenarios where the option is needed for the purpose of uniquely 
              identifying an internal host in addition to the information found in 
              the THIRD_PARTY option.
			</t>
		   			  <t>
			  Both scenarios elaborated in this document are refinements of
			  the same basic scenario shown in
		      <xref target="fig-scenario"></xref> that is considered as a PCP 
              deployment scenario employing L2-aware NATs as listed in Section
              2.1 of <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>.
			  It has a carrier operating 
			  a CGN and a Port Control Protocol Interworking Function (PCP IWF)
			  <xref target="RFC6970"></xref>
			  for subscribers to request port mappings at the CGN. The PCP IWF
			  communicates with the CGN using PCP. For this purpose, the PCP IWF
			  contains a PCP client
			  serving multiple subscribers
			  and the CGN is co-located with a PCP server. 
		      The way subscribers interact with the PCP IWF for requesting port 
			  mappings for their internal hosts is not specified in this basic
			  scenario, but it is elaborated on more in the
			  specific scenarios in Sections <xref target="sec-upnp" format="counter"/> and <xref
			  target="sec-portal" format="counter"/>. 
		</t> <t>
		    The CGN operates as a L2-aware NAT.
		    Unlike a standard NAT, it includes a subscriber identifier in addition
		    to the source IP address in entries of the NAT mapping table.
	        </t>
<figure title="Carrier Hosted PCP IWF for Port Mapping Requests" anchor="fig-scenario"><artwork> 
+--------------+    +------------------+
| Subscriber   |    | Carrier          |    ==== L2 connection(s)
|              |    | +--------------+ |         between subscriber
|              +......+ PCP          | |         and CGN
| +----------+ |    | | Interworking | |    #### PCP communication
| | Internal | |    | | Function     | |    .... Subscriber-IWF
| | Host     | |    | +-----#--------+ |         interaction
| +----+-----+ |    |       #          |         (elaborated
|      |       |    | +-----#--------+ |         in specific
| +----+-----+ |    | | PCP Server   | |         scenarios below)
| |  CPE     | |    | |              | |
| |          +-+======+ CGN L2NAT    +--------- Public Internet
| +----------+ |    | +--------------+ |
+--------------+    +------------------+
</artwork>
		    </figure> 
		    <t>
		      Internal hosts in the subscriber's network use private IP addresses 
			  <xref target="RFC1918"></xref>. 



There is no 
			  NAT between the internal host and the CGN, and there is an overlap of 
			  addresses used by internal hosts of different subscribers. That is 
			  why the CGN needs more than just the internal host's IP address to 
		      distinguish internal hosts of different subscribers. A commonly
		      deployed method for solving this issue is using an additional 
		      identifier for this purpose. A natural candidate for this 
		      additional identifier at the CGN is the ID of the tunnel that 
		      connects the CGN to the subscriber's network.
		      The subscriber's  Customer Premises Equipment (CPE)
		      operates as a Layer 2 bridge.
		    </t> <t>
		      Requests for port mappings from the PCP IWF to the CGN need to
		      uniquely identify the internal host for which a port mapping 
		      is to be established or modified. Already existing for this
		      purpose is the THIRD_PARTY option that can be used to specify
		      the internal host's IP address. The THIRD_PARTY_ID option is 
		      introduced for carrying the additional third-party information 
		      needed to identify the internal host in this scenario. 
		    </t> <t>
		      The additional identifier for internal hosts needs to be 
		      included in MAP requests from the PCP IWF in order to uniquely 
		      identify the internal host that should have its address mapped.
		      This is the purpose that the new THIRD_PARTY_ID option serves in this 
		      scenario. It carries the additional identifier, that is the tunnel
		      ID, that serves for identifying an internal host in combination
		      with the internal host's (private) IP address. The IP address
		      of the internal host is included in the PCP IWF's mapping
		      requests by using the THIRD_PARTY option.
		    </t> <t>
		      The information carried by the THIRD_PARTY_ID option is not just 
		      needed to identify an internal host in a PCP request. The CGN 
		      needs this information in its internal mapping tables for 
		      translating packet addresses and for forwarding packets to 
		      subscriber-specific tunnels.
		    </t> <t>
		      How the carrier PCP IWF is managing port mappings, such as, 
			  for example, automatically extending the lifetime of a mapping,
			  is beyond the scope of this document.
		    </t>
		  
            <section anchor="sec-upnp" title="Carrier-Hosted UPnP IGD-PCP IWF">
              <t>
		        This scenario further elaborates the basic one above by choosing UPnP-IGD
		        as the communication protocol between the subscriber and the carrier's
		        PCP IWF. Then obviously, the PCP IWF is realized as a UPnP
		        IGD-PCP IWF as specified in <xref target="RFC6970"></xref>. 
              </t><t>
		        As shown in <xref target="fig-upnp"></xref>, it is assumed here 
		        that the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF is not embedded in the subscriber 
		        premises router, but offered as a service to the subscriber.
		        Further, it is assumed that the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF is not
		        providing NAT functionality.
              </t><t>
                This requires that the subscriber can connect to
                the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF
                to request port mappings at the CGN 
                using UPnP-IGD as specified in <xref target="RFC6970"></xref>.
                In this scenario, the connection is provided via (one of the) 
                tunnel(s) connecting the subscriber's network to the 
			    Broadband Remote Access Server (BRAS)	
                and an extension of this tunnel from the BRAS to the UPnP 
                IGD-PCP IWF. Note that there are other alternatives that can 
                be used for providing the connection to the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF. 
                The tunnel extension used in this scenario can, for example, 
                be realized by a forwarding function for UPnP messages at 
                the BRAS that forwards such messages through per-subscriber 
                tunnels to the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF. Depending on an actual 
                implementation, the UPnP IGD-PCP IWF can then either
                use the ID of the tunnel in which the UPnP message arrived
                directly as the THIRD_PARTY_ID option for PCP requests to the CGN,
                or it uses the ID of the tunnel to retrieve the THIRD_PARTY_ID option
                from the Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) server.
              </t><t>
		        To support the latter option, the BRAS needs to register the 
                subscriber's tunnel IDs at the AAA server at the time it contacts
                the AAA server for authentication and/or authorization of the subscriber.
                The tunnel IDs to be registered per subscriber at the AAA server 
                may include the tunnel between CPE and BRAS, between BRAS and 
                UPnP IGD-PCP IWF, and between BRAS and CGN. The UPnP IGD-PCP IWF 
                queries the AAA server for the ID of the tunnel between BRAS and 
                CGN, because this is the identifier to be used as the THIRD_PARTY_ID option
		        in the subsequent port mapping request.
              </t>
              <figure title="UPnP IGD-PCP IWF" 
                anchor="fig-upnp">
                <artwork> 
+--------------+    +------------------------------------+
| Subscriber   |    | Carrier                            |    
|              |    | +----------------------------+     |    
|              |    | |          AAA Server        |     |    
|              |    | +-----+---------------+------+     |    
|              |    |       |               |            |    
| +----------+ |    | +-----+---+     +-----+------+     |    
| | Internal | |    | |         +=====+            |     |    
| | Host     | |    | |    ...........| UPnP IGD   |     |    
| +----+-----+ |    | |    .    +=====+ PCP IWF    |     |    
|      |  .    |    | |    .    |     +-----#------+     |
| +----+--.--| |    | |    .    |           #            |    
| |    |  .  +========+    .    |     +-----#------+     |        
| |    |  ..................    +=====+ PCP Server |     |
| |    +------------------------------|            |     |
| |  CPE     +========+  BRAS   +=====+ CGN L2NAT  +------- Public
| +----------+ |    | +---------+     +------------+     |  Internet
+--------------+    +------------------------------------+

==== L2 tunnel borders between subscriber, BRAS, IWF, and CGN
.... UPnP communication            
#### PCP communication  
                </artwork>
              </figure> 
              <t>
                A potential extension to <xref target="RFC6970"></xref>
                regarding an additional state variable for the THIRD_PARTY_ID option
                and regarding an additional error code for a mismatched THIRD_PARTY_ID option
                and its processing might be a logical next step. However, 
				this is not in the scope of this document.
              </t>
            </section> 
			
            <section anchor="sec-portal" title="Carrier Web Portal">
              <t>
		        This scenario shown in <xref target="fig-http"></xref> is 
				different from the previous one concerning the protocol 
				used between the subscriber and the IWF. Here, HTTP(S) is 
				the protocol that the subscriber uses for port
				mapping 
				requests. The subscriber may make requests manually using 
				a web browser or automatically -- as in the previous scenario
				-- with applications in the subscriber's network issuing port mapping requests on demand. 


				The web portal queries the AAA server for the subscriber's
				ID of the tunnel (BRAS to CGN) that was reported
				by the BRAS.
				The returned ID of the tunnel (BRAS to CGN) is used as
				the THIRD_PARTY_ID option in the subsequent port mapping request.
              </t>
              <figure title="Carrier Web Portal" 
                anchor="fig-http">
                <artwork> 
+--------------+    +------------------------------------+
| Subscriber   |    | Carrier                            |    
|              |    |                 +------------+     |    
|              |    | +------------+  | Web Portal |     |    
| +----------+ |    | | AAA Server +--+            +--+  |    
| | Internal | |    | +-----+------+  | PCP Client |  |  |    
| | Host     | |    |       |         +-----#------+  |  |    
| +----+-----+ |    |       |               #         |  |    
|      |       |    | +-----+---+     +-----#------+  |  |        
| +----+-----+ |    | |         |     | PCP Server |  |  |
| |  CPE     | |    | |  BRAS   |     |            |  |  |
| |          +-+======+         +=====+ CGN L2NAT  +--+---- Public
| +----------+ |    | +---------+     +------------+     |  Internet
+--------------+    +------------------------------------+

==== L2 tunnel(s) between subscriber, BRAS, and CGN            
#### PCP communication  
                </artwork>
              </figure> 
              <t>
			    The PCP IWF is realized as a combination of a web server
				and a PCP client.
						  </t>
	        </section> 

	      </section> 
                
            <section anchor="format" title="Format">
              <t>
	        The THIRD_PARTY_ID option as shown in
                <xref target="third_party_id_option"></xref>
		uses the format of PCP options as 
		specified in <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>:
              </t> 
              <figure anchor="third_party_id_option" title="THIRD_PARTY_ID Option">
<artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Option Code=13 |  Reserved     |      Option Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                      THIRD_PARTY_ID                           |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Option Name:         THIRD_PARTY_ID
Option Code:         13
Purpose:             Together with the THIRD_PARTY option, the 
                     THIRD_PARTY_ID option identifies a third party 
                     for which a request for an external IP address 
                     and port is made.
Valid for Opcodes:   MAP, PEER
Length:              Variable; maximum 1016 octets.
May appear in:       Request. May appear in response only if it
                     appeared in the associated request.
Maximum occurrences: 1
]]></artwork>
              </figure>
              <t>
		The "Reserved" field and the "Option length" field are to be set
		as specified in Section 7.3 of <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>.
              </t>
              <t>
	        The "THIRD_PARTY_ID" field contains a deployment-specific identifier 
		that identifies a realm of a NAT map entry. Together with a THIRD_PARTY 
		option it can be used to identify a subscriber's session on a PCP-controlled device. It has no other semantics.  
              </t>
              <t>
		The "THIRD_PARTY_ID" is not bound to any specific identifier. It can 
		contain any deployment-specific value that the PCP client and the PCP server
		agree on. How this agreement is reached if both PCP server and client 
		are not administered by the same entity is beyond the scope of this 
		document. Also, the client does not need to have an understanding of how
		the ID is being used at the PCP server.</t>
	
		<t> 
		If an identifier is used that is based on an existing standard, 
		then the encoding rules of that standard must be followed. As an example,
		in case a session ID of the Layer 2 Tunneling Protocol version 3 (L2TPv3) <xref target="RFC3931"/> is being used, then that identifier
		has to be encoded the same way it would be encoded in the L2TPv3 session 
		header. This allows for a simple octet-by-octet comparison at the 
		PCP-controlled device.</t>

		<t>
		<xref target="RFC6887"></xref> expects option data to always come in
		multiples of an octet. An ID, however, might not fulfill this criterion.
		As an example, an MPLS label is 20 bits wide. In these cases, padding is
		done by appending 0 bits until the byte boundary is reached. 
		After that, the padding rules of 	
        <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> apply.</t>
              <t>
		The option number is in the mandatory-to-process range (0-127), meaning 
		that a request with a THIRD_PARTY_ID option is processed by the PCP 
		server if and only if the THIRD_PARTY_ID option is supported by the PCP 
		server. Therefore, it should not be included unless the PCP client is
		certain that a mapping without the THIRD_PARTY_ID is impossible.
              </t>
	      <section anchor="resultcodes" title="Result Codes">
		<t>
		  The following PCP Result Codes are new:
		</t>
		<t>

		  <list style="hanging">
		    <t hangText="24:">THIRD_PARTY_ID_UNKNOWN:
		      The provided identifier in a THIRD_PARTY_ID option
		      is unknown/unavailable to the PCP server.
		      This is a long lifetime error.
		    </t>
		    <t hangText="25:">THIRD_PARTY_MISSING_OPTION:
		      This error occurs if both THIRD_PARTY and THIRD_PARTY_ID
		      options are expected in a request but one option is
		      missing.
		      This is a long lifetime error.
		    </t>
		    <t hangText="26:">UNSUPP_THIRD_PARTY_ID_LENGTH:
		      The received option length is not supported.
		      This is a long lifetime error.
		    </t>
		  </list>
		</t>
	      </section> 
            </section> 


            <section anchor="behavior" title="Behavior">
              <t>
	        The following sections describe the operations of a PCP client
		and a PCP server when generating the request and processing
		the request and response.
              </t>

	      <section anchor="GeneratingRequest" title="Generating a Request">
              <t>
	        In addition to generating a PCP request that is described
		in <xref target="RFC6887"></xref>, the following has to be
		applied.
                The THIRD_PARTY_ID option MAY be included either in
                a PCP MAP or PEER opcode. It MUST be used in
		combination with the THIRD_PARTY option, which
		provides an IP address.
                The THIRD_PARTY_ID option holds an identifier to
		allow the PCP-controlled device to uniquely identify the internal host (specified
		in the THIRD_PARTY option) for which
		the port mapping is to be established or modified.
		The padding rules described in 
		<xref target="format"></xref> apply.
              </t>
	      </section>

	      <section anchor="ProcessRequest" title="Processing a Request">
              <t>
	        The THIRD_PARTY_ID option is in the mandatory-to-process range;
		if the PCP server does not support this option, it MUST return
		an UNSUPP_OPTION response.
	        If the provided identifier in a THIRD_PARTY_ID option
		is unknown/unavailable, the PCP server
		MUST return a THIRD_PARTY_ID_UNKNOWN response.
		If the PCP server receives a request with an unsupported THIRD_PARTY_ID option length,
		it MUST return an UNSUPP_THIRD_PARTY_ID_LENGTH response.
		If the PCP server receives a THIRD_PARTY_ID option without a THIRD_PARTY option, 
		it MUST return a THIRD_PARTY_MISSING_OPTION response.
              </t>
		<t>
        Upon receiving a valid request with a legal THIRD_PARTY_ID option
		identifier, the message is processed as specified in <xref target="RFC6887"/>, 
		except that the identifier contained in the THIRD_PARTY_ID is used 
		in addition when accessing a mapping table. Instead of just using 
		the value contained in the THIRD_PARTY option when accessing
		the internal Internet address of a mapping table, now the combination
		of the two values contained in the THIRD_PARTY option and in the
		THIRD_PARTY_ID option is used to access the combination of the
		internal Internet address and the internal realm of a NAT map entry.
		</t>

		<t>
		If two or more different tunnel technologies are being used,
		precautions need to be taken to handle potential overlap of the 
        ID spaces of these technologies.  For example, different 
        PCP client/PCP server pairs can be used per tunnel technology.
		</t>
	      </section>

	      <section anchor="ProcessResponse" title="Processing a Response">
              <t>
		In addition to the response processing described in
		<xref target="RFC6887"></xref>,
		if the PCP client receives a THIRD_PARTY_ID_UNKNOWN
		or a UNSUPP_THIRD_PARTY_ID_LENGTH or a THIRD_PARTY_MISSING_OPTION
		response back for
		its previous request, it SHOULD report an error. Where to report an error is based on policy. 
              </t>
	      </section>

            </section> 


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        The following PCP Option Code has been allocated in the
        mandatory-to-process range:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>13: THIRD_PARTY_ID
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The following PCP Result Codes have been allocated:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>24: THIRD_PARTY_ID_UNKNOWN</t>
	  <t>25: THIRD_PARTY_MISSING_OPTION</t>
	  <t>26: UNSUPP_THIRD_PARTY_ID_LENGTH</t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        This option is to be used in combination with the THIRD_PARTY 
        option.  Consequently, all corresponding security considerations 
        in Section 18.1.1 of <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> apply. In particular, the
		network on which the PCP messages are sent must be sufficiently protected.
        Further, it is RECOMMENDED to use PCP authentication <xref target="RFC7652"/>
		unless the network already has appropriate authentication means in place.
      </t>
      <t>
        The THIRD_PARTY_ID option carries a context identifier whose type
	and length is deployment and implementation dependent.
	This identifier might carry privacy sensitive information. It is therefore
	RECOMMENDED to utilize identifiers that do not have such privacy concerns.
	Means to protect unauthorized access to this information
	MUST be put in place. In the scenarios described in this document, for
	example, access to the web portal or UPnP IGD-PCP IWF MUST be authenticated.

	Generally speaking, the identifier itself MUST only be accessible by the network
	operator and MUST only be handled on operator equipment.
	For example, creation of a PCP message on 
	the web portal or the UPnP IGD PCP IWF is triggered by
	the subscriber, but the actual option filling is done by an
	operator-controlled entity.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>


  <back>

     <references title="Normative References">

             &RFC1918;
             &RFC6598;
             &RFC2119;
             &RFC6887;
     </references>


     <references title="Informative References">

	     &RFC6970; 
	     &RFC6674; 
	     &RFC6619; 
		 &RFC3931;
		 &RFC7652;

	     
     </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>
	  Thanks to Mohamed Boucadair for many valuable suggestions, in
	  particular for suggesting a variable length for the THIRD_PARTY_ID
	  option. Thanks to Dave Thaler, Tom Taylor, and Dan Wing
	  for their comments and review.
      </t>
    </section> 

  </back>
</rfc>


