<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<rfc number="7785" category="info"
     submissionType="independent"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Prefix Binding for DS-Lite">Recommendations for Prefix
    Binding in&nbsp;the&nbsp;Context&nbsp;of&nbsp;Softwire&nbsp;Dual&nbhy;Stack&nbsp;Lite</title>

    <author fullname="Suresh Vinapamula" initials="S." surname="Vinapamula">
      <organization abbrev="Juniper Networks">Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Mathilda Avenue</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 936 5441</phone>

        <email>sureshk@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2016" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <keyword>IPv4 service continuity</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv4 address exhaustion</keyword>

    <keyword>Service Availability</keyword>

    <keyword>High Availability</keyword>

    <keyword>Address sharing</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>Reliability</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv4 over IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>State migration</keyword>

    <keyword>Stability</keyword>

    <keyword>Disruption</keyword>

    <keyword>Privacy</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses issues induced by the change of the
      Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite) Basic Bridging BroadBand (B4) IPv6 address and
      sketches a set of recommendations to solve those issues.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>IPv6 deployment models assume IPv6 prefixes are delegated by Service
      Providers to the connected CPEs (Customer Premises Equipment) or hosts,
      which in turn derive IPv6 addresses from that prefix. In the case of
      Dual-Stack Lite (DS-Lite) <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>, which is an
      IPv4 service continuity mechanism over an IPv6 network, the Basic
      Bridging BroadBand (B4) element derives an IPv6 address for the
      IPv4-in-IPv6 softwire setup purposes.</t>

      <t>The B4 element might obtain a new IPv6 address for a variety of
      reasons that include (but are not limited to) a reboot of the CPE, power
      outage, DHCPv6 lease expiry, or other actions undertaken by the Service
      Provider. If this occurs, traffic forwarded to a B4's previous IPv6
      address may never reach its destination or may be delivered to another B4
      that now uses the address formerly assigned to the original B4. This
      situation affects all mapping types, both implicit (e.g., by sending a
      TCP SYN) and explicit (e.g., using Port Control Protocol (PCP) <xref
      target="RFC6887"></xref>). The problem is further elaborated in <xref
      target="problem"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document proposes recommendations to soften the impact of such
      renumbering issues (<xref target="reco"></xref>).</t>

      <t>This document complements <xref target="RFC6908"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="problem" title="The Problem">
      <t>Since private IPv4 addresses assigned to hosts serviced by a B4
      element overlap across multiple CPEs, the IPv6 address of a B4 element
      plays a key role in demultiplexing connections, enforcing policies, and
      in identifying associated resources assigned for each of the connections
      maintained by the Address Family Transition Router (AFTR) <xref
      target="RFC6333"></xref>. For example, these resources maintain state
      of Endpoint-Independent Mapping (EIM) as defined in Section 4.1 of <xref
      target="RFC4787"></xref>, Endpoint-Independent Filtering (EIF) as
      defined in Section
      5 of <xref target="RFC4787"></xref>, preserve the external IPv4 address
      assigned in the AFTR (i.e., "IP address pooling" behavior as defined in
      Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC4787"></xref>), PCP mappings, etc.</t>

      <t>However, the IPv6 address used by the B4 element may change for some
      reason, e.g., because of a change in the CPE itself or because of
      privacy extensions enabled for generating the IPv6 address (e.g., <xref
      target="RFC7217"></xref> or <xref target="RFC4941"></xref>). Whenever
      the B4's IPv6 address changes, the associated mappings created in the
      AFTR are no longer valid. This may result in the creation of a new set
      of mappings in the AFTR.</t>

      <t>Furthermore, a misbehaving user may be tempted to change the B4's
      IPv6 address in order to "grab" more ports and resources at the AFTR
      side. This behavior can be seen as a potential denial-of-service (DoS)
      attack from misbehaving users. Note that this DoS attack can be achieved
      whatever the port assignment policy enforced by the AFTR may be (individual
      ports, port sets, randomized port bulks, etc.).</t>

      <t>Service Providers may want to enforce policies in order to limit the
      usage of the AFTR resources on a per-subscriber basis for fairness of
      resource usage (see REQ-4 of <xref target="RFC6888"></xref>). These
      policies are used for dimensioning purposes and also to ensure that AFTR
      resources are not exhausted. If the derived B4's IPv6 address can
      change, resource tracking using that address will give incomplete
      results. Also, whenever the B4's IPv6 address changes, enforcing
      policies based on that address doesn't resolve stale mappings hanging
      around in the system, consuming not only system resources, but also
      reducing the available quota of resources per subscriber. Clearing those
      mappings can be envisaged, but that will cause a lot of churn in the
      AFTR and could be disruptive to existing connections; this is not
      desirable. More concretely, if stale mappings have not been migrated to
      the new B4's IPv6 address so that packets can be forwarded to the
      appropriate B4, all incoming packets that are associated with those
      mappings will be rejected by the AFTR. 


Such behavior is not desirable because it's detrimental to
quality of experience.
      </t>

      <t>When application servers are hosted behind a B4 element, and when
      there is a change of the B4's IPv6 address that results in a change of
      the external IPv4 address and/or the external port number at the AFTR
      side, these servers have to advertise their change (see Section
      1.1 of <xref target="RFC7393"></xref>). Some means to discover the change of
      B4's IPv6 address, the external IPv4 address, and/or the external port
      are therefore required. Latency issues are likely to be experienced when
      an application server has to advertise its newly assigned external IPv4
      address and port, and the application clients have to discover that
      newly assigned address and/or port and re-initiate connections with the
      application server.</t>

      <t>A solution to these problems is to enforce policies based on the IPv6
      prefix assigned to subscribers that have DS-Lite service instead of
      based on the B4's IPv6
      address. <xref target="sm"></xref> introduces the subscriber-mask that
      is meant to derive the IPv6 prefix assigned to a subscriber's CPE from
      the source IPv6 address of a packet received from a B4 element.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sm" title="Introducing Subscriber-Mask">
      <t>The subscriber-mask is defined as an integer that indicates the
      length of significant bits to be applied on the source IPv6 address
      (internal side) to identify unambiguously a CPE.</t>

      <t>Subscriber-mask is an AFTR system-wide configuration parameter that
      is used to enforce generic per-subscriber policies. Applying these
      generic policies does not require configuring every subscriber's
      prefix.</t>

      <t>Subscriber-mask must be configurable; the default value is 56. The
      default value is motivated by current practices to assign IPv6 prefix
      lengths of /56 to end-sites (e.g., <xref target="RIPE"></xref>, <xref
      target="LACNIC"></xref>).</t>

      <t>Example: suppose the 2001:db8:100:100::/56 prefix is assigned to a
      CPE that is DS-Lite enabled. Suppose also that the 2001:db8:100:100::1 address
      is the IPv6 address used by the B4 element that resides in that CPE.
      When the AFTR receives a packet from this B4 element (i.e., the source
      address of the IPv4-in-IPv6 packet is 2001:db8:100:100::1), the AFTR
      applies the subscriber-mask (e.g., 56) on the source IPv6 address to
      compute the associated prefix for this B4 element (that is,
      2001:db8:100:100::/56). Then, the AFTR enforces policies based on that
      prefix (2001:db8:100:100::/56), not on the exact source IPv6
      address.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="reco" title="Recommendations">
      <t>In order to mitigate the issues discussed in <xref
      target="problem"></xref>, the following recommendations are made:<list
          style="numbers">
          <t>A policy SHOULD be enforced at the AFTR to limit the number of
          active DS-Lite softwires per subscriber. The default value MUST be
          1. <list style="empty">
              <t>This policy aims to prevent a misbehaving subscriber from
              mounting several DS-Lite softwires that would consume additional
              AFTR resources (e.g., get more external ports if the quota were
              enforced on a per-softwire basis, consume extra processing
              due to a large number of active softwires).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Resource contexts created and maintained by the AFTR SHOULD be
          based on the delegated IPv6 prefix instead of the B4's IPv6 address.
          The AFTR derives the delegated prefix from the B4's IPv6 address by
          means of a configured subscriber-mask (<xref target="sm"></xref>).
          Administrators SHOULD configure per-prefix limits of resource usage,
          instead of per-tunnel limits. These resources include the maximum
          number of active flows, the maximum number of PCP-created mappings,
          NAT pool resources, etc.</t>

          <t>In the event a new IPv6 address is assigned to the B4 element,
          the AFTR SHOULD migrate existing state to be bound to the new IPv6
          address. This operation ensures that traffic destined to the
          previous B4's IPv6 address will be redirected to the newer B4's IPv6
          address. The destination IPv6 address for tunneling return traffic
          from the AFTR SHOULD be the last seen as the B4's IPv6 source
          address from the CPE. <list style="empty">
              <t>This recommendation avoids stale mappings at the AFTR and
              minimizes the risk of service disruption for subscribers.</t>

              <t>The AFTR uses the subscriber-mask to determine whether two
              IPv6 addresses belong to the same CPE (e.g., if the
              subscriber-mask is set to 56, the AFTR concludes that
              2001:db8:100:100::1 and 2001:db8:100:100::2 belong to the same
              CPE assigned with 2001:db8:100:100::/56).</t>

              <t>As discussed in <xref target="sec-security"></xref>, changing
              the source B4's IPv6 address may be used as an attack vector.

              Packets with a new B4's IPv6 address from the same prefix SHOULD be
              rate-limited. It is RECOMMENDED to set this rate limit to 30
              minutes; other values can be set on a per-deployment basis.</t>

              <t>One side effect of migrating mapping state is that a server
              deployed behind an AFTR does not need to update its DNS records
              (if any) by means of dynamic DNS, for example. 

If a dedicated mapping is instantiated, migrating the state
during its validity lifetime will ensure that the same
external IP address and port are assigned to that server.
	      </t>
            </list></t>

          <t>In the event of change of the CPE WAN's IPv6 prefix, unsolicited
          PCP ANNOUNCE messages SHOULD be sent by the B4 element to internal
          hosts connected to the PCP-capable CPE so that they update their
          mappings accordingly. <list style="empty">
              <t>This allows internal PCP clients to update their mappings
              with the new B4's IPv6 address and to trigger updates to
              rendezvous servers (e.g., dynamic DNS). A PCP-based dynamic DNS
              solution is specified in <xref target="RFC7393"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>When a new prefix is assigned to the CPE, stale mappings may
          exist in the AFTR. This will consume both implicit and explicit
          resources. In order to avoid such issues, stable IPv6 prefix
          assignment is RECOMMENDED.</t>

          <t>If for any reason an IPv6 prefix has to be reassigned, it is
          RECOMMENDED to reassign an IPv6 prefix (that was previously assigned
          to a given CPE) to another CPE only when all the resources in use
          associated with that prefix are cleared from the AFTR. Doing so
          avoids redirecting traffic, destined to the previous prefix owner,
          to the new one.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations related to DS-Lite are discussed in <xref
      target="RFC6333"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Enforcing the recommendations documented in <xref
      target="reco"></xref> together with rate-limiting softwires with new
      source IPv6 addresses from the same prefix defend against DoS attacks
      that would result in varying the B4's IPv6 address to exhaust AFTR
      resources. A misbehaving CPE can be blacklisted by enforcing appropriate
      policies based on the prefix derived from the subscriber-mask.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>A CPE connected to a DS-Lite network is identified by a set of
      information that is specific to each network domain (e.g., service
      credentials, device identifiers, etc.). This document does not make any
      assumption nor introduce new requirements on how such identification is
      implemented network-wide.</t>

      <t>This document adheres to Sections 6 and 8 of <xref
      target="RFC6333"></xref> for handling IPv4-in-IPv6 packets and IPv4
      translation operations. In particular, this document does not leak extra
      information in packets exiting a DS-Lite network domain.</t>

      <t>The recommendations in <xref target="reco"></xref> (item 6, in
      particular) ensure that the traffic is forwarded to a legitimate CPE. If
      those recommendations are not implemented, privacy concerns may arise.
      For example, if an IPv6 prefix is reassigned while mapping entries associated
      with that prefix are still active in the AFTR, sensitive data that
      belong to a previous prefix owner may be disclosed to the new prefix
      owner.</t>

      <t>These recommendations do not interfere with privacy extensions for
      generating IPv6 addresses (e.g., <xref target="RFC7217"></xref> or <xref
      target="RFC4941"></xref>). These recommendations allow a CPE to generate
      new IPv6 addresses with privacy extensions without experiencing DS-Lite
      service degradation. Even if activating privacy extensions makes it more
      difficult to track a CPE over time when compared to using a permanent
      Interface Identifier, tracking a CPE is still possible based on the
      first 64 bits of the IPv6 address. This is even exacerbated for
      deployments relying on stable IPv6 prefixes.</t>

      <t>This document does not nullify the privacy effects that may motivate
      the use of non-stable IPv6 prefixes. Particularly, the subscriber-mask
      does not enable identifying a CPE across renumbering (even within a
      DS-Lite network domain). This document mitigates some of the undesired
      effects of reassigning an IPv6 prefix to another CPE (e.g., update a
      rendezvous service, clear stale mappings).</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6333'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6887'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6908'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7393'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6888'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4787'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4941'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7217'?>

      <reference anchor="RIPE"
                 target="https://www.ripe.net/publications/docs/ripe&nbhy;650">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Address Allocation and Assignment Policy</title>

          <author>
            <organization>RIPE</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="August" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LACNIC"
                 target="http://www.lacnic.net/en/web/lacnic/manual-4">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Address Allocation and Assignment Policies</title>

          <author>
            <organization>LACNIC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section numbered="no" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>G.&nbsp;Krishna, C.&nbsp;Jacquenet, I.&nbsp;Farrer, Y.&nbsp;Lee,
      Q.&nbsp;Sun, R.&nbsp;Weber, T.&nbsp;Taylor, D.&nbsp;Harkins,
      D.&nbsp;Gillmor, S.&nbsp;Sivakumar, A.&nbsp;Cooper, and B.&nbsp;Campbell
      provided useful comments. Many thanks to them.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
