<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="8284"
     ipr="trust200902" 
     category="info" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="LDAP Schema for XMPP">
      Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Schema for Supporting
      the&nbsp;Extensible&nbsp;Messaging&nbsp;and&nbsp;Presence&nbsp;Protocol&nbsp;(XMPP)&nbsp;in&nbsp;White&nbsp;Pages
    </title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Kille" fullname="Steve Kille">
      <organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>14 Castle Mews</street>
	  <city>Hampton</city>
	  <region>Middlesex</region>
	  <code>TW12 2NP</code>
	  <country>United Kingdom</country>
	</postal>
	<email>Steve.Kille@isode.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
      
    <date month="November" year="2017"/>
    
    <abstract>

    <t>
      The Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) identifies users
      by use of Jabber IDs (JIDs).  The Lightweight Directory Access Protocol
      (LDAP) enables provision of a white pages service with a schema relating
      to users and support for Internet protocols.  This specification defines
      a schema to enable XMPP JIDs to be associated with objects in an LDAP
      directory so that this information can be used with white pages
      applications.
    </t>
	
    </abstract>
    
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      
      <t>
        Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) <xref target="RFC6120"/>
        identifies users by use of Jabber IDs (JIDs).   The Lightweight Directory
	Access Protocol (LDAP) <xref target="RFC4510"/> enables provision of a
	white pages service with a schema relating to users and support for
	Internet protocols defined in <xref target="RFC4519"/>.  This
	specification defines a schema to enable XMPP JIDs to be associated with LDAP directory objects so that this information can be used with white pages applications. 
   
      </t>

<t>The LDAP schema for storing JIDs is defined to enable JIDs to be associated
with any object stored in the directory.  This is done by associating the new
JID Attribute with a new Auxiliary Object Class called JIDObject.</t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>

   <section title="Schema Definition">
     
     <t>This section defines the schema used to store JIDs in the directory.</t>
     

     <section title="Object Class">
       <t>This section defines a new Auxiliary Object Class called JIDObject, which MAY be associated with any structural Object Class.
      This Object Class is used to augment entries for objects that act or may
      act as an XMPP client.   The JID attribute is optional in order to enable configuring an object that is allowed to have an associated JID but does not currently have one.
       </t>
 
 
<t>    
 <figure>
   <artwork>
     ( 1.3.6.1.1.23.1 NAME 'JIDObject'
     AUXILIARY
     MAY jid )   
   </artwork>
 </figure>
</t>       
     </section>
     
     <section title="Attribute">
       <t>This section defines the JID attribute referenced by the JIDObject
       Auxiliary Object Class.   The syntax of the JID attribute MUST follow
       the rules of <xref target="RFC7622"/>. The JID stored MUST be a bare
       JID (e.g., a JID such as romeo@shakespeare.example.com representing a
       human user) and not a full JID (e.g., a JID such as
       romeo@shakespare.example.com/&wj;AABBCC, which represents a specific XMPP
       client used by the human user and is identified by the resource AABBCC).  Note that the LDAP directory server is not expected to enforce this syntax.    The syntax rules are for LDAP clients setting this attribute, noting that human usage is a key target.  Applications using this attribute should format that string in a manner appropriate to the application, and XMPP applications SHOULD apply <xref target="RFC7622"/> to the attribute.   The directory service doesn't enforce the JID syntax, and values are compared according to the matching rules specified in the attribute definition.</t>
       
       <t>
         Note that for the convenience of users and administrators as well as
	 implementers, the Directory String syntax and the caseIgnoreMatch matching rule are chosen to allow entry and matching of values according to common rules used within the directory.  As this syntax and matching rule differ from <xref target="RFC7622"/>, false positives and false negatives can possibly occur. This is not anticipated to cause operational issues (based on implementation experience with similar syntax/matching rule mismatches).
       </t>
       
<t>    
  <figure>
    <artwork>
      ( 1.3.6.1.1.23.2 NAME 'jid'
         EQUALITY caseIgnoreMatch
         SUBSTR caseIgnoreSubstringsMatch
         SYNTAX 1.3.6.1.4.1.1466.115.121.1.15 )
    </artwork>
  </figure>
</t> 
       
 <t>
   1.3.6.1.4.1.1466.115.121.1.15 refers to the Directory String syntax defined in <xref target="RFC4517"/>.

 </t>
     </section>
   </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

 
      <t>The following registrations have been made in the "Lightweight
      Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Parameters" registry 
        &lt;https://www.iana.org/assignments/ldap-parameters&gt; in line with BCP 64 <xref target="RFC4520"/>. 
        
      </t>
      
      <t>Object Identifier Registration</t>
      
      <t>An object identifier has been assigned to support the registrations necessary for this specification by an entry in the Internet Directory Numbers (iso.org.dod.internet.directory [1.3.6.1.1.]) registry:</t>
      <t>    
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            Decimal: 23
            Name: xmpp
            Description: LDAP schema for XMPP
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>     
      
      <t>Two object identifiers have been assigned:</t>
      
      <t>'JIDObject' Descriptor Registration</t>
      
      <t>    
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            Name: JIDObject
            Type: O
            OID: 1.3.6.1.1.23.1
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>   
      
      <t>'jid' Descriptor Registration</t>
      
      <t>    
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            Name: jid
            Type: A
            OID: 1.3.6.1.1.23.2
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>   
      

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="seccons">

      <t>XMPP JIDs are often personal identifiers enabling electronic
      communication and have similar considerations to email addresses.   This schema enables publishing of this information in LDAP directories, which may be corporate or public services.   

     Care should be taken to only publish JID information that is acceptable
     both to be linked to the LDAP object and to be made accessible to all LDAP users.
      
      The general LDAP security considerations specified in  <xref target="RFC4510"/> also apply.</t>

    </section>
    
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4510"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4517"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4519"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4520"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6120"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7622"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
	
      <t>Thanks to Alexey Melnikov for suggestions on preparing this document.
      Thanks to Alan Murdock, Yoav Nir, Peter Saint-Andre, and Kurt Zeilenga
      for their review comments.</t>

      
    </section>


    
  </back>
</rfc>
