<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY LFA-APPLICABILITY SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6571.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1195 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2328 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6976 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6976.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY ULOOP-DELAY SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8333.xml">
<!ENTITY BACKOFF SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8405.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" number="8541" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">
  <front>




    <title abbrev="SPF Impact on IGP Micro-loops">Impact of Shortest Path
    First (SPF) Trigger and Delay Strategies on IGP Micro-loops</title>

    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S" surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange Business Service</organization>

      <address>
        <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	    <author fullname="Bruno Decraene" initials="B" surname="Decraene">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	<author fullname="Martin Horneffer" initials="M" surname="Horneffer">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <email>martin.horneffer@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date month="March" year="2019"/>

    <area/>

    <workgroup>Routing Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>A micro-loop is a packet-forwarding loop that may occur transiently
   among two or more routers in a hop-by-hop packet-forwarding paradigm.
	</t>
	<t>This document analyzes the impact of using different link
	state IGP implementations in a single network with respect to
	micro-loops. 
	The analysis is focused on the Shortest Path First (SPF) delay
	algorithm but also mentions the impact of SPF trigger strategies.</t>
    </abstract>  
  </front>

  <middle>

	<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
	  <t>
	Link state IGP protocols are based on a topology database on which the SPF algorithm is run to find a consistent set of non-looping routing paths.
	</t>
	<t>Specifications like IS-IS <xref target="RFC1195"/> propose some optimizations of the route computation (see Appendix C.1 of <xref target="RFC1195"/>), but not all implementations follow those non-mandatory optimizations.</t>
	<t>In this document, we refer to the events that lead to a new SPF
	computation based on the topology as "SPF triggers".</t>

	<t>
	Link state IGP protocols, like OSPF <xref target="RFC2328"/> and IS-IS
	<xref target="RFC1195"/>, use multiple timers to control the router
	behavior in case of churn: SPF delay, Partial Route Computation (PRC)
	delay, Link State Packet (LSP) generation delay, LSP flooding delay,
	and LSP retransmission interval.
	</t>

	<t>Some of the values and behaviors of these timers are standardized
	in
	protocol specifications, and some are not. The SPF
	computation-related timers have generally remained unspecified.</t> 
	<t>Implementations are free to implement non-standardized timers in any way. 
	For some standardized timers, implementations may offer dynamically
	adjusted timers to help control the churn rather than use static
	configurable values.</t>
	<t>"SPF delay" refers to the timer in most implementations that
	specifies the required delay before running an SPF computation after an
	SPF trigger is received.</t>
	<t>
	A micro-loop is a packet-forwarding loop that may occur transiently
   among two or more routers in a hop-by-hop packet-forwarding paradigm. 
These micro-loops are formed when two routers do not update their Forwarding
Information Bases (FIBs) for a certain prefix at the same time.
	The micro-loop phenomenon is described in <xref target="MICROLOOP-LSRP"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	Two micro-loop mitigation techniques have been defined by IETF. The
	mechanism in <xref
	target="RFC6976"/> has not been widely implemented, presumably due to
	the complexity of the technique. The mechanism in <xref
	target="RFC8333"/> has been implemented. However, it does not prevent
	all micro-loops that can occur for a given topology and failure
	scenario.
	</t>
	<t>
	In multi-vendor networks, using different implementations of a link state protocol may favor micro-loop creation during the convergence process due to discrepancies in timers.
	Service providers already know to use timers with similar values and behaviors
	for all of the network as a best practice, but this is sometimes
	not possible due to the limitations of implementations.
	</t>
	<t>
	This document presents reasons for service providers to have
	consistent implementation of link state protocols across vendors. In
	particular, this document analyzes the impact of using different link state
	IGP implementations in a single network with regard to micro-loops. 
	The analysis focuses on the SPF delay algorithm.
	</t>
	<t><xref target="RFC8405"/> defines a solution that partially
	addresses this problem statement, and this document captures the
	reasoning of the provided solution.</t>

	</section>
    <section anchor="problem" title="Problem Statement">


      <t>
	<figure anchor="fig-network-top" title="Network Topology Experiencing Micro-loops">
	  <artwork>
                           S ---- E
                           |      |
                        10 |      | 10
                           |      |
                           D ---- A
                           |  2
                           Px
          </artwork>
	  </figure>
	  <xref target="fig-network-top"/> represents a small network composed of four routers (S, D,
	  E, and A).  Router S primarily uses the SD link to reach the
	  prefixes behind router D (named Px). When the SD link fails, the
	  IGP convergence occurs. If S converges before E, S will forward the
	  traffic to Px through E; however, because E has not converged yet, E will
	  loop the traffic back to S, leading to a micro-loop.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	  The micro-loop appears due to the asynchronous convergence of nodes in a network when an event occurs.
	  </t>

	  <t>Multiple factors (or a combination of factors) may increase the probability of a micro-loop appearing: 
	  <list style="symbols">
	  <t>Delay of failure notification: The greater the time gap
	  between E and S being advised of the failure, the greater the
	  chance that a micro-loop may appear.</t>
	  <t>SPF delay: Most implementations support a delay for the SPF
	  computation to catch as many events as possible. If S uses an SPF
	  delay timer of x ms, E uses an SPF delay timer of y ms, and x &lt;
	  y, E would start converging after S, leading to a potential
	  micro-loop.</t>

	  <t>SPF computation time: This is mostly a matter of CPU power
	  and optimizations like incremental SPF. If S computes its SPF faster
	  than E, there is a chance for a micro-loop to appear. Today, CPUs are fast enough
	  to consider the SPF computation time as negligible (on the order of milliseconds in a large network).</t>
	  <t>SPF computation ordering: An SPF trigger can be common to
	  multiple IGP areas or levels (e.g., IS-IS Level 1 and Level 2) or 
          to multiple address families with multi-topologies. There is no specified order for SPF computation today, and 
        it is implementation dependent. In such scenarios, if the order of SPF computation done
        in S and E for each area, level, topology, or SPF algorithm is different,
	there is a possibility for a
	micro-loop to appear.  
       </t>
	  <t>RIB and FIB prefix insertion speed or ordering: This is highly
	  dependent on the implementation.</t>

	  </list>
	  </t>
		<t>Even if all of these factors increase the probability of a
		micro-loop appearing, the SPF delay plays a significant role, especially in case of churn.

  As the number of IGP events increases, the
  delta between the SPF delay values used by routers becomes significant; in fact,
  it becomes the dominating factor (especially when one router increases its
  timer exponentially while another one increases it in a smoother
  way).  

		Another important factor is the time to update the FIB. As of
		today, the total FIB update time is the major factor for IGP convergence. However, for micro-loops, what matters is not the total time but the difference in installing the same prefix between nodes. 
		The time to update the FIB may be the main part for the first
		iteration but not for subsequent IGP events. 
		In addition, the time to update the FIB is very implementation
		specific and difficult or impossible to standardize, while the SPF delay algorithm may be standardized.</t>
	  <t>
	  As a consequence, this document will focus on an analysis of SPF
	  delay behavior and associated triggers.
	  </t>
    </section>
	<section anchor="spf-trigger" title="SPF Trigger Strategies">
	<t>
	Depending on the change advertised in the LSP
	or LSA (Link State Advertisement), the topology may or may not be affected.
	An implementation may avoid running the SPF computation (and may only run an IP reachability computation instead) if the advertised change does not affect the topology.
	</t>
	<t>
	Different strategies can trigger the SPF computation:
	<list style="numbers">
	<t>An implementation may always run a full SPF for any type of change.</t>
	<t>An implementation may run a full SPF only when required. For example, if a link fails, a local node will run an SPF for its local LSP update. If the LSP from the neighbor (describing the same failure)
	is received after SPF has started, the local node can decide that a new full SPF is not required as the topology has not changed.</t>
	<t>If the topology does not change, an implementation may only recompute the IP reachability.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	As noted in <xref target="introduction"/>, SPF optimizations are not mandatory in specifications. This has led to the implementation of different strategies.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section anchor="spf-delay" title="SPF Delay Strategies">
	<t>
	Implementations of link state routing protocols use different strategies to delay SPF computation. The two most common SPF delay behaviors are the following:
	<list style="numbers">
	<t>Two-step SPF delay</t>
	<t>Exponential back-off delay</t>
	</list>
	These behaviors are explained in the following sections.
	</t>




		<section anchor="spf-delay-2step" title="Two-Step SPF Delay">
		<t>
		The SPF delay is managed by four parameters:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>rapid delay: the amount of time to wait before running SPF after the initial SPF trigger event.</t>
				<t>rapid runs: the number of consecutive SPF runs that can use the rapid delay. When the number is exceeded, the delay moves to the slow delay value.</t>
				<t>slow delay: the amount of time to wait
				before running an SPF.</t>
				<t>wait time: the amount of time to wait without detecting SPF trigger events before going back to the rapid delay.</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
		<xref target="fig-2phase"/> displays the evolution of the SPF delay
		timer (based on a two-step delay algorithm) upon the reception
		of multiple events. <xref target="fig-2phase"/> considers the
		following parameters for the algorithm: rapid delay (RD) = 50
		ms, rapid runs = 3, slow delay (SD) = 1 s, wait time = 2 s.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="fig-2phase" title="Two-Step SPF Delay Algorithm">
                <artwork>
SPF delay time
    ^
    |
    |
SD- |             x xx x
    |
    |
    |
RD- |   x  x   x                    x
    |
    +---------------------------------> Events
        |  |   |  | || |            |
                        &lt; wait time &gt;
                </artwork>
		</figure>
		
		</section>
		<section anchor="spf-delay-exp" title="Exponential Back-Off Delay">
		<t>
		The algorithm has two modes: fast mode and back-off mode. In
		fast mode, the SPF delay is usually delayed by a very small amount of time (fast reaction). 
		When an SPF computation is run in fast mode, the
		algorithm automatically moves to back-off mode (a single SPF
		run is authorized in fast mode).
		In back-off mode, the SPF delay increases exponentially in each run.
		When the network becomes stable, the algorithm moves back to
		fast mode.
		The SPF delay is managed by four parameters:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>first delay: amount of time to wait before running SPF. This delay is used only when SPF is in fast mode.</t>
				<t>incremental delay: amount of time to wait before running SPF. This delay is used only when SPF is in back-off mode and increments exponentially at each SPF run.</t>
				<t>maximum delay: maximum amount of time to wait before running SPF.</t>
				<t>wait time: amount of time to wait without
				events before going back to fast mode.</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
		<xref target="fig-expo"/> displays the evolution of the SPF delay
		timer (based on an exponential back-off delay algorithm) upon
		the reception of multiple events. <xref target="fig-expo"/>
		considers the following parameters for the algorithm: first
		delay (FD) = 50 ms, incremental delay (ID) = 50 ms, maximum
		delay (MD) = 1 s, wait time = 2 s

		</t>
                <figure anchor="fig-expo" title="Exponential Back-Off Delay Algorithm">
                <artwork>
SPF delay time
    ^
MD- |               xx x
    |
    |
    |
    |                
    |
    |             x
    |
    |               
    |
    |          x
    |
FD- |   x  x                        x
ID  |
    +---------------------------------> Events
        |  |   |  | || |            |
                        &lt; wait time &gt;
       FM-&gt;BM --------------------&gt;FM               
                </artwork>
		</figure>
		</section>

	</section>
	<section anchor="spf-mix" title="Mixing Strategies">
	<t>

	<xref target="fig-network-top"/> illustrates a flow of packets
	from S to D. 
	S uses optimized SPF triggering (full SPF is triggered only
	when necessary) and two-step SPF delay (rapid delay = 150 ms, rapid
	runs = 3, slow delay = 1 s). As the implementation of S is optimized,
	PRC is available. 
	For PRC delay, we consider the same timers as for SPF delay.
	E uses an SPF trigger strategy that always computes
	a full SPF for any change and uses the exponential back-off strategy
	for SPF delay (first delay = 150 ms, incremental delay = 150 ms,
	maximum delay = 1 s).
	</t>
	<t>
	Consider the following sequence of events:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>t0=0 ms: A prefix is declared down in the network. This
	event happens at time=0.</t>
	<t>200 ms: The prefix is declared up.</t>
	<t>400 ms: The prefix is declared down in the network.</t>
	<t>1000 ms: S-D link fails.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<texttable anchor="Table-1" title="Route Computation When S and E Use Different Behaviors and Multiple Events Appear"> 
	<ttcol width="11%" align="center">Time</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Network Event</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router S Events</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router E Events</ttcol>
	<c>t0=0</c><c>Prefix DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>10&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>160&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>161&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c></c>
	<c>162&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>163&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>164&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>175&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>178&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>200&nbsp;ms</c><c>Prefix UP</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>212&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c><c></c>
	<c>214&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>370&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c></c>
	<c>372&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c></c>
	<c>373&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>373&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>375&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>376&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>383&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>385&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>400&nbsp;ms</c><c>Prefix DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>410&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 300 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 300 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>710&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>711&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c></c>
	<c>712&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>713&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>714&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>716&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1000&nbsp;ms</c><c>S-D link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1010&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 600 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1160&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c></c>
	<c>1161&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c></c>
	<c>1162&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop may start from here</c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>1175&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
    <c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
    <c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1612&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>1615&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>1616&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>1626&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop ends</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>

	</texttable>
	
	<t>
	In <xref target="Table-1"/>, due to discrepancies in the SPF
	management and after multiple events of different types, the values of the SPF delay are completely misaligned between node S and node E, leading to the creation of micro-loops.
	</t>
	<t>
	The same issue can also appear with only a single type of event as shown below:</t>
	
	<texttable anchor="Table-2" title="Route Computation upon Multiple Link Down Events When S and E Use Different Behaviors">
	<ttcol width="11%" align="center">Time</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Network Event</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router S Events</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router E Events</ttcol>
	<c>t0=0</c><c>Link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>10&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>160&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>161&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c></c>
	<c>162&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>163&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>164&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>175&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>178&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>200&nbsp;ms</c><c>Link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>212&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c><c></c>
	<c>214&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>370&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c></c>
	<c>372&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c></c>
	<c>373&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>373&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>375&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>376&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>383&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>385&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>400&nbsp;ms</c><c>Link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>410&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 300 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>560&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c></c>
	<c>561&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c></c>
	<c>562&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop may start from here</c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>568&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>710&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>713&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>714&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>716&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop ends</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1000&nbsp;ms</c><c>Link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1010&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 1 s)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 600 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
    <c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1612&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>1615&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>1616&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop may start from here</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>1626&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
    <c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>2012&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c></c>
	<c>2014&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c></c>
	<c>2015&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>2025&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop ends</c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
    <c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	</texttable>

	
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="workitems" title="Benefits of Standardized SPF Delay Behavior">


	<t><xref target="Table-3"/> uses the same event sequence as <xref
	target="Table-1"/>. Fewer and/or shorter
  micro-loops are expected using a standardized SPF delay.
</t>
	
	<texttable anchor="Table-3" title="Route Computation When S and E Use the Same Standardized Behavior">
	<ttcol width="11%" align="center">Time</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Network Event</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router S Events</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="center">Router E Events</ttcol>
	<c>t0=0</c><c>Prefix DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>10&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>160&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c>PRC starts</c>
	<c>161&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c></c>
	<c>162&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c>PRC ends</c>
	<c>163&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>175&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>176&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>200&nbsp;ms</c><c>Prefix UP</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>212&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c><c></c>
	<c>213&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>370&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c>PRC starts</c>
	<c>372&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c></c>
	<c>373&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c>PRC ends</c>
	<c>374&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>383&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>384&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>400&nbsp;ms</c><c>Prefix DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>410&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule PRC (in 300 ms)</c><c>Schedule PRC (in 300 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>710&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC starts</c><c>PRC starts</c>
	<c>711&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>PRC ends</c><c>PRC ends</c>
	<c>712&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c></c>
	<c>713&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>716&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1000&nbsp;ms</c><c>S-D link DOWN</c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1010&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c><c>Schedule SPF (in 150 ms)</c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c>1160&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF starts</c><c></c>
	<c>1161&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>SPF ends</c><c>SPF starts</c>
	<c>1162&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop may start from here</c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c><c>SPF ends</c>
	<c>1163&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB starts</c>
	<c>1175&nbsp;ms</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c><c></c>
	<c>1177&nbsp;ms</c><c>Micro-loop ends</c><c></c><c>RIB/FIB ends</c>
	</texttable>
	
	
	<t>
	As displayed above, there can be other parameters, like router
	computation power and flooding timers, that may also influence micro-loops. 
	In all the examples in this document comparing the SPF timer behavior
	of router S and router E, we have made router E a bit slower than
	router S. This can lead to micro-loops even when both S and E use a common standardized SPF behavior. 
	However, by aligning implementations
	of the SPF delay, we expect that service providers may reduce the number and duration of micro-loops.
	</t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>
	This document does not introduce any security considerations.
	</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>


  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

	  &RFC2328;
	  &RFC1195;
	  &BACKOFF;

    </references>
	    <references title="Informative References">
	  &RFC6976;
	  &ULOOP-DELAY;

<!-- draft-ietf-rtgwg-microloop-analysis-01: Expired -->
<reference anchor='MICROLOOP-LSRP'>
<front>
<title>Analysis and Minimization of Microloops in Link-state Routing Protocols</title>

<author initials='A' surname='Zinin' fullname='Alex Zinin'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2005' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-rtgwg-microloop-analysis-01' />
</reference>
	 
    </references>
<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
	<t>The authors would like to thank Mike Shand and Chris Bowers for their useful comments.</t>
	</section>

  </back>
</rfc>
