<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC3986 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5246 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5730 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5730.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7481 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7481.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7482 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7482.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7483 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7483.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7484 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7484.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC8126 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>

<rfc number="8521"
seriesNo="221" 
     category="bcp" 
     ipr="trust200902" 
     updates="7484"
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">

<front>
    <title abbrev="RDAP Object Tagging">Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) Object Tagging</title>
    
    <author initials="S." surname="Hollenbeck" fullname="Scott Hollenbeck">
      <organization>Verisign Labs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shollenbeck@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.verisignlabs.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Andrew Lee Newton" initials="A.L." surname="Newton">
      <organization abbrev="ARIN">American Registry for Internet Numbers</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box 232290</street>
          <city>Centreville</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
          <code>20120</code>
        </postal>
        <email>andy@arin.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.arin.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2018"/>

    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <workgroup>Registration Protocols Extensions</workgroup>
    <keyword>RDAP</keyword>
    <keyword>Entity</keyword>
    <keyword>Bootstrap</keyword>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>The Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) includes a method that
      can be used to identify the authoritative server for processing domain
      name, IP address, and autonomous system number queries. The  method does
      not describe how to identify the authoritative server for processing
      other RDAP query types, such as entity queries. This limitation exists
      because the identifiers associated with these query types are typically
      unstructured. This document updates RFC 7484 by describing an
      operational practice that can be used to add structure to RDAP
      identifiers and makes it possible to identify the authoritative server for additional RDAP queries.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) includes a method <xref target="RFC7484"/> that can be used to identify the authoritative server for processing domain name, IP address, and Autonomous System Number (ASN) queries. This method works because each of these data elements is structured in a way that facilitates automated parsing of the element and association of the data element with a particular RDAP service provider. For example, domain names include labels (such as "com", "net", and "org") that are associated with specific service providers.</t>
      
      <t>As noted in Section 9 of RFC 7484 <xref target="RFC7484"/>, the
      method does not describe how to identify the authoritative server for
      processing entity queries, name server queries, help queries, or queries
      using certain search patterns. This limitation exists because the
      identifiers bound to these queries are typically not structured in a way
      that makes it easy to associate an identifier with a specific service
      provider. This document describes an operational practice that can be
      used to add structure to RDAP identifiers and makes it possible to identify the authoritative server for additional RDAP queries.</t>
      
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
      
    <section anchor="practice" title="Object Naming Practice">
      <t>Tagging object identifiers with a service provider tag makes it
      possible to identify the authoritative server for processing an RDAP
      query using the method described in RFC 7484 <xref target="RFC7484"/>. A
      service provider tag is constructed by prepending the Unicode
      HYPHEN-MINUS character "-" (U+002D, described as an "unreserved"
      character in RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/>) to an IANA-registered
      value that represents the service provider. For example, a tag for a
      service provider identified by the string value "ARIN" is represented as
      "-ARIN".</t> 
      
      <t>In combination with the rdapConformance attribute described in <xref target="conformance"/>, service provider tags are concatenated to the end of RDAP query object identifiers to unambiguously identify the authoritative server for processing an RDAP query. Building on the example from Section 3.1.5 of RFC 7482 <xref target="RFC7482"/>, an RDAP entity handle can be constructed to allow an RDAP client to bootstrap an entity query. The following identifier is used to find information for the entity associated with handle "XXXX" at service provider "ARIN":<list>
      
      <t>XXXX-ARIN</t></list></t>
      
      <t>Clients that wish to bootstrap an entity query can parse this
      identifier into distinct handle and service provider identifier
      elements. Handles can themselves contain HYPHEN-MINUS characters; the
      service provider identifier is found following the last HYPHEN-MINUS
      character in the tagged identifier. The service provider identifier is
      used to retrieve a base RDAP URL from an IANA registry. The base URL and
      entity handle are then used to form a complete RDAP query path
      segment. For example, if the base RDAP URL "https://example.com/rdap/"
      is associated with service provider "YYYY" in an IANA registry, an RDAP
      client will parse a tagged entity identifier "XXXX-YYYY" into distinct
      handle ("XXXX") and service provider ("YYYY") identifiers. The service
      provider identifier "YYYY" is used to query an IANA registry to retrieve
      the base RDAP URL "https://example.com/rdap/". The RDAP query URL is
      formed using the base RDAP URL and entity path segment described in
      Section 3.1.5 of RFC 7482 <xref target="RFC7482"/> and using "XXXX-YYY" as the value of the handle identifier. The complete RDAP query URL becomes "https://example.com/rdap/entity/XXXX-YYYY".</t>
      
      <t>Implementation of this practice requires tagging of unstructured potential query identifiers in RDAP responses. Consider these elided examples ("..." is used to note elided response objects) from Section 5.3 of RFC 7483 <xref target="RFC7483"/> in which the handle identifiers have been tagged with service provider tags "RIR", "DNR", and "ABC", respectively:</t>

      <figure anchor="dom-rir-7483-example">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve">
{
  "objectClassName" : "domain",
  "handle" : "XXXX-RIR",
  "ldhName" : "0.2.192.in-addr.arpa",
  "nameservers" :
  [
    ...
  ],
  "secureDNS":
  {
    ...
  },
  "remarks" :
  [
    ...
  ],
  "links" :
  [
    ...
  ],
  "events" :
  [
    ...
  ],
  "entities" :
  [
    {
      "objectClassName" : "entity",
      "handle" : "XXXX-RIR",
      "vcardArray":
      [
        ...
      ],
      "roles" : [ "registrant" ],
      "remarks" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "links" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "events" :
      [
        ...
      ]
    }
  ],
  "network" :
  {
    "objectClassName" : "ip network",
    "handle" : "XXXX-RIR",
    "startAddress" : "192.0.2.0",
    "endAddress" : "192.0.2.255",
    "ipVersion" : "v4",
    "name": "NET-RTR-1",
    "type" : "DIRECT ALLOCATION",
    "country" : "AU",
    "parentHandle" : "YYYY-RIR",
    "status" : [ "active" ]
  }
}
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <figure anchor="dom-dnr-7483-example">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve">
{
  "objectClassName" : "domain",
  "handle" : "XXXX-YYY-DNR",
  "ldhName" : "xn--fo-5ja.example",
  "unicodeName" : "foo.example",
  "variants" :
  [
    ...
  ],
  "status" : [ "locked", "transfer prohibited" ],
  "publicIds":
  [
    ...
  ],
  "nameservers" :
  [
    {
      "objectClassName" : "nameserver",
      "handle" : "XXXX-DNR",
      "ldhName" : "ns1.example.com",
      "status" : [ "active" ],
      "ipAddresses" :
      {
        ...
      },
      "remarks" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "links" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "events" :
      [
        ...
      ]
    },
    {
      "objectClassName" : "nameserver",
      "handle" : "XXXX-DNR",
      "ldhName" : "ns2.example.com",
      "status" : [ "active" ],
      "ipAddresses" :
      {
        ...
      },
      "remarks" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "links" :
      [
        ...
      ],
      "events" :
      [
        ...
      ]
    }
   ],
   "secureDNS":
   {
     ...
   },
   "remarks" :
   [
     ...
   ],
   "links" :
   [
     ...
   ],
   "port43" : "whois.example.net",
   "events" :
   [
     ...
   ],
   "entities" :
   [
     {
       "objectClassName" : "entity",
       "handle" : "XXXX-ABC",
       "vcardArray":
       [
         ...
       ],
       "status" : [ "validated", "locked" ],
       "roles" : [ "registrant" ],
       "remarks" :
       [
         ...
       ],
       "links" :
       [
         ...
       ],
       "events" :
       [
         ...
       ]
     }
   ]
}
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <t>As described in Section 5 of RFC 7483 <xref target="RFC7483"/>, RDAP responses can contain "self" links. Service provider tags and self references SHOULD be consistent. If they are inconsistent, the service provider tag is processed with higher priority when using these values to identify a service provider.</t>
      
      <t>There is a risk of unpredictable processing behavior if the
      HYPHEN-MINUS character is used for naturally occurring, non-separator
      purposes in an entity handle. This could lead to a client mistakenly
      assuming that a HYPHEN-MINUS character represents a separator and that the text that follows HYPHEN-MINUS is a service provider identifier. A client that queries the IANA registry for what they assume is a valid service provider will likely receive an unexpected, invalid result. As a consequence, use of the HYPHEN-MINUS character as a service provider tag separator MUST be noted by adding an rdapConformance value to query responses as described in <xref target="conformance"/>.</t>
      
      <t>The HYPHEN-MINUS character was chosen as a separator for two reasons: 1) it is a familiar separator character in operational use, and 2) it avoids collision with URI-reserved characters. The list of unreserved characters specified in Section 2.3 of RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/> provided multiple options for consideration:<list>
      
      <t>unreserved  = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "." / "_" / "~"</t></list></t>
      
      <t>ALPHA and DIGIT characters were excluded because they are commonly used in entity handles for non-separator purposes. HYPHEN-MINUS is commonly used as a separator, and recognition of this practice will reduce implementation requirements and operational risk. The remaining characters were excluded because they are not broadly used as separators in entity handles.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="bootstrap-entity-1" title="Bootstrap Service Registry for Provider Object Tags">
      <t>The bootstrap service registry for the RDAP service provider space is
      represented using the structure specified in Section 3 of RFC 7484 <xref
      target="RFC7484"/>. The JSON output of this registry contains contact
      information for the registered service provider identifiers,
      alphanumeric identifiers that identify RDAP service providers, and base
      RDAP service URLs as shown in this example.</t> 

      <figure anchor="reg-example">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve">
{
  "version": "1.0",
  "publication": "YYYY-MM-DDTHH:MM:SSZ",
  "description": "RDAP bootstrap file for service provider object tags",
  "services": [
    [
      ["contact@example.com"],
      ["YYYY"],
      [
        "https://example.com/rdap/"
      ]
    ],
    [
      ["contact@example.org"],
      ["ZZ54"],
      [
        "http://rdap.example.org/"
      ]
    ],
    [
      ["contact@example.net"],
      ["1754"],
      [
        "https://example.net/rdap/",
        "http://example.net/rdap/"
      ]
    ]
  ]
 }
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        
        <t>Alphanumeric service provider identifiers conform to the suffix portion ("\w{1,8}") of the "roidType" syntax specified in Section 4.2 of RFC 5730 <xref target="RFC5730"/>.</t>
      
      <section anchor="reg-proc" title="Registration Procedure">
        <t>The service provider registry is populated using the "First Come First Served" policy defined in RFC 8126 <xref target="RFC8126"/>. Provider identifier values can be derived and assigned by IANA on request. Registration requests include an email address to be associated with the registered service provider identifier, the requested service provider identifier (or an indication that IANA should assign an identifier), and one or more base RDAP URLs to be associated with the service provider identifier.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
      
    <section anchor="conformance" title="RDAP Conformance">      
      <t>RDAP responses that contain values described in this document MUST
      indicate conformance with this specification by including an
      rdapConformance <xref target="RFC7483"/> value of
      "rdap_objectTag_level_0". The information needed to register this value
      in the "RDAP Extensions" registry is described in <xref
      target="ext-registry"/>.</t>

<t>The following is an example rdapConformance structure with the extension
specified.</t> 
        
      <figure anchor="rdapConformance_lunarNic">
	  <artwork xml:space="preserve">
          "rdapConformance" : 
          [
            "rdap_level_0",
            "rdap_objectTag_level_0"
          ]
          </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations"> 

      <t>IANA has created the RDAP "Bootstrap Service Registry for Provider
      Object Tags" listed below and made it available as a JSON object. The
      contents of this registry are described in <xref
      target="bootstrap-entity-1"/>; the formal syntax is specified in
      Section 10 of RFC 7484 <xref target="RFC7484"/>.</t> 
      
      <section anchor="bootstrap-entity-2" title="Bootstrap Service Registry Structure">
        <t>Entries in this registry contain the following information:</t>
        
        <t><list style="symbols">
	  <t>an email address that identifies a contact associated with the registered RDAP service provider value.</t>
	  <t>an alphanumeric value that identifies the RDAP service provider
	  being registered.</t>
	  <t>one or more URLs that provide the RDAP service regarding this registration. The URLs are expected to supply the same data, but they can differ in scheme or other components as required by the service operator.</t>
	</list></t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="ext-registry" title="RDAP Extensions Registry">
        <t>IANA has registered the following value in the "RDAP Extensions" registry:</t>
      
        <t><list style="none">
          <t>Extension identifier: rdap_objectTag</t>
          <t>Registry operator: Any</t>
          <t>Published specification: This document</t>
          <t>Contact: IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</t>
          <t>Intended usage: This extension describes a best practice for structuring entity identifiers to enable query bootstrapping.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This practice uses IANA as a well-known, centrally trusted authority to
      allow users to get RDAP data from an authoritative source, which reduces the
      risk of sending queries to non-authoritative sources and divulging query
      information to unintended parties. Using TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/> to
      protect the connection to IANA allows the server to authenticate itself
      as being operated by IANA and provides integrity protection for the
      resulting referral information, as well as provides privacy protection
      via data confidentiality. The subsequent RDAP connection is performed as
      usual and retains the same security properties of the RDAP protocols
      themselves as described in RFC 7481 <xref target="RFC7481" />.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC5730;
      &RFC7484;
      &RFC8126;
      &RFC8174;
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3986;
      &RFC5246;
      &RFC7481;
      &RFC7482;
      &RFC7483;
    </references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>The authors would like to acknowledge the following individuals for their
contributions to the development of this document: Tom Harrison, Patrick
Mevzek, and Marcos Sanz.  In addition, the authors would like to recognize the
Regional Internet Registry (RIR) operators (AFRINIC, APNIC, ARIN, LACNIC, and RIPE) that have been implementing
and using the practice of tagging handle identifiers for several years.  Their
experience provided significant inspiration for the development of this document.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
