<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" number="8570"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="7810" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS TE Metric Extensions">IS-IS Traffic Engineering (TE)
    Metric Extensions</title>

    <author fullname="Les Ginsberg" initials="L." role="editor"
            surname="Ginsberg">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>ginsberg@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." role="editor"
            surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>stefano@previdi.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Spencer Giacalone" initials="S" surname="Giacalone">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>spencer.giacalone@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Ward" initials="D" surname="Ward">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>wardd@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Drake" initials="J" surname="Drake">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jdrake@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q" surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>
          <city>Nanjing</city>
          <region>Jiangsu</region>
          <code>210012</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bill.wu@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2019"/>

    <keyword>IGP</keyword>
    <keyword>IS-IS</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In certain networks, such as, but not limited to, financial
      information networks (e.g., stock market data providers),
      network-performance criteria (e.g., latency) are becoming as critical to
      data-path selection as other metrics.</t>

      <t>This document describes extensions to IS-IS Traffic Engineering
      Extensions (RFC 5305). These extensions provide a way to distribute
 and collect network-performance information in a scalable fashion.
 The information
      distributed using IS-IS TE Metric Extensions can then be used to make
      path-selection decisions based on network performance.</t>

      <t>Note that this document only covers the mechanisms with which
      network-performance information is distributed. The mechanisms for
      measuring network performance or acting on that information, once
      distributed, are outside the scope of this document.</t>

      <t>This document obsoletes RFC 7810.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In certain networks, such as, but not limited to, financial
      information networks (e.g., stock market data providers),
      network-performance information (e.g., latency) is becoming as critical
      to data-path selection as other metrics.</t>

      <t>In these networks, extremely large amounts of money rest on the
      ability to access market data in "real time" and to predictably make
      trades faster than the competition. Because of this, using metrics such
      as hop count or cost as routing metrics is becoming only tangentially
      important. Rather, it would be beneficial to be able to make
      path-selection decisions based on performance data (such as latency) in
      a cost-effective and scalable way.</t>

      <t>This document describes extensions (hereafter called "IS-IS TE Metric
      Extensions") to the Extended IS Reachability TLV defined in
      <xref target="RFC5305"/>; these extensions can be used to distribute
      network-performance information (such as link delay, delay variation,
      packet loss, residual bandwidth, and available bandwidth).</t>

      <t>The data distributed by the IS-IS TE Metric Extensions described in
      this document is meant to be used as part of the operation of the
      routing protocol (e.g., by replacing cost with latency or considering
      bandwidth as well as cost), to enhance Constrained Shortest Path First
      (CSPF), or for other uses such as supplementing the data used by an
      Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) server <xref
      target="RFC7285"/>. With respect to CSPF, the data distributed by IS-IS
      TE Metric Extensions can be used to set up, fail over, and fail back
      data paths using protocols such as RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209"/>.</t>

      <t>Note that the mechanisms described in this document only disseminate
      performance information. The methods for initially gathering that
      performance information (such as the methods described in <xref
      target="RFC6375"/>) or how to act on the information once it is
      distributed are outside the scope of this document. Example mechanisms
      to measure latency, delay variation, and loss in an MPLS network are
      given in <xref target="RFC6374"/>. While this document does not specify
      how the performance information should be obtained, the measurement of
      delay SHOULD NOT vary significantly based upon the offered traffic
      load. Thus, queuing delays SHOULD NOT be included in the delay
      measurement. For links such as forwarding adjacencies
      <xref target="RFC4206"/>, care must be taken that measurement of
      the associated delay avoids significant queuing delays; that could be
      accomplished in a variety of ways, including either  (1)&nbsp;measuring
      with a traffic class that experiences minimal queuing or
      (2)&nbsp;summing the measured link delays of the components of the
      link's path.</t>

      <t>This document obsoletes <xref target="RFC7810"/>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
       "SHALL&nbsp;NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD&nbsp;NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
       "NOT&nbsp;RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
       are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
       <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when,
       and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="TE Metric Extensions to IS-IS">

      <t>This document registers new IS-IS TE sub-TLVs 
      in the "Sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223" registry. These new
      sub-TLVs provide ways 
      to distribute network-performance information.

 The extensions in this
      document build on the extensions provided in IS-IS TE <xref target="RFC5305"/>
      and GMPLS <xref target="RFC4203"/>.</t>

      <t>The Extended IS Reachability TLV (type 22) (defined in <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>), Inter-AS Reachability TLV
      (also called "inter-AS reachability information TLV") (type&nbsp;141)
      (defined in <xref target="RFC5316"/>), and MT-ISN TLV (type&nbsp;222)
      (defined in <xref target="RFC5120"/>) have nested sub-TLVs that permit
      the TLVs to be readily extended. This document registers several
      sub&nbhy;TLVs:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   Type    Description
   ----------------------------------------------------
    33     Unidirectional Link Delay

    34     Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay

    35     Unidirectional Delay Variation

    36     Unidirectional Link Loss

    37     Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth

    38     Unidirectional Available Bandwidth

    39     Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth
]]></artwork>
        </figure>As can be seen in the list above, the sub-TLVs described in
      this document carry different types of network-performance information.
      The new sub-TLVs include a bit called the Anomalous (or "A") bit.  When
      the A bit is clear (or when the sub-TLV does not include an
      A&nbsp;bit), the sub-TLV describes steady-state link performance.
 This information
      could conceivably be used to construct a steady-state performance
      topology for initial tunnel-path computation or to verify alternative
      failover paths.</t>

      <t>When network performance violates configurable link-local thresholds,
      a sub-TLV with the A bit set is advertised. That sub-TLV could be used
      by the receiving node to determine whether to (1)&nbsp;fail traffic to
      a backup path or (2)&nbsp;calculate an entirely new path. From an MPLS
      perspective, the intent of the A bit is to permit label switched path
      ingress nodes to determine whether the link referenced in the sub-TLV
      affects any of the label switched paths for which it is ingress. If they
      are affected, then they can determine whether those label switched paths
      still meet end-to-end performance objectives. If not, then the node
      could conceivably move affected traffic to a pre&nbhy;established
      protection label switched path or establish a new label switched path
      and place the traffic in it.</t>

      <t>If link performance then improves beyond a configurable minimum value
      (reuse threshold), that sub-TLV can be re-advertised with the A bit
      cleared. In this case, a receiving node can conceivably do whatever
      re-optimization (or failback) it wishes to do (including nothing).</t>

      <t>Note that when a sub-TLV does not include the A bit, that sub-TLV
      cannot be used for failover purposes. The A bit was intentionally
      omitted from some sub-TLVs to help mitigate oscillations. See 
      <xref target="announ-thresh-filters"/> for more information.</t>

      <t>Consistent with the existing IS-IS TE specification <xref
      target="RFC5305"/>, the bandwidth advertisements defined in this
      document MUST be encoded as IEEE floating-point values <xref
      target="IEEE754"/>. The delay and delay-variation advertisements defined
      in this document MUST be encoded as integer values. Delay values MUST be
      quantified in units of microseconds, packet loss MUST be quantified as a
      percentage of packets sent, and bandwidth MUST be sent as bytes per
      second. All values (except residual bandwidth) MUST be calculated as
      rolling averages, where the averaging period MUST be a configurable
      period of time. See <xref target="announ-thresh-filters"/> for more
      information.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Interface and Neighbor Addresses">
      <t>The use of IS-IS TE Metric Extensions sub-TLVs is not confined to the
      TE context. In other words, IS-IS TE Metric Extensions sub-TLVs defined
      in this document can also be used for computing paths in the absence of
      a TE subsystem.</t>

      <t>However, as for the TE case, Interface Address and Neighbor Address
      sub-TLVs (IPv4 or IPv6) MUST be present. The encoding is defined in
      <xref target="RFC5305"/> for IPv4 and in <xref target="RFC6119"/> for IPv6.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Sub-TLV Details">
      <t/>

      <section title="Unidirectional Link Delay Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the average link delay between two directly
        connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay advertised by this sub-TLV MUST
        be the delay from the local neighbor to the remote neighbor (i.e., the
        forward-path latency). The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 1">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |A|  RESERVED   |                   Delay                       |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">33</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="A bit:">This field represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The
        A&nbsp;bit is set when the measured value of this parameter exceeds its
        configured maximum threshold. The A bit is cleared when the measured
        value falls below its configured reuse threshold. If the A bit is
        cleared, the sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t hangText="RESERVED:">This field is reserved for future use. It MUST
        be set to&nbsp;0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t hangText="Delay:">This 24-bit field carries the average link delay
        over a configurable interval in microseconds, encoded as an integer
        value. When set to the maximum value 16,777,215
        (16.777215&nbsp;seconds), then the delay is at least that value and
        may be larger.</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the minimum and maximum delay values
        between two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the delay from the local neighbor to the
        remote neighbor (i.e., the forward-path latency). The format of this
        sub&nbhy;TLV is shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 2">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |A| RESERVED    |                   Min Delay                   |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   RESERVED    |                   Max Delay                   |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">34</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">8</t>

        <t hangText="A bit:">This field represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The
        A bit is set when one or more measured values exceed a configured
        maximum threshold. The A bit is cleared when the measured value falls
        below its configured reuse threshold. If the A bit is cleared, the
        sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t hangText="RESERVED:">This field is reserved for future use. It MUST
        be set to&nbsp;0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t hangText="Min Delay:">This 24-bit field carries the minimum
        measured link delay value (in microseconds) over a configurable
        interval, encoded as an integer value.</t>

        <t hangText="Max Delay:">This 24-bit field carries the maximum
        measured link delay value (in microseconds) over a configurable
        interval, encoded as an integer value.</t>
      </list></t>

        <t>Implementations MAY also permit the configuration of an offset
        value (in microseconds) to be added to the measured delay value, to
        facilitate the communication of operator-specific delay
        constraints.</t>

        <t>It is possible for Min Delay and Max Delay to be the same value.</t>

        <t>When the delay value (Min Delay or Max Delay) is set to the maximum
        value 16,777,215 (16.777215&nbsp;seconds), then the delay is at least
        that value and may be larger.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Delay Variation Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the average link delay variation between
        two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The delay variation advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the delay from the local neighbor to the
        remote neighbor (i.e., the forward-path latency). The format of this
        sub&nbhy;TLV is shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 3">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  RESERVED     |               Delay Variation                 |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">35</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="RESERVED:">This field is reserved for future use. It MUST
        be set to&nbsp;0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t hangText="Delay Variation:">This 24-bit field carries the average
        link delay variation over a configurable interval in microseconds,
        encoded as an integer value. When set to 0, it has not been
        measured. When set to the maximum value 16,777,215
        (16.777215&nbsp;seconds), then the delay is at least that value and
        may be larger.</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Link Loss Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the loss (as a packet percentage) between
        two directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The link loss advertised by
        this sub-TLV MUST be the packet loss from the local neighbor to the
        remote neighbor (i.e., the forward-path loss). The format of this
        sub-TLV is shown in the following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 4">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |A|  RESERVED   |                    Link Loss                  |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">36</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="A bit:">This field represents the Anomalous (A) bit. The
        A&nbsp;bit is set when the measured value of this parameter exceeds its
        configured maximum threshold. The A bit is cleared when the measured
        value falls below its configured reuse threshold. If the A bit is
        cleared, the sub-TLV represents steady-state link performance.</t>

        <t hangText="RESERVED:">This field is reserved for future use. It MUST
        be set to&nbsp;0 when sent and MUST be ignored when received.</t>

        <t hangText="Link Loss:">This 24-bit field carries link packet loss as
        a percentage of the total traffic sent over a configurable
        interval. The basic unit is 0.000003%, where (2^24 - 2) is
        50.331642%. &nbsp;This value is the highest packet-loss percentage
        that can be expressed (the assumptions being that
        (1)&nbsp;precision is more important on high&nbhy;speed links than
        the ability to advertise loss rates greater than this and
        (2)&nbsp;high&nbhy;speed links with over 50% loss are
        unusable). Therefore, measured values that are larger than the field
        maximum SHOULD be encoded as the maximum value.</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth Sub-TLV" anchor="unidir-res-bw">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the residual bandwidth between two directly
        connected IS-IS neighbors. The residual bandwidth advertised by this
        sub-TLV MUST be the residual bandwidth from the system originating the
        Link State Advertisement (LSA) to its neighbor.</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 5">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                          Residual Bandwidth                   |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">37</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="Residual Bandwidth:">This field carries the residual
        bandwidth on a link, forwarding adjacency <xref target="RFC4206"/>, or
        bundled link in IEEE floating-point format with units of bytes per
        second. For a link or forwarding adjacency, residual bandwidth is
        defined to be the maximum bandwidth <xref target="RFC5305"/> minus the
        bandwidth currently allocated to RSVP&nbhy;TE label switched
        paths. For a bundled link, residual bandwidth is defined to be the sum
        of the component link residual bandwidths.</t>

        <t>The calculation of residual bandwidth is different than that of
        unreserved bandwidth <xref target="RFC5305"/>. This calculation
        subtracts tunnel reservations from maximum bandwidth (i.e., the link
        capacity) <xref target="RFC5305"/> and provides an aggregated
        remainder across priorities. Unreserved bandwidth, on the other hand,
        is subtracted from the maximum reservable bandwidth (the bandwidth
        that can theoretically be reserved) and provides per-priority
        remainders. Residual bandwidth and unreserved bandwidth <xref
        target="RFC5305"/> can be used concurrently, and each has a separate
        use case (e.g., the former can be used for applications like Weighted
        ECMP, while the latter can be used for call admission control).</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Available Bandwidth Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the available bandwidth between two
        directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The available bandwidth advertised
        by this sub-TLV MUST be the available bandwidth from the system
        originating this sub-TLV. The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 6">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                      Available Bandwidth                      |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">38</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="Available Bandwidth:">This field carries the available
        bandwidth on a link, forwarding adjacency, or bundled link in IEEE
        floating-point format with units of bytes per second. For a link or
        forwarding adjacency, available bandwidth is defined to be residual
        bandwidth (see <xref target="unidir-res-bw"/>) minus the measured
        bandwidth used for the actual forwarding of non-RSVP-TE label switched
        path packets. For a bundled link, available bandwidth is defined to be
        the sum of the component link available bandwidths.</t>
   </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth Sub-TLV">
        <t>This sub-TLV advertises the bandwidth utilization between two
        directly connected IS-IS neighbors. The bandwidth utilization
        advertised by this sub-TLV MUST be the bandwidth from the system
        originating this sub-TLV. The format of this sub-TLV is shown in the
        following diagram:</t>

        <t><figure title="Figure 7">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   Type        |     Length    |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                     Utilized Bandwidth                        |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure>where:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Type:">39</t>

        <t hangText="Length:">4</t>

        <t hangText="Utilized Bandwidth:">This field carries the bandwidth
        utilization on a link, forwarding adjacency, or bundled link in IEEE
        floating&nbhy;point format with units of bytes per second. For a link
        or forwarding adjacency, bandwidth utilization represents the actual
        utilization of the link (i.e., as measured by the advertising
        node). For a bundled link, bandwidth utilization is defined to be the
        sum of the component link bandwidth utilizations.</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Announcement Thresholds and Filters" anchor="announ-thresh-filters">
      <t>The values advertised in all sub-TLVs (except minimum/maximum delay
      and residual bandwidth) MUST represent an average over a period of
      time or be obtained by a filter that is reasonably representative of an
      average. For example, a rolling average is one such filter.</t>

      <t>Minimum and maximum delay MUST each be derived in one of the following
      ways: by taking the lowest and/or highest measured value over a
      measurement interval or by making use of a filter or other technique to
      obtain a reasonable representation of a minimum value and a maximum value
      representative of the interval, with compensation for outliers.</t>

      <t>The measurement interval, any filter coefficients, and any
      advertisement intervals MUST be configurable per sub-TLV.</t>

      <t>In addition to the measurement intervals governing re-advertisement,
      implementations SHOULD provide configurable accelerated advertisement
      thresholds per sub-TLV, such that:<list style="numbers">
          <t>If the measured parameter falls outside a configured upper bound
          for all but the minimum delay metric (or lower bound for the minimum
          delay metric only) and the advertised sub-TLV is not already outside
          that bound, or</t>

          <t>If the difference between the last advertised value and current
          measured value exceeds a configured threshold, then</t>

          <t>The advertisement is made immediately.</t>

          <t>For sub-TLVs that include an A bit, an additional threshold
          SHOULD be included corresponding to the threshold for which the
          performance is considered anomalous (and sub-TLVs with the A bit are
          sent). The A bit is cleared when the sub-TLV's performance has been
          below (or re-crosses) this threshold for one or more advertisement
          intervals to permit failback.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>To prevent oscillations, only the high threshold or the low threshold
      (but not both) may be used to trigger any given sub-TLV that supports
      both.</t>

      <t>Additionally, once outside the bounds of the threshold, any
      re&nbhy;advertisement of a measurement within the bounds would remain
      governed solely by the measurement interval for that sub-TLV.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Announcement Suppression" anchor="announ-suppress">
      <t>When link-performance values change by small amounts that fall under
      thresholds that would cause the announcement of a sub-TLV,
      implementations SHOULD suppress sub-TLV re-advertisement and/or lengthen
      the period within which the sub-TLVs are refreshed.</t>

      <t>Only the accelerated advertisement threshold mechanism described in
      <xref target="announ-thresh-filters"/> may shorten the re-advertisement interval. All suppression and
      re-advertisement interval backoff timer features SHOULD be
      configurable.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Stability and Announcement Periodicity" anchor="net-stabil-announc-period">
      <t>Sections <xref target="announ-thresh-filters" format="counter"/> and
      <xref target="announ-suppress" format="counter"/> provide configurable
      mechanisms to bound the number of re-advertisements. Instability might
      occur in very large networks if measurement intervals are set low enough
      to overwhelm the processing of flooded information at some of the
      routers in the topology. Therefore, care should be taken in setting
      these values.</t>

      <t>Additionally, the default measurement interval for all sub-TLVs
      SHOULD be 30&nbsp;seconds.</t>

      <t>Announcements MUST also be able to be throttled using configurable
      inter-update throttle timers. The minimum announcement periodicity is
      one announcement per second. The default value SHOULD be set to
      120&nbsp;seconds.</t>

      <t>Implementations SHOULD NOT permit the inter-update timer to be lower
      than the measurement interval.</t>

      <t>Furthermore, it is RECOMMENDED that any underlying
      performance-measurement mechanisms not include any significant buffer
      delay, any significant buffer-induced delay variation, or any
      significant loss due to buffer overflow or due to active queue
      management.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Enabling and Disabling Sub-TLVs">
      <t>Implementations MUST make it possible to individually enable or
      disable each sub-TLV based on configuration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Static Metric Override">
      <t>Implementations SHOULD permit static configuration and/or manual
      override of dynamic measurements for each sub-TLV in order to simplify
      migration and to mitigate scenarios where dynamic measurements are not
      possible.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Compatibility">
      <t>As per <xref target="RFC5305"/>, unrecognized sub-TLVs should be silently
      ignored.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The sub-TLVs introduced in this document allow an operator to
      advertise state information of links (bandwidth, delay) that could be
      sensitive and that an operator may not want to disclose.</t>

      <t><xref target="net-stabil-announc-period"/> describes a mechanism to
      ensure network stability when the new sub-TLVs defined in this document
      are advertised. Implementations SHOULD follow the described guidelines
      to mitigate the risk of instability.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC5304"/> describes an authentication method for IS-IS Link State
      PDUs that allows cryptographic authentication of IS-IS Link State
      PDUs.</t>

      <t>It is anticipated that in most deployments, the IS-IS protocol is
      used within an infrastructure entirely under the control of the same
      operator. However, it is worth considering that the effect of sending
      IS-IS Traffic Engineering sub-TLVs over insecure links could include
      a man-in-the-middle attacker delaying real-time data to a given site or
      destination; this could negatively affect the value of the data for
      that site or destination. The use of Link State PDU cryptographic
      authentication allows mitigation of the risk of
      man&nbhy;in&nbhy;the&nbhy;middle attacks.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA maintains the registry for the sub-TLVs. IANA has registered the
      following sub-TLVs in the "Sub-TLVs for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223"
      registry:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   Type    Description
   ----------------------------------------------------
    33     Unidirectional Link Delay

    34     Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay

    35     Unidirectional Delay Variation

    36     Unidirectional Link Loss

    37     Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth

    38     Unidirectional Available Bandwidth

    39     Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth
 ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="IEEE754">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic</title>
          <author>
            <organization abbrev="IEEE">Institute of Electrical and
            Electronics Engineers</organization>
          </author>
<!--          <date month="Aug" year="2008"/> -->
          <date/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Std" value="754-2008"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4206"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5120"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5304"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5305"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5316"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7471"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7810"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4203"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6374"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6375"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7285"?>

<!-- draft-ietf-idr-te-pm-bgp (RFC 8571) -->
<reference anchor='RFC8571' target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8571">
<front>
<title>BGP - Link State (BGP-LS) Advertisement of IGP Traffic Engineering Performance Metric Extensions</title>
<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='Q' surname='Wu' fullname='Qin Wu'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2019' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8571"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8571"/>
</reference>

    </references>

    <section title="Changes from RFC 7810">
      <t>Errata ID 5293
      (https://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/eid5293) correctly
      identified that in <xref target="RFC7810"/> the length associated with the following
      sub-TLVs did not match the figures associated with each:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   37    Unidirectional Residual Bandwidth

   38    Unidirectional Available Bandwidth

   39    Unidirectional Utilized Bandwidth
 ]]></artwork>
        </figure>The length specified was 4, which did not include the RESERVED
      field shown in the figures. Subsequent investigation revealed that some
      implementations had used the specified length (4) and omitted the
      RESERVED field while other implementations included the specified
      RESERVED field and used a length of 5.</t>

      <t>Because these different implementation choices are not interoperable,
      it was decided that a bis version should be generated to resolve this
      ambiguity.</t>

      <t>The choice made here is to omit the unused RESERVED field from these
      sub-TLVs and use the length of 4. This matches the corresponding
      advertisements specified in the equivalent OSPF TE specification <xref
      target="RFC7471"/> and the corresponding BGP - Link State (BGP-LS)
      specification <xref target="RFC8571"/>.</t>

      <t>Some minor editorial corrections have also been made.</t>

      <t>Errata ID 5486 (https://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/eid5486)
      identified that in Section&nbsp;4.6 of <xref target="RFC7810"/> the definition
      of available bandwidth on bundled links used a circular definition, i.e.,
      it used "sum of the component link available bandwidths" when it should
      have used "sum of the component link residual bandwidths". This has been
      corrected and clarified.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>In <xref target="RFC7810"/>, the authors recognized Ayman Soliman,
      Nabil Bitar, David McDysan, Edward Crabbe, Don Fedyk, Hannes Gredler,
      Uma Chunduri, Alvaro Retana, Brian Weis, and Barry Leiba for their
      contributions and reviews of this document.</t>

      <t>The authors also recognized Curtis Villamizar for significant
      comments and direct content collaboration.</t>

      <t>For this document, the authors thank Jeff Haas for identifying and
      reporting the incorrect encoding of the bandwidth-related sub-TLVs.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The following people contributed substantially to the content of this
      document and should be considered coauthors:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   Alia Atlas
   Juniper Networks
   United States of America
   Email: akatlas@juniper.net

   Clarence Filsfils
   Cisco Systems, Inc.
   Belgium
   Email: cfilsfil@cisco.com
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
