<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8350" 
     category="exp" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Alternate Tunnel">Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation for Data
    Frames in Control&nbsp;and&nbsp;Provisioning&nbsp;of&nbsp;Wireless&nbsp;Access&nbsp;Points&nbsp;(CAPWAP)</title>

    <author fullname="Rong Zhang" initials="R." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No.109 Zhongshandadao avenue</street>

          <city>Guangzhou</city>

          <code>510630</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhangr@gsta.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rajesh S. Pazhyannur" initials="R." surname="Pazhyannur">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose, CA 95134</city>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rpazhyan@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sri Gundavelli" initials="S." surname="Gundavelli">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose, CA 95134</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zhen Cao" initials="Z." surname="Cao">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Xinxi Rd. 3</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100085</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhencao.ietf@gmail.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hui Deng" initials="H." surname="Deng">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Xinxi Rd. 3</street>

          <city>Beijing 100085</city>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>denghui02@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zongpeng Du" initials="Z." surname="Du">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No.156 Beiqing Rd. Z-park, HaiDian District</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>duzongpeng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2018"/>

    <area>OPS</area>

    <workgroup>OPSAWG</workgroup>

    <abstract>


   <t>Control and Provisioning of Wireless Access Points (CAPWAP) is a
   protocol for encapsulating a station's data frames between 
   the Wireless Transmission Point (WTP) and Access Controller (AC).
      Specifically, the station's IEEE 802.11 data frames can be either 
      locally bridged or tunneled to the AC. When tunneled, a CAPWAP Data
      Channel is used for tunneling. In many deployments, encapsulating data
      frames to an entity other than the AC (for example, to an Access Router
      (AR)) is desirable. Furthermore, it may also be desirable to use
      different tunnel encapsulation modes between the WTP and the Access
      Router. This document defines an extension to the CAPWAP protocol that
      supports this capability and refers to it as alternate tunnel
      encapsulation. The alternate tunnel encapsulation allows 1) the WTP to
      tunnel non-management data frames to an endpoint different from the AC
      and 2) the WTP to tunnel using one of many known encapsulation types,
      such as IP-IP, IP-GRE, or CAPWAP. The WTP may advertise support for
      alternate tunnel encapsulation during the discovery and join process,
      and the AC may select one of the supported alternate tunnel encapsulation types
      while configuring the WTP.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction ">
      <t>Service Providers are deploying very large Wi-Fi networks containing
      hundreds of thousands of Access Points (APs), which are referred to as
      Wireless Transmission Points (WTPs) in Control and Provisioning of
      Wireless Access Points (CAPWAP) terminology <xref target="RFC5415"/>.
      These networks are designed to carry traffic generated from mobile
      users. The volume in mobile user traffic is already very large and
      expected to continue growing rapidly. As a result, operators are looking
      for scalable solutions that can meet the increasing demand. The
      scalability requirement can be met by splitting the control/management
      plane from the data plane. This enables the data plane to scale
      independent of the control/management plane. This specification provides
      a way to enable such separation.</t>

      <t>CAPWAP <xref target="RFC5415"/> <xref target="RFC5416"/> defines a
      tunnel mode that describes how the WTP handles the data plane (user
      traffic). The following types are defined:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Local Bridging: All data frames are locally bridged.</t>

          <t>IEEE 802.3 Tunnel: All data frames are tunneled to the Access
          Controller (AC) in IEEE 802.3 format.</t>

          <t>IEEE 802.11 Tunnel: All data frames are tunneled to the AC in
	  IEEE 802.11
          format.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><xref target="Fig.scenario"/> describes a system with Local Bridging.
      The AC is in a centralized location. 
   The data plane is locally bridged by the WTPs; this
   leads to a system with a centralized control plane and a distributed
   data plane.  This system has two benefits: 1) it reduces the
      scale requirement on the data traffic handling capability of the AC, and 2) it
      leads to more efficient/optimal routing of data traffic while
      maintaining centralized control/management.</t>

      <figure anchor="Fig.scenario"
              title="Centralized Control with Distributed Data ">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[        Locally Bridged
+-----+ Data Frames   +----------------+
| WTP |===============|  Access Router |
+-----+               +----------------+
       \\
        \\  CAPWAP Control Channel   +----------+
          ++=========================|   AC     |
         // CAPWAP Data Channel:     |          |
        //  IEEE 802.11 Mgmt Traffic +----------+  
       //
+-----+               +----------------+
| WTP |============== |  Access Router |
+-----+               +----------------+
       Locally Bridged
       Data Frames
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The AC handles control of WTPs. In addition, the AC also handles the
      IEEE 802.11 management traffic to/from the stations. There is a CAPWAP
      Control and Data Channel between the WTP and the AC. Note that even
      though there is no user traffic transported between the WTP and AC,
      there is still a CAPWAP Data Channel. The CAPWAP Data Channel carries
      the IEEE 802.11 management traffic (like IEEE 802.11 Action Frames).</t>

      <t><xref target="Centralized-data.scenario"/> shows a system where the
      tunnel mode is configured to tunnel data frames between the WTP and the
      AC using either the IEEE 802.3 Tunnel or 802.11 Tunnel configurations. Operators
      deploy this configuration when they need to tunnel the user traffic. The
      tunneling requirement may be driven by the need to apply policy at the
      AC. This requirement could be met in the locally bridged system (<xref target="Fig.scenario"/>) if the Access Router (AR) implemented the
      required policy. However, in many deployments, the operator managing the
      WTP is different than the operator managing the Access Router. When the
      operators are different, the policy has to be enforced in a tunnel
      termination point in the WTP operator's network. <figure
          anchor="Centralized-data.scenario"
          title="Centralized Control and Centralized Data ">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+-----+
| WTP |
+-----+
    \\
      \\  CAPWAP Control Channel   +----------+
        ++=========================|   AC     |
       // CAPWAP Data Channel:     |          |
      //  IEEE 802.11 Mgmt Traffic |          |
     //   Data Frames              +----------+
    //
+-----+
| WTP |
+-----+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>The key difference with the locally bridged system is that
      the data frames are tunneled to the AC instead of being locally bridged.
      There are two shortcomings with the system in <xref
      target="Centralized-data.scenario"/>: 1) it does not allow the WTP to
      tunnel data frames to an endpoint different from the AC, and 2) it does
      not allow the WTP to tunnel data frames using any encapsulation other
      than CAPWAP (as specified in Section 4.4.2 of <xref
      target="RFC5415"/>).</t>

      <t><xref target="Fig.scenario2"/> shows a system where the WTP tunnels
      data frames to an alternate entity different from the AC. The WTP also
      uses an alternate tunnel encapsulation such as Layer 2 Tunneling
      Protocol (L2TP), L2TPv3, IP-in-IP,
      IP/GRE, etc. This enables 1) independent scaling of data plane and 2)
      leveraging of commonly used tunnel encapsulations such as L2TP, GRE,
      etc.<figure anchor="Fig.scenario2"
          title="Centralized Control with an Alternate Tunnel for Data">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ Alternate Tunnel to AR (L2TPv3, IP-IP, CAPWAP, etc.)
              _________
+-----+      (         )              +-----------------+
| WTP |======+Internet +==============|Access Router(AR)|
+-----+      (_________)              +-----------------+
      \\      ________  CAPWAP Control
       \\    (        ) Channel                +--------+
          ++=+Internet+========================|   AC   |
         //  (________)CAPWAP Data Channel:    +--------+    
        //             IEEE 802.11 Mgmt Traffic
       //   _________
+-----+    (         )                +----------------+
| WTP |====+Internet +================|  Access Router |
+-----+    (_________)                +----------------+ 
 Alternate Tunnel to AR (L2TPv3, IP-in-IP, CAPWAP, etc.)
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The WTP may support widely used encapsulation types such as L2TP,
      L2TPv3, IP-in-IP, IP/GRE, etc. The WTP advertises the different
      alternate tunnel encapsulation types it can support. The AC configures
      one of the advertised types. As is shown in <xref target="Fig.scenario2"/>, there is a CAPWAP
      Control and Data Channel between the WTP and AC. The CAPWAP Data Channel
      carries the stations' management traffic, as in the case of the locally
      bridged system. The main reason to maintain a CAPWAP Data Channel is to
      maintain similarity with the locally bridged system. The WTP maintains
      three tunnels: CAPWAP Control, CAPWAP Data, and another alternate tunnel
      for the data frames. The data frames are transported by an alternate
      tunnel between the WTP and a tunnel termination point, such as an Access
      Router. This specification describes how the alternate tunnel can be
      established. The specification defines message elements for the WTP to
      advertise support for alternate tunnel encapsulation, for the AC to
      configure alternate tunnel encapsulation, and for the WTP to report
      failure of the alternate tunnel.</t>

      <t>The alternate tunnel encapsulation also supports the third-party WLAN
      service provider scenario (i.e., Virtual Network Operator (VNO)). Under
      this scenario, the WLAN provider owns the WTP and AC resources while
      the VNOs can rent the WTP resources from the WLAN provider for network
      access. The AC belonging to the WLAN service provider manages the WTPs
      in the centralized mode.</t>

      <t>As shown in <xref target="Fig.scenario3"/>, VNO 1 and VNO 2 don't possess
      the network access resources; however, they provide services by acquiring
      resources from the WLAN provider. Since a WTP is capable of supporting
      up to 16 Service Set Identifiers (SSIDs), the WLAN provider may provide
      network access service for different providers with different SSIDs. For
      example, SSID1 is advertised by the WTP for VNO 1 while SSID2 is
      advertised by the WTP for VNO 2. Therefore, the data traffic from the user
      can be directly steered to the corresponding Access Router of the VNO
      who owns that user. As is shown in <xref target="Fig.scenario3"/>, AC can
      notify multiple AR addresses for load balancing or redundancy.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Fig.scenario3"
          title="Third-Party WLAN Service Provider">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                            +----+
                            | AC |
                            +--+-+
                 CAPWAP-CTL    |
             +-----------------+
             |   CAPWAP-DATA: IEEE 802.11 Mgmt Traffic
             |
WLAN Provider|                            VNO 1
       +-----+   CAPWAP-DATA (SSID1)    +---------------+
SSID1  | WTP +--------------------------|Access Router 1|
SSID2  +--+-++                          +---------------+
          | |
          | |                             VNO 1
          | |    GRE-DATA (SSID1)       +---------------+
          | +---------------------------|Access Router 2|
          |                             +---------------+
          |
          |                               VNO 2
          |      CAPWAP-DATA (SSID2)    +---------------+
          +-----------------------------|Access Router 3|
                                        +---------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>Station (STA): A device that contains an IEEE 802.11-conformant
        Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical layer (PHY) interface to the
        Wireless Medium (WM).</t>

        <t>Access Controller (AC): The network entity that provides WTP access
        to the network infrastructure in the data plane, control plane,
        management plane, or a combination therein.</t>

        <t>Access Router (AR): A specialized router usually residing at the
        edge or boundary of a network. This router ensures the connectivity of
        its network with external networks, a wide area network, or the
        Internet.</t>

        <t>Wireless Termination Point (WTP): The physical or network entity
        that contains a Radio Frequency (RF) antenna and wireless Physical layer (PHY) to
        transmit and receive station traffic for wireless access networks.</t>

        <t>CAPWAP Control Channel: A bidirectional flow defined by the AC IP
        Address, WTP IP Address, AC control port, WTP control port, and the
        transport-layer protocol (UDP or UDP-Lite) over which CAPWAP Control
        packets are sent and received.</t>

        <t>CAPWAP Data Channel: A bidirectional flow defined by the AC IP
        Address, WTP IP Address, AC data port, WTP data port, and the
        transport-layer protocol (UDP or UDP-Lite) over which CAPWAP Data
        packets are sent and received. In certain WTP modes, the CAPWAP Data
        Channel only transports IEEE 802.11 management frames and not the data
        plane (user traffic).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="History of the Document">
        <t>This document was started to accommodate Service Providers' need of
        a more flexible deployment mode with alternative tunnels <xref
        target="RFC7494"/>. Experiments and tests have been done for this
        alternate tunnel network infrastructure. However important, the deployment
        of relevant technology is yet to be completed. This Experimental document
        is intended to serve as an archival record for any future work on
        the operational and deployment requirements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation Overview">
      <figure anchor="fig.tunnel-neg" title="Setup of an Alternate Tunnel">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[  +-+-+-+-+-+-+                             +-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    WTP    |                             |    AC     |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+                             +-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |Join Request [ Supported Alternate       |
        |       Tunnel Encapsulations ]           |
        |---------------------------------------->|
        |                                         |
        |Join Response                            |
        |<----------------------------------------|
        |                                         |
        |IEEE 802.11 WLAN Configuration Request [ |
        | IEEE 802.11 Add WLAN,                   |
        | Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation (        |
        |   Tunnel Type, Tunnel Info Element)     |
        | ]                                       |
        |<----------------------------------------|
        |                                         |
        |                                         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+                                  |
   | Setup     |                                  |
   | Alternate |                                  |
   | Tunnel    |                                  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+                                  |
        |IEEE 802.11 WLAN Configuration Response  |
        |[ Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation (       |
        |   Tunnel Type, Tunnel Info Element) ]   |
        |---------------------------------------->|
        |                                         |
        |                                         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+                                  |
   | Tunnel    |                                  |
   | Failure   |                                  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+                                  |
        |WTP Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication  |
        |(Report Failure (AR Address(es)))        |
        |---------------------------------------->|
        |                                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                   |
| Tunnel      |                                   |
| Established |                                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                   |
        |WTP Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication  |
        |(Report Clearing Failure)                |
        |---------------------------------------->|
        |                                         |
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The above example describes how the alternate tunnel encapsulation
      may be established. When the WTP joins the AC, it should indicate its
      alternate tunnel encapsulation capability. The AC determines whether an
      alternate tunnel configuration is required. If an appropriate alternate
      tunnel type is selected, then the AC provides the Alternate Tunnel
      Encapsulations Type message element containing the tunnel type and a
      tunnel-specific information element. The tunnel-specific information
      element, for example, may contain information like the IP address of the
      tunnel termination point. The WTP sets up the alternate tunnel using the
      Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type message element.</t>

      <t>Since an AC can configure a WTP with more than one AR available for the
      WTP to establish the data tunnel(s) for user traffic, it may be useful
      for the WTP to communicate the selected AR. To enable this, the IEEE
      802.11 WLAN Configuration Response may carry the Alternate Tunnel
      Encapsulations Type message element containing the AR list element
      corresponding to the selected AR as shown in <xref
      target="fig.tunnel-neg"> </xref>.</t>

      <t>On detecting a tunnel failure, the WTP SHALL forward data frames to the
      AC and discard the frames. In addition, the WTP may dissociate existing
      clients and refuse association requests from new clients. Depending on
      the implementation and deployment scenario, the AC may choose to
      reconfigure the WLAN (on the WTP) to a Local Bridging mode or to tunnel
      frames to the AC. When the WTP detects an alternate tunnel failure, the
      WTP informs the AC using a message element, IEEE 802.11 WTP Alternate Tunnel Failure
      Indication (defined in <xref target="tunnel-failure"/>). It MAY be carried in the WTP
      Event Request message, which is defined in <xref target="RFC5415"/>.</t>

      <t>The WTP also needs to notify the AC of which AR(s) are unavailable.
      Particularly, in the VNO scenario, the AC of the WLAN service provider
      needs to maintain the association of the AR addresses of the VNOs and
      SSIDs and provide this information to the WTP for the purpose of load
      balancing or master-slave mode.</t>

      <t>The message element has a Status field that indicates whether the
      message is reporting a failure or clearing the previously
      reported failure.</t>

      <t>For the case where an AC is unreachable but the tunnel endpoint is
      still reachable, the WTP behavior is up to the implementation. For
      example, the WTP could choose to either tear down the alternate tunnel
      or let the existing user's traffic continue to be tunneled.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extensions for CAPWAP Protocol Message Elements">
      <section anchor="tunnel-support"
               title="Supported Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations">
        <t>This message element is sent by a WTP to communicate its capability
        to support alternate tunnel encapsulations. The message element
        contains the following fields:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="support-encap"
            title="Supported Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Tunnel-Type 1            |      Tunnel-Type 2            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            ...                |      Tunnel-Type N            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Type: 54 for Supported Alternate Tunnel
            Encapsulations Type</t>

            <t>Length: The length in bytes; two bytes for each Alternative
            Tunnel-Type that is included</t>

            <t>Tunnel-Type: This is identified by the value defined in <xref
	    target="tunnel-config"/>. There may be one or more Tunnel-Types,
	    as is shown in <xref
            target="support-encap"/>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tunnel-config"
               title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type">
        <t>This message element can be sent by the AC, allows the 
	AC to select the alternate tunnel encapsulation, and may be provided along with the IEEE 802.11 Add WLAN
        message element. When the message element is present, the following
        fields of the IEEE 802.11 Add WLAN element SHALL be set as follows:
        MAC mode is set to 0 (Local MAC), and Tunnel Mode is set to 0 (Local
        Bridging). Besides, the message element can also be sent by the WTP to
        communicate the selected AR(s).</t>

        <t>The message element contains the following fields:</t>

        <figure anchor="format2" title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Tunnel-Type              |  Info Element Length          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Info Element
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Type: 55 for Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type</t>

            <t>Length: &gt; 4</t>

            <t>Tunnel-Type: The Tunnel-Type is specified by a 2-byte value.
            This specification defines the values from 0 to 6 as
            given below. The remaining values are reserved for future
            use.<list style="symbols">
                <t>0: CAPWAP. This refers to a CAPWAP Data Channel described
                in <xref target="RFC5415"/> and <xref target="RFC5416"/>.</t>

                <t>1: L2TP. This refers to tunnel encapsulation described in
                <xref target="RFC2661"/>.</t>

                <t>2: L2TPv3. This refers to tunnel encapsulation described in
                <xref target="RFC3931"/>.</t>

                <t>3: IP-in-IP. This refers to tunnel encapsulation described
                in <xref target="RFC2003"/>.</t>

                <t>4: PMIPv6-UDP. 
		This refers to the UDP encapsulation mode for Proxy Mobile
		IPv6 (PMIPv6)
                described in <xref target="RFC5844"/>. This encapsulation mode
                is the basic encapsulation mode and does not include the TLV
                header specified in Section 7.2 of <xref
                target="RFC5845"/>.</t>

                <t>5: GRE. This refers to GRE tunnel encapsulation as
                described in <xref target="RFC2784"/>.</t>

                <t>6: GTPv1-U. This refers to the GPRS Tunnelling Protocol
		(GTP) User Plane mode as
                described in <xref target="TS29281"/>.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Info Element: This field contains tunnel-specific configuration
            parameters to enable the WTP to set up the alternate tunnel. This
            specification provides details for this element for CAPWAP,
            PMIPv6, and GRE. This specification reserves the tunnel type
            values for the key tunnel types and defines the most common
            message elements. It is anticipated that message elements for the
            other protocols (like L2TPv3) will be defined in other
            specifications in the future.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tunnel-failure"
               title="IEEE 802.11 WTP Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication">
        <t>The WTP MAY include the Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication message
        in a WTP Event Request message to inform the AC about the status of
        the alternate tunnel. For the case where the WTP establishes data tunnels
        with multiple ARs (e.g., under a VNO scenario), the WTP needs to notify
        the AC of which AR(s) are unavailable. The message element contains
        the following fields:</t>

        <figure anchor="format3"
                title="IEEE 802.11 WTP Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      WLAN ID  |     Status    |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.              Access Router Information Element                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Type: 1062 for IEEE 802.11 WTP Alternate Tunnel
            Failure Indication</t>

            <t>Length: &gt; 4</t>

            <t>WLAN ID: An 8-bit value specifying the WLAN Identifier. The
            value MUST be between 1 and 16.</t>

            <t>Status: An 8-bit boolean indicating whether the radio failure
            is being reported or cleared. A value of 0 is used to clear the
            event, while a value of 1 is used to report the event.</t>

            <t>Reserved: MUST be set to a value of 0 and MUST be ignored by
            the receiver.</t>

            <t>Access Router Information Element: The IPv4 or IPv6 address
            of the Access Router that terminates the alternate tunnel. The
            Access Router Information Elements allow the WTP to notify the AC
            of which AR(s) are unavailable.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="alt-tunnel-types" title="Alternate Tunnel Types">
      <t/>

      <section anchor="capwap-tunnel" title="CAPWAP-Based Alternate Tunnel">
        <t>If the CAPWAP encapsulation is selected by the AC and configured by
        the AC to the WTP, the Info Element field defined in <xref
        target="tunnel-config"/> SHOULD contain the following information:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Access Router Information: The IPv4 or IPv6 address of the
            Access Router for the alternate tunnel.</t>

            <t>Tunnel DTLS Policy: The CAPWAP protocol allows optional
            protection of data packets using DTLS. Use of data packet
            protection on a WTP is not mandatory but is determined by the
            associated AC policy. (This is consistent with the WTP behavior
            described in <xref target="RFC5415"/>.)</t>

            <t>IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy: It is used to specify how the
            CAPWAP Data Channel packets are to be tagged for QoS purposes (see
            <xref target="RFC5416"/> for more details).</t>

            <t>CAPWAP Transport Protocol: The CAPWAP protocol supports both
            UDP and UDP-Lite (see <xref target="RFC3828"/>). When run over
            IPv4, UDP is used for the CAPWAP Data Channels. When run over
            IPv6, the CAPWAP Data Channel may use either UDP or UDP-Lite.</t>
          </list>The message element structure for CAPWAP encapsulation is
        shown in <xref target="CAPWAP"> </xref>:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="CAPWAP"
            title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation - CAPWAP">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Tunnel-Type=0             |   Info Element Length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.              Access Router Information Element                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.              Tunnel DTLS Policy Element                       .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.             IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy Element           .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.             CAPWAP Transport Protocol Element                 .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pmipv6-tunnel" title="PMIPv6-Based Alternate Tunnel">
        <t>A user plane based on PMIPv6 (defined in <xref target="RFC5213"/>) 
	can also be used as an alternate tunnel encapsulation
        between the WTP and the AR. In this scenario, a WTP acts as the Mobile
        Access Gateway (MAG) function that manages the mobility-related
        signaling for a station that is attached to the WTP IEEE 802.11 radio
        access. The Local Mobility Anchor (LMA) function is at the AR. If
        PMIPv6 UDP encapsulation is selected by the AC and configured by the
        AC to a WTP, the Info Element field defined in <xref
        target="tunnel-config"/> SHOULD contain the following information:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Access Router (acting as LMA) Information: IPv4 or IPv6 address
            for the alternate tunnel endpoint.</t>
          </list> The message element structure for PMIPv6 encapsulation is
        shown in <xref target="pmipv6"> </xref>:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="pmipv6"
            title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation - PMIPv6">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Tunnel-Type=4             |   Info Element Length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                 Access Router Information Element             .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gre-tunnel" title="GRE-Based Alternate Tunnel">
        <t>A user plane based on Generic Routing Encapsulation (defined in <xref target="RFC2784"/>)
        can also be used as an alternate tunnel
        encapsulation between the WTP and the AR. In this scenario, a WTP and
        the Access Router represent the two endpoints of the GRE tunnel. If
        GRE is selected by the AC and configured by the AC to a
        WTP, the Info Element field defined in <xref target="tunnel-config"/>
        SHOULD contain the following information:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Access Router Information: The IPv4 or IPv6 address for the
            alternate tunnel endpoint.</t>

            <t>GRE Key Information: The Key field is intended to be used for
            identifying an individual traffic flow within a tunnel <xref
            target="RFC2890"/>.</t>
          </list>The message element structure for GRE is shown
        in <xref target="grefigure"/>:</t>

        <t/>

        <figure anchor="grefigure"
                title="Alternate Tunnel Encapsulation - GRE">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Tunnel-Type=5             |   Info Element Length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.              Access Router Information Element                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                    GRE Key Element                            .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="subelements"
             title="Alternate Tunnel Information Elements">
      <t>This section defines the various elements described in Sections <xref
      target="capwap-tunnel" format="counter"/>, <xref target="pmipv6-tunnel" format="counter"/>, and <xref
      target="gre-tunnel" format="counter"/>.</t>

      <t>These information elements can only be included in the Alternate
      Tunnel Encapsulations Type message element and the IEEE 802.11 WTP
      Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication message element as their
      sub-elements.</t>

      <section title="Access Router Information Elements">
        <t>The Access Router Information Elements allow the AC to notify a WTP
        of which AR(s) are available for establishing a data tunnel. The AR
        information may be an IPv4 or IPv6 address. 
For any Tunnel-Type, this information element SHOULD be included in the
Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type message element.
	</t>

        <t>
If the Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type message element is sent by the WTP
to communicate the selected AR(s), this Access Router Information Element
SHOULD be included in it.
	</t>
        <t>The following are the Access Router Information Elements defined in
        this specification. 
   The AC can use one of them to notify the WTP about the
   destination information of the data tunnel. 
The Elements
        containing the AR IPv4 address MUST NOT be used if an IPv6 Data
        Channel with IPv6 transport is used.</t>

        <section title="AR IPv4 List Element">
          <t>This element (see <xref target="capwapv4"/>) is used by
          the AC to configure a WTP with the AR IPv4 address available for the
          WTP to establish the data tunnel for user traffic.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="capwapv4" title="AR IPv4 List Element">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  AR IPv4 Element Type         |          Length               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv4 Address-1                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv4 Address-2                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv4 Address-N                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Type: 0</t>

          <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element,
          excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

          <t>AR IPv4 Address: The IPv4 address of the AR. At least one IPv4
          address SHALL be present. Multiple addresses may be provided for
          load balancing or redundancy.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="AR IPv6 List Element">
          <t>This element (see <xref target="capwapv6"> </xref>) is used by
          the AC to configure a WTP with the AR IPv6 address available for the
          WTP to establish the data tunnel for user traffic.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="capwapv6" title=" AR IPv6 List Element">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   AR IPv6 Element Type        |          Length               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv6 Address-1                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv6 Address-2                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                     AR IPv6 Address-N                         .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Type: 1</t>

          <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element
          excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

          <t>AR IPv6 Address: The IPv6 address of the AR. At least one IPv6
          address SHALL be present. Multiple addresses may be provided for
          load balancing or redundancy.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Tunnel DTLS Policy Element">
        <t>The AC distributes its Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) usage policy for the CAPWAP data tunnel
        between a WTP and the AR. There are multiple supported options, which
	are represented by the bit fields below as defined in AC Descriptor message
        elements. The WTP MUST abide by one of the options for tunneling user
        traffic with AR. The Tunnel DTLS Policy Element obeys the definition
        in <xref target="RFC5415"/>. If, for reliability reasons, the AC has
        provided more than one AR address in the Access Router Information
        Element, the same Tunnel DTLS Policy (the last one in <xref
        target="dtls"/>) is generally applied for all tunnels associated with
        those ARs. Otherwise, Tunnel DTLS Policy MUST be bonded together with
        each of the Access Router Information Elements, and the WTP will
        enforce the independent tunnel DTLS policy for each tunnel with a
        specific AR.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="dtls" title="Tunnel DTLS Policy Element">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Tunnel DTLS Policy Element Type|        Length                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                         |D|C|R|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                         |D|C|R|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                         ......                                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                         |D|C|R|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Type: 2</t>

        <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element
        excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

        <t>Reserved: A set of reserved bits for future use. All
        implementations complying with this protocol MUST set to 0 any bits
        that are reserved in the version of the protocol supported by that
        implementation. Receivers MUST ignore all bits not defined for the
        version of the protocol they support.</t>

        <t>D: DTLS-Enabled Data Channel Supported (see <xref
        target="RFC5415"/>).</t>

        <t>C: Clear Text Data Channel Supported (see <xref
        target="RFC5415"/>).</t>

        <t>R: A reserved bit for future use (see <xref
        target="RFC5415"/>).</t>

        <t>AR Information: This means Access Router Information Element. In
        this context, each address in AR Information MUST be one of previously
        specified AR addresses.</t>

        <t>In <xref target="dtls"/>, the last element that has no AR Information
        is the default tunnel DTLS policy, which provides options for any
        address not previously mentioned. Therefore, the AR Information field
        here is optional. 


   In this element, if all ARs share the same tunnel DTLS policy,
   there won't be an AR Information field or its specific 
   tunnel DTLS policy.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy Element">
        <t>In IEEE 802.11 networks, the IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy Element is used
        to specify how the WTP applies the QoS tagging policy when receiving
        the packets from stations on a particular radio. When the WTP sends
        out the packet to data channel to the AR(s), the packets have to be
        tagged for QoS purposes (see <xref target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>The IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy abides by the IEEE 802.11 WTP
        Quality of Service defined in Section 6.22 of <xref
        target="RFC5416"/>.</t>

        <t>If, for reliability reasons, the AC has provided more than one AR
        address in the Access Router Information Element, the same IEEE 802.11
        Tagging Mode Policy (the last one in <xref target="tmp"/>) is
        generally applied for all tunnels associated with those ARs.
        Otherwise, IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy MUST be bonded together
        with each of the Access Router Information Elements, and the WTP will
        enforce the independent IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy for each
        tunnel with a specific AR.</t>

        <figure anchor="tmp" title="IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy Element">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Tagging Mode Policy Ele. Type |        Length                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                     |P|Q|D|O|I|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                     |P|Q|D|O|I|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                         ......                                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Reserved                     |P|Q|D|O|I|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t/>

        <t>Type: 3</t>

        <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element
        excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

        <t>Reserved: A set of reserved bits for future use.</t>

        <t>P: When set, the WTP is to employ the IEEE 802.1p QoS mechanism (see
        <xref target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>Q: When the 'P' bit is set, the 'Q' bit is used by the AC to
        communicate to the WTP how IEEE 802.1p QoS is to be enforced (see <xref
        target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>D: When set, the WTP is to employ the DSCP QoS mechanism (see <xref
        target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>O: When the 'D' bit is set, the 'O' bit is used by the AC to
        communicate to the WTP how Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) QoS is to be enforced on the outer
        (tunneled) header (see <xref target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>I: When the 'D' bit is set, the 'I' bit is used by the AC to
        communicate to the WTP how DSCP QoS is to be enforced on the station's
        packet (inner) header (see <xref target="RFC5416"/>).</t>

        <t>AR Information: This means Access Router Information Element. In
        this context, each address in AR information MUST be one of the previously
        specified AR addresses.</t>

        <t>In <xref target="tmp"/>, the last element that has no AR
	information is the default IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy, which provides options
        for any address not previously mentioned. Therefore, the AR
        Information field here is optional. If all ARs share the same IEEE
        802.11 Tagging Mode Policy, in this element, there will not be an AR
        Information field and its specific IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode
        Policy.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="CAPWAP Transport Protocol Element">
        <t>The CAPWAP data tunnel supports both UDP and UDP-Lite (see <xref
        target="RFC3828"/>). When run over IPv4, UDP is used for the CAPWAP
        Data Channels. When run over IPv6, the CAPWAP Data Channel may use
        either UDP or UDP-Lite. The AC specifies and configures the WTP for
        which the transport protocol is to be used for the CAPWAP data tunnel.</t>

        <t>The CAPWAP Transport Protocol Element abides by the definition in
        Section 4.6.14 of <xref target="RFC5415"/>.</t>

        <t>If, for reliability reasons, the AC has provided more than one AR
        address in the Access Router Information Element, the same CAPWAP
        Transport Protocol (the last one in <xref target="capwape"/>) is
        generally applied for all tunnels associated with those ARs.
        Otherwise, CAPWAP Transport Protocol MUST be bonded together with each
        of the Access Router Information Elements, and the WTP will enforce
        the independent CAPWAP Transport Protocol for each tunnel with a
        specific AR.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="capwape" title="CAPWAP Transport Protocol Element">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Type=4                  |        Length                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Transport               |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Transport               |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                          ......                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Transport               |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Type: 4</t>

        <t>Length: 1</t>

        <t>Transport: The transport to use for the CAPWAP Data Channel. The
        following enumerated values are supported:
<list>
        <t>1 - UDP-Lite: The UDP-Lite transport protocol is to be used for the
        CAPWAP Data Channel. Note that this option MUST NOT be used if the
        CAPWAP Control Channel is being used over IPv4 and if the AR address
        contained in the AR Information Element is an IPv4 address.</t>

        <t>2 - UDP: The UDP transport protocol is to be used for the CAPWAP
        Data Channel.</t>
</list></t>
        <t>AR Information: This means Access Router Information Element. In
        this context, each address in AR information MUST be one of the previously
        specified AR addresses.</t>

        <t>In <xref target="capwape"/>, the last element that has no AR
	information is the default CAPWAP Transport Protocol, which
        provides options for any address not previously mentioned. Therefore,
        the AR Information field here is optional. If all ARs share the same
        CAPWAP Transport Protocol, in this element, there will not be an AR
        Information field and its specific CAPWAP Transport Protocol.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="GRE Key Element">

<t>If a WTP receives the GRE Key Element in the Alternate Tunnel
   Encapsulations Type message element for GRE selection, the WTP MUST insert
   the GRE Key to the encapsulation packet (see <xref
        target="RFC2890"/>). An AR acting as a decapsulating tunnel endpoint
        identifies packets belonging to a traffic flow based on the Key
        value.</t>

        <t>The GRE Key Element field contains a 4-octet number defined in
        <xref target="RFC2890"/>.</t>

        <t>If, for reliability reasons, the AC has provided more than one AR
        address in the Access Router Information Element, a GRE Key Element
        MAY be bonded together with each of the Access Router Information
        Elements, and the WTP will enforce the independent GRE Key for each
        tunnel with a specific AR.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="grekey" title="GRE Key Element">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| GRE Key Element Type          |        Length                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         GRE Key                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         GRE Key                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                         ......                                .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Type: 5</t>

        <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element
        excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

        <t>GRE Key: The Key field contains a 4-octet number that is
        inserted by the WTP according to <xref target="RFC2890"/>.</t>

        <t>AR Information: This means Access Router Information Element. In
        this context, it SHOULD be restricted to a single address and MUST be
        the address of one of previously specified AR addresses.</t>

        <t>Any address not explicitly mentioned here does not have a GRE
        key.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 MTU Element">
        <t>If AC has chosen a tunneling mechanism based on IPv6, it SHOULD
        support the minimum IPv6 MTU requirements <xref target="RFC8200"/>.
        This issue is described in <xref target="ARCH-TUNNELS"/>.
        AC SHOULD inform the WTP about the IPv6 MTU information in the Tunnel
        Info Element field.</t>

        <t>If, for reliability reasons, the AC has provided more than one AR
        address in the Access Router Information Element, an IPv6 MTU Element
        MAY be bonded together with each of the Access Router Information
        Elements, and the WTP will enforce the independent IPv6 MTU for each
        tunnel with a specific AR.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="ipv6mtu" title="IPv6 MTU Element">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     IPv6 MTU Element Type     |          Length               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Minimum IPv6 MTU        |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Minimum IPv6 MTU        |         Reserved              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                       AR Information                          .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         ......                                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Type: 6</t>

        <t>Length: This refers to the total length in octets of the element
        excluding the Type and Length fields.</t>

        <t>Minimum IPv6 MTU: The field contains a 2-octet number indicating
        the minimum IPv6 MTU in the tunnel.</t>

        <t>AR Information: This means Access Router Information Element. In
        this context, each address in AR information MUST be one of previously
        specified AR addresses.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>Per this document, IANA has registered the following values in the
      existing "CAPWAP Message Element Type" registry,
      defined in <xref target="RFC5415"/>. 
      <list style="symbols">
          <t>54: Supported Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type as defined in <xref
          target="tunnel-support"/>.</t>

          <t>55: Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type as defined in <xref
          target="tunnel-config"/>.</t>

          <t>1062: IEEE 802.11 WTP
          Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication as defined in <xref
          target="tunnel-failure"/>.</t>
	</list></t>

          <t>Per this document, IANA has created a                                 
          registry called "Alternate Tunnel-Types" under "CAPWAP Parameters". This specification defines the
          Alternate Tunnel Encapsulations Type message element. This element
          contains a field Tunnel-Type. The namespace for the field is 16 bits
          (0-65535). This specification defines values 0 through 6 and can be 
	  found in <xref target="tunnel-config"/>. Future
          allocations of values in this namespace are to be assigned by IANA
          using the "Specification Required" policy <xref target="RFC8126"/>. The registry format
          is given below. 

	  <figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     Description           Value         Reference
     CAPWAP                0             [RFC5415] [RFC5416]
     L2TP                  1             [RFC2661]
     L2TPv3                2             [RFC3931]
     IP-IP                 3             [RFC2003]
     PMIPv6-UDP            4             [RFC5844]
     GRE                   5             [RFC2784]
     GTPv1-U               6             [3GPP TS 29.281]
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Per this document, IANA has created a registry called "Alternate
	  Tunnel Sub-elements" under "CAPWAP Parameters". This specification
          defines the Alternate Tunnel Sub-elements. Currently, these
          information elements can only be included in the Alternate Tunnel
          Encapsulations Type message element with the IEEE 802.11 WTP
          Alternate Tunnel Failure Indication message element as its
          sub-elements. These information elements contain a Type field. The
          namespace for the field is 16 bits (0-65535). This specification
          defines values 0 through 6 in <xref
          target="subelements"/>. This namespace is managed by IANA, and
          assignments require an Expert Review <xref target="RFC8126"/>.

	  <figure>
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     Description                              Value  
     AR IPv4 List                             0            
     AR IPv6 List                             1        
     Tunnel DTLS Policy                       2      
     IEEE 802.11 Tagging Mode Policy          3         
     CAPWAP Transport Protocol                4            
     GRE Key                                  5            
     IPv6 MTU                                 6  
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces three new CAPWAP WTP message elements. These
      elements are transported within CAPWAP Control messages as the existing
      message elements. Therefore, this document does not introduce any new
      security risks to the control plane compared to <xref target="RFC5415"/>
      and <xref target="RFC5416"/>. In the data plane, if the encapsulation
      type selected itself is not secured, it is suggested to protect the
      tunnel by using known secure methods, such as IPsec.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2003"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2890"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2661"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2784"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3931"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5415"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5416"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3828"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8200"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc ?>

<reference anchor='ARCH-TUNNELS'>
<front>
<title>IP Tunnels in the Internet Architecture</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Touch' fullname='Joseph Touch'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Townsley' fullname='Mark Townsley'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2018' />

<abstract><t>This document discusses the role of IP tunnels in the Internet architecture. An IP tunnel transits IP datagrams as payloads in non- link layer protocols. This document explains the relationship of IP tunnels to existing protocol layers and the challenges in supporting IP tunneling, based on the equivalence of tunnels to links. The implications of this document are used to derive recommendations that update MTU and fragment issues in RFC 4459.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-intarea-tunnels-08' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-intarea-tunnels-08.txt' />
</reference>



      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7494"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5844"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5845"?>

      <reference anchor="TS29281">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio System (GPRS)
          Tunnelling Protocol User Plane (GTPv1-U)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2016" month="March"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 29.281," value="V13.1.0"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Andreas Schultz, Hong Liu, Yifan
      Chen, Chunju Shao, Li Xue, Jianjie You, Jin Li, Joe Touch, Alexey
      Melnikov, Kathleen Moriarty, Mirja Kuehlewind, Catherine Meadows,
      and Paul Kyzivat for their valuable comments.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>

