<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY rfc2141 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.2141.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2288 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.2288.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2611 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.2611.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3406 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.3406.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3044 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.3044.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3187 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.3187.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3188 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.3188.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8141 PUBLIC '' "reference.RFC.8141.xml">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc  number="8254" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902"  category="std"
     obsoletes="3044, 3187">


  <front>

    <title abbrev="URN Registration Transition">
         Uniform Resource Name (URN) Namespace Registration Transition
    </title>

    <author fullname="John C. Klensin" initials="J.C." surname="Klensin">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1770 Massachusetts Ave, Ste 322</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city> <region>MA</region>
          <code>02140</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 617 245 1457</phone>
        <email>john-ietf@jck.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Juha Hakala" initials="J." surname="Hakala">
      <organization> The National Library of Finland</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 15, Helsinki University</street>
          <city>Helsinki</city> <region>MA</region>
          <code>FIN-00014</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>juha.hakala@helsinki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2017" />

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>URNbis</workgroup>

	<keyword>ISBN</keyword>
	<keyword>ISSN</keyword>
	<keyword>NBN</keyword>
	<keyword>national bibliography number</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The original registration procedure for formal Uniform Resource Name
         (URN) namespaces required IETF Consensus.
         That requirement discouraged
         some registrations and increased the risk for problems that
         could occur as a result.  The requirements have now been
         changed by RFC 8141, which adopts a different model,
         focusing on encouraging registration and publication of
         information for all appropriate namespaces.  This
         document clarifies the status of relevant older RFCs and
         confirms and documents advice to IANA about selected
         existing registrations.
        This document also obsoletes RFCs 3044 and 3187 and moves them to Historic status.  
        These RFCs describe the ISSN and ISBN namespaces, which are now outdated because 
        the descriptions reside in registration templates. </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
       <t>
    As a part of the initial development of the Uniform Resource Name
    (URN) system in the late 1990s,
    the IETF URN Working Group agreed that it was important to
	demonstrate that the URN syntax could accommodate existing
	identifier systems. <xref target="RFC2288"> RFC 2288 </xref>
	showed the feasibility of using
    International Standard Book Number (ISBN),
    International Standard Serial Number (ISSN),
    and Serial Item and Contribution Identifier (SICI) <xref target="ANSI-SICI"/>
    as URNs;
    however, it did not formally register corresponding URN namespaces.
    This was in part due to the still-evolving process to formalize
    criteria for namespace definition documents and registration,
    consolidated later by the IETF into successive Namespace
    Definition Mechanism documents
    <xref target="RFC2611"/> <xref target="RFC3406"/>.
  </t>

  <t> URN namespaces were subsequently registered for
    ISBN <xref target="RFC3187"/> and ISSN <xref target="RFC3044"/>
    as well as for a fairly large collection of other identifiers including
    National Bibliography Number (NBN) <xref target="RFC3188"/>.
    The comprehensive list can be found in the IANA Uniform Resource
	Names (URN) Namespaces registry <xref target="IANA-URN"/>
    (see also <xref target="OtherNamespaces"/>).
   </t>
   <t>While a URN namespace for SICI could be registered at any time,
        the SICI standard has not gained broad international acceptance and has
        not had a namespace defined to date.</t>

      <t>The predecessor registration procedure for URN
         namespaces <xref target="RFC3406"/>
         required IETF Consensus for formal namespaces.
         That requirement discouraged
         some registrations and increased the risk for problems,
         including use of names without registration ("squatting").
			 
		 If names are not registered in a consistent way, there is a possibility of the
		 same name being used to identify different namespaces with
         different rules, resulting in considerable confusion.
         The requirements have now been
         changed in <xref target="RFC8141">RFC 8141</xref> to adopt a different
         model that focuses more on encouraging registration of all
         namespaces that follow the formal namespace syntax, with as
         much information collected as possible consistent with that
         goal.</t>
      <t>Therefore, this document does the following:
         <list style="symbols">
            <t>Describes the instructions developed with IANA to
               adapt selected existing registrations to the new model.
                Those registration updates have been completed for
                ISBN and ISSN Namespace Identifiers (NIDs) and URN namespaces. </t>
            <t>Obsoletes the separate RFCs that specify the
               namespaces for ISSNs and ISBNs to eliminate any
               ambiguity about the status of new templates and
               updated registrations.</t>
            <t> Provides information about the status of NBNs under
               the new definitions.</t>
            <t>Provides suggestions to IANA about the handling of
               other existing registrations not explicitly discussed
               in this document.</t>
         </list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Obsoleting Older Registration RFCs for ISSNs and ISBNs"
            anchor="NewTemplates">
       <t>The existing RFCs that describe URN namespaces for
          ISSNs <xref target="RFC3044"/>
          and ISBNs <xref target="RFC3187"/>
         have been identified as "Historic" concurrent with publication of this document.
         The new registration templates for
         those namespaces have already been submitted and
         incorporated into the URN Namespaces registry by IANA.
       </t>
       <t>Those updated templates reflect not only the new template
          formats but substantive changes to the definitions of the
          namespaces.  The significant changes are summarized in the
          subsections that follow.</t>

       <t>For both ISSN and ISBN namespaces, URN registration
		  practices within them are expected to evolve along with the
		  ISO ISBN and ISSN standards without requiring resubmission
		  of the templates or other formal IETF or IANA URN namespace
		  registration update approval procedures.
		  The subsections that follow clarify the
          relationship between the original URN namespace
          registrations for ISBN and ISSN and the recently registered templates
          that follow the principles of RFC 8141.  Approval
          and registration of those new templates made the older
          templates obsolete.</t>

          <section title="ISBN URN Changes">
             <t>The revised ISBN namespace reflects the latest version of the ISO
                ISBN standard, ISO 2108:2017 <xref target="ISO-ISBN-b"/>.
                The namespace
                allows for the use of both the old ten-character ISBN
                numbers described in RFC 3187 and
                ISO 2108:1992 <xref target="ISO-ISBN-a"/>
                (formerly known as ISBN-10) and the thirteen-character
                identifiers introduced in
                ISO 2108:2005 <xref target="ISO-ISBN-c"/>
                (formerly known as ISBN-13). </t>
             <t>For more details, review the new ISBN registration
                template and associated documentation
                <xref target="ISBN-Template"/>. </t>
          </section>

          <section title="ISSN URN Changes">
             <t>The updated ISSN namespace reflects the changes
                between the current ISSN standard
                <xref target="ISO-ISSN"/> and its
                predecessor on which RFC 3044 was based. ISO 3297:2007
                introduced the linking ISSN (ISSN-L), which
                is designated for all media of a serial publication,
                irrespective of how many there are.  Traditional ISSN
                applies to a single medium only, such as the printed version
                of a serial.
             </t>
             <t>For more details, review the new ISSN registration
                template and associated documentation
                <xref target="ISSN-Template"/>. </t>
          </section>
    </section>
    <section title="The Older Registration RFC for NBNs">
       <t> NBN is not a formal international standard or even a
          single identifier system but an umbrella concept that
          covers all of the identifier systems the adopting national
          libraries and their partners use to identify resources that
          do not have
          other identifiers. For instance, if a book received via
          legal deposit does not have an ISBN, the national library
          gives it a local identifier. The NBN specification provides
          a simple means of expressing these local identifiers so
          that they become globally unique URNs, such as
          urn:nbn:fi-fe19981001.</t>

       <t>In addition to the namespace registration itself, RFC 3188
          provides some generic information about NBNs and their use
          and specifies the syntax of URN:NBNs.  That syntax guarantees
          uniqueness by requiring the usage of country codes and
          institutional identifiers as a part of the Namespace Specific String (NSS).
          When RFC 3188 is revised, it should be accompanied with a template
          that revises the registration of the URN:NBN namespace.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Other Existing URN Registrations and RFCs"
            anchor="OtherNamespaces">

       <t>The RFC Series and the IANA URN Namespaces registry contain many URN
          namespace registrations in addition to those for which this document
          calls out explicit actions.  In general, those existing
          registrations are still appropriate but omit some
          information called
          for in <xref target="RFC8141"> RFC 8141</xref>.
          Reregistration
          with new templates is recommended but not required.  Until
          and unless those registrations are updated as provided for in
          RFC 8141, the existing registration templates should be
          read as not requiring or allowing any features that were
          not allowed and specified by the
          earlier URN <xref target="RFC2141"/> and registration
          <xref target="RFC3406"/> specifications.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Registration Examples">

       <t> For examples of registrations using the new model and for
          information and help in understanding other parts of this
          document, review the new ISBN and ISSN registration
          templates  <xref target="ISBN-Template"/>
          <xref target="ISSN-Template"/> and associated documentation in the
          IANA URN Namespaces registry.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations" >
      <t>IANA has completed updates for the registry entries for URN
         ISSN and ISBN namespaces to reflect the new
         templates that are compliant with RFC 8141.
         With respect to namespaces other than those listed above,
         when registrations and templates are available that conform
		 to the newer rules, they may be substituted for the older ones.
         However, neither this document nor RFC 8141 supersedes any 
         existing registrations (those for ISBN and ISSN are
		 superseded by the recently registered templates).
         Therefore, IANA needs to be prepared
		 to maintain a registry whose contents
         reflect old-style templates for some namespaces and the newer
         ones for others.</t>
      <t>IANA should also note that the portions of the ISBN and ISSN registrations
         that point to ISO Standards are intended to identify current
         versions (which may change) rather than only the versions
         that are active at the time this document is approved
         (see <xref target="NewTemplates"/>).
			 
		 That provision relies on ISO TC 46 and its respective
		 registration authorities to 
	     maintain stability of URN references discussed in this
	     document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>While particular URN namespaces and their registrations might
         conceivably have security implications, this specification
         merely specifies a transition of a set of namespace
         registrations and
         does not have such implications.   The security implications
         associated with particular namespaces are expected to be
         listed in registration templates as specified in RFC 8141.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>


  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

        &rfc8141; 

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
        &rfc2141;
        &rfc3406;
        &rfc3044;
        &rfc3187;
        &rfc3188;
        &rfc2611;
        &rfc2288;


<reference anchor="ISBN-Template"
           target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-formal/isbn">
   <front>
      <title>Namespace Registration for International Standard Book Number (ISBN) ISO 2108:2017</title>
      <author>
         <organization>ISBN International Agency</organization>
         <address/>
      </author>
      <date month="June" year="2017"/>
   </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ISSN-Template"
           target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-formal/issn">
   <front>
      <title>Namespace Registration for International Standard Serial
         Number (ISSN) and Linking ISSN (ISSN-L) based on ISO 3297:2007</title>
      <author>
         <organization>ISSN International Centre</organization>
         <address/>
      </author>
       <date month="June" year="2017"/>
   </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ANSI-SICI">
        <front>
           <title>Serial Item and Contribution Identifier (SICI)</title>
           <author>
              <organization>ANSI/NISO</organization>
              <address/>
           </author>
           <date month="August" year="1996"/>
        </front>
    <seriesInfo name="ANSI/NISO" value="Z39.56-1996 (Version 2)"/>
     </reference>

<reference anchor="ISO-ISBN-a">
        <front>
          <title>Information and documentation - International
              Standard Book Number (ISBN)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date year="1992" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="2108:1992"/>
      </reference>

<reference anchor="ISO-ISBN-b">
        <front>
          <title>Information and documentation - International
              Standard Book Number (ISBN)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date year="2017" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="2108:2017"/>
      </reference>

<reference anchor="ISO-ISBN-c">
        <front>
          <title>Information and documentation - International
              Standard Book Number (ISBN)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="2108:2005"/>
      </reference>
 
<reference anchor="ISO-ISSN">
        <front>
          <title>Information and documentation - International
             Standard Serial Number (ISSN)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="3297:2007"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA-URN"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-namespaces">
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Resource Names (URN) Namespaces</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
    <t>This document draws heavily on discussions in the IETF URNbis
        Working Group in the second and third quarters of 2013, particularly
        during IETF 87 in August 2013, and on informal discussions during the
        plenary meeting of ISO TC 46 in June 2013.  The efforts of those who
        participated in those discussions are greatly appreciated.  It also
        draws on Internet-Drafts that were developed to update the older
        registrations before that approach was replaced by the new extended
        template model.  Those documents were prepared by Pierre Godefroy, Juha
        Hakala, Alfred Hoenes, and Maarit Huttunen.</t>

    <t>The current specification benefits significantly from a careful
        reading and suggestions for editorial changes by
        Peter Saint-Andre; from considerable work by Stella
        Griffiths of the ISBN International Agency to refine the ISBN
        discussion and develop the corresponding template; and from
        Gaelle Bequet, Pierre Godefroy, and Clement Oury of the
        ISSN International Centre for similar refinements of the ISSN
        discussion and template.</t>
     
     </section>
     <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
     <t> Alfred Hoenes was the editor and co-author of two of the
        documents from which this one is, in part, derived.  This
        document would not have been possible without his
        contributions.</t>
     </section>



  </back>
</rfc>
