<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8077 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8077.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7432 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7432.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7623 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7623.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4761 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4761.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4762 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4762.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7041 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7041.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6074 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6074.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7080 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7080.xml">
<!ENTITY IEEE.802.1ah SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml6/reference.IEEE.802.1ah.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4684 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4684.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" number="8560" category="std" >
	<!-- Originally generated by id2xml 1.4.4 on 2019-02-09T05:04:56Z -->
	<?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
	<front>


	<title abbrev="(PBB-)EVPN and (PBB-)VPLS Integration"> Seamless Integration of Ethernet VPN (EVPN) with Virtual Private LAN Service (VPLS) and Their Provider Backbone Bridge (PBB) Equivalents</title>
	<author fullname="Ali Sajassi" initials="A." role="editor" surname="Sajassi">
	<organization>Cisco</organization>
	<address><email>sajassi@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Samer Salam" initials="S." surname="Salam">
	<organization>Cisco</organization>
	<address><email>ssalam@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Nick Del Regno" initials="N." surname="Del Regno">
	<organization>Verizon</organization>
	<address><email>nick.delregno@verizon.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Jorge Rabadan" initials="J." surname="Rabadan">
	<organization>Nokia</organization>
	<address><email>jorge.rabadan@nokia.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<date month="May" year="2019"/>
	<workgroup>BESS Workgroup</workgroup>



	<abstract><t> This document specifies mechanisms for backward
	compatibility of Ethernet VPN (EVPN) and Provider Backbone
	Bridge Ethernet VPN (PBB- EVPN) solutions with Virtual Private
	LAN Service (VPLS) and Provider Backbone Bridge VPLS
	(PBB-VPLS) solutions. It also provides mechanisms for the
	seamless integration of these two technologies in the same
	MPLS/IP network on a per-VPN-instance basis. Implementation of
	this document enables service providers to introduce
	EVPN/PBB-EVPN Provider Edges (PEs) in their brownfield
	deployments of VPLS/PBB-VPLS networks.  This document
	specifies the control-plane and forwarding behavior needed for
	the auto-discovery of the following: 1) a VPN instance, 2)
	multicast and unicast operation, and 3) a Media Access Control
	(MAC) mobility operation.  This enables seamless integration
	between EVPN and VPLS PEs as well as between PBB-VPLS and
	PBB-EVPN PEs.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	<section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
   Virtual Private LAN Service (VPLS) and Provider Backbone Bridging
   VPLS (PBB-VPLS) are widely deployed Layer 2 VPN (L2VPN) technologies.
   Many service providers who are looking at adopting Ethernet VPN
   (EVPN) and Provider Backbone Bridging EVPN (PBB-EVPN) want to
   preserve their investments in the VPLS and PBB-VPLS networks. Hence,
   they require mechanisms by which EVPN and PBB-EVPN technologies can
   be introduced into their brownfield VPLS and PBB-VPLS networks
   without requiring any upgrades (software or hardware) to these
   networks. This document specifies procedures for the seamless
   integration of the two technologies in the same MPLS/IP network.
   Throughout this document, we use the term "(PBB-)EVPN" to correspond to
   both EVPN and PBB-EVPN, and we use the term "(PBB-)VPLS" to correspond
   to both VPLS and PBB-VPLS. This document specifies the control-plane and
   forwarding behavior needed for 1) auto-discovery of a VPN instance,
   2) multicast and unicast operations, and 3) a MAC mobility operation.  This 
   enables seamless integration between (PBB-)EVPN Provider
   Edge (PE) devices and (PBB-)VPLS PEs.</t>

	<figure title="Seamless Integration of (PBB-)EVPN and (PBB-)VPLS" anchor="ref-seamless-integration-of-pbb-evpn-pbb-vpls"><artwork><![CDATA[
                         VPLS PE
                          +---+
                          |PE1|
                          +---+
                            /
     EVPN/VPLS PE  +---------------+   EVPN/VPLS PE
          +---+    |               |   +---+
          |PE4|----|    MPLS/IP    |---|PE5|
          +---+    |     Core      |   +---+
                   |               |
                   +---------------+
                     /        \
                  +---+     +---+
                  |PE2|     |PE3|
                  +---+     +---+
                VPLS PE     VPLS PE
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   <xref target="section-2"/> provides the details of the requirements. <xref target="section-3"/>
   specifies procedures for the seamless integration of VPLS and EVPN
   networks. <xref target="section-4"/> specifies procedures for the seamless
   integration of PBB-VPLS and PBB-EVPN networks.</t>

	<t>
   It should be noted that the scenarios for both PBB-VPLS integration with
   EVPN and VPLS integration with PBB-EVPN are not covered in this
   document because there haven't been any requirements from service
   providers for these scenarios;
   deployments that employ PBB-VPLS typically require PBB encapsulation
   for various reasons. Hence, it is expected that for those deployments,
   the evolution path would move from PBB-VPLS towards PBB-EVPN.
   Furthermore, the evolution path from VPLS is expected to move towards
   EVPN.</t>

	<t>
   The seamless integration solution described in this document has the
   following attributes:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>When ingress replication is used
	for multi-destination traffic delivery, the solution reduces
	the scope of MMRP (which is a
	soft-state protocol defined in Clause 10 of <xref target="IEEE.802.1Q"/>) to only that of existing VPLS PEs and
	uses the more robust BGP-based mechanism for multicast pruning
	among new EVPN PEs.</t>

	<t>It is completely backward compatible.</t>

	<t>New PEs can leverage the extensive multihoming mechanisms and
	provisioning simplifications of (PBB-)EVPN:

	<list style="format (%c)"><t>Auto-sensing of Multihomed Networks (MHNs) / Multihomed Devices (MHDs)</t>

	<t>Auto-discovery of redundancy groups</t>

	<t>Auto-provisioning of Designated Forwarder election and
         VLAN carving</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<section title="Specification of Requirements"
		 anchor="section-1.1">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

	</section>



	<section title="Abbreviations" anchor="section-1.2"><t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">


	  	<t hangText="B-MAC:">Backbone MAC, e.g., the
		PE's MAC address</t>

			<t hangText="C-MAC:">Customer MAC, e.g., a
	host or CE's MAC address</t>


<t hangText="CE:">A Customer Edge device, e.g., a host, router, or switch
	</t>


		<t hangText="ES:">Ethernet Segment -- refers to the set of
	Ethernet links that connects a customer site (device or
	network) to one or more PEs</t>

	<t hangText="FEC:">Forwarding Equivalence Class</t>	
	<t hangText="FIB:">Forwarding Information Base -- an instantiation of a forwarding
	table on a MAC-VRF</t>
		<t hangText="I-SID:">Service Instance Identifier</t>


	<t hangText="LSP:">Label Switched Path</t>
	
	<t hangText="MAC:">Media Access Control</t>


	<t hangText="MAC-VRF:">A Virtual Routing and Forwarding table for Media Access
	Control (MAC) addresses on an EVPN PE
	</t>
	<t hangText="MHD:">Multihomed Device</t>

	<t hangText="MHN:">Multihomed Network</t>

	<t hangText="MP2P:">Multipoint to Point -- an MP2P LSP typically refers
	to an LSP for unicast traffic as the result of a downstream-assigned label</t>

	<t hangText="P2MP:">Point to Multipoint -- a P2MP LSP typically
	refers to an LSP for multicast traffic
	</t>

		<t hangText="PBB:">Provider Backbone Bridge</t>

			<t hangText="(PBB-)EVPN:">Both PBB-EVPN and
	EVPN -- this document uses this abbreviation when a given
	description applies to both technologies</t>

	<t hangText="(PBB-)VPLS:">Both PBB-VPLS and
	VPLS -- this document uses this abbreviation when a given
	description applies to both technologies</t>

	        <t hangText="PE:">Provider Edge device
	</t>
	<t hangText="PW:">Pseudowire</t>

	<t hangText="RIB:">Routing Information Base -- an instantiation of a routing table
   on a MAC-VRF</t>

	<t hangText="VSI:">Virtual Switch Instance</t>

	<t hangText="VPLS:">Virtual Private LAN Service</t>

	<t hangText="VPLS A-D:">Virtual Private LAN Service
	with BGP-based auto-discovery as in <xref
	target="RFC6074"/></t>


	

      </list></t>


	</section>

	<section title="Terminology" anchor="section-1.3"><t> <list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="All-Active redundancy mode:">When all PEs
	attached to an Ethernet segment are allowed to forward known
	unicast traffic to/from that Ethernet segment for a given
	VLAN, then the Ethernet segment is defined as operating in
	All-Active redundancy mode.</t>
	
	  <t hangText="Bridge table:">An instantiation of a broadcast domain on a MAC-VRF (VPN Routing and Forwarding).
	</t>

<t hangText="Broadcast domain:">In a bridged network, the broadcast domain
	corresponds to a Virtual LAN (VLAN), where a VLAN is typically
   represented by a single VLAN ID (VID) but can be represented by
   several VIDs where Shared VLAN Learning (SVL) is used, per
   <xref target="IEEE.802.1Q"/>.
</t>

	<t hangText="Ethernet Tag:">
	An Ethernet Tag identifies a particular broadcast
	domain, e.g., a VLAN.  An EVPN instance consists of one or more
   broadcast domains.
	</t>

		<t hangText="Single-Active redundancy mode:">When only a
	single PE, among all the PEs attached to an Ethernet segment,
	is allowed to forward traffic to/from that Ethernet segment
	for a given VLAN, then the Ethernet segment is defined as
	operating in Single-Active redundancy mode.</t></list></t>
	
</section>
	</section>

	<section title="Requirements" anchor="section-2"><t>
   The following are the key requirements for backward compatibility between
   (PBB-)EVPN and (PBB-)VPLS:</t>

	<t><list style="numbers"><t>The solution must allow for staged migration towards (PBB-)EVPN on
      a site-by-site basis per VPN instance, e.g., new EVPN sites to be
      provisioned on (PBB-)EVPN Provider Edge devices (PEs).</t>

	<t>The solution must not require any changes to existing VPLS or PBB-VPLS PEs, not even a software upgrade.</t>

	<t>The solution must allow for the coexistence of PE devices running
      (PBB-)EVPN and (PBB-)VPLS for the same VPN instance and single-homed
      segments.</t>

	<t>The solution must support single-active redundancy of multihomed
      networks and multihomed devices for (PBB-)EVPN PEs.</t>

	<t>In cases of single-active redundancy, the participant VPN instances
      may span across both (PBB-)EVPN PEs and (PBB-)VPLS PEs as long as the
      MHD or MHN is connected to (PBB-)EVPN PEs.</t>

	<t>Support of the All-Active redundancy mode across both (PBB-)EVPN
      PEs and (PBB-)VPLS PEs is outside the scope of this document.  All-Active redundancy is not applicable to VPLS and PBB-VPLS. Therefore,
   when EVPN (or PBB-EVPN) PEs need to operate seamlessly with VPLS (or
   PBB-VPLS) PEs, they MUST use a redundancy mode that is
   applicable to VPLS (or PBB-VPLS). This redundancy mode is Single-Active.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   These requirements collectively allow for the seamless insertion of
   (PBB-)EVPN technology into brownfield (PBB-)VPLS deployments.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="VPLS Integration with EVPN" anchor="section-3"><t>
   In order to support seamless integration with VPLS PEs, this document
   requires that VPLS PEs support VPLS A-D per <xref target="RFC6074"/>, and it requires EVPN PEs to 
   support both BGP EVPN routes per <xref target="RFC7432"/> and VPLS A-D per
   <xref target="RFC6074"/>. All the logic for seamless integration shall reside on the
   EVPN PEs.


   If a VPLS instance is set up without the use of VPLS A-D, it is still possible (but cumbersome) for EVPN PEs to integrate
that VPLS instance by manually configuring
 pseudowires (PWs) to all
   the VPLS PEs in that instance (i.e., the integration is no longer
   seamless).</t>

	<section title="Capability Discovery" anchor="section-3.1"><t>
   The EVPN PEs MUST advertise both the BGP VPLS auto-discovery (A-D)
   route as well as the BGP EVPN Inclusive Multicast Ethernet Tag (IMET)
   route for a given VPN instance. The VPLS PEs only advertise the BGP
   VPLS A-D route, per the procedures specified in <xref target="RFC4761"/>, <xref target="RFC4762"/>
   and <xref target="RFC6074"/>. The operator may decide to use the same Route Target
   (RT) to identify a VPN on both EVPN and VPLS networks. In this case,
   when a VPLS PE receives the EVPN IMET route, it MUST ignore it on the
   basis that it belongs to an unknown Subsequent Address Family Identifier (SAFI). However, the operator may
   choose to use two RTs -- one to identify the VPN on the VPLS network and
   another for the EVPN network -- and employ RT Constrain mechanisms <xref target="RFC4684"/> in order
   to prevent BGP EVPN routes from reaching the VPLS PEs.</t>

	<t>
   When an EVPN PE receives both a VPLS A-D route as well as an EVPN
   IMET route from a given remote PE for the same VPN instance, it MUST
   give preference to the EVPN route for the purpose of discovery. This
   ensures that, at the end of the route exchanges, all EVPN-capable PEs
   discover other EVPN-capable PEs in addition to the VPLS-only PEs for
   that VPN instance. Furthermore, all the VPLS-only PEs will discover
   the EVPN PEs as if they were standard VPLS PEs. In other words, when
   the discovery phase is complete, the EVPN PEs will have discovered
   all the PEs in the VPN instance along with their associated
   capability (EVPN or VPLS-only), whereas the VPLS PEs will have
   discovered all the PEs in the VPN instance as if they were all VPLS-only
	PEs.</t>




	</section>

	<section title="Forwarding Setup and Unicast Operation" anchor="section-3.2"><t>
   The procedures for the forwarding state setup and unicast operation on
   the VPLS PE are per <xref target="RFC8077"/>, <xref target="RFC4761"/>, and <xref target="RFC4762"/>.</t>

	<t>
   The procedures for forwarding state setup and unicast operation on
   the EVPN PE are as follows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The EVPN PE MUST establish a PW to each remote PE from which it has
     received only a VPLS A-D route for the corresponding VPN instance
     and MUST set up the label stack corresponding to the PW FEC. For
     seamless integration between EVPN and VPLS PEs, the PW that is set up
     between a pair of VPLS and EVPN PEs is between the VSI of the VPLS PE
     and the MAC-VRF of the EVPN PE.</t>

	<t>The EVPN PE MUST set up the label stack corresponding to the MP2P
     VPN unicast FEC to any remote PE that has advertised an EVPN IMET route.</t>

	<t>If an EVPN PE receives a VPLS A-D route from a given PE, it sets up
     a PW to that PE. If it then receives an EVPN IMET route from the same
     PE, the EVPN PE MUST bring that PW operationally down.</t>

	<t>If an EVPN PE receives an EVPN IMET route followed by a VPLS A-D
     route from the same PE, then the EVPN PE will set up the PW but MUST
     keep it operationally down.</t>

	<t>In case VPLS A-D is not used in some VPLS PEs, the EVPN PEs need to
     be provisioned manually with PWs to those remote VPLS PEs for each
     VPN instance. In that case, if an EVPN PE receives an EVPN IMET route
     from a PE to which a PW exists, the EVPN PE MUST bring the PW
     operationally down.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   When the EVPN PE receives traffic over the VPLS PWs, it learns the
   associated C-MAC addresses in the data plane. The C-MAC addresses
   learned over these PWs MUST be injected into the bridge table of the
   associated MAC-VRF on that EVPN PE. The learned C-MAC addresses MAY
   also be injected into the RIB/FIB tables of the associated MAC-VRF on
   that EVPN PE. For seamless integration between EVPN and VPLS PEs, because these PWs belong to the same split-horizon group (see <xref target="RFC4761"/> and
   <xref target="RFC4762"/>) as the MP2P EVPN service tunnels, the C-MAC addresses
   learned and associated with the PWs MUST NOT be advertised in the
   control plane to any remote EVPN PEs. This is because every EVPN PE
   can send and receive traffic directly to/from every VPLS PE belonging
   to the same VPN instance; thus, every EVPN PE can learn the C-MAC
   addresses over the corresponding PWs directly.</t>

	<t>
   The C-MAC addresses learned over local Attachment Circuits (ACs) by
   an EVPN PE are learned in the data plane. For EVPN PEs, these C-MAC
   addresses MUST be injected into the corresponding MAC-VRF and
   advertised in the control plane using BGP EVPN routes. Furthermore,
   the C-MAC addresses learned in the control plane via the BGP EVPN
   routes sent by remote EVPN PEs are injected into the corresponding
   MAC-VRF table.</t>

	<t>
   In case of a link failure in a single-active Ethernet segment, the
   EVPN PEs MUST perform both of the following tasks:
<list style="numbers">
	<t>
   send a BGP mass withdraw to the EVPN peers</t>

	<t>
   follow existing VPLS MAC Flush procedures with the VPLS peers</t></list></t>

	</section>

	<section title="MAC Mobility" anchor="section-3.3"><t>
   In EVPN, host addresses (C-MAC addresses) can move around among EVPN
   PEs or even between EVPN and VPLS PEs.</t>
   

	<t>
   When a C-MAC address moves from an EVPN PE to a VPLS PE, as soon
   as Broadcast, Unknown Unicast, and Multicast (BUM) traffic is initiated
   from that MAC address, it is flooded to all other PEs (both VPLS and
   EVPN PEs), and the receiving PEs update their MAC tables (VSI or
   MAC-VRF). The EVPN PEs do not advertise the C-MAC addresses learned over
   the PW to each other because every EVPN PE learns them directly over
   its associated PW to that VPLS PE. If only known unicast traffic is
   initiated from the moved C-MAC address toward a known C-MAC, 
   the result can be the black-holing of traffic destined to the C-MAC that
   has moved until there is BUM traffic that has been originated with the moved C-MAC
   address as the source MAC address (e.g., as a result of the MAC age-out
   timer expiring). Such black-holing happens for traffic destined to the moved C-MAC from both EVPN and VPLS PEs and is typical for VPLS PEs.</t>

	<t>
   When a C-MAC address moves from a VPLS PE to an EVPN PE, then as soon
   as any traffic is initiated from that C-MAC address, the C-MAC is
   learned and advertised in the BGP to other EVPN PEs, and the MAC mobility
   procedure is performed among EVPN PEs. For BUM traffic, both EVPN and
   VPLS PEs learn the new location of the moved C-MAC address; however,
   if there is only known unicast traffic, then only EVPN PEs learn the
   new location of the C-MAC that has moved and not VPLS PEs. This can
   result in the black-holing of traffic sent from VPLS PEs destined to the
   C-MAC that has moved until there is BUM traffic originated with the
   moved C-MAC address as the source MAC address (e.g., as a result of
the MAC age-out timer expiring). Such black-holing happens for traffic
   destined to the moved C-MAC for only VPLS PEs but not for EVPN PEs and is typical for
   VPLS PEs.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Multicast Operation" anchor="section-3.4">
<t></t>
	  <section title="Ingress Replication" anchor="section-3.4.1"><t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the VPLS PE using ingress
   replication are per <xref target="RFC4761"/>, <xref target="RFC4762"/>, and <xref target="RFC7080"/>.</t>

	<t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the EVPN PE for ingress
   replication are as follows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The EVPN PE builds a replication sub-list to all the remote EVPN
     PEs per EVPN instance as the result of the exchange of the EVPN IMET
     routes per <xref target="RFC7432"/>. This will be referred to as sub-list A. It
     comprises MP2P service tunnels (for ingress replication) used for
     delivering EVPN BUM traffic <xref target="RFC7432"/>.</t>

	<t>The EVPN PE builds a replication sub-list per VPLS instance to all
     the remote VPLS PEs. This will be referred to as sub-list B. It
     comprises PWs from the EVPN PE in question to all the remote VPLS PEs
     in the same VPLS instance.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   The replication list, maintained per VPN instance, on a given EVPN PE
   will be the union of sub-list A and sub-list B. The EVPN PE MUST
   enable split horizon over all the entries in the replication list
   across both PWs and MP2P service tunnels.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="P2MP Tunnel" anchor="section-3.4.2"><t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the EVPN PEs using P2MP
   tunnels are outside of the scope of this document.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="PBB-VPLS Integration with PBB-EVPN" anchor="section-4"><t>
   In order to support seamless integration between PBB-VPLS and PBB-
   EVPN PEs, this document requires that PBB-VPLS PEs support VPLS A-D
   per <xref target="RFC6074"/> and PBB-EVPN PEs support both BGP EVPN routes per
   <xref target="RFC7432"/> and VPLS A-D per <xref target="RFC6074"/>. All the logic for this seamless
   integration shall reside on the PBB-EVPN PEs.</t>

	<section title="Capability Discovery" anchor="section-4.1"><t>
   The procedures for capability discovery are per <xref target="section-3.1"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Forwarding Setup and Unicast Operation" anchor="section-4.2"><t>
   The procedures for forwarding state setup and unicast operation on
   the PBB-VPLS PE are per <xref target="RFC8077"/> and <xref target="RFC7080"/>.</t>

	<t>
   The procedures for forwarding state setup and unicast operation on
   the PBB-EVPN PE are as follows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The PBB-EVPN PE MUST establish a PW to each remote PBB-VPLS PE from
     which it has received only a VPLS A-D route for the corresponding VPN
     instance and MUST set up the label stack corresponding to the PW
     FEC. For seamless integration between PBB-EVPN and PBB-VPLS PEs, the
     PW that is set up between a pair of PBB-VPLS and PBB-EVPN PEs is
     between the B-components of PBB-EVPN PE and PBB-VPLS PE per Section 4 of
     <xref target="RFC7041"/>.</t>

	<t>The PBB-EVPN PE MUST set up the label stack corresponding to the
     MP2P VPN unicast FEC to any remote PBB-EVPN PE that has advertised an
     EVPN IMET route.</t>

	<t>If a PBB-EVPN PE receives a VPLS A-D route from a given PE, it sets
     up a PW to that PE. If it then receives an EVPN IMET route from the
     same PE, the PBB-EVPN PE MUST bring that PW operationally down.</t>

	<t>If a PBB-EVPN PE receives an EVPN IMET route followed by a VPLS A-D
     route from the same PE, then the PBB-EVPN PE will set up the PW but
     MUST keep it operationally down.</t>

	<t>In case VPLS A-D is not used in some PBB-VPLS PEs, the PBB-EVPN PEs
     need to be provisioned manually with PWs to those remote PBB-VPLS PEs
     for each VPN instance. In that case, if a PBB-EVPN PE receives an
     EVPN IMET route from a PE to which a PW exists, the PBB-EVPN PE MUST
     bring the PW operationally down.</t>

	<t>When the PBB-EVPN PE receives traffic over the PBB-VPLS PWs, it
     learns the associated B-MAC addresses in the data plane. The B-MAC
     addresses learned over these PWs MUST be injected into the bridge
     table of the associated MAC-VRF on that PBB-EVPN PE. The learned B-MAC
     addresses MAY also be injected into the RIB/FIB tables of the
     associated MAC-VRF on that BPP-EVPN PE. For seamless integration
     between PBB-EVPN and PBB-VPLS PEs, since these PWs belong to the
     same split-horizon group as the MP2P EVPN service tunnels, the
     B-MAC addresses learned and associated with the PWs MUST NOT be
     advertised in the control plane to any remote PBB-EVPN PEs. This is
     because every PBB-EVPN PE can send and receive traffic directly
     to/from every PBB-VPLS PE belonging to the same VPN instance.</t>

	<t>The C-MAC addresses learned over local Attachment Circuits (ACs) by
     a PBB-EVPN PE are learned in the data plane. For PBB-EVPN PEs, these
     C-MAC addresses are learned in the I-component of PBB-EVPN PEs and are not advertised in the control plane, per <xref target="RFC7623"/>.</t>

	<t>The B-MAC addresses learned in the control plane via the BGP EVPN
     routes sent by remote PBB-EVPN PEs are injected into the
     corresponding MAC-VRF table.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   In case of a link failure in a single-active Ethernet segment, the
   PBB-EVPN PEs MUST perform both of the following tasks:</t>

	<t><list style="numbers"><t>send a BGP B-MAC withdraw message to the PBB-EVPN peers *or* MAC advertisement with the MAC Mobility extended community</t>


	<t>
   follow existing VPLS MAC Flush procedures with the PBB-VPLS peers</t></list></t>

	</section>

	<section title="MAC Mobility" anchor="section-4.3"><t>
   In PBB-EVPN, a given B-MAC address can be learned either over the BGP
   control plane from a remote PBB-EVPN PE or in the data plane over a
   PW from a remote PBB-VPLS PE. There is no mobility associated with B-MAC
   addresses in this context. Hence, when the same B-MAC address
   shows up behind both a remote PBB-VPLS PE as well as a PBB-EVPN PE,
   the local PE can deduce that it is an anomaly and SHOULD notify the
   operator.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Multicast Operation" anchor="section-4.4"><section title="Ingress Replication" anchor="section-4.4.1"><t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the PBB-VPLS PE using
   ingress replication are per <xref target="RFC7041"/> and <xref target="RFC7080"/>.</t>

	<t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the PBB-EVPN PE for
   ingress replication are as follows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The PBB-EVPN PE builds a replication sub-list per I-SID to all the
     remote PBB-EVPN PEs in a given VPN instance as a result of the
     exchange of the EVPN IMET routes, as described in <xref target="RFC7623"/>. This
     will be referred to as sub-list A. It comprises MP2P service tunnels
     used for delivering PBB-EVPN BUM traffic.</t>

	<t>The PBB-EVPN PE builds a replication sub-list per VPN instance to
     all the remote PBB-VPLS PEs. This will be referred to as sub-list B.
     It comprises PWs from the PBB-EVPN PE in question to all the remote
     PBB-VPLS PEs in the same VPN instance.</t>

	<t>The PBB-EVPN PE may further prune sub-list B on a per-I-SID basis
     by running MMRP (see Clause 10 of <xref target="IEEE.802.1Q"/>) over the PBB-VPLS network. This will be referred to
     as sub-list C. This list comprises a pruned set of the PWs in
     sub-list B.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   The replication list maintained per I-SID on a given PBB-EVPN PE will
   be the union of sub-list A and sub-list B if MMRP  is not used and
   the union of sub-list A and sub-list C if MMRP is used. Note that
   the PE MUST enable split horizon over all the entries in the
   replication list, across both pseudowires and MP2P service tunnels.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="P2MP Tunnel: Inclusive Tree" anchor="section-4.4.2"><t>
   The procedures for multicast operation on the PBB-EVPN PEs using P2MP
   tunnels are outside of the scope of this document.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="section-5"><t>
   All the security considerations in <xref target="RFC4761"/>, <xref target="RFC4762"/>, <xref target="RFC7080"/>,
   <xref target="RFC7432"/>, and <xref target="RFC7623"/> apply directly to this document because it leverages the control-plane and data-plane procedures
   described in those RFCs.</t>

	<t>
   This document does not introduce any new security considerations
   beyond those of the above RFCs because the advertisements and
   processing of MAC addresses in BGP follow <xref
   target="RFC7432"/>, and the processing of MAC addresses learned over PWs
   follows <xref target="RFC4761"/>, <xref target="RFC4762"/>, and <xref target="RFC7080"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-6"><t>
   This document has no IANA actions.</t>

	</section>

	</middle>

	
	<back>


	<references title="Normative References">
	&RFC2119;
	&RFC8174;
	&RFC8077;
	&RFC7432;
	&RFC7623;
	&RFC4761;
	&RFC4762;
	&RFC7041;
	&RFC6074;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">

	&RFC7080;
	&RFC4684;

   <reference anchor="IEEE.802.1Q">

     <front>
       <title>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Network
      -- Bridges and Bridged Networks</title>

       <author>
         <organization>IEEE</organization>
       </author>

       <date month="July" year="2018" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="IEEE Standard" value="802.1Q" />
       <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2018.8403927" />
   </reference>
	
	</references>
	</back>


	</rfc>
	
