<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7387 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7387.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7432 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7432.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7623 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7623.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7385 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7385.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7153 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7153.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6514 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6514.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4360 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3032 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3032.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7796 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7796.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-bess-evpn-inter-subnet-forwarding SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-bess-evpn-inter-subnet-forwarding.xml">
]>

<!-- XML source generated using id2xml December 2017-->

<rfc number="8317"
     submissionType="IETF" 
     consensus="yes"
     category="std" 
     updates="7385">

  <?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="--o*+"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
	
<front>
	<title abbrev="E-Tree Support in EVPN and PBB-EVPN">Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree) Support in Ethernet VPN (EVPN) and Provider Backbone
	Bridging EVPN (PBB-EVPN)</title>
	<author fullname="Ali Sajassi" initials="A." role="editor" surname="Sajassi">
	<organization>Cisco</organization>
	<address><email>sajassi@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Samer Salam" initials="S." surname="Salam">
	<organization>Cisco</organization>
	<address><email>ssalam@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="John Drake" initials="J." surname="Drake">
	<organization>Juniper</organization>
	<address><email>jdrake@juniper.net</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Jim Uttaro" initials="J." surname="Uttaro">
	<organization abbrev="ATT">AT&amp;T</organization>
	<address><email>ju1738@att.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Sami Boutros" initials="S." surname="Boutros">
	<organization>VMware</organization>
	<address><email>sboutros@vmware.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="Jorge Rabadan" initials="J." surname="Rabadan">
	<organization>Nokia</organization>
	<address><email>jorge.rabadan@nokia.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<date month="January" year="2018"/>
	<workgroup>BESS Workgroup</workgroup>

	<abstract><t>

   The MEF Forum (MEF) has defined a rooted-multipoint
   Ethernet service known as Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree). A solution
   framework for supporting this service in MPLS networks is described
   in RFC 7387, "A Framework for Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree) Service over a
   Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Network". This document
   discusses how those functional requirements can be met with a
   solution based on RFC 7432, "BGP MPLS Based Ethernet VPN (EVPN)",
   with some extensions and a description of how such a solution can offer a
   more efficient implementation of these functions than that of RFC
   7796, "Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree) Support in Virtual Private LAN
   Service (VPLS)". This document makes use of the most significant
   bit of the Tunnel Type field (in the P-Multicast Service Interface
   (PMSI) Tunnel attribute) governed by the IANA registry created by
   RFC 7385; hence, it updates RFC 7385 accordingly.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>

	<section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
   The Metro Ethernet Forum (MEF) has defined a rooted-multipoint
   Ethernet service known as Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree) <xref target="MEF6.1"/>. 
In an E-Tree service, a customer site that is typically represented by an
Attachment Circuit (AC) (e.g., an 802.1Q VLAN tag <xref
target="IEEE.802.1Q"/>), is labeled as either a Root or a Leaf site. A
customer site may also be represented by a Media Access Control (MAC) address
along with a VLAN tag.

Root sites can communicate with all other customer sites (both
   Root and Leaf sites). However, Leaf sites can communicate with Root
   sites but not with other Leaf sites. In this document, unless
   explicitly mentioned otherwise, a site is always represented by an
   AC.</t>

	<t>
   <xref target="RFC7387"/> describes a solution framework for supporting E-Tree
   service in MPLS networks. This document identifies the functional components of an overall solution to
emulate E-Tree services in MPLS networks and supplements the
multipoint-to-multipoint Ethernet LAN (E-LAN) services specified in <xref target="RFC7432"/> and <xref target="RFC7623"/>.</t>

	<t>
<xref target="RFC7432"/> defines EVPN, a solution for multipoint Layer 2 Virtual
Private Network (L2VPN) services with advanced multihoming
capabilities that uses BGP for distributing customer/client MAC address
reachability information over the MPLS/IP network. <xref target="RFC7623"/>
	combines the functionality of EVPN with <xref target="IEEE.802.1ah"/>
	Provider Backbone Bridging (PBB) for MAC address scalability.</t>

<t>This document discusses how the functional requirements for
   E-Tree service can be met with a solution based on EVPN <xref
   target="RFC7432"/> and PBB-EVPN <xref target="RFC7623"/> with some extensions to their procedures and
   BGP attributes. Such a solution based on PBB-EVPN or EVPN can offer a more
   efficient implementation of these functions than that of <xref target="RFC7796"/>, "Ethernet-Tree (E-Tree) Support in Virtual Private LAN Service (VPLS)". This efficiency
   is achieved by performing filtering of unicast traffic at the ingress
   Provider Edge (PE) nodes as opposed to egress filtering where the traffic is sent
   through the network and gets filtered and discarded at the egress PE
   nodes. The details of this ingress filtering are described in <xref target="section-3.1"/>.
Since this document specifies a solution based on <xref target="RFC7432"/>,
the knowledge of that document is a prerequisite.
This document makes use of the most significant bit of
   the Tunnel Type field (in the PMSI Tunnel attribute) governed by the
   IANA registry created by <xref target="RFC7385"/>; hence, it updates <xref target="RFC7385"/>
   accordingly. <xref target="section-2"/> discusses E-Tree
   scenarios, Sections <xref target="section-3" format="counter"/> and <xref
   target="section-4" format="counter"/>
   describe E-Tree solutions for EVPN and PBB-EVPN (respectively), and
   <xref target="section-5"/> covers BGP encoding for E-Tree solutions.</t>
 </section>

<section title="Terminology" anchor="new-section2">
	<section title="Specification of Requirements" anchor="section-1.1">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
	</section>

	<section title="Terms and Abbreviations" anchor="section-1.2">
<t><list style="hanging">

<t hangText="Broadcast Domain:">In a bridged network, the broadcast domain
   corresponds to a Virtual LAN (VLAN), where a VLAN is typically
   represented by a single VLAN ID (VID) but can be represented by
   several VIDs where Shared VLAN Learning (SVL) is used per <xref target="IEEE.802.1ah"/>.</t>

<t hangText="Bridge Table:">An instantiation of a broadcast domain on a MAC-VRF.</t>

<t hangText="CE:">A Customer Edge device, e.g., a host, router, or switch.</t>

<t hangText="EVI:">An EVPN Instance spanning the Provider Edge (PE) devices
   participating in that EVPN.</t>

<t hangText="MAC-VRF:">A Virtual Routing and Forwarding table for Media Access
   Control (MAC) addresses on a PE.</t>

<t hangText="ES:">When a customer site (device or network) is
   connected to one or more PEs via a set of Ethernet links, then that
   set of links is referred to as an "Ethernet Segment".</t>

<t hangText="ESI:">An Ethernet Segment Identifier is a unique non-zero identifier that
   identifies an ES.</t>

<t hangText="Ethernet Tag:">An Ethernet Tag identifies a particular broadcast
   domain, e.g., a VLAN.  An EVPN instance consists of one or more
   broadcast domains.</t>

<t hangText="P2MP:">Point-to-Multipoint.</t>

<t hangText="PE:">Provider Edge device.</t>
</list></t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="E-Tree Scenarios" anchor="section-2"><t>
   This document categorizes E-Tree scenarios into the following three
   categories, depending on the nature of the Root/Leaf site association:</t>

	<t><list style="format Scenario %d:">
	<t>either Leaf or Root site(s) per PE;</t>

	<t>either Leaf or Root site(s) per Attachment Circuit (AC); or,</t>

	<t>either Leaf or Root site(s) per MAC address.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<section title="Scenario 1: Leaf or Root Site(s) per PE" anchor="section-2.1"><t>
   In this scenario, a PE may receive traffic from either Root ACs or
   Leaf ACs for a given MAC-VRF/bridge table, but not both. In other
   words, a given EVPN Instance (EVI) on a Provider Edge (PE) device is
   either associated with Root(s) or Leaf(s). The PE may have both Root
   and Leaf ACs, albeit for different EVIs.</t>


	<figure title="Scenario 1" anchor="ref-scenario-1"><artwork><![CDATA[
                +---------+            +---------+
                |   PE1   |            |   PE2   |
 +---+          |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  |            +---+
 |CE1+---AC1----+--+   |  |  | MPLS |  |  |   +--+----AC2-----+CE2|
 +---+  (Root)  |  |MAC|  |  |  /IP |  |  |MAC|  |   (Leaf)   +---+
                |  |VRF|  |  |      |  |  |VRF|  |
                |  |   |  |  |      |  |  |   |  |            +---+
                |  |   |  |  |      |  |  |   +--+----AC3-----+CE3|
                |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  |   (Leaf)   +---+
                +---------+            +---------+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   In this scenario, tailored BGP Route Target (RT) import/export
   policies among the PEs belonging to the same EVI can be used to
   prevent communication among Leaf PEs. To prevent
   communication among Leaf ACs connected to the same PE and belonging
   to the same EVI, split-horizon filtering is used to block traffic
   from one Leaf AC to another Leaf AC on a MAC-VRF for a given E-Tree
   EVI. The purpose of this topology constraint is to avoid having PEs
   with only  Leaf sites importing and processing BGP MAC routes from
   each other. To support such a topology constraint in EVPN, two BGP
   RTs are used for every EVI: one RT is
   associated with the Root sites (Root ACs) and the other is associated
   with the Leaf sites (Leaf ACs). On a per-EVI basis, every PE exports
   the single RT associated with its type of site(s). Furthermore, a PE
   with a Root site(s) imports both Root and Leaf RTs, whereas a PE with a Leaf site(s) only imports the Root RT.</t>

	<t>
   For this scenario, if it is desired to use only a single RT per EVI
   (just like E-LAN services in <xref target="RFC7432"/>), then approach B in
   Scenario 2 (described below) needs to be used.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Scenario 2: Leaf or Root Site(s) per AC" anchor="section-2.2"><t>
   In this scenario, a PE can receive traffic from both Root ACs and
   Leaf ACs for a given EVI. In other words, a given EVI on a PE can be
   associated with both Root(s) and Leaf(s).</t>

	<figure title="Scenario 2" anchor="ref-scenario-2"><artwork><![CDATA[
                  +---------+            +---------+
                  |   PE1   |            |   PE2   |
 +---+            |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  |        +---+
 |CE1+-----AC1----+--+   |  |  |      |  |  |   +--+---AC2--+CE2|
 +---+    (Leaf)  |  |MAC|  |  | MPLS |  |  |MAC|  | (Leaf) +---+
                  |  |VRF|  |  |  /IP |  |  |VRF|  |
                  |  |   |  |  |      |  |  |   |  |        +---+
                  |  |   |  |  |      |  |  |   +--+---AC3--+CE3|
                  |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  | (Root) +---+
                  +---------+            +---------+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   In this scenario, (as in Scenario 1 <xref target="section-2.1"/>),
   two RTs (one for Root and another for Leaf) can be used.
   However, the difference is that on a PE with both Root and Leaf ACs,
   all remote MAC routes are imported; thus, in order to apply the proper
   ingress filtering, there needs to be a way
   to differentiate remote MAC routes associated with Leaf ACs versus
   the ones associated with Root ACs.</t>

	<t>
   In order to recognize the association of a destination MAC address to
   a Leaf or Root AC and, thus, support ingress filtering on the ingress
   PE with both Leaf and Root ACs, MAC addresses need to be colored with a 
   Root or Leaf-Indication before advertising to other PEs. There are
   two approaches for such coloring:</t>

	<t><list style="format (%C)">
   <t>to always use two RTs (one to designate Leaf RT and another for
   Root RT), or</t>

	<t>to allow for a single RT to be used per EVI, just like <xref target="RFC7432"/>, and,
   thus, color MAC addresses via a "color" flag in a new extended
   community as detailed in <xref target="section-5.1"/>.</t>
 </list></t>

	<t>
   Approach A would require the same data-plane enhancements as
   approach B if MAC-VRF and bridge tables used per VLAN are to
   remain consistent with Section 6 of <xref target="RFC7432"/>. In order to avoid data-plane enhancements for approach A, multiple bridge tables per VLAN
   may be considered; however, this has major drawbacks (as described in
   Appendix A); thus, it is not recommended.</t>

	<t>
   Given that both approaches A and B would require the same
   data-plane enhancements, approach B is chosen here in order to
   allow for RT usage consistent with baseline EVPN <xref
   target="RFC7432"/> and for better generality. It should be noted
   that if one wants to use RT constraints in order to avoid MAC
   advertisements associated with a Leaf AC to PEs with only Leaf ACs,
   then two RTs (one for Root and another for Leaf) can still be used
   with approach B; however, in such applications, Leaf/Root RTs will
   be used to constrain MAC advertisements and are not used to color
   the MAC routes for ingress filtering (i.e., in approach B, the
   coloring is always done via the new extended community).</t>

	<t>
   If, for a given EVI, a significant number of PEs have both Leaf and
   Root sites attached (even though they may start as Root-only or Leaf-only PEs), then a single RT per EVI should be used. The reason for such a 
   recommendation is to alleviate the configuration overhead
   associated with using two RTs per EVI at the expense of having some
   unwanted MAC addresses on the Leaf-only PEs.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Scenario 3: Leaf or Root Site(s) per MAC Address" anchor="section-2.3"><t>
In this scenario, a customer Root or Leaf site is represented by a MAC address
on an AC and a PE may receive traffic from both Root and Leaf sites on that AC
for an EVI.

This scenario is
   not covered in either <xref target="RFC7387"/> or <xref target="MEF6.1"/>; however, it is covered
   in this document for the sake of completeness. In this scenario,
   since an AC carries traffic from both Root and Leaf sites, the
   granularity at which Root or Leaf sites are identified is on a per-MAC-address basis. 

This scenario is considered in this document for EVPN
   service with only known unicast traffic because the Designated
   Forwarder (DF) filtering per <xref target="RFC7432"/> would not be compatible with
   the required egress filtering; that is, Broadcast, Unknown Unicast, and
   Multicast (BUM) traffic is not supported in this scenario; it is
   dropped by the ingress PE.</t>

	<t>
   For this scenario, the approach B in Scenario 2 is
   used in order to allow for single RT usage by service providers.</t>

	<figure title="Scenario 3" anchor="figure-3"><artwork><![CDATA[
                  +---------+            +---------+
                  |   PE1   |            |   PE2   |
 +---+            |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  |            +---+
 |CE1+-----AC1----+--+   |  |  |      |  |  |   +--+-----AC2----+CE2|
 +---+    (Root)  |  | E |  |  | MPLS |  |  | E |  | (Leaf/Root)+---+
                  |  | V |  |  |  /IP |  |  | V |  |
                  |  | I |  |  |      |  |  | I |  |            +---+
                  |  |   |  |  |      |  |  |   +--+-----AC3----+CE3|
                  |  +---+  |  +------+  |  +---+  |   (Leaf)   +---+
                  +---------+            +---------+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

<t>In conclusion, the approach B in scenario 2 is the recommended approach
across all the above three scenarios, and the corresponding solution is
detailed in the following sections.</t>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Operation for EVPN" anchor="section-3"><t>
   <xref target="RFC7432"/> defines the notion of the Ethernet Segment Identifier (ESI)
   MPLS label used for split-horizon filtering of BUM traffic at the
   egress PE. Such egress filtering capabilities can be leveraged in
   provision of E-Tree services, as it will be seen shortly for BUM
   traffic. For known unicast traffic, additional extensions to <xref target="RFC7432"/>
   are needed (i.e., a new BGP extended community for Leaf-Indication
   described in <xref target="section-5.1"/>) in order to enable ingress filtering as
   described in detail in the following sections.</t>

	<section title="Known Unicast Traffic" anchor="section-3.1"><t>
   In EVPN, MAC learning is performed in the control plane via
   advertisement of BGP routes. Because of this, the filtering needed by an E-Tree service
   for known unicast traffic can be performed at the ingress PE, thus
   providing very efficient filtering and avoiding sending known unicast
   traffic over the MPLS/IP core to be filtered at the egress PE, as is done
   in traditional E-Tree solutions (i.e., E-Tree for VPLS <xref target="RFC7796"/>).</t>

	<t>
   To provide such ingress filtering for known unicast traffic, a PE
   MUST indicate to other PEs what kind of sites (Root or Leaf) its MAC
   addresses are associated with. This is done by advertising a Leaf-Indication flag (via an extended community) along with each of its
   MAC/IP Advertisement routes learned from a Leaf site. The lack of
   such a flag indicates that the MAC address is associated with a Root
   site. This scheme applies to all scenarios described in <xref target="section-2"/>.</t>

	<t>
   Tagging MAC addresses with a Leaf-Indication enables remote PEs to
   perform ingress filtering for known unicast traffic; that is, on
   the ingress PE, the MAC destination address lookup yields (in
   addition to the forwarding adjacency) a flag that indicates whether
   or not the target MAC is associated with a Leaf site. The ingress
   PE cross-checks this flag with the status of the originating AC,
   and if both are Leafs, then the packet is not forwarded.</t>

	<t>
   In a situation where MAC moves are allowed among Leaf and Root sites
   (e.g., non-static MAC), PEs can receive multiple MAC/IP
   Advertisement routes for the same MAC address with different
   Root or Leaf-Indications (and possibly different ESIs for multihoming
   scenarios). In such situations, MAC mobility procedures (see Section 15
   of <xref target="RFC7432"/>) take precedence to first identify the location of the
   MAC before associating that MAC with a Root or a Leaf site.</t>

	<t>
   To support the above ingress filtering functionality, a new E-Tree
   extended community with a Leaf-Indication flag is introduced (see <xref target="section-5.1"/>). This new extended community MUST be advertised with MAC/IP
   Advertisement routes learned from a Leaf site. 
Besides MAC/IP Advertisement routes, no other EVPN routes are required to
carry this new extended community for the purpose of known unicast traffic.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="BUM Traffic" anchor="section-3.2"><t>
   This specification does not provide support for filtering 
   Broadcast, Unknown Unicast, and Multicast (BUM) traffic on the ingress PE; due to
   the multidestination nature of BUM traffic, it is not possible to
   perform filtering of the same on the ingress PE. As such, the
   solution relies on egress filtering. In order to apply the proper
   egress filtering, which varies based on whether a packet is sent from
   a Leaf AC or a Root AC, the MPLS-encapsulated frames MUST be tagged
   with an indication of when they originated from a Leaf AC (i.e., to be
   tagged with a Leaf label as specified in <xref target="section-5.1"/>). This Leaf label
   allows for disposition PE (e.g., egress PE) to perform the necessary
   egress filtering function in a data plane similar to the ESI label in
   <xref target="RFC7432"/>. The allocation of the Leaf label is on a per-PE basis
   (e.g., independent of ESI and EVI) as described in the following
   sections.</t>

	<t>
   The Leaf label can be upstream assigned for Point-to-Multipoint (P2MP)
   Label Switched Path (LSP) or downstream
   assigned for Ingress Replication tunnels. The main difference between
   a downstream- and upstream-assigned Leaf label is that, in the case of
   downstream-assigned Leaf labels, not all egress PE devices need to receive the
   label in MPLS-encapsulated BUM packets, just like the ESI label for
   Ingress Replication procedures defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/>.</t>

	<t>
   On the ingress PE, the PE needs to place all its Leaf ACs for a given
   bridge domain in a single split-horizon group in order to prevent
   intra-PE forwarding among its Leaf ACs. This intra-PE split-horizon
   filtering applies to BUM traffic as well as known unicast traffic.</t>

	<t>
   There are four scenarios to consider as follows. In all these
   scenarios, the ingress PE imposes the right MPLS label associated
   with the originated Ethernet Segment (ES) depending on whether the
   Ethernet frame originated from a Root or a Leaf site on that Ethernet
   Segment (ESI label or Leaf label). 

The mechanism by which the PE identifies whether a given frame originated from
a Root or a Leaf site on the segment is based on the AC identifier for that
segment (e.g., Ethernet Tag of the frame for 802.1Q frames <xref target="IEEE.802.1Q"/>).

Other mechanisms
   for identifying Root or Leaf sites, such as the use of the source MAC
   address of the receiving frame, are optional. The scenarios below are
   described in context of a Root/Leaf AC, however, they can be extended
   to the Root/Leaf MAC address if needed.</t>

	<section title="BUM Traffic Originated from a Single-Homed Site on a Leaf AC" anchor="section-3.2.1"><t>
   In this scenario, the ingress PE adds a Leaf label advertised using
   the E-Tree extended community (see <xref target="section-5.1"/>), which indicates a Leaf site.
   This Leaf label, used for single-homing scenarios, is not on a per-ES basis but rather on a per PE basis (i.e., a single Leaf MPLS label
   is used for all single-homed ESs on that PE). This Leaf label is
   advertised to other PE devices using the E-Tree extended community
   (see <xref target="section-5.1"/>) along with an Ethernet Auto-Discovery per ES (EAD-ES)
   route with an ESI of zero and a set of RTs corresponding
   to all EVIs on the PE where each EVI has at least one Leaf site.
   Multiple EAD-ES routes will need to be advertised if the number of
   RTs that need to be carried exceed the limit on a
   single route per <xref target="RFC7432"/>. The ESI for the EAD-ES route is set to
   zero to indicate single-homed sites.</t>

	<t>
   When a PE receives this special Leaf label in the data path, it
   blocks the packet if the destination AC is of type Leaf; otherwise,
   it forwards the packet.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="BUM Traffic Originated from a Single-Homed Site on a Root AC" anchor="section-3.2.2"><t>
   In this scenario, the ingress PE does not add any ESI or Leaf
   labels and it operates per the procedures in <xref target="RFC7432"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="BUM Traffic Originated from a Multihomed Site on a Leaf AC" anchor="section-3.2.3"><t>
   In this scenario, it is assumed that while different ACs (VLANs) on
   the same ES could have a different Root/Leaf designation (some being
   Roots and some being Leafs), the same VLAN does have the same
   Root/Leaf designation on all PEs on the same ES. Furthermore, it is
   assumed that there is no forwarding among subnets (i.e., the service
   is EVPN L2 and not EVPN Integrated Routing and Bridging (IRB) <xref target="EVPN-INTEGRATED"/>). IRB use cases described in
   <xref target="EVPN-INTEGRATED"/> are outside the scope of this document.</t>

	<t>
   In this scenario, if a multicast or broadcast packet is originated
   from a Leaf AC, then it only needs to carry a Leaf label as described in
   <xref target="section-3.2.1"/>. This label is sufficient in providing the necessary
   egress filtering of BUM traffic from getting sent to Leaf ACs,
   including the Leaf AC on the same ES.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="BUM Traffic Originated from a Multihomed Site on a Root AC" anchor="section-3.2.4"><t>
   In this scenario, both the ingress and egress PE devices follow the
   procedure defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/> for adding and/or processing an ESI
   MPLS label; that is, existing procedures for BUM traffic in <xref target="RFC7432"/>
   are sufficient and there is no need to add a Leaf label.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="E-Tree Traffic Flows for EVPN" anchor="section-3.3"><t>
   Per <xref target="RFC7387"/>, a generic E-Tree service supports all of the following
   traffic flows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols">
	<t>known unicast traffic from Root to Roots &amp; Leafs</t>

	<t>known unicast traffic from Leaf to Roots</t>

	<t>BUM traffic from Root to Roots &amp; Leafs</t>

	<t>BUM traffic from Leaf to Roots</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   A particular E-Tree service may need to support all of the above
   types of flows or only a select subset, depending on the target
   application. In the case where only multicast and broadcast flows
   need to be supported, the L2VPN PEs can avoid performing any MAC
   learning function.</t>

	<t>
   The following subsections will describe the operation of EVPN to
   support E-Tree service with and without MAC learning.</t>

	<section title="E-Tree with MAC Learning" anchor="section-3.3.1"><t>
   The PEs implementing an E-Tree service must perform MAC learning when
   unicast traffic flows must be supported among Root and Leaf sites. In
   this case, the PE(s) with Root sites performs MAC learning in the
   data path over the ESs and advertises reachability in
   EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement routes. These routes will be imported by
   all PEs for that EVI (i.e., PEs that have Leaf sites as well as PEs
   that have Root sites). Similarly, the PEs with Leaf sites perform MAC
   learning in the data path over their ESs and advertise
   reachability in EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement routes. For scenarios where
   two different RTs are used per EVI (one to designate a Root site and
   another to designate a Leaf site), the MAC/IP Advertisement routes are
   imported only by PEs with at least one Root site in the EVI (i.e., a
   PE with only Leaf sites will not import these routes). PEs with Root
   and/or Leaf sites may use the Ethernet Auto-Discovery per EVI (EAD-EVI) 
   routes for aliasing (in the case of multihomed segments) and
   EAD-ES routes for mass MAC withdrawal per <xref target="RFC7432"/>.</t>

	<t>
   To support multicast/broadcast from Root to Leaf sites, either a P2MP
   tree rooted at the PE(s) with the Root site(s) (e.g., Root PEs) or
   Ingress Replication can be used (see Section 16 of <xref target="RFC7432"/>). The
   multicast tunnels are set up through the exchange of the EVPN
   Inclusive Multicast route, as defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/>.</t>

	<t>
   To support multicast/broadcast from Leaf to Root sites, either
   Ingress Replication tunnels from each Leaf PE or a P2MP tree rooted
   at each Leaf PE can be used. The following two paragraphs describe
   when each of these tunneling schemes can be used and how to signal
   them.</t>

	<t>
   When there are only a few Root PEs with small amount of
   multicast/broadcast traffic from Leaf PEs toward Root PEs, then
   Ingress Replication tunnels from Leaf PEs toward Root PEs should be
   sufficient. Therefore, if a Root PE needs to support a P2MP tunnel in the 
   transmit direction from itself to Leaf PEs, and, at the same time, it
   wants to support Ingress Replication tunnels in the receive direction,
   the Root PE can signal it efficiently by using a new composite tunnel
   type defined in <xref target="section-5.2"/>.  This new composite tunnel type is
   advertised by the Root PE to simultaneously indicate a P2MP tunnel in the 
   transmit direction and an Ingress Replication tunnel in the receive
   direction for the BUM traffic.</t>

	<t>
   If the number of Root PEs is large, P2MP tunnels (e.g., Multipoint LDP
   (mLDP) or RSVP-TE) originated at the Leaf PEs may be used; thus, there will be no
   need to use the modified PMSI Tunnel attribute and the composite
   tunnel type values defined in <xref target="section-5.2"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="E-Tree without MAC Learning" anchor="section-3.3.2"><t>
   The PEs implementing an E-Tree service need not perform MAC learning
   when the traffic flows between Root and Leaf sites are mainly
   multicast or broadcast. In this case, the PEs do not exchange EVPN
   MAC/IP Advertisement routes. Instead, the Inclusive Multicast
   Ethernet Tag route is used to support BUM traffic. In such scenarios,
   the small amount of unicast traffic (if any) is sent as part of BUM
   traffic.</t>

	<t>
   The fields of this route are populated per the procedures defined in
   <xref target="RFC7432"/>, and the multicast tunnel setup criteria are as described
   in the previous section.</t>

	<t>
   Just as in the previous section, if the number of Root PEs are only a
   few and, thus, Ingress Replication is desired from Leaf PEs to these
   Root PEs, then the modified PMSI attribute and the composite tunnel
   type values defined in <xref target="section-5.2"/> should be used.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Operation for PBB-EVPN" anchor="section-4"><t>
   In PBB-EVPN, the PE advertises a Root or Leaf-Indication along with each
   Backbone MAC (B-MAC) Advertisement route to indicate whether the associated B-MAC
   address corresponds to a Root or a Leaf site. Just like the EVPN
   case, the new E-Tree extended community defined in <xref target="section-5.1"/> is
   advertised with each EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement route.</t>

	<t>
   In the case where a multihomed ES has both Root and
   Leaf sites attached, two B-MAC addresses are advertised: one B-MAC
   address is per ES (as specified in <xref target="RFC7623"/>) and implicitly
   denotes Root, and the other B-MAC address is per PE and explicitly denotes
   Leaf. The former B-MAC address is not advertised with the E-Tree
   extended community, but the latter B-MAC denoting Leaf is advertised
   with the new E-Tree extended community where a "Leaf-indication" flag
   is set. In multihoming scenarios where an ES has both
   Root and Leaf ACs, it is assumed that while different ACs (VLANs) on
   the same ES could have a different Root/Leaf designation (some being
   Roots and some being Leafs), the same VLAN does have the same
   Root/Leaf designation on all PEs on the same ES. Furthermore, it is
   assumed that there is no forwarding among subnets (i.e., the service
   is L2 and not IRB). An IRB use case is outside the scope of this
   document.</t>

	<t>
   The ingress PE uses the right B-MAC source address depending on
   whether the Ethernet frame originated from the Root or Leaf AC on
   that ES. The mechanism by which the PE identifies
   whether a given frame originated from a Root or Leaf site on the
   segment is based on the Ethernet Tag associated with the frame. Other
   mechanisms of identification, beyond the Ethernet Tag, are outside
   the scope of this document.</t>

	<t>
   Furthermore, a PE advertises two special global B-MAC addresses, one
   for Root and another for Leaf, and tags the Leaf one as such in the
   MAC Advertisement route. These B-MAC addresses are used as source
   addresses for traffic originating from single-homed segments. The B-MAC address used for indicating Leaf sites can be the same for both
   single-homed and multihomed segments.</t>

	<section title="Known Unicast Traffic" anchor="section-4.1"><t>
   For known unicast traffic, the PEs perform ingress filtering: on the
   ingress PE, the Customer/Client MAC (C-MAC) <xref target="RFC7623"/> destination address lookup yields, in
   addition to the target B-MAC address and forwarding adjacency, a flag
   that indicates whether the target B-MAC is associated with a Root or
   a Leaf site. The ingress PE also checks the status of the originating
   site; if both are Leafs, then the packet is not forwarded.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="BUM Traffic" anchor="section-4.2"><t>
   For BUM traffic, the PEs must perform egress filtering. When a PE
   receives an EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement route (which will be used as a
   source B-MAC for BUM traffic), it updates its egress filtering (based
   on the source B-MAC address) as follows:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>If the EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement route indicates that the
     advertised B-MAC is a Leaf, and the local ES is a Leaf
     as well, then the source B-MAC address is added to its B-MAC list
     used for egress filtering (i.e., to block traffic from that B-MAC
     address). Otherwise, the B-MAC filtering list is not updated.</t>

	<t>If the EVPN MAC/IP Advertisement route indicates that the
     advertised B-MAC has changed its designation from a Leaf to a Root,
     and the local ES is a Leaf, then the source B-MAC
     address is removed from the B-MAC list corresponding to the local
     ES used for egress filtering (i.e., to unblock traffic
     from that B-MAC address).</t>

	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
   When the egress PE receives the packet, it examines the B-MAC source
   address to check whether it should filter or forward the frame. 

Note that this uses the same filtering logic as the split-horizon filtering
described in Section 6.2.1.3 of <xref target="RFC7623"/> and does not require any additional flags in the data
	plane.</t>

	<t>
   Just as in <xref target="section-3.2"/>, the PE places all Leaf ESs of a
   given bridge domain in a single split-horizon group in order to
   prevent intra-PE forwarding among Leaf segments. This split-horizon
   function applies to BUM traffic as well as known unicast traffic.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="E-Tree without MAC Learning" anchor="section-4.3"><t>
   In scenarios where the traffic of interest is only multicast and/or
   broadcast, the PEs implementing an E-Tree service do not need to do
   any MAC learning. In such scenarios, the filtering must be performed
   on egress PEs. For PBB-EVPN, the handling of such traffic is per
   <xref target="section-4.2"/> without the need for C-MAC learning (in the data
   plane) in the I-component (C-bridge table) of PBB-EVPN PEs (at both ingress and
   egress PEs).</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="BGP Encoding" anchor="section-5"><t>
   This document defines a new BGP extended community for EVPN.</t>

	<section title="E-Tree Extended Community" anchor="section-5.1"><t>
   This extended community is a new transitive extended community
   <xref target="RFC4360"/> having a Type field value of 0x06 (EVPN) and the Sub-Type
   0x05. It is used for Leaf-Indication of known unicast and BUM
   traffic. It indicates that the frame is originated from a Leaf site.</t>

	<t>
   The E-Tree extended community is encoded as an 8-octet value as
   follows:</t>

	<figure title="E-Tree Extended Community" anchor="ref-e-tree-extended-community"><artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Type=0x06     | Sub-Type=0x05 | Flags(1 Octet)|  Reserved=0   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  Reserved=0   |           Leaf Label                          |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>The Flags field has the following format:</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |     MBZ     |L|     (MBZ = MUST Be Zero)
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>This document defines the following flags:</t>
<t><list>
    <t>+ Leaf-Indication (L)</t>
   </list></t>
	<t>
   A value of one indicates a Leaf AC/site. The rest of the flag bits are
   reserved and should be set to zero.</t>

	<t>
   When this extended community is advertised along with the MAC/IP
   Advertisement route (for known unicast traffic) per <xref target="section-3.1"/>, the
   Leaf-Indication flag MUST be set to one and the Leaf label SHOULD be set
   to zero. The receiving PE MUST ignore Leaf label and only process the
   Leaf-Indication flag. A value of zero for the Leaf-Indication flag is
   invalid when sent along with a MAC/IP Advertisement route, and an error
   should be logged.</t>

	<t>
   When this extended community is advertised along with the EAD-ES route (with an ESI of zero)
   for BUM traffic to enable egress filtering on disposition PEs per Sections 
   <xref target="section-3.2.1" format="counter"/> and <xref
   target="section-3.2.3" format="counter"/>, the Leaf label MUST be set to a valid MPLS
   label (i.e., a non-reserved, assigned MPLS label <xref target="RFC3032"/>) and the
   Leaf-Indication flag SHOULD be set to zero. The value of the 20-bit
   MPLS label is encoded in the high-order 20 bits of the Leaf label
   field. The receiving PE MUST ignore the Leaf-Indication flag. A non-valid
   MPLS label, when sent along with the EAD-ES route, should be
   ignored and logged as an error.</t>

	<t>
   The reserved bits SHOULD be set to zero by the transmitter and MUST
   be ignored by the receiver.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="PMSI Tunnel Attribute" anchor="section-5.2"><t>
   <xref target="RFC6514"/> defines the PMSI Tunnel attribute, which is an optional
   transitive attribute with the following format:</t>

	<texttable title="PMSI Tunnel Attribute" anchor="ref-pmsi-tunnel-attribute" style="all"><ttcol> Flags (1 octet)</ttcol>
	<c>Tunnel Type (1 octet)</c>
	<c>Ingress Replication MPLS Label (3 octets)</c>
	<c>Tunnel Identifier (variable)</c>
	</texttable>
	<t>
   This document defines a new composite tunnel type by introducing a
   new 'composite tunnel' bit in the Tunnel Type field and adding an MPLS
   label to the Tunnel Identifier field of the PMSI Tunnel attribute, as
   detailed below. All other fields remain as defined in <xref target="RFC6514"/>.
   Composite tunnel type is advertised by the Root PE to simultaneously
   indicate a non-Ingress-Replication tunnel (e.g., P2MP tunnel) in the 
   transmit direction and an Ingress Replication tunnel in the receive
   direction for the BUM traffic.</t>

	<t>
   When receiver Ingress Replication labels are needed, the high-order
   bit of the Tunnel Type field (composite tunnel bit) is set while the
   remaining low-order seven bits indicate the Tunnel Type as before
   (for the existing Tunnel Types). When this composite tunnel bit is
   set, the "tunnel identifier" field begins with a three-octet label,
   followed by the actual tunnel identifier for the transmit tunnel.
   PEs that don't understand the new meaning of the high-order bit treat
   the Tunnel Type as an undefined Tunnel Type and treat the PMSI Tunnel
   attribute as a malformed attribute <xref target="RFC6514"/>. That is why the
   composite tunnel bit is allocated in the Tunnel Type field rather
   than the Flags field. For the PEs that do understand the new meaning
   of the high-order, if Ingress Replication is desired when sending BUM
   traffic, the PE will use the label in the Tunnel Identifier field
   when sending its BUM traffic.</t>

	<t>
   Using the composite tunnel bit for Tunnel Types 0x00 'no tunnel
   information present' and 0x06 'Ingress Replication' is invalid. A
   PE that receives a PMSI Tunnel attribute with such information
   considers it malformed, and it SHOULD treat this Update as though
   all the routes contained in this Update had been withdrawn per
   <xref target="section-5"/> of <xref target="RFC6514"/>.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="section-7"><t>
   Since this document uses the EVPN constructs of <xref target="RFC7432"/> and
   <xref target="RFC7623"/>, the same security considerations in these documents are
   also applicable here. Furthermore, this document provides an
   additional security check by allowing sites (or ACs) of an EVPN
   instance to be designated as a "Root" or "Leaf" by the network
   operator / service provider and thus prevent any traffic exchange
   among "Leaf" sites of that VPN through ingress filtering for known
   unicast traffic and egress filtering for BUM traffic. Since (by
   default and for the purpose of backward compatibility) an AC that
   doesn't have a Leaf designation is considered a Root AC, in order
   to avoid any traffic exchange among Leaf ACs, the operator SHOULD
   configure the AC with a proper role (Leaf or Root) before activating
   the AC.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-8"><t>
   IANA has allocated sub-type value 5 in the "EVPN Extended Community Sub-Types"
   registry defined in <xref target="RFC7153"/> as follows:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      SUB-TYPE VALUE     NAME                        Reference
      --------------     -------------------------   -------------
      0x05               E-Tree Extended Community   This document
]]></artwork></figure>
   
	<t>
   This document creates a one-octet registry called "E-Tree Flags".
   New registrations will be made through the "RFC Required" procedure
   defined in <xref target="RFC8126"/>.  Initial registrations are as follows:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      Bit               Name                         Reference
      ----              --------------               -------------
      0-6               Unassigned
      7                 Leaf-Indication              This document
]]></artwork></figure>


	<section title="Considerations for PMSI Tunnel Types" anchor="section-8.1"><t>


   The "P-Multicast Service Interface (PMSI) Tunnel Types"
   registry in the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Parameters" registry
   has been updated to reflect the use of the most significant bit as the
   "composite tunnel" bit (see <xref target="section-5.2"/>).</t>

	<t>
   For this purpose, this document updates <xref target="RFC7385"/> by changing the
   previously unassigned values (i.e., 0x08 - 0xFA) as follows:</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Value          Meaning                            Reference
---------      -----------------------------      --------------
0x0C-0x7A      Unassigned
0x7B-0x7E      Experimental                       This Document
0x7F           Reserved                           This Document
0x80-0xFA      Reserved for Composite Tunnel      This Document
0xFB-0xFE      Experimental                       [RFC7385]
0xFF           Reserved                           [RFC7385]
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   The allocation policy for values 0x08-0x7A is per IETF Review
   <xref target="RFC8126"/>. The range for "Experimental" has been expanded to include
   the previously assigned range of 0xFB-0xFE and the new range of 0x7B-
   0x7E. The values in these ranges are not to be assigned. The value
   0x7F, which is the mirror image of (0xFF), is reserved in this
   document.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">

<reference  anchor='RFC2119' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>

&RFC8174;
	&RFC8126;
	&RFC7387;

	<reference anchor="MEF6.1" target="https://mef.net/PDF_Documents/technical-specifications/MEF6-1.pdf"><front>
	<title>Ethernet Services Definitions - Phase 2</title>
	<author>
	<organization>MEF Forum</organization>
	</author>

	<date month="April" year="2008"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="MEF" value="6.1"/>
	</reference>

	&RFC7432;
	&RFC7623;
	&RFC7385;
	&RFC7153;
	&RFC6514;
	&RFC4360;

	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	&RFC3032;
	&RFC7796;

<!--draft-ietf-bess-evpn-inter-subnet-forwarding-03: I-D Expired-->
<reference anchor='EVPN-INTEGRATED'>
<front>
<title>Integrated Routing and Bridging in EVPN</title>

<author initials='A' surname='Sajassi' fullname='Ali Sajassi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Salam' fullname='Samer Salam'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Thoria' fullname='Samir Thoria'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Drake' fullname='John Drake'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Rabadan' fullname='Jorge Rabadan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Yong' fullname='Lucy Yong'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>EVPN provides an extensible and flexible multi-homing VPN solution for intra-subnet connectivity among hosts/VMs over an MPLS/IP network. However, there are scenarios in which inter-subnet forwarding among hosts/VMs across different IP subnets is required, while maintaining the multi-homing capabilities of EVPN. This document describes an Integrated Routing and Bridging (IRB) solution based on EVPN to address such requirements.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-bess-evpn-inter-subnet-forwarding-03' />

</reference>

<reference anchor="IEEE.802.1Q">
<front>
<title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Bridges and
Bridged Networks - Media Access Control (MAC) Bridges and Virtual Bridged
Local Area Networks</title>
<author><organization>IEEE</organization></author>
<date/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="Std 802.1Q"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value=" 10.1109/IEEESTD.2011.6009146"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="IEEE.802.1ah">
<front>
<title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Media Access
Control (MAC) Bridges and Virtual Bridged Local Area Networks</title>
<author><organization>IEEE</organization></author>
<date/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Clauses 25 and 26," value="IEEE Std 802.1Q"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2011.6009146"/>
</reference>

	</references>

	<section title="Multiple Bridge Tables per E-Tree Service Instance" anchor="section-a"><t>
   When two MAC-VRFs (two bridge tables per VLAN) are used for an E-Tree service (one for Root ACs and another for Leaf ACs) on a given
   PE, then the following complications in a data-plane path can result.</t>

	<t>
   Maintaining two MAC-VRFs (two bridge tables) per VLAN (when both Leaf
   and Root ACs exists for that VLAN) would require either
  that two lookups be performed per MAC address in each direction in case of a miss or
  that the duplication of many MAC addresses between the two bridge tables
   belonging to the same VLAN (same E-Tree instance) be made. Unless two lookups
   are made, duplication of MAC addresses would be needed for both
   locally learned and remotely learned MAC addresses. Locally learned
   MAC addresses from Leaf ACs need to be duplicated onto a Root bridge
   table, and locally learned MAC addresses from Root ACs need to be
   duplicated onto a Leaf bridge table. Remotely learned MAC addresses
   from Root ACs need to be copied onto both Root and Leaf bridge
   tables. Because of potential inefficiencies associated with data-plane implementation of additional MAC lookup or duplication of MAC
   entries, this option is not believed to be implementable without
   data-plane performance inefficiencies in some platforms; thus, this
   document introduces the coloring as described in  <xref
   target="section-2.2" /> and
   detailed in <xref target="section-3.1"/>.</t>

	</section>

        <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks" numbered="no">
	  <t>We would like
        to thank Eric Rosen, Jeffrey Zhang, Wen Lin, Aldrin Issac, Wim
        Henderickx, Dennis Cai, and Antoni Przygienda for their valuable
        comments and contributions. The authors would also like to thank
        Thomas Morin for shepherding this document and providing valuable
        comments.</t>
        </section>

	</back>

	</rfc>
	
