<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
<!ENTITY rfc1195 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5304 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5304.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5305 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5310 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5310.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5443 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5443.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5120 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5120.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5817 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5817.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5919 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5919.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6138 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6138.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7645 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7645.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8126 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc number="8500" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Reverse Metric">
      IS-IS Routing with Reverse Metric
    </title>

    <author fullname="Naiming Shen" initials="N."
            surname="Shen">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>560 McCarthy Blvd.</street>
          <street/>
          <city>Milpitas</city>
          <code>95035</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>naiming@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shane Amante" initials="S."
            surname="Amante">
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	    <postal>
          <street>One Apple Park Way</street>
          <street/>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <code>95014</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amante@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mikael Abrahamsson" initials="M."
            surname="Abrahamsson">
      <organization>T-Systems Nordic</organization>
      <address>
	    <postal>
          <street>Kistagangen 26</street>
          <street/>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Mikael.Abrahamsson@t-systems.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="February" year="2019"/>
    <area>Routing</area>

<keyword>IGP, IS-IS, Metric, Reverse-Metric, IIH</keyword>


    <abstract>
      <t>
	This document describes a mechanism to allow IS-IS routing to
	quickly and accurately shift traffic away from either
    a point-to-point or multi-access LAN interface during network
    maintenance or other operational events. This is accomplished
    by signaling adjacent IS-IS neighbors with a higher reverse
    metric, i.e., the metric towards the signaling IS-IS router.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>


  <middle>

    <section anchor="Intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
	The IS-IS <xref target='ISO10589'/> routing protocol has been
	widely used in Internet Service Provider IP/MPLS networks.
	Operational experience with the protocol combined with ever
	increasing requirements for lossless operations have demonstrated
	some operational issues.  This document describes the issues and
	a mechanism for mitigating them.
      </t>
      <t>
          This document defines the IS-IS "Reverse Metric" mechanism that
          allows an IS-IS node to send a Reverse Metric TLV through the
          IS-IS Hello (IIH) PDU to the neighbor or pseudonode to adjust the
          routing metric on the inbound direction.
      </t>
    <section anchor="node-isolation" title="Node and Link Isolation">
        <t> The IS-IS routing mechanism has the overload bit, which can be used
            by operators to perform disruptive maintenance on the router.
            But in many operational maintenance cases, it is not necessary
            to divert all the traffic away from this node. It is 
            necessary to avoid only a single link during the maintenance. More
            detailed descriptions of the challenges can be found in Appendices
            <xref target='Appendix-A' format="counter"/> and <xref target='Appendix-B' format="counter"/>
            of this document.
      </t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="Forwarding-Download"
        title="Distributed Forwarding Planes">
	<t> In a distributed forwarding platform, different forwarding line cards
        may have interfaces and IS-IS connections to neighbor routers.
        If one of the line card's software resets, it may take some time
        for the forwarding entries to be fully populated on the line card,
        in particular if the router is a PE (Provider Edge) router in
        an ISP's MPLS VPN.
        An IS-IS adjacency may be established with a neighbor router long
        before the entire BGP VPN prefixes are downloaded to the
        forwarding table. It is important to signal to the adjacent IS-IS
        routers to raise metric values and not
        to use the corresponding IS-IS adjacency inbound to this router
        if possible. Temporarily signaling the 'Reverse Metric' over
        this link to discourage the traffic via the corresponding
        line card will
        help to reduce the traffic loss in the network. In the meantime,
        the remote PE routers will select a different set of PE routers
        for the BGP best path calculation or use a different link towards the
        same PE router on which a line card is resetting.
	</t>
	</section> 

    <section anchor="Spine-Leaf"
        title="Spine-Leaf Applications">
        <t> In the IS-IS Spine-Leaf extension
            <xref target="IS-IS-SL-EXT"/>, the leaf nodes
            will perform equal-cost or unequal-cost load sharing towards
            all the spine
            nodes. In certain operational cases, for instance, when one of
            the backbone links on a spine node is congested, a spine
            node can push a higher metric towards the connected leaf
            nodes to reduce the transit traffic through the
            corresponding spine node or link.
	</t>
	</section> 

    <section anchor="IGP-LDP"
        title="LDP IGP Synchronization">
        <t> In <xref target='RFC5443'/>, a mechanism is described
            to achieve LDP IGP synchronization by using the maximum
            link metric value on the interface. But in the case of
            a new IS-IS node joining the broadcast network (LAN), it
            is not optimal to change all the nodes on the LAN to the
            maximum link metric value, as described in
            <xref target='RFC6138'/>. In this case, the Reverse Metric
            can be used to discourage both outbound and inbound
            traffic without affecting the traffic of other
            IS-IS nodes on the LAN.
	</t>
	</section> 

	<section anchor="reverse-metric-solution"
             title="IS-IS Reverse Metric">
         
 <t>
	This document uses the routing protocol itself as the
    transport mechanism to allow one IS-IS router to advertise a
    "reverse metric" in an IS-IS Hello (IIH) PDU to an adjacent
    node on a point-to-point or multi-access LAN link. 
    This would allow the provisioning to be performed only on a single node,
    setting a "reverse metric" on a link and
	having traffic bidirectionally shift away from that link gracefully
	to alternate viable paths.
	  </t>
     

 <t> This Reverse Metric mechanism is used for both point-to-point
      and multi-access LAN links. Unlike the point-to-point links, the IS-IS
      protocol currently does not have a way to influence the traffic towards a
      particular node on LAN links. This mechanism provides IS&nbhy;IS routing with
      the capability of altering traffic in both directions on either
      a point-to-point link or a multi-access link of an IS-IS node.
      </t>

<t>
   The metric value in the Reverse Metric TLV and the Traffic
   Engineering metric in the sub-TLV being advertised are offsets or
   relative metrics to be added to the existing local link and Traffic
   Engineering metric values of the receiver; the accumulated metric
   value is bounded as described in <xref target="reverse-metric-tlv"/>.
      </t>
	</section> 

      <section anchor="Req" title="Specification of Requirements">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
   
	</section>
	</section> 

	<section anchor="reverse-metric-tlv"
	         title="IS-IS Reverse Metric TLV">
      <t>
          The Reverse Metric TLV is a new TLV to be used inside an IS-IS
          Hello PDU. This TLV is used to support the IS-IS Reverse Metric
          mechanism that allows a "reverse metric" to be sent to the
          IS-IS neighbor.
      </t>

      <figure title="Reverse Metric TLV" align="center" anchor="r-metric-tlv-fig">
          <preamble></preamble>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |      Type     |     Length    |    Flags      |     Metric 
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          Metric  (Continued)       | sub-TLV Len   |Optional sub-TLV
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ ]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>

      <t>
    The Value part of the Reverse Metric TLV is composed of a 3
    octet field containing an IS-IS Metric value, a 1 octet field of Flags,
    and a 1 octet Reverse Metric sub-TLV length field
	representing the length of a variable number of sub-TLVs.
    If the "sub-TLV Len" is non-zero, then the Value field MUST also
    contain one or more sub-TLVs.
      </t>
	  <t>
    The Reverse Metric TLV MAY be present in any IS-IS Hello PDU.
    A sender MUST only transmit a single
    Reverse Metric TLV in an IS-IS Hello PDU. If a received IS-IS Hello PDU
    contains more than one Reverse Metric TLV, an implementation MUST
    ignore all the Reverse Metric TLVs.
      </t>
	  <t>
	     <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
	     <list>
	        <t>TYPE: 16</t>
	        <t>LENGTH: variable (5 - 255 octets)</t>
	        <t>VALUE:
	           <list>
	           <t>Flags (1 octet)</t>
	           <t>Metric (3 octets)</t>
	           <t>sub-TLV length (1 octet)</t>
	           <t>sub-TLV data (0 - 250 octets)</t>
               </list>
            </t>
	     </list>
	     <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	  </t>
	  <t>
      <figure title="Flags" anchor="reverse-metric-tlv-flags">
	  <artwork type="drawing">
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |  Reserved |U|W|
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+</artwork>
      </figure>
          </t>
	  <t>
          The Metric field contains a 24-bit unsigned integer. This value is
          a metric offset that a neighbor SHOULD add to the existing
          configured Default Metric for the IS-IS link <xref target='ISO10589'/>.
          Refer to "Elements of
	      Procedure" in <xref target='procedure-elements'/> of this
	      document for
          details on how an IS-IS router should process the Metric field
          in a Reverse Metric TLV.
	  </t>
      <t>
          The Metric field, in the Reverse Metric TLV, is a
          "reverse offset metric" that
	will either be in the range of 0 - 63 when a "narrow" IS-IS metric is used
	(IS Neighbors TLV / Pseudonode LSP) <xref target='RFC1195'/> or in the
	range of 0 - (2^24 - 2) when a "wide" Traffic Engineering metric value is
    used (Extended IS Reachability TLV) <xref target='RFC5305'/>
    <xref target='RFC5817'/>. As described below, when the U bit is set,
    the accumulated value of the wide metric is in the range of
    0&nbsp;-&nbsp;(2^24&nbsp;-&nbsp;1), with the (2^24 - 1) metric value as non-reachable in IS-IS routing.
    The IS-IS metric value of (2^24 - 2) serves as the link of last resort.
       </t>
	  <t>
	There are currently only two Flag bits defined.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	W bit (0x01): The "Whole LAN" bit is only used in the context of
	multi-access LANs.  When a Reverse Metric TLV is transmitted from a
    node to the Designated Intermediate System (DIS),
    if the "Whole LAN" bit is set (1), then a
	DIS SHOULD add the received Metric value in the Reverse Metric TLV
	to each node's existing Default Metric in the Pseudonode LSP.  If
	the "Whole LAN" bit is not set (0), then a DIS SHOULD add the received
	Metric value in the Reverse Metric TLV to the existing "default
	metric" in the Pseudonode LSP for the single node from whom the
	Reverse Metric TLV was received.  Please refer to "Multi-access LAN
	Procedures", in <xref target="lan-procedures"/>, for additional
	details.  The W bit MUST be clear when a Reverse Metric TLV is
    transmitted in an IIH PDU on a point-to-point link
    and MUST be ignored when received on a point-to-point link.
	  </t>
	  <t>
    U bit (0x02): The "Unreachable" bit specifies that the metric
    calculated by the addition of the reverse metric to the "default
    metric" is limited to the maximum value of (2^24-1).
    This "U" bit applies to both the default
    metric in the Extended IS Reachability TLV and the Traffic Engineering
    Default Metric
    sub-TLV of the link. This is only relevant to the IS-IS "wide"
    metric mode.
	  </t>
	  <t>
          The Reserved bits of Flags field MUST be set to zero and
          MUST be ignored when received.
	  </t>

	  <t>
    The Reverse Metric TLV MAY include sub-TLVs when an IS-IS router
    wishes to signal additional information to its neighbor. In this
    document, the Reverse Metric Traffic Engineering Metric sub-TLV,
    with Type 18, is defined. This Traffic Engineering Metric contains
    a 24-bit unsigned integer. This sub-TLV is optional; if it appears
    more than once, then the entire Reverse Metric TLV MUST be ignored.
    Upon receiving this Traffic Engineering METRIC sub-TLV in a Reverse Metric TLV,
    a node SHOULD add
    the received Traffic Engineering Metric offset value to its
    existing configured Traffic Engineering Default
	Metric within its Extended IS Reachability TLV.  The use of other sub-TLVs
	is outside the scope of this document.
    The "sub-TLV Len" value MUST be set to zero when an IS-IS router
    does not have Traffic Engineering
	sub-TLVs that it wishes to send to its IS-IS neighbor.
	  </t>
    </section> 

    <section anchor="procedure-elements"
	         title="Elements of Procedure">
	
	<section anchor="metric-changes"
		title="Processing Changes to Default Metric">
	  <t>
    It is
    important to use the same IS-IS metric type on both ends of the link and
    in the entire IS-IS area or level.
    On the receiving side of the 'reverse-metric' TLV, the accumulated value
    of the configured metric and the reverse-metric needs
    to be limited to 63 in "narrow" metric mode and to (2^24 - 2) in "wide"
    metric mode. This applies to both the Default Metric of Extended IS
    Reachability TLV and
    the Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV in LSP or Pseudonode LSP for the "wide"
    metric mode case. If the "U" bit is present in the flags, the accumulated
    metric value is to be limited to (2^24 - 1)
    for both the normal link metric and Traffic Engineering metric in IS&nbhy;IS "wide" metric mode.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	If an IS-IS router is configured to originate a Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV
	for a link but receives a Reverse Metric TLV from its neighbor that does
    not contain a Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV, then the IS-IS router MUST NOT
    change the value of its Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV for that link.
	  </t>
	</section> 
	
	<section anchor="mt-isis-metric-changes"
		title="Multi-Topology IS-IS Support on Point-to-Point Links">
	  <t>
	The Reverse Metric TLV is applicable to Multi-topology IS-IS (M-ISIS)
	<xref target='RFC5120'/>. On point-to-point links, if an IS-IS
	router is configured for M-ISIS, it MUST send only a single Reverse
	Metric TLV in IIH PDUs toward its neighbor(s) on the designated link.
	When an M-ISIS router
    receives a Reverse Metric TLV, it MUST add the received Metric
    value to
	its Default Metric of the link in all Extended IS Reachability TLVs for all
	topologies.  If an M-ISIS router receives a Reverse Metric TLV with a
	Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV, then the M-ISIS router MUST add the received
	Traffic Engineering Default Metric value to each of its  Default Metric sub-TLVs in
	all of its MT Intermediate Systems TLVs.  If an M-ISIS router is
	configured to advertise Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLVs for one or more
	topologies but does not receive a Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLV in a
    Reverse Metric TLV, then the M-ISIS router MUST NOT change the value
    in each of the Traffic Engineering Default Metric sub-TLVs for all topologies.
	  </t>
	</section> 

	<section anchor="lan-procedures"
             title="Multi-access LAN Procedures">
	  <t>
	On a Multi-access LAN, only the DIS SHOULD act upon information
	contained in a received Reverse Metric TLV.  All non-DIS nodes MUST
    silently ignore a received Reverse Metric TLV. The decision process
    of the routers on the LAN MUST follow the procedure in
    Section 7.2.8.2 of <xref target='ISO10589'/>, and use the
    "Two-way connectivity check" during the topology and route calculation.
	  </t>
	  <t>
    The Reverse Metric Traffic Engineering sub-TLV also applies to the DIS. If a DIS is
    configured to apply Traffic Engineering over a link and it receives
    Traffic Engineering Metric sub-TLV in a Reverse Metric TLV,
    it should update the Traffic Engineering Default Metric
    sub-TLV value of the corresponding Extended IS Reachability TLV or
    insert a new one if not present.
      </t>
	  <t>
	In the case of multi-access LANs, the "W" Flags bit is used to
	signal from a non-DIS to the DIS whether or not to change the metric and,
	optionally, Traffic Engineering parameters for all nodes in the
    Pseudonode LSP or solely the node on the LAN originating the
    Reverse Metric TLV. 
	  </t>
	  <t>
	A non-DIS node, e.g., Router B, attached to a multi-access LAN will
	send the DIS a Reverse Metric TLV with the W bit clear when
	Router B wishes the DIS to add the Metric value to the Default Metric
	contained in the Pseudonode LSP specific to just Router B.  Other
	non-DIS nodes, e.g., Routers C and D, may simultaneously send a
	Reverse Metric TLV with the W bit clear to request the DIS to add
	their own Metric value to their Default Metric contained in the
	Pseudonode LSP.
	  </t>
	  <t>
    As long as at least one IS-IS node on the LAN sending the signal
    to DIS with the W bit set, the DIS would add the metric value
    in the Reverse Metric TLV to all neighbor adjacencies in the
    Pseudonode LSP, regardless if some of the nodes on the LAN
    advertise the Reverse Metric TLV without
    the W bit set. The DIS MUST use the reverse metric of the highest source
    MAC address Non-DIS advertising the Reverse Metric TLV with the W bit set.
      </t>
	  <t>
	Local provisioning on the DIS to adjust the Default Metric(s)
    is another way to insert Reverse Metric in the Pseudonode LSP
    towards an IS-IS node
    on a LAN. In the case where a Reverse Metric TLV is also used in
    the IS-IS Hello PDU of the node, the local provisioning
	MUST take precedence over
    received Reverse Metric TLVs. For instance, local policy on
    the DIS may be provisioned to ignore the W bit signaling
    on a LAN.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	Multi-topology IS-IS <xref target='RFC5120'/> specifies there is no
	change to construction of the Pseudonode LSP regardless of the
	Multi-topology (MT) capabilities of a multi-access LAN.  If any MT capable
	node on the LAN advertises the Reverse Metric TLV to the DIS, the DIS
	should update, as appropriate, the
	Default Metric contained in the Pseudonode LSP.  If the DIS updates
	the Default Metric and floods a new Pseudonode LSP, those default
	metric values will be applied to all topologies during Multi-topology
	Shortest Path First calculations.
	  </t>
    </section> 

    <section anchor="LDP"
        title="LDP/IGP Synchronization on LANs">
        <t> As described in <xref target='RFC6138'/>, when a new
            IS-IS node joins a broadcast network, it is unnecessary and
            sometimes even harmful for all IS-IS nodes on the LAN to
            advertise the maximum link metric.
            <xref target='RFC6138'/> proposes a solution
            to have the new node not advertise its adjacency towards
            the pseudonode when it is not in a "cut-edge" position.
       </t>
       <t> With the introduction of Reverse Metric in this document,
           a simpler alternative solution to the above mentioned problem
           can be used.  The Reverse Metric allows the new
           node on the LAN to advertise its inbound metric value to be the
           maximum, and this puts the link of this new node in the last resort
           position without impacting the other IS-IS nodes on the same LAN.
       </t>
       <t> Specifically, when IS-IS adjacencies are being established
           by the new node on the LAN, besides setting the maximum link
           metric value (2^24 - 2) on the interface of the LAN for
           LDP IGP synchronization as
           described in <xref target='RFC5443'/>, it 
           SHOULD advertise the maximum metric offset value in the
           Reverse Metric TLV in its IIH PDU sent on the LAN. It SHOULD
           continue this advertisement until it completes all the LDP
           label binding exchanges with all the neighbors over this LAN,
           either by receiving the LDP End-of-LIB
           <xref target='RFC5919'/> for all the sessions or by
           exceeding the provisioned timeout value for the node
           LDP/IGP synchronization.
       </t>
    </section> 

	<section anchor="ops-guidelines"
		title="Operational Guidelines">
	  <t>
          For the use case in <xref target="node-isolation"/>, a router
          SHOULD limit the period of advertising a Reverse Metric TLV
          towards a neighbor only for the duration of a network
          maintenance window.
	  </t>
	  <t>
          The use of a Reverse Metric does not alter IS-IS metric parameters
          stored in a router's persistent provisioning database.
	  </t>	
	  <t>
	If routers that receive a Reverse Metric TLV send a syslog message or
	SNMP trap, this will assist in rapidly identifying the node in the
	network that is advertising an IS-IS metric or Traffic Engineering
	parameters different from that which is configured locally on the 
	device.
	  </t>
	  <t>
          When the link Traffic Engineering metric is raised to
          (2^24 - 1) <xref target='RFC5817'/>,
          either due to the Reverse Metric mechanism or
          by explicit user configuration, this SHOULD immediately trigger
          the CSPF (Constrained Shortest Path First) recalculation
          to move the Traffic Engineering traffic away from
          that link. It is RECOMMENDED also that the CSPF does the immediate
          CSPF recalculation when the Traffic Engineering metric is
          raised to (2^24 - 2) to be the last resort link.
	  </t>
	  <t>
    It is advisable that implementations provide a configuration
    capability to disable
    any IS-IS metric changes by a Reverse Metric mechanism through
    neighbors' Hello PDUs.
	  </t>
	  <t>
          If an implementation enables this mechanism by default,
          it is RECOMMENDED that it be disabled by the operators when
          not explicitly using it.
	  </t>
	</section>
	
	</section> 


    <section anchor="Security"
             title="Security Considerations">
	  <t>
          Security concerns for IS-IS are addressed in <xref target='ISO10589'/>,
          <xref target="RFC5304"/>, <xref target="RFC5310"/>, and with
          various deployment and operational security considerations in
          <xref target="RFC7645"/>.
	The enhancement in this document makes it possible for one
    IS-IS router to manipulate the IS-IS Default Metric and, optionally,
    Traffic Engineering parameters of adjacent IS-IS neighbors on
    point-to-point or LAN interfaces.  Although
	IS-IS routers within a single Autonomous System nearly always are
	under the control of a single administrative authority, it is
	highly recommended that operators configure authentication of IS-IS
	PDUs to mitigate use of the Reverse Metric TLV as a potential attack
	vector.
	  </t>


    </section> 

    <section anchor="IANA"
             title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
    IANA has allocated IS-IS TLV Codepoint 16 for the Reverse Metric TLV.
    This new TLV has the following attributes: IIH = y, LSP = n, SNP = n, Purge = n.
      </t>
      <t>
      This document also introduces a new registry for sub-TLVs of the Reverse Metric TLV.
      The registration policy is Expert Review as defined in <xref target='RFC8126'/>.
      This registry is part of the "IS-IS TLV Codepoints" registry. The name of the
      registry is "Sub-TLVs for TLV 16 (Reverse Metric TLV)". The defined
      values are: 

<!-- [rfced] FYI, in the final step before publication, we will remove 
the extra blank lines above the registry values in Section 5. (They appear 
due to xml2rfc's handling of the nested list elements. We could simply 
remove the outer list element, but presumably you want the indentation.)
-->

         <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
      <list><t>
         <list hangIndent="9" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="0:"> Reserved</t>
            <t hangText="1-17:"> Unassigned</t>
            <t hangText="18:">Traffic Engineering Metric as specified in this
               document (<xref target='reverse-metric-tlv'/>)</t>
            <t hangText="19-255:">Unassigned</t>
         <?rfc subcompact="no"?> 
       </list>
      </t>
      </list></t>

    </section> 


    
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      <reference anchor="ISO10589">
	<front>
          <title>
Information technology -- Telecommunications and information exchange between
systems -- Intermediate System to Intermediate System intra-domain routeing
information exchange protocol for use in conjunction with the protocol for
providing the connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)
	  </title> 
          <author> 
	    <organization>ISO</organization>
	  </author>
      <date month="November" year="2002" />
	</front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:2002, Second Edition"/>
      </reference>

      &rfc1195;
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc5120;
      &rfc5305;
      &rfc5443;
      &rfc8126;
      &rfc8174;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
	
	  
	   &rfc5304;
	   &rfc5310;
	   &rfc5817;
	   &rfc5919;
	   &rfc6138;
	   &rfc7645;
	
      
      <!-- draft-ietf-lsr-isis-spine-leaf-ext-00: I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='IS-IS-SL-EXT'>
<front>
<title>IS-IS Routing for Spine-Leaf Topology</title>
<author initials='N' surname='Shen' fullname='Naiming Shen'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Thyamagundalu' fullname='Sanjay Thyamagundalu'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' day='18' year='2018' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-lsr-isis-spine-leaf-ext-00'/>
</reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix-A" title="Node Isolation Challenges">
	   <t>
	On rare occasions, it is necessary for an operator to perform disruptive
	network maintenance on an entire IS-IS router node, i.e., major
	software upgrades, power/cooling augments, etc.  In these cases, an
	operator will set the IS-IS Overload Bit (OL bit) within the Link State
	Protocol Data Units (LSPs) of the IS-IS router about to undergo
	maintenance.  The IS-IS router immediately floods its updated LSPs to
	all IS-IS routers in the IS-IS domain.  Upon receipt of the
	updated LSPs, all IS-IS routers recalculate their Shortest Path First
	(SPF) tree excluding IS-IS routers whose LSPs have the OL bit set.
	This effectively removes the IS-IS router about to undergo maintenance
	from the topology, thus preventing it from receiving any transit
	traffic during the maintenance period.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	After the maintenance activity has completed, the operator resets the
	IS-IS Overload Bit within the LSPs of the original IS-IS router causing
	it to flood updated IS-IS LSPs throughout the IS-IS domain.  All IS-IS
	routers recalculate their SPF tree and now include the original IS-IS
	router in their topology calculations, allowing it to be used for transit
	traffic again.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	Isolating an entire IS-IS router from the topology can be especially
	disruptive due to the displacement of a large volume of traffic
	through an entire IS-IS router to other suboptimal paths (e.g., those
	with significantly larger delay).  Thus, in the majority of network
	maintenance scenarios, where only a single link or LAN needs to be
	augmented to increase its physical capacity, or is experiencing
	an intermittent failure, it is much more common and desirable
	to gracefully remove just the targeted link or LAN from service
	temporarily, so that the least amount of user-data traffic is affected 
    during the link-specific network maintenance.
	   </t>
    </section> 

    <section anchor="Appendix-B"  title="Link Isolation Challenges">
	   <t>
	  Before network maintenance events are performed on individual
	  physical links or LANs, operators substantially
	  increase the IS-IS metric simultaneously on both devices attached
	  to the same link or LAN.  In doing so, the devices generate new
	  Link State Protocol Data Units (LSPs) that are flooded throughout
	  the network and cause all routers to gradually shift traffic onto
	  alternate paths with very little or no disruption to in-flight
	  communications by applications or end users.  When performed
	  successfully, this allows the operator to confidently perform
	  disruptive augmentation, fault diagnosis, or repairs on a link without
	  disturbing ongoing communications in the network.
	</t>
	<t>
	  There are a number of challenges with the above solution.  First, it is
	  quite common to have routers with several hundred interfaces
	  and individual interfaces that move anywhere from several
	  hundred gigabits/second to terabits/second of traffic.  Thus, it is
	  imperative that operators accurately identify the same point-to-point
	  link on two separate devices in order to increase (and afterward
	  decrease) the IS-IS metric appropriately.  Second, the aforementioned
	  solution is very time-consuming and even more error-prone to perform
	  when it's necessary to temporarily remove a multi-access LAN from the
	  network topology.  Specifically, the operator needs to configure ALL
	  devices that have interfaces attached to the multi-access LAN with
	  an appropriately high IS-IS metric (and then decrease the IS-IS
	  metric to its original value afterward).  Finally, with respect to
	  multi-access LANs, there is currently no method to bidirectionally
	  isolate only a single node's interface on the LAN when performing
	  more fine-grained diagnoses and repairs to the multi-access LAN.
	</t>

<t>
   In theory, use of a Network Management System (NMS) could improve the
   accuracy of identifying the appropriate subset of routers attached to
   either a point-to-point link or a multi-access LAN.  It could also signal 
   to those devices, using a network management protocol, to adjust the IS-IS
   metrics on the pertinent set of interfaces.  The
	  reality is that NMSs are, to a very large extent, not
	  used within Service Provider's networks for a variety of reasons.  In
	  particular, NMSs do not interoperate very well across different vendors
	  or even separate platform families within the same vendor.
	</t>
    </section> 

<section anchor="Acknowledgments"
             title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>
    The authors would like to thank Mike Shand, Dave Katz,
    Guan Deng, Ilya Varlashkin, Jay Chen, Les Ginsberg,
    Peter Ashwood-Smith, Uma Chunduri, Alexander Okonnikov,
    Jonathan Harrison, Dave Ward, Himanshu Shah, Wes George, 
    Danny McPherson, Ed Crabbe, Russ White, Robert Raszuk,
    Tom Petch, Stewart Bryant, and Acee Lindem for their comments
    and contributions.
      </t>
     </section>


    <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
	   <t>
      <figure>
	  <artwork type="drawing">
Tony Li

Email: tony.li@tony.li</artwork>
      </figure>
	   </t>
    </section>


  </back>
</rfc>
