<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8579" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">


<front>
<title abbrev="Sieve: Special-Use Mailboxes">
Sieve Email Filtering: Delivering to Special-Use Mailboxes
</title>

<author fullname="Stephan Bosch" initials="S." surname="Bosch">
  <organization>Open Xchange Oy</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Lars Sonckin kaari 12</street>
      <code>02600</code>
      <city>Espoo</city>
      <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>stephan.bosch@open-xchange.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date month="May" year="2019"/>

<area>ART</area>
<workgroup>EXTRA</workgroup>
<keyword>sieve, mailbox, special-use</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>The SPECIAL-USE capability of the IMAP protocol (RFC 6154) allows clients to
identify special-use mailboxes, e.g., where draft or sent messages should be
put. This simplifies client configuration. In contrast, the Sieve mail filtering
language (RFC 5228) currently has no such capability. This memo defines a Sieve
extension that fills this gap: it adds a test for checking whether a special-use
attribute is assigned for a particular mailbox or any mailbox, and it adds the
ability to file messages into a mailbox identified solely by a special-use
attribute.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
<t>Commonly, several mailboxes in an
<xref target="IMAP">IMAP message store</xref> have a special use. For example,
there can be a special-use mailbox for storing the user's draft messages, for
keeping copies of sent messages, and for collecting spam messages that were
classified as such at delivery. The <xref target="SPECIAL-USE">SPECIAL-USE
capability</xref> of the IMAP protocol defines mailbox attributes that identify
these special mailboxes explicitly to the client. This way, client configuration
is simplified significantly. Using the
<xref target="SPECIAL-USE">CREATE-SPECIAL-USE capability</xref>, IMAP clients
can also configure these attributes dynamically based on user preference.</t>

<t>Unlike the IMAP protocol, the Sieve mail filtering language
<xref target="SIEVE"/> currently cannot freely access these special-use
mailbox attributes. Particularly, the Sieve interpreter has no means to identify
a mailbox with a particular special-use attribute. This would be very useful, for
example, to find the user's "Spam" mailbox at delivery.</t>

<t>In Sieve, limited access to the special-use attributes is provided using the
<xref target="SIEVE-MAILBOX">"mboxmetadata" extension</xref>, which allows
testing for the presence of a special-use attribute in the "/private/specialuse"
<xref target="IMAP-METADATA">IMAP METADATA</xref> entry of a mailbox.
Still, not all implementers will be willing to add the complexity of the IMAP
METADATA capability just to provide access to special-use attributes to the
Sieve interpreter.</t>

<t>This document defines an extension to the Sieve mail filtering language that
adds the ability to freely access mailbox special-use attributes. 

It adds a test called "specialuse_exists" that checks 1) whether a special-use
attribute is assigned for a particular mailbox or 2) whether any of the user's
personal mailboxes have a special-use attribute assigned. It also adds the
ability to file messages into a personal mailbox identified by a particular
special-use attribute rather than the mailbox's name.  This is achieved using
the new ":specialuse" argument for the <xref target="SIEVE">"fileinto"
command</xref>.</t>
</section>

<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="KEYWORDS"/> <xref target="KEYWORDS-UPD"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>


<t>Conventions for notations are as described in Section 1.1 of <xref target="SIEVE"/>,
including use of the "Usage:" label for the definition of the action and the
syntax of tagged arguments.</t>
<t>In <xref target="IMAP"/> examples, "C:" and "S:" indicate lines sent by the
client and server, respectively. If such lines are wrapped without a new "C:" or
"S:" label, then the wrapping is for editorial clarity and is not part of the
command.</t>
</section>

<section title="Test &quot;specialuse_exists&quot;">

<?rfc needLines="3" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
Usage:  specialuse_exists [<mailbox: string>]
                          <special-use-attrs: string-list>
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>If the "mailbox" string argument is omitted, the "specialuse_exists" test
yields "true" if all of the following statements are true for each of the
special-use attributes listed in the special-use-attrs argument:
<list style="letters">
<t>At least one mailbox exists in the user's personal namespace
<xref target="NAMESPACE"/> that has that particular special-use attribute
assigned.</t>
<t>That mailbox allows the user in whose context the Sieve script runs to
"deliver" messages into it.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>If the mailbox argument is specified, the "specialuse_exists" test yields
"true" if all of the following statements are true:
<list style="letters">
<t>The indicated mailbox exists. </t>
<t>That mailbox allows the user in whose context the Sieve script runs
to "deliver" messages into it.</t>
<t>That mailbox has all of the special-use attributes listed in the
special-use-attrs argument assigned to it.</t>
</list>
</t>


<t>Refer to the specification of the "mailboxexists" test in Section 3.1 of
<xref target="SIEVE-MAILBOX">RFC 5490</xref> for a definition of when "delivery"
of messages into a mailbox is deemed possible.</t>

<section title="Equivalent IMAP Operations" anchor="special_use_exists_imap">

<t>To clarify, the following IMAP protocol examples show a sequence of <xref
target="IMAP"/> commands that a client
could send to perform an assessment without Sieve that is equivalent to the
"specialuse_exists" test.</t>

<t>First, the client queries which namespaces are available using the
NAMESPACE command <xref target="NAMESPACE"/>:</t>
<?rfc needLines="4" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A01 NAMESPACE
S: * NAMESPACE (("INBOX/" "/")("Archive/" "/")) NIL (("Public/" "/"))
S: A01 OK NAMESPACE command completed
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Subsequently, when no particular mailbox is of interest (i.e., the
"specialuse_exists" test has no mailbox argument), the client lists all
mailboxes with special-use attributes in the two returned personal namespaces
(this extended LIST command requires the LIST-EXTENDED IMAP capability
<xref target="LIST-EXTENDED"/>):</t>
<?rfc needLines="8" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A02 LIST (SPECIAL-USE) "" ("INBOX/*" "Archive/*")
    RETURN (SPECIAL-USE)
S: * LIST (\Drafts) "/" INBOX/Drafts
S: * LIST (\Trash) "/" INBOX/Trash
S: * LIST (\Sent) "/" INBOX/Sent
S: * LIST (\Archive) "/" Archive/Default
S: A02 OK LIST command completed
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Finally, using the MYRIGHTS command <xref target="IMAP-ACL"/>, the client
determines the access rights it has for the mailbox or mailboxes that have all
the requested attributes assigned. This way, it can determine whether messages
can be saved to any of those. In this example, an "\Archive" special-use mailbox
is sought:</t>
<?rfc needLines="4" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A03 MYRIGHTS Archive/Default
S: * MYRIGHTS Archive/Default lrwsip
S: A03 OK Myrights completed
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The MYRIGHTS response indicates that the user has "insert" rights
<xref target="IMAP-ACL"/> for the "Archive/Default" mailbox,
meaning that the client can deliver (APPEND) messages to that mailbox and that
the Sieve "specialuse_exists" test would yield "true" in this case.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section title="&quot;:specialuse&quot; Argument to &quot;fileinto&quot; Command">

<?rfc needLines="3" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
Usage:  fileinto [:specialuse <special-use-attr: string>]
                 <mailbox: string>
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Normally, the "fileinto" command delivers the message in the mailbox
specified using its positional mailbox argument, which is the name of the
mailbox. However, if the optional ":specialuse" argument is also specified, the
"fileinto" command first checks whether a mailbox exists in the user's personal
namespace <xref target="NAMESPACE"/> with the specified special-use attribute
assigned to it. If that is the case, that special-use mailbox is used for
delivery instead. If there is no such mailbox or if the specified special-use
attribute is unknown to the implementation in general, the "fileinto" action
proceeds as it would without the ":specialuse" argument.</t>

<t>Summarizing, if the ":specialuse" argument is specified, the "fileinto"
command deals with two mailboxes that may or may not exist and may, in fact, be
equal:
<list style="symbols">
<t>A special-use mailbox in the user's personal namespace, which has
at least the special-use attribute specified with the ":specialuse" argument
assigned to it. The name for this mailbox is not relevant here; it is only
identified by the assigned special-use attribute.</t>
<t>The default mailbox named by the positional string argument of the
"fileinto" command, which is used when the special-use mailbox is not found.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>The special-use attribute specified with the ":specialuse" argument conforms
to the "use-attr" syntax described in Section 6 of
<xref target="SPECIAL-USE">RFC 6154</xref>. Implementations SHOULD handle an
invalid special-use attribute in the same way as an invalid mailbox name is
handled. The string parameter of the ":specialuse" argument is not a constant
string, which means that variable substitutions are allowed when the
<xref target="VARIABLES">"variables" extension</xref> is active. In that case,
the syntax of the special-use attribute is only verified at runtime.</t>

<t>If neither the special-use mailbox nor the default mailbox exists, the 
"fileinto" action MUST proceed exactly as it does in case the ":specialuse"
argument is absent and the mailbox named by its positional argument does
not exist. The various options for handling this situation are described in
Section 4.1 of <xref target="SIEVE">RFC 5228</xref>.</t>

<t>More than one mailbox in the user's personal namespace can have a particular
special-use attribute assigned. If one of those mailboxes is, in fact, the default
mailbox named by the positional string argument of the "fileinto" command, that
mailbox MUST be used for delivery. If the default mailbox is not one of the
options, the mailbox that is chosen for delivery is implementation defined.
However, while the set of mailboxes to which the involved special-use
attribute are assigned remains unchanged, implementations SHOULD ensure that the
mailbox choice is made consistently, so that the same mailbox is used every
time. Conversely, the chosen mailbox MAY change once the assignments of the
special-use attribute that are relevant for the mailbox choice are changed (usually by
user interaction).</t>

<t>If delivery to the special-use mailbox fails for reasons not relating to its
existence, the Sieve interpreter MUST NOT subsequently attempt delivery in
the indicated default mailbox as a fallback. Instead, it MUST proceed exactly
as it does in case the ":specialuse" argument is absent and delivery to the
mailbox named by its positional argument fails. This prevents the situation
where messages are unexpectedly spread over two mailboxes in case transient or
intermittent delivery failures occur.</t>

<section title="Mailboxes Created Implicitly by the &quot;fileinto&quot; Command">

<t>Before attempting to deliver the message into the specified mailbox, the
"fileinto" command may implicitly create the mailbox if it does not exist (see
Section 4.1 of <xref target="SIEVE">RFC 5228</xref>). This optional behavior can
be requested explicitly using the
<xref target="SIEVE-MAILBOX">"mailbox" extension</xref>,
which adds the optional ":create" argument to the "fileinto" command. If the
":create" argument is specified with "fileinto", it instructs the Sieve
interpreter to unconditionally create the specified mailbox if needed. Note that
the ":create" argument has no effect when the implicit creation of mailboxes for
delivery is the default behavior.</t>

<t>When the ":specialuse" argument is present, this behavior does not change;
the Sieve interpreter will implicitly create the specified default mailbox if
needed. This need arises when both the special-use mailbox and the default
mailbox are not found.</t>

<t>If the server implementation supports the
<xref target="SPECIAL-USE">CREATE-SPECIAL-USE capability</xref> for IMAP (i.e.,
it allows assigning special-use attributes to new mailboxes), it SHOULD assign
the special-use attribute specified with the ":specialuse" argument to the
newly created mailbox.</t>  

</section>

<section title="Equivalent IMAP Operations">

<t>To clarify, the following                   
IMAP protocol examples show a sequence of <xref target="IMAP"/> commands that a client
could send to perform an action without Sieve that is equivalent to the
"fileinto" action with the ":specialuse" argument.
The following Sieve script is assumed:</t>

<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require "fileinto";
require "special-use";

fileinto :specialuse "\\Archive" "INBOX/Archive";
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>First, the client proceeds as in <xref target="special_use_exists_imap"/> to
find out whether the indicated special-use attribute is assigned to any mailbox
in the user's personal namespace. If a matching special-use mailbox is found,
the message is delivered there using the IMAP APPEND command. If no matching
special-use mailbox is found, the client attempts to deliver the message to the
indicated default mailbox:</t>

<?rfc needLines="3" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A04 APPEND INBOX/Archive {309}
S: A04 NO [TRYCREATE] Mailbox does not exist: INBOX/Archive
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>In this example, the default mailbox does not exist either. In that case,
the client MAY create the default mailbox and assign the indicated special-use
attribute to it:
</t>

<?rfc needLines="13" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A05 CREATE INBOX/Archive (USE (\Archive))
S: A05 OK Create completed
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Finally, the client completes the delivery:</t>
<?rfc needLines="14" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
C: A06 APPEND INBOX/Archive {309}
S: + OK
C: Date: Wed, 18 Jul 2018 22:00:09 +0200
C: From: mooch@owatagu.siam.example
C: To: Fred Foobar <foobar@Blurdybloop.example>
C: Subject: afternoon meeting
C: Message-Id: <Q234234-01012222@owatagu.siam.example>
C: MIME-Version: 1.0
C: Content-Type: text/plain; charset=UTF-8
C: 
C: Hi Fred, do you think we can meet again at 3:30 tomorrow?
C: 
S: A06 OK [APPENDUID 1533375901 2312] Append completed.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Sieve Capability Strings">
<t>A Sieve implementation that defines the "specialuse_exists" test and
the ":specialuse" argument for the "fileinto" command  will advertise the
capability string "special-use".
</t>
</section>

<section title="Examples">

<t>The following example saves the message in the mailbox where messages deemed
to be junk mail are held. This mailbox is identified using the "\Junk"
special-use attribute. If no mailbox has this attribute assigned, the message
is filed into the mailbox named "Spam". If the mailbox named "Spam" does not
exist either, the result of this Sieve script is implementation dependent,
e.g., it may trigger an error or the mailbox may be created implicitly.</t>

<?rfc needLines="5" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require "fileinto";
require "special-use";

fileinto :specialuse "\\Junk" "Spam";
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The following very similar example explicitly handles the case in which
neither a "\Junk" special-use mailbox nor the "Spam" mailbox exists. In that
case, a mailbox called "Spam" is created, and the message is stored
there. Additionally, the "\Junk" special-use attribute may be assigned to it.
</t>

<?rfc needLines="6" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require "fileinto";
require "special-use";
require "mailbox";

fileinto :specialuse "\\Junk" :create "Spam";
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The following example is used in a Sieve script that is triggered from an
IMAP event rather than at message delivery <xref target="IMAPSIEVE"/>. This
Sieve script redirects messages to an automated recipient that processes junk
mail if those messages are copied or moved into a mailbox that has the "\Junk"
special-use attribute assigned.</t>

<?rfc needLines="15" ?>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
require "imapsieve";
require "special-use";
require "environment";
require "variables";

if environment :contains "imap.mailbox" "*" {
    set "mailbox" "${1}";
}

if allof(
    environment "imap.cause" "COPY",
    specialuse_exists "${mailbox}" "\\Junk") {
    redirect "spam-report@example.org";
}
]]></artwork>
</figure>

</section>


<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>Security considerations are discussed in <xref target="SIEVE"/>,
<xref target="VARIABLES"/>, and <xref target="SPECIAL-USE"/>. It is believed
that this extension does not introduce any additional security concerns.</t>

<t>Note that this specification explicitly restricts the special-use mailbox to
the user's personal namespace. First, this avoids the need to search the entire
mail storage for mailboxes that have a particular special-use attribute
assigned. This could put undue load on the system, while shared special-use
mailboxes are deemed of limited use with the currently defined special-use
attributes. Secondly, it prevents security concerns with shared mailboxes that
have special-use attributes assigned that apply to all users. Searching the
entire mail storage for special-use mailboxes could lead to messages
unexpectedly or even maliciously being filed to shared mailboxes.</t>

<t>This restriction could be lifted for particular future special-use
attributes, but such new attributes should have a clear application for shared
mailboxes, and the security concerns should be considered carefully.</t> 
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">


<t>IANA has registered the Sieve extension specified in this document in the
"Sieve Extensions" registry at
&lt;https://www.iana.org/assignments/sieve-extensions&gt;:</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
   Capability name: special-use
   Description:     adds a test for checking whether an IMAP
                    special-use attribute is assigned for a
                    particular mailbox or any mailbox; also adds
                    the ability to file messages into a mailbox
                    identified solely by a special-use attribute.
   RFC number:      RFC 8579
   Contact address: Sieve discussion list <sieve@ietf.org>
]]></artwork>
</figure>

</section>
</middle>



<back>


<references title="Normative References">


<reference  anchor='KEYWORDS' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='KEYWORDS-UPD' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174'>
<front>
<title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<date year='2017' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8174'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8174'/>
</reference>

  <reference anchor='IMAP-METADATA' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5464'>
    <front>
    <title>The IMAP METADATA Extension</title>
    <author initials='C.' surname='Daboo' fullname='C. Daboo'><organization /></author>
    <date year='2009' month='February' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5464'/>
    <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5464'/>
  </reference>

  <reference  anchor='NAMESPACE' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2342'>
    <front>
    <title>IMAP4 Namespace</title>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Gahrns' fullname='M. Gahrns'><organization /></author>
    <author initials='C.' surname='Newman' fullname='C. Newman'><organization /></author>
    <date year='1998' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2342'/>
    <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2342'/>
  </reference>

<reference  anchor='SIEVE' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5228'>
<front>
<title>Sieve: An Email Filtering Language</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Guenther' fullname='P. Guenther' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Showalter' fullname='T. Showalter' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5228'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5228'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='SPECIAL-USE' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6154'>
<front>
<title>IMAP LIST Extension for Special-Use Mailboxes</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Nicolson' fullname='J. Nicolson'><organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6154'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6154'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='SIEVE-MAILBOX' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5490'>
<front>
<title>The Sieve Mail-Filtering Language -- Extensions for Checking Mailbox Status and Accessing Mailbox Metadata</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Melnikov' fullname='A. Melnikov'><organization /></author>
<date year='2009' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5490'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5490'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='VARIABLES' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5229'>
<front>
<title>Sieve Email Filtering: Variables Extension</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Homme' fullname='K. Homme'><organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5229'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5229'/>
</reference>

</references>


<references title="Informative References">

<reference  anchor="IMAP" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3501'>
<front>
<title>INTERNET MESSAGE ACCESS PROTOCOL - VERSION 4rev1</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Crispin' fullname='M. Crispin'><organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='March' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3501'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3501'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='IMAP-ACL' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4314'>
<front>
<title>IMAP4 Access Control List (ACL) Extension</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Melnikov' fullname='A. Melnikov'><organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='December' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4314'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC4314'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='IMAPSIEVE' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6785'>
<front>
<title>Support for Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) Events in Sieve</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6785'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6785'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='LIST-EXTENDED' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5258'>
<front>
<title>Internet Message Access Protocol version 4 - LIST Command Extensions</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='B. Leiba'><organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Melnikov' fullname='A. Melnikov'><organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='June' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5258'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5258'/>
</reference>


</references>


<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>Thanks to Stan Kalisch, Barry Leiba, Alexey Melnikov, Ken Murchison,
and Ned Freed for reviews and suggestions.</t>
<t>Thanks to the authors of <xref target="SIEVE-MAILBOX">RFC 5490</xref>, from
which some descriptive text in this document is borrowed.</t>
</section>


</back>

</rfc>
