<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" number="8082"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="5104" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
  <front>

    <title abbrev="CCM for Layered Codecs">Using Codec Control Messages in the RTP
    Audio-Visual Profile with Feedback with Layered Codecs</title>

    <author fullname="Stephan Wenger" initials="S." surname="Wenger">
      <organization>Vidyo, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>stewe@stewe.org</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Lennox" initials="J." surname="Lennox">
      <organization>Vidyo, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>jonathan@vidyo.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bo Burman" initials="B." surname="Burman">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kistavagen 25</street>

          <city>SE - 164 80 Kista</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>bo.burman@ericsson.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M." surname="Westerlund">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Farogatan 2</street>

          <city>SE - 164 80 Kista</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46107148287</phone>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>magnus.westerlund@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document updates RFC 5104 by fixing a shortcoming in the
      specification language of the Codec Control Message Full Intra Request
      (FIR) description when using it with layered codecs. In
      particular, a decoder refresh point needs to be sent by a media sender
      when a FIR is received on any layer of the layered bitstream, regardless
      of whether those layers are being sent in a single or in multiple RTP
      flows. The other payload-specific feedback messages defined in RFC 5104
      and RFC 4585 (which was updated by RFC 5506) have also been analyzed, and no
      corresponding shortcomings have been found.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and Problem Statement">
      <t>The <xref target="RFC4585">"Extended RTP Profile for Real-time Transport Control Protocol (RTCP)-Based Feedback (RTP/AVPF)"</xref> and <xref
      target="RFC5104">"Codec Control Messages in the RTP Audio-Visual Profile
      with Feedback (AVPF)"</xref> specify a number of payload-specific
      feedback messages that a media receiver can use to inform a media
      sender of certain conditions or to make certain requests. The feedback
      messages are being sent as RTCP receiver reports, and RFC 4585 specifies
      timing rules that make the use of those messages practical for
      time-sensitive codec control.</t>

      <t>Since the time those RFCs were developed, layered codecs have gained
      in popularity and deployment. Layered codecs use multiple sub-bitstreams
      called "layers" to represent the content in different fidelities.
      Depending on the media codec and its RTP payload format in use, a number of 
      options exist on how to transport those layers in RTP. Summarizing 
      <xref target="RFC7656">"A Taxonomy of Semantics and Mechanisms for Real-Time 
      Transport Protocol (RTP) Sources" </xref>):

      <list>
      <t> single layers or groups of layers may be sent in their own RTP streams 
      in Multiple RTP streams on a Single media Transport (MRST) or Multiple RTP 
      streams on Multiple media Transports (MRMT) mode;</t>
      
      <t>using media-codec specific multiplexing mechanisms, multiple layers may
      be sent in a single RTP stream in Single RTP stream on a Single media Transport 
      (SRST) mode.</t>
      </list>

      The dependency relationship between layers in a truly layered, pyramid-shaped 
      bitstream forms a
      directed graph, with the base layer at the root. Enhancement layers
      depend on the base layer and potentially on other enhancement layers,
      and the target layer and all layers it depends on have to be decoded
      jointly in order to recreate the uncompressed media signal at the
      fidelity of the target layer.  Such a layering structure is assumed henceforth;
      for more exotic layering structures, please see <xref target="sec_ident" />.
      </t>

      <t>Implementation experience has shown that the Full Intra Request (FIR)
      command as defined in <xref target="RFC5104"/> is underspecified when
      used with layered codecs and when more than one RTP stream is used to
      transport the layers of a layered bitstream at a given fidelity. In
      particular, from the <xref target="RFC5104"/> specification language, it
      is not clear whether a FIR received for only a single RTP stream of
      multiple RTP streams covering the same layered bitstream necessarily
      triggers the sending of a decoder refresh point (as defined in <xref
      target="RFC5104"/>, Section 2.2) for all layers, or only for the layer
      that is transported in the RTP stream that the FIR request is
      associated with.</t>

      <t>This document fixes this shortcoming by: <list style="letters">
          <t>Updating the definition of the decoder refresh point (as defined
          in <xref target="RFC5104"/>, Section 2.2) to cover layered codecs, in
          line with the corresponding definitions used in a popular layered
          codec format, namely <xref target="H.264">H.264/SVC (Scalable Video Coding)</xref>.
          Specifically, a decoder refresh point, in conjunction with layered
          codecs, resets the state of the whole decoder, which implies that it
          includes hard or gradual single-layer decoder refresh for all
          layers;</t>

          <t>Requiring a media sender to send a decoder refresh point after
          the media sender has received a FIR
          over an RTCP stream associated with any of the RTP streams over
          which a part of the layered bitstream is transported;</t>

          <t>Requiring that a media receiver send the FIR on the RTCP stream
          associated with the base layer.  The option of receiving FIR on the
          enhancement-layer-associated RTCP stream as specified in point b)
          above is kept for backward compatibility; and</t>

          <t>Providing guidance on how to detect that a layered bitstream is in
          use for which the above rules apply.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>While, clearly, the reaction to FIR for layered codecs in <xref
      target="RFC5104"/> and the companion documents is underspecified, it appears
      that this is not the case for any of the other payload-specific codec
      control messages defined in <xref target="RFC4585"/> and <xref
      target="RFC5104"/>. A brief summary of the analysis that led to this
      conclusion is also included in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document 
      are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="DRP" title="Updated Definition of Decoder Refresh Point">
      <t>The remainder of this section replaces the definition of decoder refresh point in
      Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC5104"/> in its entirety.</t>

      <t>Decoder Refresh Point: A bit string, packetized in one or more RTP
      packets, that completely resets the decoder to a known state.</t>

      <t>Examples for "hard" single-layer decoder refresh points are Intra
      pictures in <xref target="H.261">H.261</xref>, <xref
      target="H.263">H.263</xref>, <xref target="MPEG-1">MPEG-1</xref>, <xref
      target="MPEG-2">MPEG-2</xref>, and <xref target="MPEG-4">MPEG-4</xref>;
      Instantaneous Decoder Refresh (IDR) pictures in <xref
      target="H.264">H.264</xref> and <xref target="H.265">H.265</xref>; and
      keyframes in <xref target="RFC6386">VP8</xref> and <xref
      target="VP9-BITSTREAM">VP9</xref>. "Gradual" decoder refresh
      points may also be used; see, for example, <xref
      target="H.264">H.264</xref>. While both "hard" and "gradual" decoder
      refresh points are acceptable in the scope of this specification, in
      most cases the user experience will benefit from using a "hard" decoder
      refresh point.</t>

      <t>A decoder refresh point also contains all header information above
      the syntactical level of the picture layer that is conveyed in-band. In <xref
      target="H.264"/>, for example, a decoder refresh point contains those
      parameter set Network Adaptation Layer (NAL) units that generate
      parameter sets necessary for the decoding of the following slice/data
      partition NAL units.  (That is, assuming the parameter sets have not been
      conveyed out of band.)</t>

      <t>When a layered codec is in use, the above definition -- in
      particular, the requirement to completely reset the decoder to a known
      state -- implies that the decoder refresh point includes hard or gradual
      single-layer decoder refresh points for all layers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Full Intra Request for Layered Codecs">

    <t>
    A media receiver or middlebox may decide to send a FIR command
    based on the guidance provided in Section 4.3.1 of <xref
      target="RFC5104"/>.  When sending the FIR command, it
    MUST target the RTP stream that carries the base layer of the
    layered bitstream, and this is done by setting the Feedback Control
    Information (FCI) (and, in particular, the synchronization source (SSRC) field therein) to refer
    to the SSRC of the forward RTP stream that carries the base layer. </t>
    
      <t>When a Full Intra Request command is received by the designated media
      sender in the RTCP stream associated with any of the RTP streams in
      which any layer of a layered bitstream are sent, the designated media
      sender MUST send a <xref target="DRP">decoder refresh point</xref> as
      defined above at its earliest opportunity. The requirements related to
      congestion control on the forward RTP streams as specified in Sections
      3.5.1 and 5 of <xref target="RFC5104"/> apply for the RTP streams both
      in isolation and combined.</t>

      <t>Note: the requirement to react to FIR commands associated with
      enhancement layers is included for robustness and backward-compatibility
      reasons.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Identifying the Use of Layered Bitstreams (Informative)" anchor="sec_ident">
      <t>The above modifications to RFC 5104 unambiguously define how to deal
      with FIR commands when layered bitstreams are in use. However, it is surprisingly
      difficult to identify the use of a layered bitstream. In general, it is expected that
      implementers know when layered bitstreams (in its commonly understood sense:
      with inter-layer prediction between pyramid-arranged layers) are in use
      and when not and can therefore implement the above updates to RFC 5104
      correctly. However, there are scenarios in which layered codecs are employed
      creating non-pyramid-shaped bitstreams.  Those scenarios may be viewed 
      as somewhat exotic today but clearly are supported by
      certain video coding syntaxes, such as H.264/SVC.  When blindly applying the above rules to those
      non-pyramid-arranged layering structures, suboptimal system behavior
      would result. Nothing would break, and there would not be
      an interoperability failure, but the user experience may suffer through the
      sending or receiving of decoder refresh points at times or on parts of
      the bitstream that are unnecessary from a user experience viewpoint.
      Therefore, this informative section is included that provides the
      current understanding of when a layered bitstream is in use and when
      not.</t>

      <t>The key observation made here is that the RTP payload format
      negotiated for the RTP streams, in isolation, is not necessarily an
      indicator for the use of a layered bitstream. Some layered codecs (including
      H.264/SVC) can form decodable bitstreams including only (one or more)
      enhancement layers, without the base layer, effectively creating
      simulcastable sub-bitstreams within a single scalable bitstream (as defined
      in the video coding standard),  but without inter-layer prediction. 
      In such a scenario, it is
      potentially, though not necessarily, counterproductive to send a decoder 
      refresh point on all layers for that payload format and media source.  It is 
      beyond the scope of this document to discuss optimized reactions to FIRs
      received on RTP streams carrying such exotic bitstreams.</t>

      <t>One good indication of the likely use of pyramid-shaped layering with 
      inter-layer prediction is when the various RTP streams are "bound" together on the
      signaling level. In an SDP environment, this would be the case if they
      are marked as being dependent on each other using <xref
      target="RFC5888">"The Session Description Protocol (SDP) Grouping
      Framework"</xref> and layer dependency <xref
      target="RFC5583"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Layered Codecs and Non-FIR Codec Control Messages (Informative)">
      <t>Between them, <xref target="RFC4585">AVPF</xref> and <xref
      target="RFC5104">Codec Control Messages</xref> define a total of seven
      payload-specific feedback messages. For the FIR command message,
      guidance has been provided above. In this section, some information is
      provided with respect to the remaining six codec control messages.</t>

      <section title="Picture Loss Indication (PLI)">
        <t>PLI is defined in <xref target="RFC4585">Section 6.3.1 of</xref>.
        The prudent response to a PLI message received for an enhancement
        layer is to "repair" 
        that enhancement layer and all dependent enhancement layers through 
        appropriate source-coding-specific means.  However, 
        the reference layer or layers used by the enhancement layer for which the PLI
        was received do not require repair. The encoder can figure out by 
        itself what constitutes a dependent enhancement layer and does not 
        need help from the system stack in doing so. Thus, there is nothing 
        that needs to be specified herein.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Slice Loss Indication (SLI)">
        <t>SLI is defined in <xref target="RFC4585">Section 6.3.2 of</xref>.
        The current understanding is that the prudent response to an
        SLI message received for an enhancement layer is to "repair" the 
        affected spatial area of
        that enhancement layer and all dependent enhancement layers through
        appropriate source-coding-specific means.  As in PLI, the reference 
        layers used by the enhancement layer for which the SLI
        was received do not need to be repaired. Again, as in PLI, the encoder 
        can determine by itself what constitutes a
        dependent enhancement layer and does not need help from the system
        stack in doing so. Thus, there is nothing that needs to be
        specified herein. SLI has seen very little implementation and, as far
        as it is known, none in conjunction with layered systems.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="RPSI"
               title="Reference Picture Selection Indication (RPSI)">
        <t>RPSI is defined in <xref target="RFC4585">Section 6.3.3 of</xref>.
        While a technical equivalent of RPSI has been in use with non-layered
        systems for many years, no implementations are known in conjunction of
        layered codecs. The current understanding is that the
reception of an RPSI message on any layer indicating a missing
reference picture forces the encoder to appropriately handle that
missing reference picture in the layer indicated, and in all dependent
layers.
Thus, RPSI should work without further need for
        specification language.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Temporal-Spatial Trade-Off Request and Notification (TSTR/TSTN)">
        <t>TSTR/TSTN are defined in <xref target="RFC5104">Sections 4.3.2 and
        4.3.3 of</xref>, respectively. The TSTR request communicates
        guidance of the preferred trade-off between spatial quality and frame 
        rate. A technical equivalent of TSTR/TSTN has seen deployment for many years in
        non-scalable systems.</t>

        <t>TSTR and TSTN messages include an SSRC target, which, similarly to FIR, may refer to an RTP
        stream carrying a base layer, an enhancement layer, or multiple
        layers. Therefore, the current understanding is that the
        semantics of the message applies to the layers present in the targeted
        RTP stream.</t>

        <t>It is noted that per-layer TSTR/TSTN is a mechanism that is, in
        some ways, counterproductive in a system using layered codecs. Given a
        sufficiently complex layered bitstream layout, a sending system has
        flexibility in adjusting the spatio/temporal quality balance by adding
        and removing temporal, spatial, or quality enhancement layers. At
        present, it is unclear whether an allowed (or even recommended) option
        to the reception of a TSTR is to adjust the bit allocation within the
        layer(s) present in the addressed RTP stream or to adjust the
        layering structure accordingly -- which can involve more than just the
        addressed RTP stream.</t>

        <t>Until there is a sufficient critical mass of implementation
        practice, it is probably prudent for an implementer not to assume
        either of the two options or any middle ground that may exist between
        the two.  Instead, it is suggested that an implementation be liberal 
        in accepting TSTR messages and upon receipt, responding in
        TSTN indicating "no change".  Further, it is suggested that new 
        implementations do not send TSTR messages except when
        operating in SRST mode as defined in <xref target="RFC7656"/>.  Finally,
        implementers are encouraged to contribute to the IETF documentation of 
        any implementation requirements that make per-layer TSTR/TSTN useful.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="H.271 Video Back Channel Message (VBCM)">
        <t>VBCM is defined in <xref target="RFC5104">Section 4.3.4 of</xref>.
        What was said above for <xref target="RPSI">RPSI</xref> applies here
        as well.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC4585">AVPF</xref> (as
      updated by <xref target="RFC5506">"Support for Reduced-Size Real-Time
      Transport Control Protocol (RTCP): Opportunities and
      Consequences"</xref>) and <xref target="RFC5104">Codec Control
      Messages</xref> apply. The clarified response to FIR does not introduce 
      additional security considerations.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>


  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4585'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5104'?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5506"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5888'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5583'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7656'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6386'?>


<reference anchor='VP9-BITSTREAM' target="https://storage.googleapis.com/downloads.webmproject.org/docs/vp9/vp9-bitstream-specification-v0.6-20160331-draft.pdf">
<front>
<title>VP9 Bitstream &amp; Decoding Process Specification</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Grange' fullname='Adrian Grange'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='P' surname='de Rivaz' fullname='Peter de Rivaz'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Hunt' fullname='Jonathan Hunt'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='March' year='2016' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Version' value='0.6' />
</reference>


      <reference anchor="H.261"
                 target="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/1088">
        <front>
          <title>Video codec for audiovisual services at p x
          64 kbit/s</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1993"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='H.261' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H.263"
                 target="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/7497">
        <front>
          <title>Video coding for low bit rate
          communication</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2005"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='H.263' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H.264"
                 target="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/12904">
        <front>
          <title>Advanced video coding for generic
          audiovisual services</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2016"/>
        </front>
     <seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='H.264, Version 11' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H.265"
                 target="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/12905">
        <front>
          <title>High efficiency video coding</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2016"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='H.265, Version 4' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPEG-1">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Coding of
          moving pictures and associated audio for digital storage media at up
          to about 1,5 Mbit/s -- Part 2: Video</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="1993"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name='ISO/IEC' value='11172-2:1993' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPEG-2">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Generic coding
          of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 2:
          Video</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name='ISO/IEC' value='13818-2:2013' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPEG-4">
        <front>
          <title>Information technology -- Coding of
          audio-visual objects -- Part 2: Visual</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2004"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name='ISO/IEC' value='14496-2:2004' />
      </reference>
    </references>

     <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors want to thank Mo Zanaty for useful discussions.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
