<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1321 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2046 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2141 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2141.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2288 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2288.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2611 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2611.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3044 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3044.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3187 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3187.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3188 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3188.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3406 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6234 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3406.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8141 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8141.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8254 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8254.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8174 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8458" 
     ipr="trust200902"  
     category="info"
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     obsoletes='3188'>

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="NBN URNs">Using National Bibliography Numbers as Uniform Resource Names</title>

    <author fullname="Juha Hakala" initials="J." surname="Hakala">
      <organization>The National Library of Finland</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 26</street>
          <city/> <region/>
          <code>FIN-00014 Helsinki University</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>juha.hakala@helsinki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2018" />

    <!-- You can add <keyword/> elements here. -->
    <keyword>National bibliography numbers</keyword>
    <keyword>Uniform resource names</keyword>


    <abstract>
      <t>   National Bibliography Numbers (NBNs) are used by national
       libraries and other organizations in order to identify
       resources in their collections. NBNs are usually applied
       to resources that are not catered for by established (standard) identifier
       systems such as International Standard Book Number (ISBN).</t>
      <t> A Uniform Resource Name (URN) namespace for NBNs was established in
           2001 in RFC 3188.  Since then, a number of European national libraries
           have implemented URN:NBN-based systems.</t>
      <t> This document replaces RFC 3188 and defines how NBNs can be supported
           within the updated URN framework.  A revised namespace registration
           (version 4) compliant to RFC 8141 is included.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>One of the basic permanent Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes (cf.&nbsp;<xref
      target="RFC3986"/> and <xref target="IANA-URI"/>) is Uniform Resource
      Name (URN).  URNs were originally defined in <xref
      target="RFC2141">RFC 2141</xref>.  In 2017, a revision was adopted with
      new definitions and registration procedures <xref target="RFC8141"/>.
      Any traditional identifier, when used within the URN system, must have a
      namespace of its own that is registered with IANA <xref target="IANA-URN"/>. National
      Bibliography Number (NBN) is one such namespace, specified in 2001 in
      <xref target="RFC3188">RFC 3188</xref>.</t>

      <t>This document describes the syntax and usage of NBN URNs and updates the
	registration of the associated URN namespace. This document additionally describes
	certain policy assumptions about how national libraries and their partner
	organizations partition, delegate, and manage the namespace. Violation of those
	assumptions could impact the utility of the NBN URN namespace.</t>
      <t>URN:NBNs are in production use in several European countries
          including (in alphabetical order) Austria, Finland, Germany, Hungary,
                  Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, and Switzerland.  The URN:NBN
          namespace is collectively managed by these national libraries.  URN:
          NBNs have been applied to diverse content including Web archives,
          digitized materials, research data, and doctoral dissertations.  They
          can be used by national libraries and organizations cooperating
          with them.</t>
       <t> As a part of the initial development of the URN system in the
          late 1990s, the IETF URN Working Group agreed that it was important
          to demonstrate that the URN syntax can accommodate existing
          identifier systems. 
   RFC 2288 <xref target="RFC2288"/> investigated the feasibility of using
   ISBN, ISSN, and SICI (Serial Item and Contribution Identifier) as
   URNs, with positive results; however, it did not formally register
   corresponding URN namespaces.  (For further discussion of how these 
   systems have evolved as URNs, see RFC 8254 <xref target="RFC8254"/>.)
   This was in part due to the still-evolving process to formalize criteria
   for namespace definition documents and registration.  The criteria were 
   consolidated later in the IETF, first in RFC 2611 <xref target="RFC2611"/>, then RFC 3406
   <xref target="RFC3406"/>, and now RFC 8141 <xref target="RFC8141"/>.</t>

    <t> URN namespaces have been registered for NBN, ISBN, and ISSN in RFCs 3188
    <xref target="RFC3188"/>, 3187 <xref target="RFC3187"/>, and 3044 <xref target="RFC3044"/>, respectively. ISBN and ISSN namespaces
       were made compliant with RFC 8141 <xref target="RFC8141"/> in 2017
       by publishing revised ISSN <xref target="ISSN-namespace"/> and ISBN
       <xref target="ISBN-namespace"/> namespace registrations. </t>
    <t>  The term "National Bibliography Number" encompasses persistent local
       identifier systems that national libraries and their partner
       organizations use in addition to the more formally (and
       internationally) established identifiers.
       These partner organizations include universities and their
       libraries and other subsidiaries, other research
       institutions, plus governmental and public organizations.
	   Some national libraries maintain a significant number
       of these liaison relationships; for instance, the German National Library
           had almost 400 by early 2018 <xref target="NBN-Resolving"/>.</t>

    <t> In practice, NBN differs
       from standard identifier systems such as ISBN and ISSN because it is
       not a single identifier system with standard-specified scope and syntax.
       Each NBN implementer creates its own system with its own
       syntax and assignment rules. Each user organization is also
       obliged to keep track of how NBNs are being
       used; however, within the generic framework set in this document, local
       NBN assignment policies may vary considerably.</t>
    <t>  Historically, NBNs have been applied in the national bibliographies
       to identify the resources catalogued into them.  Prior to the emergence
       of bibliographic standard identifiers in the early
       1970s, national libraries assigned NBNs to all catalogued publications. </t>
    <t> Since the late 1990s, the NBN scope has been extended to cover a
       vast range of resources, both originally digital and digitized.
       Only a small subset of these resources is catalogued in
       the national bibliographies or other bibliographic databases.
       Digitized resources and their component parts (such as still
       images in books or journal articles) are examples of resources
       that may get NBNs.</t>
    <t> It is possible to extend the scope of the NBN much further.
       The National Library of Finland is using them in the Finnish
       National Ontology Service Finto to identify corporate names
       (see &lt;http://finto.fi/cn/en/&gt;).
       Using NBNs to identify metadata elements provides a stable basis for
       creation of linked data.</t>
    <t>  Simple guidelines for using NBNs as URNs and the original namespace
       registration were published in RFC 3188 <xref target="RFC3188"/>.  The RFC at hand
       replaces RFC 3188; sections discussing the methods by which URN:NBNs
       should be resolved have been updated, unused features have been
       eliminated, and the text is compliant with the stipulations of the
       revised URN specification <xref target="RFC8141"/>.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
       <t>   "NBN" refers to any National Bibliography Number identifier system
           used by the national libraries
           (or equivalent organizations) and other institutions,
           which use these identifiers with national libraries' support and
           permission.</t>
       <t> In this memo, "URN:NBN" is used as a shorthand for
           "NBN-based URN".</t>

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Fundamental Namespace and Community Considerations for NBN">
       <section title="The URN:NBN Namespace">
          <t>NBNs are widely used to identify both hand-held and digital resources
           in the collections of national libraries and other
           institutions that are responsible for preserving the cultural
           heritage of their constituents.  Resources in these collections
           are usually preserved for a long time (i.e., for
           centuries).  While the preferred methods for
           digital preservation may vary over time and depend on the content,
           the favorite one has been migration.  Whenever necessary, a
           resource in an outdated file format is migrated into a more modern file
           format.  To the extent possible, all old versions of the resource are also kept in order to
           alleviate the negative effects of partially successful
           migrations and the gradual loss of original look and feel that
           may accompany even fully successful migrations.  When NBN is used to identify manifestations and
           there are many of them for a single work, local policy can require that each
           manifestation ought to have its own NBN.</t>
        <t>NBNs are typically used to identify objects for which standard identifiers such
           as ISBN are not applicable.  However, NBNs can be used for component
           resources even when the resource as a whole qualifies for a standard
           identifier.  For instance, if a digitized book has an
           ISBN, JPEG image files of its pages might be assigned NBNs.  These
           URN:NBNs can be used as persistent links to the pages.</t>
        <t>The scope of standard identifier systems such as ISBN and ISSN is
           limited; they are applicable only to certain kinds of resources.
           One of the roles of the NBN is to fill in the gaps left by the standard identifiers.
           Collectively, these identifiers and NBNs cover
           all resources that national libraries and
           their partners need to include in their collections.</t>
        <t><xref target="NBNs"/> below, and particularly
           <xref target="NBN-assignment"/>, present a more
           detailed overview of the structure of the NBN namespace, related
           institutions, and the identifier assignment principles used.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Community Considerations for NBNs">
       <t>National libraries are the key organizations providing persistent URN
           resolution services for resources identified with NBNs, independent
           of their form.  As coordinators of NBN usage, national libraries have allowed other organizations, such
           as university libraries or governmental organizations, to assign NBNs
           to the resources these organizations preserve for the long term.  In such case, the
           national library coordinates the use of NBNs at the national
           level.  National libraries can also provide URN resolution services
           and technical services to other NBN users.  These
           organizations are expected to
           either establish their own URN resolution services or use the
           technical infrastructure provided by the national library.
           URN:NBNs are expected to be resolvable
           and support one or more resolution services.</t>

        <t>Although NBNs can be used to identify component resources, the NBN
           namespace does not specify a generic, intrinsic syntax for doing
           that.  However, there are at least two different ways in which
           component resources can be taken into account within the NBN
           namespace.</t>

        <t>The simplest and probably the most common approach is to
           assign a separate NBN for each component
           resource, such as a file containing a digitized page of a book, and
           make no provisions to make such NBNs discernible in a systematic
           way from others.</t>

        <t>Second, if the stipulations of the
           URI generic syntax <xref target="RFC3986"/> and the
           Internet media type specification <xref target="RFC2046"/>
           are met, in accordance with the provisions in <xref target="RFC8141">RFC 8141</xref>, the
           URN f-component can be attached to URN:NBNs in order to
           indicate the desired location within the resource supplied
           by URN resolution. </t>

        <t>From the library community point of view, it is important that the f-component is not a part of
           the Namespace-Specific String (NSS), and therefore f-component attachment does not mean that the relevant component part is identified.
           Moreover, the resolution process still retrieves the entire resource even if there is an
           f-component.  The component part selection is applied by the
           resolution client (e.g., browser) to the resource returned by the
           resolution process.  In other words, in this latter case the
           component parts are just logical and physical parts of the
           identified resource whereas in the former cases they are independently named entities.</t>

        <t>  Resources identified by NBNs are not always available in the
           Internet.  If one is not, the URN:NBN can resolve to a surrogate such as a metadata record
           describing the identified resource.</t>

        <t> <xref target="NBNs"/> below, and
           particularly <xref target="NBN-ResolvePersist"/>, presents a
           detailed overview of the application of the URN:NBN namespace as well
           as the principles of, and systems used for, the resolution of NBN&nbhy;based URNs.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="National Bibliography Number URNs" anchor="NBNs">
     <section title="Assignment" anchor="NBN-assignment">
        <t> National Bibliography Number (NBN) is a generic term referring to a
           group of identifier systems administered by national libraries
           and institutions authorized by them.  The NBN assignment is typically
           performed by the organization hosting the resource.  National
           libraries are committed to permanent preservation of their
           deposit collections.</t>
            <t>  Assignment of NBN-based URNs is controlled on a national level
              by the national library (or national libraries, if
              there is more than one).  National guidelines can differ, but the
              identified resources themselves are usually persistent.</t>

            <t>  Different national URN:NBN assignment policies have resulted in varying
              levels of control of the assignment process.  Manual URN:NBN
              assignment by the library personnel provides the tightest control,
              especially if the URN:NBNs cover only resources catalogued into
              the national bibliography.  In most national libraries,
              the scope of URN:NBN is already much broader than this.
              Usage rules can vary within one
              country, from one URN:NBN sub-namespace to the next.</t>

        <t> Each national library uses NBNs independently of other national
           libraries; apart from this document, there are no guidelines
           that specify or control NBN usage.  As such, NBNs are unique
           only on the national level.  When used as URNs, base NBN strings MUST
           be augmented with a controlled prefix, which is the particular
           nation's ISO 3166-1 alpha-2 two-letter country code
           (referred to as "ISO country code" below)
           <xref target="ISO3166-1"/>.  These prefixes
           guarantee uniqueness of the URN:NBNs at the global scale
           <xref target='ISO3166MA'/>.</t>

        <t> National libraries using URN:NBNs usually specify local assignment
           policies for themselves. Such policy can limit the URN:NBN usage to, e.g., the
           resources stored in the national library's digital collections
           or databases.  Although this specification does not specify principles for
           URN:NBN assignment policies that can be applied, NBNs assigned to
           short-lived resources should not be made URN:NBNs unless such policy can be justified.</t>

        <t> URN:NBN assignment policy can clarify, for instance, the local policy
           concerning identifier assignment to component parts of resources
	   and can specify, with
           sufficient detail, the syntax of local component identifiers (if
           there is one as a discernible part of the NBNs).  The policy can also
           cover any employed extensions to the default NBN scope.</t>
        <t> NBNs as such are locally but not globally unique; two national libraries can
              assign the same NBN to different resources.  A prefix,
              based on the ISO country code as described above,
              guarantees the global uniqueness of URN:NBNs.
              Once an NBN has been assigned to a resource, it MUST
              be persistent, and therefore URN:NBNs are persistent as well.</t>
        <t> A URN:NBN, once it has been generated from a NBN, MUST NOT be reused for another resource.</t>
        <t> Users of the URN:NBN namespace MUST ensure that they do not assign
              the same URN:NBN twice.  Different policies can be applied to
              guarantee this.  For instance, NBNs and corresponding URN:NBNs can
              be assigned sequentially by programs in order to avoid human
              mistakes.  It is also possible to use printable representations of
              checksums such as SHA-1 <xref target="RFC6234"/> as NBNs.</t>
    </section>
     <section title="Syntax" anchor="NBN-syntax">
            <t>  The Namespace-Specific String (NSS) will consist of
              three parts:
              <list style="symbols">
                 <t> a prefix consisting of an ISO 3166-1 alpha-2 country code and
                    optional sub-namespace code(s) separated by a 
                    colon(s);</t>
                 <t>a hyphen (-) as the delimiting character; and,</t>
                 <t>an NBN string assigned by the national library or sub-delegated
                    authority.</t>
               </list></t>

                <t> The following formal definition uses ABNF <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>
<!-- .... Putting this syntax in as a Figure because I'm too lazy at
                 present to convert it to hanging indented lists or a
                 table ..Jck 20170226  ....
		  RFC Editor: please reformat at your discretion 

[From the RFC Editor] Actually, it's fine to put ABNF in artwork.
-->

<!-- [rfced] The ABNF below does not parse using Bill's ABNF parser
(https://tools.ietf.org/tools/bap/abnf.cgi). Each underscore character
gives an error as follows:
  error: Illegal character '_' - skipping to end of line

Please review and let us know whether any changes should be made 
to the ABNF syntax.
-->

      <figure>
        <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
    nbn-nss     = prefix "-" nbn-string

    prefix      = iso-cc *( ":" subspc )
                ; The entire prefix is case insensitive.

    iso-cc      = 2ALPHA
                ; Alpha-2 country code as assigned by part 1 of ISO 3166
                ; (identifies the national library to which the branch
                ; is delegated).

    subspc      = 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT)
                ; As assigned by the respective national library.

    nbn-string  = path-rootless
                ; The "path-rootless" rule is defined in RFC 3986.
                ; Syntax requirements specified in RFC 8141 MUST be
                ; taken into account.
            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

            <t>A colon SHOULD be used within the prefix only as a delimiting character
              between the ISO 3166-1 country code and sub-namespace code(s),
              which splits the national namespace into smaller parts.</t>
            <t>  The structure (if any) of the nbn_string is determined by the authority for the prefix.
              Whereas the prefix is regarded as case insensitive, NBN
              strings
              can be case sensitive at the preference of the assigning
              authority; parsers therefore MUST treat these as case sensitive,
	      and 
              any case mapping needed to introduce case insensitivity is the responsibility
              of the relevant resolution system.</t>
            <t>A hyphen SHOULD be used as the delimiting character between the prefix
              and the NBN string.  Within the NBN string, a hyphen MAY be used for
              separating different sections of the identifier from one another.</t>
            <t> All two-letter codes are reserved by the ISO 3166 Maintenance
              Agency for either existing or possible future ISO country codes
              (or for private use).</t>
            <t>  Sub-namespace identifiers MUST be registered on the national level
              by the national library that assigned the identifier.  The list of such
              identifiers can be made publicly available via the Web.</t>

           <t>Note that because case mapping for ASCII letters is
              completely reversible and does not lose information,
              the case used in case-insensitive matching is a local
              matter. Implementations can convert to lower or upper
              case as they see fit; they only need to do it
              consistently.</t>

           <section title="Usage of r-component and q-component">

            <t>  URN:NBN resolvers do not currently support the use of either r-component or q-component.
                 </t>

            <t>  Resolution services based on r-component can be implemented in the future
              when the r-component syntax and semantics have been specified.
              </t>

                   </section>
           <section title="Usage of f-component">

            <t>  If URN:NBN resolves to the identified resource and the media type
              of the resource supports f-component usage, it
              can be used to indicate a location within the
              identified resource. Persistence is achieved if the
             URN:NBN is assigned to one and only one version of a
              resource, such as a PDF/A version of a book.
              </t>

              <t>  The URN:NBN namespace does not impose any restrictions of its own
              on f-component usage.
              </t>
                   </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Encoding Considerations and Lexical Equivalence">
        <t> Expressing NBNs as URNs is usually straightforward, as
           normally only ASCII characters are used in NBN strings.
           If this is not the case, non-ASCII characters in
           NBNs MUST be translated into canonical form as specified in
           RFC 8141. If a national library uses NBNs that can contain percent-encoded
           characters higher than U+007F, the library needs to carefully define the canonical
           transformation from these NBNs into URNs, including normalization forms. </t>

        <t> When an NBN is used as a URN, the NSS
           MUST consist of three parts:
           <list style="symbols">
              <t>a prefix, structured as a primary prefix, which is a two-letter
              ISO 3166-1 country code of the library's country, and zero or
	      more secondary prefixes that are each
              indicated by a delimiting colon character (:) and a sub-namespace
              identifier;</t>
           <t>a hyphen (-) as a delimiting character; and,</t>
           <t>the NBN string.</t>
        </list></t>

        <t> Different delimiting characters are not semantically
           equivalent.</t>

        <t> The syntax and roles of the three parts listed above are
           described in <xref target="NBN-syntax"/>.</t>

        <t> If there are several national libraries in one country, these
           libraries MUST agree on how to divide the national namespace between
           themselves using this method before the URN:NBN assignment begins in
           any of these libraries.</t>

        <t>A national library MAY also assign URN:NBN sub-namespaces to trusted
           organizations such as universities or government
           institutions.
           The sub-namespace MAY be further divided by the partner
           organization.
           All sub-namespace identifiers used within a country-code-based
           namespace MUST be registered on the national level by the national
           library that assigned the code.
		   The national register of these codes
           SHOULD be made available online.</t>
        <t> Being part of the prefix, sub-namespace identifier strings are case-
           insensitive.  They MUST NOT contain any colons or hyphens.</t>

            <t>  Formally, two URN:NBNs are lexically equivalent if they are octet-
              by-octet equal after the following (conceptional)
              preprocessing: <vspace blankLines="0"/>
              <list style="numbers">
                 <t>convert all characters in the leading "urn:nbn:"
                    token to a single case;</t>
                 <t>convert all characters in the prefix (country code
                    and its optional sub-divisions) to a single case; and, </t>
                 <t>convert all characters embedded in any
                    percent-encodings to a single case.</t>
              </list></t>

        <t> Models (indicated line break inserted for readability):
           <list style="empty">
              <t>URN:NBN:&lt;ISO 3166 alpha-2 country
                 code&gt;-&lt;assigned NBN string&gt; </t>

              <t>URN:NBN:&lt;ISO 3166 alpha-2 country code&gt;:&lt;sub-namespace code&gt;-\
                  &lt;assigned NBN string&gt;</t>
            </list></t>

        <t> Examples:
           <list style="empty">
              <t> URN:NBN:fi-fe201003181510 </t>
              <t> urn:nbn:ch:bel-9039</t>
              <t> urn:nbn:se:uu:diva-3475</t>
              <t> urn:nbn:hu-3006 </t>
           </list></t>
     </section>

     <section title="Resolution and Persistence of NBN-based URNs"
             anchor="NBN-ResolvePersist">
        <t> Eventually, URNs might be resolved with the help of a Global Resolver
           Discovery Service (GRDS), and URN:NBN syntax makes it possible to locate the
           relevant resolver.  Since no GRDS system has been installed yet
           in the Internet, URN:NBNs are embedded in HTTP URIs in order
           to make them actionable in the present Internet.  In these HTTP URIs,
           the authority part must point to the appropriate URN resolution
           service.  For instance, in Finland, the address of the national URN
           resolver is &lt;http://urn.fi&gt;.  Thus, the HTTP URI for the Finnish URN
           in the example above is &lt;http://urn.fi/URN:NBN:fi-fe201003181510&gt;.
           </t>

        <t> The country-code-based prefix part of the URN:NBN namespace-specific
           string will provide a hint needed to find the correct
           resolution service for URN:NBNs from the GRDS when it is established.</t>
        <t> There are three interrelated aspects of persistence that need to be
           discussed: persistence of the objects itself, persistence of the
           identifier, and persistence of the URN resolvers.</t>
        <t> NBNs have traditionally been assigned to printed resources, which
           tend to be persistent.  In contrast, digital resources require
           frequent migrations to guarantee accessibility.  Although it is
           impossible to estimate how often migrations are needed, hardware and
           software upgrades take place frequently, and a lifetime exceeding
           10-20 years can be considered as long.</t>
        <t> However, it is a common practice to keep also the original
           and previously migrated versions of resources.  Therefore, even
           outdated versions of resources can be available in digital archives,
           no matter how old or difficult to use they have become. </t>

        <t> If all versions of a resource are kept, a user who
           requires authenticity can retrieve the original version of the
           resource, whereas a user to whom the ease of use is a priority is likely
           to be satisfied with the latest version.  In order to enable
           the users to find the best match, a national library can link
           all manifestations of a resource to each
           other so as to make a user aware of them.</t>
        <t> Thus, even if specific versions of digital resources are
           not normally persistent, persistent identifiers such as URN:NBNs
           support information architectures that enable
           persistent access to any version of the resource,
           including ones that can only be utilized by
           using digital archaeology tools such as custom-made
           applications to render the resource.</t>
        <t> Persistence of URN resolvers themselves is mainly an organizational
           issue that is related to the persistence of organizations maintaining them.
           As URN:NBN resolution services will be supplied (primarily) by the
           national libraries, these services are likely to be long lived.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Additional Considerations">
       <t> It is a good idea to apply URN:NBNs (or other persistent identifiers)
          to all resources that have been prioritized in the
          organization's digital preservation plan.</t>
       <t> Assignment of URN:NBNs to resources that are known to not be
           persistent should be considered carefully. URN:NBNs
           can, however, be applied to resources that have a low-level preservation
           priority and will not be migrated to more modern file
           formats or preserved via emulation.</t>
        <t> If the identified version of a resource has disappeared,
           the resolution process can supply a surrogate if one exists.
           A surrogate can be, for instance, a
           more modern digital version of the original electronic resource.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="URN Namespace ID (NID) Registration for the National Bibliography Number (NBN)"
             anchor="RegistrationSpec">
        <t>  This URN namespace registration describes how National Bibliography
           Numbers (NBNs) can be supported within the URN framework;
           it uses the updated IANA template specified in RFC 8141.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="Namespace Identifier:  NBN"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
              This namespace ID was formally assigned to the National
	      Bibliography Number in October 2001, when the namespace was
              registered officially <xref target="RFC3188"/>.  Utilization of URN:NBNs had started in
              demo systems already in 1998.  Since 2001, tens of millions of
              URN:NBNs have been assigned.  The number of users of the namespace
              has grown in two ways: new national libraries have started using
              NBNs, and many national libraries using the system have formed new
              liaisons.</t>

           <t hangText="Version:">4</t>

           <t hangText="Date:">2018-04-09</t>

           <t hangText="Registrant:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
              Name: Juha Hakala<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              Affiliation: Senior Adviser, The National Library of Finland<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              Email: juha.hakala@helsinki.fi<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              Postal: P.O.&nbsp;Box 15, 00014 Helsinki University, Finland<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              Web URL: http://www.nationallibrary.fi/<vspace blankLines="1"/>

              The National Library of Finland registered the namespace on behalf
              of the Conference of the European National Librarians (CENL) and
              Conference of Directors of National Libraries (CDNL).
              The NBN
              namespace is available for free for the national libraries.  They
              can allow other organizations to assign URN:NBNs and use the
              resolution services established by the library for free or for a
              fee.  The fees, if collected, can be based on, e.g., the
              maintenance costs of the system.</t>

           <t hangText="Purpose:">See Section 3 of RFC 8458</t>

           <t hangText="Syntax:">See Section 4.2 of RFC 8458</t>
           <t hangText="Assignment:">See Section 4.1 of RFC 8458</t>

    <t hangText="Security and Privacy:">See Section 7 of RFC 8458</t>

<t hangText="Interoperability:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>

              National libraries and their partners usually apply URN:NBNs if a standard
              identifier such as ISBN is not applicable for the resource to be
              identified. Some overlap with other URN namespaces is
              possible.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>

              URN:NBNs may contain characters which must be percent-encoded,
              but usually they consist of printable ASCII characters only.</t>

           <t hangText="Resolution:">See Section 4.4 of RFC 8458</t>

           <t hangText="Documentation:">RFC 8458</t>

<t hangText="Revision Information:"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
      This version of the URN:NBN namespace registration has been updated to use the revised
     definition of URN syntax from RFC 8141, although usage of r-components is not specified yet.
     In addition, non-ISO 3166 (country code) based NBNs have been deleted
     due to lack of deployment.  The entire NBN prefix is now specified
     to be case insensitive in accordance with established practice.
     This version also includes numerous clarifications based on actual usage
     of URN:NBNs.</t>
           </list></t>
        </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
       <t> IANA has updated the existing registration of the formal URN
           namespace, "NBN", using the template given above in
           <xref target="RegistrationSpec"/>.
           </t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
       <t> This document defines means of encoding NBNs as URNs.  A URN
           resolution service for NBN-based URNs is depicted but only at a
           generic level; thus, questions of secure or authenticated resolution
           mechanisms and authentication of users are out of scope of this
           document.</t>

            <t>Although no validation mechanisms are specified on the global level (beyond a routine check of
              those characters that require special encoding when employed in
              URIs), NBNs assigned by any given authority can have a well-specified and rich syntax (including,
              e.g., fixed length and checksum).  In such cases, it is possible to
              validate the correctness of NBNs programmatically.</t>

     <t>Issues regarding intellectual property rights associated with objects
           identified by the URN:NBNs are beyond the scope of this
           document, as are questions about rights to the databases that might
           be used to construct resolution services.</t>

        <t>  Beyond the generic security considerations laid out in the underlying
           documents listed in the Normative References, no
           specific security threats have been identified for
           NBN-based URNs.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

     <references title="Normative References">

      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3986;
      &rfc5234;
      &rfc8141;
      &rfc8174;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

   &rfc2046;
   &rfc2141;
   &rfc2288;
   &rfc2611;
   &rfc3044;
   &rfc3187;
   &rfc3188;
   &rfc3406;
   &rfc6234;
   &rfc8254;

   <reference anchor="PERSID" target="http://www.persid.org">
      <front>
         <title>persid: Building a persistent identifier
            infrastructure</title>
         <author><organization> PersID initiative, 2009-2011</organization> </author>
         <date/>
      </front>
   </reference>

<!-- Note to RFC Editor: Second character of fuer and first of ueber
   should properly be U+00FC and immediately following "e" should be
   dropped  -->

   <reference anchor="NBN-Resolving"
              target="https://nbn-resolving.org/institutions">
      <front>
         <title>URN:NBN Resolver fuer Deutschland und Schweiz:
            Information ueber Partner Institutionen </title>
         <author><organization>Deutsche Nationalbibliothek</organization> </author>
         <date/>
      </front>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="ISBN-namespace" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-formal/isbn">
      <front>
         <title>Namespace Registration for International Standard Book Number (ISBN) ISO 2108:2017</title>
         <author  initials="S." surname="Griffiths">
            <organization>The International ISBN Agency</organization>
            <address/>
         </author>
         <date/>
      </front>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="ISSN-namespace" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-formal/issn">
      <front>
         <title>Namespace Registration for International Standard Serial Number (ISSN) and Linking ISSN (ISSN-L) based on ISO 3297:2007</title>
         <author  initials="G." surname="Bequet">
            <organization>The ISSN International Centre</organization>
            <address/>
         </author>
         <date month="June" year="2017"/>
      </front>
   </reference>

<reference anchor="IANA-URI" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes">
      <front>
         <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes</title>
         <author >
            <organization>IANA</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
   </reference>


   <reference anchor="IANA-URN" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-namespaces">
      <front>
         <title>Uniform Resource Names (URN) Namespaces</title>
         <author >
            <organization>IANA</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date />
        </front>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="ISO3166-1"
              target="https://www.iso.org/standard/63545.html">
      <front>
         <title>Codes for the representation of names of countries
            and their subdivisions -- Part 1: Country codes</title>
         <author >
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2013" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="3166-1:2013"/>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="ISO3166MA" target="https://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes.htm">
      <front>
         <title>ISO 3166 Country Codes</title>
         <author >
            <organization>ISO</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <date />
        </front>
   </reference>

    </references>


<!--   Sections below here become  Appendices.  -->

    <section title="Significant Changes from RFC 3188">
       <t>Numerous clarifications have been made based on a decade of experience with
          RFC 3188.</t>
       <t> NBNs that are not based on ISO 3166 (country codes) have been removed
          due to lack of usage.</t>
       <t> In accordance with established practice, the whole NBN
          prefix is now declared case insensitive.</t>
       <t> The document is based on the new URN syntax specification, RFC 8141.</t>
       <t> Use of query components and fragment components with this namespace is now
           specified in accordance with RFC 8141.</t>
    </section>


<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>Revision of RFC 3188 started during the project PersID <xref
target="PERSID"/>. Later, the revision was included in the charter of the URNbis
Working Group and worked on in that group in parallel with what became RFCs
8141 and 8254. The author wishes to thank his colleagues in the PersID
project and the URNbis participants for their support and review comments.</t>

<t>Tommi Jauhiainen has provided feedback on an early draft version of this
document. The author wishes to thank Tommi Jauhiainen, Bengt Neiss, and Lars
Svensson for the comments they have provided to various draft versions of this
document.</t>

<t>John Klensin provided significant editorial and advisory support for later
draft versions of the document.</t>
</section>

<section title="Contributors" numbered="no">

  <!-- Note to RFC Editor.  Correct spelling of name is H\u'00F6'nes.
     -->

<t>This document would not have been possible without contributions by Alfred
Hoenes.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>

