<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8371" category="std" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
  <front>
<title abbrev="MN Identifier Types for MIPv6">
	Mobile Node Identifier Types for MIPv6</title>

   <author fullname="Charles E. Perkins" initials="C.E." surname="Perkins">
      <organization abbrev="Futurewei">Futurewei Inc. </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <code>95050</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-408-330-4586</phone>
        <email>charliep@computer.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="V." surname="Devarapalli" fullname="Vijay Devarapalli">
       <organization>Vasona Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2900 Lakeside Drive, Suite 180</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA 95054</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
	<email>dvijay@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2018"/>  

  <area>Internet</area>
  <workgroup>Distributed Mobility Management [dmm]</workgroup>
<keyword>Mobility</keyword>
<keyword>IPv6</keyword>
<keyword>Authentication</keyword>


<abstract>

<t>
	This document defines additional identifier type numbers for use with
	the mobile node identifier option for Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) as
	defined by RFC 4283.
</t>
</abstract>

</front>
<middle>
<section anchor='intro' title='Introduction'>
<t>
	The "Mobile Node Identifier Option for Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6)"
	<xref target="RFC4283"/>
	has proved to be a popular design tool for providing
	identifiers for mobile nodes during authentication procedures
	with Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) protocols
	such as Diameter <xref target="RFC6733"/>. 
	To date, only a single
	type of identifier has been specified, namely the Mobile Node (MN)
	NAI.

	Other types of identifiers are in common use and are even 
	referenced in RFC 4283.  In this document, we propose adding some
	basic identifier types that are defined in various telecommunications
	standards, including types for International Mobile Subscriber
	Identity (IMSI) <xref target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/>,
	Packet - Temporary Mobile Subscriber Identity (P-TMSI) <xref
	target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/>, 
	International Mobile station Equipment Identities (IMEI) <xref
	target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/>, and Globally Unique Temporary UE Identity (GUTI) <xref
		target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/>.  

In addition, we
	specify the IPv6 address itself and IEEE MAC-layer addresses
	as Mobile Node identifiers.
	Defining identifiers that are tied to the physical elements of the
	device (e.g., the MAC address)
	help in deployment of Mobile IP
	because, in many cases, such identifiers are the most natural means
	for uniquely identifying the device and will avoid additional
	lookup steps that might be needed if other identifiers were used.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="acronyms_terms" title="Terminology">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
</section>

 
<section anchor='types'
	title='New Mobile Node Identifier Types'>

<t>
	The following types of identifiers are commonly used
	to identify mobile nodes.  For each type, references are
	provided with full details on the format of the type
	of identifier.
</t>

    <texttable title="Mobile Node Identifier Description" anchor='mnid-types'>
	<preamble/>
	<ttcol align='left'>Identifier Type</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>
	<c> IPv6 Address </c> <c> </c> <c> <xref target="RFC4291"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c> IMSI </c>
	    <c> International Mobile Subscriber Identity </c>
	        <c> <xref target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c> P-TMSI </c>
	    <c> Packet - Temporary Mobile Subscriber Identity </c>
	        <c> <xref target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>

	<c> GUTI </c>
	    <c> Globally Unique Temporary UE Identity </c>
	        <c> <xref target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c> EUI-48 Address </c>
	    <c> 48-Bit Extended Unique Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="IEEE802"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c> EUI-64 Address </c>
	    <c> 64-Bit Extended Unique Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="IEEE802"/> </c>
	<c></c><c></c><c></c>
	<c> DUID </c>
	    <c> DHCPv6 Unique Identifier</c>
	        <c> <xref target="RFC3315"/> </c>

    </texttable>

</section>

<section anchor='descr' title='Descriptions of MN Identifier Types'>

<t>
	This section provides descriptions for the various MN identifier types.
</t>

<section anchor='descr-ipv6' title='Description of the IPv6 Address Type'>

<t>
	The IPv6 address <xref target="RFC4291"/> is encoded as a 16-octet
	string containing a full IPv6 address that has been assigned to the
	mobile node.  The IPv6 address MUST be a unicast routable IPv6 address.
	Multicast addresses, link-local
	addresses, and the unspecified IPv6 address MUST NOT be used.  IPv6
	Unique Local Addresses (ULAs) MAY be used as long as any security
	operations making use of the ULA also take into
	account the domain in which the ULA is guaranteed to be unique.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-imsi' title='Description of the IMSI MN Identifier Type'>

<t>
	The International Mobile Subscriber Identity (IMSI)
	<xref target="ThreeGPP-IDS"/> is at most 15 decimal digits
	(i.e., digits from 0 through 9).  The IMSI MUST be
	encoded as a string of octets in network order (i.e., high to low
	for all digits), where each digit occupies 4 bits.  If needed for
	full octet size, the last digit MUST be padded with 0xf.  For instance,
	an example IMSI 123456123456789 would be encoded as follows:
</t>

	<t>
	<list style='hanging'>
	<t hangText=''>	0x12, 0x34, 0x56, 0x12, 0x34, 0x56, 0x78, 0x9f </t>
	</list>
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-eui48' title='Description of the EUI-48 Address Type'>

<t>
	The IEEE EUI-48 address <xref target="IEEE802-GUIDELINES"/> is encoded
	as 6 octets containing the IEEE EUI-48 address.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-eui64' title='Description of the EUI-64 Address Type'>

<t>
	The IEEE EUI-64 address <xref target="IEEE802-GUIDELINES"/> is encoded
	as 8 octets containing the full IEEE EUI-64 address.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-duid' title='Description of the DUID Type'>

<t>
	The DUID is the DHCPv6 Unique Identifier
	<xref target="RFC3315"/>.  There are various types of DUIDs, which are
	distinguished by an initial two-octet type field.  Clients and servers
	MUST treat DUIDs as opaque values and MUST only compare DUIDs for
	equality.
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor='sec' title='Security Considerations'>

<t>
	This document does not introduce any security mechanisms
	and does not have any impact on existing security mechanisms.
</t>

<t>
	Mobile node identifiers such as those described in this document are
	considered to be private information.  If used in the MN identifier extension
	as defined in  <xref target="RFC4283"/>, the packet including the MN identifier
	extension MUST be
	encrypted so that no personal information or trackable identifiers
	are inadvertently disclosed to passive observers.
	Operators can potentially apply IPsec Encapsulating Security Payload
	(ESP) <xref target="RFC4303"/> in transport mode with confidentiality
	and integrity protection for protecting the identity and location
	information in MIPv6 signaling messages.
</t>

<t>
	Some MN identifiers contain sensitive identifiers that, as used in
	protocols specified by other Standards Development Organizations
	(SDOs), are only used for signaling
	during initial network entry.  In such protocols, subsequent
	exchanges then rely on a temporary identifier allocated during the
	initial network entry.  Managing the association between
	long-lived and temporary identifiers is outside the scope
	of this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor='iana' title='IANA Considerations'>

<t>
   The new mobile node identifier types defined in this document have been
   assigned values from the "Mobile Node Identifier Option Subtypes"
   registry. The following values have been registered. 
</t>

    <texttable anchor='iana-mnids' title="New Mobile Node Identifier Types">
    <preamble/>
        <ttcol align='left'>Identifier Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='left'>Identifier Type Number</ttcol>
	<c> IPv6 Address </c>		<c> 2 </c>
	<c> IMSI </c>			<c> 3 </c>
	<c> P-TMSI </c>			<c> 4 </c>
	<c> EUI-48 address </c>		<c> 5 </c>
	<c> EUI-64 address </c>		<c> 6 </c>
	<c> GUTI </c>			<c> 7 </c>
	<c> DUID </c>		<c> 8 </c>
	<c> Reserved  </c>		<c> 9-15 </c>
	<c> Unassigned  </c>		<c> 16-255 </c>
    </texttable>

<t>
	See <xref target='descr'/> for additional information
	about the identifier types.
The registration procedure is Standards Action
	<xref target='RFC8126'/>.
	The expert must ascertain that the identifier type allows unique
	identification of the mobile device; since all MN identifiers require
	encryption, there is no additional privacy exposure attendant to
	the use of new types.
</t>

</section>	

</middle>

<back>

<references title='Normative References'>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4291.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4283.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4303.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.8126.xml'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174.xml'?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<?rfc include='reference.RFC.6733.xml'?>

<reference anchor="ThreeGPP-IDS">
  <front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project; Technical Specification
Group Core Network and Terminals; Numbering, addressing and identification
(Release 15)</title>
    <author>
    <organization>3GPP</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2018"/>
  </front>
<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="23.003, V15.3.0"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="EPC-Tag-Data" target="https://www.gs1.org/sites/default/files/docs/epc/tds_1_1_rev_1_27-standard-20050510.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>EPC Generation 1 Tag Data Standards Version 1.1 Rev.1.27 
    </title>
    <author>
    <organization>EPCglobal, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2005"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFID-DoD-spec">
  <front>
    <title>United States Department of Defense Suppliers' Passive RFID
		  Information Guide</title>
    <author><organization>Department of Defense</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2010"/>
  </front>
<seriesInfo name="Version" value="15.0"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="IEEE802">
  <front>
    <title>IEEE Standard for Local and
    Metropolitan Area Networks: Overview and Architecture</title>
    <author>
    <organization>IEEE
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="IEEE802-GUIDELINES" target="http://standards.ieee.org/develop/regauth/tut/eui.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Guidelines for Use of Extended Unique Identifier (EUI),
    Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI), and Company ID (CID)</title>
    <author>
    <organization>IEEE</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2018"/>
  </front>
</reference>	

<reference anchor="EANUCCGS">
  <front>
    <title>General EAN.UCC Specifications</title>
    <author><organization>EAN International and the Uniform Code Council
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2004"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Version" value="5.0"/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="RFID-framework">
  <front>
    <title>Heterogeneous RFID framework design, analysis and evaluation</title>
    <author fullname="Oscar Botero" surname="Botero" initials="O.">
    <organization/>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2012"/>
  </front>
<seriesInfo name="Institut National des" value="Telecommunications"/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="TRACK-IoT">
  <front>
    <title>Heterogeneous IoT Network: TRACK-IoT Plateform</title>
    <author fullname="Hakima Chaouchi" initials="H." surname="Chaouchi" >
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2012"/>
  </front>
<seriesInfo name="Telecom SudParis," value="Internal Report"/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="Using-RFID-IPv6">
  <front>
    <title>Using RFID &amp; IPv6</title>
    <author surname="IPv6.com">
    <organization>
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2006"/>
  </front>
</reference>


</references>

<section anchor='rfid' title='RFID Types'>

    <t>
	The material in this non-normative appendix was originally
	composed for inclusion in the main body of the specification
	but was moved into an appendix because
	there was insufficient support for allocating Radio Frequency
	Identification (RFID) types at the time.  It was observed that 
	RFID-based mobile devices may
	create privacy exposures unless confidentiality is assured for
	signaling.  A specification for eliminating unauthorized RFID
	tracking based on Layer 2 addresses would be helpful.
    </t>

    <t>
	Much of the following text is due to contributions from Hakima
	Chaouchi.  For an overview and some initial suggestions about using
	RFID with IPv6 on mobile devices, see <xref target="Using-RFID-IPv6"/>.
    </t>

    <t>
	In the context of Internet of Things (IoT) and Industry 4.0, vertical domain, efficient
	inventory, and tracking items are of major interest, and RFID
	technology is the identification technology in the hardware design
	of many such items.
    </t>

    <t>
	The "TRACK-IoT" project
 	<xref target="TRACK-IoT"/> <xref target="RFID-framework"/>
	explored Mobile IPv6 as a mobility management protocol for RFID-based
	mobile devices.

	<list style="numbers">
	<t>
	    Passive RFID tags (that have no processing resources) need to be
	    handled by the gateway (likely also the RFID reader), which
	    is then the endpoint of the mobility protocol.  It is also
	    the point where the Change of Address (CoA) will be created based on some combination
	    such as the RFID tag and the prefix of that gateway.
	    The point here is to offer the possibility to passive
	    RFID items to get an IPv6 address and take advantage of the
	    mobility framework to follow the mobile device (passive tag on
	    the item).  One example scenario that has been proposed, which shows
	    the need for mobility management of passive RFID items, would be 
	    pieces of art tagged with passive tags that need to be monitored 
	    while transported.
	</t>

	<t>
Using active RFID tags (where the processing resource is available on the
tag), the endpoint of the mobility protocol can be hosted directly on the RFID
active tag, which is also called an identification sensor.  A use case for
active RFID tags includes traceability of cold food during mobility
(transport). Also, mobility of cars equipped with active RFID tags that we
already use for toll payment can be added with mobility management.
	</t>
	</list>
    </t>

    <t>
	One major effort to connect IETF efforts to EPCglobal (RFID
	standardization) led to the Object Name Service (ONS), which is the DNS version applied for RFID
	logical names and page information retrieval. Attempts have been made
	to connect IPv6 on the address space to RFID identifier format.

	Other initiatives started working on gateways to map tag identifiers
	with IPv6 addresses and build signaling protocols for the application
	level. For instance, tracking of mobile items equipped with a tag
	can be triggered remotely by a remote correspondent node until a
	visiting area where a mobile item equipped with an RFID tag is
	located.  An RFID reader will be added with an IPv6-to-RFID tag
	translation.  One option is to build a home IPv6 address of that
	tagged item by using the prefix of the home agent combined with
	the tag RFID identifier of the mobile item; as the tag ID
	is unique, the home IPv6 address of that item will be also unique.
	Then, the visiting RFID reader will compose the IPv6 care of address
	of the tagged mobile item by combining the prefix of the RFID reader
	with the tag ID of the item. MIPv6 can then normally provide the
	mobility management of that RFID-tagged item.

	A different, useful example of tagged items involves items of a
	factory that can be tracked while they are transported,	especially
	for real-time localization and tracking of precious items transported
	without GPS.  An automotive car manufacturer can assign IPv6
	addresses corresponding to RFID-tagged cars or mechanical car parts
	and build a tracking data set of the mobility not only
	of the cars, but also of the mechanical pieces.
    </t>

    <t>
	The Tag Data Standard promoted by Electronic Product Code
	(EPC) <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> supports several
	encoding systems or schemes, which are commonly used in RFID
	applications, including the following:

	<list style="symbols">
	<t> RFID-GID (Global Identifier), </t>
	<t> RFID-SGTIN (Serialized Global Trade Item Number), </t>
	<t> RFID-SSCC (Serial Shipping Container Code), </t>
	<t> RFID-SGLN (Serialized Global Location Number), </t>
	<t> RFID-GRAI (Global Returnable Asset Identifier), </t>
	<t> RFID-DOD (Department of Defense ID), and </t>
	<t> RFID-GIAI (Global Individual Asset Identifier). </t>
	</list>

	For each RFID scheme except GID, there are three representations:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t> a 64-bit binary representation (for example, SGLN-64), excluding GID, </t>
	<t> a 96-bit binary representation (SGLN-96), and </t>
	<t> a representation as a URI. </t>
	</list>

	The URI representation for the RFID is actually a URN.
	The EPC document has the following language:
	<list style="none">
	<t> All categories of URIs are represented as Uniform Reference Names 
	    (URNs) as defined by [RFC2141], where the URN Namespace is epc. </t>
	</list>

	</t>

	<t> The following list includes the above RFID types.
	</t>
    <texttable anchor='mnid-rfid' title="Mobile Node RFID Identifier
					 Description">
    <preamble/>
	<ttcol align='left'>Identifier Type</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='left'>Reference</ttcol>

	<c> RFID-SGTIN-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Serialized Global Trade Item Number </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SSCC-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Serial Shipping Container Code </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SGLN-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Serialized Global Location Number </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GRAI-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Global Returnable Asset Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-DOD-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Department of Defense ID </c>
	        <c> <xref target="RFID-DoD-spec"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GIAI-64 </c>
	    <c> 64-bit Global Individual Asset Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GID-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Global Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SGTIN-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Serialized Global Trade Item Number </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SSCC-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Serial Shipping Container </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SGLN-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Serialized Global Location Number </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GRAI-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Global Returnable Asset Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-DOD-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Department of Defense ID </c>
	        <c> <xref target="RFID-DoD-spec"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GIAI-96 </c>
	    <c> 96-bit Global Individual Asset Identifier </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GID-URI </c>
	    <c> Global Identifier represented as a URI</c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SGTIN-URI </c>
	    <c> Serialized Global Trade Item Number represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SSCC-URI </c>
	    <c> Serial Shipping Container Code represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-SGLN-URI </c>
	    <c> Global Location Number represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GRAI-URI </c>
	    <c> Global Returnable Asset Identifier represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-DOD-URI </c>
	    <c> Department of Defense ID represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="RFID-DoD-spec"/> </c>
	<c> RFID-GIAI-URI </c>
	    <c> Global Individual Asset Identifier represented as a URI </c>
	        <c> <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/> </c>
    </texttable>

<section anchor='descr-rfid' title='Description of the RFID Types'>

<t>The material in this appendix has been either quoted or loosely adapted
from <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.</t>

<t>
	The General Identifier (GID) that is used with RFID is composed of
	three fields: General Manager Number, Object Class, and Serial
	Number.  The General Manager Number identifies an organizational
	entity that is responsible for maintaining the numbers in subsequent
	fields.  GID encodings include a fourth field, the header, to
	guarantee uniqueness in the namespace defined by EPC.
</t>

<t>
	Some of the RFID types depend on the Global Trade Item Number (GTIN)
	code defined in the EAN.UCC General Specifications
	<xref target="EANUCCGS"/>.  A GTIN identifies a particular class of
	object, such as a particular kind of product or SKU.
</t>

<t>
	The EPC encoding scheme for SGTIN permits the direct embedding of
	EAN.UCC System standard GTIN and Serial Number codes on EPC tags.
	In all cases, the check digit is not encoded. Two encoding schemes
	are specified, SGTIN-64 (64 bits) and SGTIN-96 (96 bits).
</t>

<t>
	The Serial Shipping Container Code (SSCC) is defined by the EAN.UCC 
	Specifications.  Unlike the GTIN, the SSCC is already intended 
	for assignment to individual objects and therefore does not require
	additional fields to serve as an EPC pure identity. Two encoding schemes
	are specified, SSCC-64 (64 bits) and SSCC-96 (96 bits).
</t>

<t>
	The Global Location Number (GLN) is defined by the EAN.UCC
	Specifications.  A GLN can represent either a discrete, unique
	physical location such as a warehouse slot, or an aggregate physical
	location such as an entire warehouse.  In addition, a GLN can
	represent a logical entity that performs a business function such
	as placing an order.  The Serialized Global Location Number (SGLN)
	includes the Company Prefix, Location Reference, and Serial Number. 
</t>

<t>
	The Global Returnable Asset Identifier (GRAI) is defined by the
	General EAN.UCC Specifications.  Unlike the GTIN, the GRAI is already
	intended for assignment to individual objects and therefore does not
	require any additional fields to serve as an EPC pure identity. 
	The GRAI
	includes the Company Prefix, Asset Type, and Serial Number.
</t>

<t>
	The Global Individual Asset Identifier (GIAI) is defined by the
	General EAN.UCC Specifications.  Unlike the GTIN, the GIAI is already
	intended for assignment to individual objects and therefore does not
	require any additional fields to serve as an EPC pure identity. 
	The GRAI
	includes the Company Prefix and Individual Asset Reference.
</t>


<t>
	The DoD Construct identifier is defined by the United States
	Department of Defense (DoD).  This tag data construct may be used to
	encode tags for shipping goods to the DoD by a supplier who has
	already been assigned a Commercial and Government Entity (CAGE) code. 
</t>

<section anchor='descr-sgtin64' title='Description of the RFID-SGTIN-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SGTIN-64 is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SGTIN-64 includes five fields: Header, Filter Value (additional
	data that is used for fast filtering and preselection),
	Company Prefix Index, Item Reference, and Serial Number.
	Only a limited number of Company Prefixes can be represented in the
	64-bit tag.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor='descr-sgtin96' title='Description of the RFID-SGTIN-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SGTIN-96 is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SGTIN-96 includes six fields: Header, Filter Value, Partition (an
	indication of where the subsequent Company Prefix and Item
	Reference numbers are divided),
	Company Prefix Index, Item Reference, and Serial Number.
	
</t>
</section>

<section anchor='descr-sscc64' title='Description of the RFID-SSCC-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SSCC-64 is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SSCC-64 includes four fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Company Prefix Index, and Serial Reference.
	Only a limited number of Company Prefixes can be represented in the
	64-bit tag.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-sscc96' title='Description of the RFID-SSCC-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SSCC-96 is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SSCC-96 includes six fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Partition, Company Prefix, and Serial Reference, as well as 24 bits
	that remain unallocated and must be zero.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor='descr-sgln64' title='Description of the RFID-SGLN-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SGLN-64 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SGLN-64 includes five fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Company Prefix Index, Location Reference, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-sgln96' title='Description of the RFID-SGLN-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-SGLN-96 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The SGLN-96 includes six fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Partition, Company Prefix, Location Reference, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor='descr-grai64' title='Description of the RFID-GRAI-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-GRAI-64 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The GRAI-64 includes five fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Company Prefix Index, Asset Type, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor='descr-grai96' title='Description of the RFID-GRAI-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-GRAI-96 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The GRAI-96 includes six fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Partition, Company Prefix, Asset Type, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-giai64' title='Description of the RFID-GIAI-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-GIAI-64 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The GIAI-64 includes four fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Company Prefix Index, and Individual Asset Reference.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-giai96' title='Description of the RFID-GIAI-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-GIAI-96 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
	The GIAI-96 includes five fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Partition, Company Prefix, and Individual Asset Reference.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor='descr-dod64' title='Description of the RFID-DoD-64 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-DoD-64 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="RFID-DoD-spec"/>.
	The DoD-64 type includes four fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Government Managed Identifier, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor='descr-dod96' title='Description of the RFID-DoD-96 Type'>

<t>
	The RFID-DoD-96 type is encoded as specified in
	<xref target="RFID-DoD-spec"/>.
	The DoD-96 type includes four fields: Header, Filter Value,
	Government Managed Identifier, and Serial Number.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor='descr-uri' title='Description of the RFID URI Types'>

<t>
	In some cases, it is desirable to encode in URI form a specific
	encoding of an RFID tag.  For example, an application
	may prefer a URI representation for report preparation.  Applications
	that wish to manipulate any additional data fields on tags may need
	some representation other than the pure identity forms.
</t>

<t>
	For this purpose, the fields as represented in previous sections
	are associated with specified fields in the various URI types.
	For instance, the URI may have fields such as CompanyPrefix,
	ItemReference, or SerialNumber.  For details and encoding specifics,
	consult <xref target="EPC-Tag-Data"/>.
</t>

</section>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor='ack' title='Acknowledgements' numbered="no">

<t>The authors wish to acknowledge Hakima Chaouchi, Tatuya Jinmei, Jouni
Korhonen, Sri Gundavelli, Suresh Krishnan, Dapeng Liu, Dale Worley, Joseph
Salowey, Linda Dunbar, and Mirja Kuhlewind for their helpful comments. The
authors also wish to acknowledge the RFC Editor for a number of valuable
suggestions and updates during the final stages of producing this document.
</t>

</section>

</back>

</rfc>
