<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" number="8408" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCE Path Setup Type">
    Conveying Path Setup Type in PCE Communication Protocol (PCEP) Messages</title>

    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2000 Innovation Drive</street>
          <city>Kanata</city>
          <region>Ontario</region>
          <code>K2K 3E8</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J." surname="Tantsura">
      <organization>Nuage Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>755 Ravendale Drive</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
      <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


   <author fullname="Ina Minei" initials="I." surname="Minei">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>inaminei@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Robert Varga" initials="R." surname="Varga">
      <organization>Pantheon Technologies SRO</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Mlynske Nivy 56</street>
          <city>Bratislava</city>
          <region>821 05</region>
          <country>Slovakia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>nite@hq.sk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 <author fullname="Jon Hardwick" initials="J." surname="Hardwick">
   <organization>Metaswitch Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Church Street</street>
          <city>Enfield</city>
          <region>Middlesex</region>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jonathan.hardwick@metaswitch.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2018" />

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>


<abstract>

<t>A Path Computation Element (PCE) can compute Traffic Engineering (TE) paths
through a network; these paths are subject to various constraints. Currently, TE paths
are Label Switched Paths (LSPs) that are set up using the RSVP-TE signaling
protocol. However, other TE path setup methods are possible within the PCE
architecture. This document proposes an extension to the PCE Communication
Protocol (PCEP) to allow support for different path setup methods over a given
PCEP session.</t>


</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the PCE
Communication Protocol (PCEP) for communication between a Path Computation
Client (PCC) and a Path Computation Element (PCE) or between a PCE and a
PCE. 
A PCC requests, from a PCE, a path subject to various constraints and
optimization criteria. The PCE responds to the PCC with a hop-by-hop path in
an Explicit
Route Object (ERO). The PCC uses the ERO to set up the path in the
network.</t>


<t><xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies extensions to PCEP that allow a PCC to
delegate its LSPs to a PCE. The PCE can then update the state of LSPs
delegated to it. In particular, the PCE may modify the path of an LSP by
sending a new ERO. The PCC uses this ERO to reroute the LSP in a
make-before-break fashion. <xref target="RFC8281"/> specifies a mechanism that
allows a PCE to dynamically instantiate an LSP on a PCC by sending the ERO and the characteristics of the LSP. The PCC creates the LSP using the ERO and other attributes sent by the PCE.</t>

<t>So far, PCEP and its extensions have assumed that the TE paths are label
switched and are established via the RSVP-TE signaling protocol. However, other methods of
LSP setup are possible in the PCE architecture (see <xref target="RFC4655"/>
and <xref target="RFC4657"/>).  This document generalizes PCEP to allow other
LSP setup methods to be used. 
It defines two new TLVs and specifies the base procedures to facilitate this:

  <list style="symbols">

    <t>The PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV allows a PCEP speaker to announce
    which LSP setup methods it supports when the PCEP session is
    established.</t>

    <t>The PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV allows a PCEP speaker to specify which
    setup method should be used for a given LSP.  When multiple path setup
    types are deployed in a network, a given PCEP session may have to
    simultaneously support more than one path setup type. A PCEP speaker uses
    the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV to explicitly indicate the intended path setup
    type in the appropriate PCEP messages, unless the path setup type is
    RSVP-TE (which is assumed to be the path setup type if no other setup type
    is indicated).  This is so that both the PCC and the PCE can take the
    necessary steps to set up the path.</t>

  </list>
</t>

<t>This document defines a path setup type code for RSVP-TE.  When a new path setup type (other than RSVP-TE) is introduced for setting up a path, a path setup type code and, optionally, a sub-TLV pertaining to the new path setup type will be defined by the document that specifies the new path setup type.</t>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section > <!--Requirements language-->

</section> <!-- Introduction -->

<section title="Terminology">
<t>The following terminology is used in this document:

	<list style="hanging">
     	<t hangText="ERO:"> Explicit Route Object</t>
    	<t hangText="PCC:"> Path Computation Client</t>
    	<t hangText="PCE:"> Path Computation Element</t>
    	<t hangText="PCEP:"> PCE Communication Protocol</t>
      <t hangText="PST:"> Path Setup Type</t>
    	<t hangText="TLV:"> Type, Length, and Value</t>
      </list>
</t>
</section> <!-- Terminology -->

<section anchor="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY-TLV" title="Path Setup Type Capability TLV">


<t>A PCEP speaker indicates which PSTs it supports during the PCEP
initialization phase using the following process.  When the PCEP session is created, it sends
an Open message with an OPEN object containing the PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY
TLV.  The format of this TLV is as follows.</t>


      <figure anchor="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY-TLV-FORMAT" title="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           Type (34)           |             Length            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                           Reserved            |  Num of PSTs  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |     PST#1     |      ...      |     PST#N     |    Padding    |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  //               Optional sub-TLVs (variable)                  //
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

<t>The TLV Type is 34.  Its Reserved field MUST be set to zero by the sender
and MUST be ignored by the receiver.  The other fields in the TLV are as
follows.
  <list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="Length:">
    The total length in bytes of the remainder of the TLV, that is, excluding the Type and Length fields.
  </t>
  <t hangText="Num of PSTs:">
    The number of PSTs in the following list, excluding padding.
  </t>
  <t hangText="List of PSTs:">
    A list of the PSTs that the PCEP speaker supports.  Each PST is a single
    byte in length.  Duplicate entries in this list MUST be ignored.  The PCEP
    speaker MUST pad the list with zeros so that it is a multiple of four
    bytes in length.  This document defines the following PST value:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>PST = 0: Path is set up using the RSVP-TE signaling protocol</t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t hangText="Optional sub-TLVs:">
    A list of sub-TLVs associated with the supported PSTs.  Each PST has zero
    or one sub-TLVs associated with it, and each sub-TLV is associated with
    exactly one PST.  Each sub-TLV MUST obey the rules for TLV formatting
    defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>.  That is, each sub-TLV is padded to a
    four-byte alignment, and the Length field of each sub-TLV does not include
    the padding bytes.  


This document does not define any sub-TLVs; an example sub-TLV
    can be found in <xref target="PCEP-EXTENSIONS"/>.
  </t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>A PCEP speaker MUST check that this TLV is correctly formatted, as follows.
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>If there are no sub-TLVs, then the TLV Length field MUST be equal to four bytes plus the size of the PST list, excluding any padding bytes. </t>
    <t>If there are sub-TLVs, then the TLV Length field MUST be equal to four bytes plus the size of the PST list (rounded up to the nearest multiple of four) plus the size of the appended sub-TLVs, excluding any padding bytes in the final sub-TLV. </t>
    <t>The Num of PSTs field MUST be greater than zero. </t>
  </list>
If a PCEP speaker receives a PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV that violates
these rules, then the PCEP speaker MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type =
10 (Reception of an invalid object) and Error-value = 11 (Malformed
object) and MUST close the PCEP session.  The PCEP speaker MAY include the
malformed OPEN object in the PCErr message as well.</t>


<t>If a PCEP speaker receives an OPEN object with more than one PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV, then it MUST ignore all but the first instance of this TLV.</t>


<t>The absence of the PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV from the OPEN object is
equivalent to a PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV containing a single PST value of 0
(Path is set up using the RSVP-TE signaling protocol) and no sub-TLVs.  A PCEP
speaker MAY omit the
PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV if the only PST it supports is RSVP-TE.  If a
PCEP speaker supports other PSTs besides RSVP-TE, then it SHOULD include the
PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV in its OPEN object.</t>


<t>If a PCEP speaker does not recognize the PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV, it will ignore the TLV in accordance with <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>

</section> <!-- Path-setup-type-capability TLV -->

<section anchor="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-TLV" title="Path Setup Type TLV">

<t>When a PCEP session is used to set up TE paths using different methods, the
corresponding PCE and PCC must be aware of the path setup method used. This
means that a PCE must be able to specify paths in the correct format, and a PCC must be able to take control-plane and forwarding-plane actions appropriate to the PST. </t>

      <figure anchor="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-TLV-FORMAT" title="PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           Type (28)           |           Length (4)          |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                           Reserved            |      PST      |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


<t>The PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV is an optional TLV associated with the Request
Parameters (RP) <xref
target="RFC5440"/> and the Stateful PCE Request Parameters (SRP) <xref
target="RFC8231"/> objects. Its format is shown in <xref
target="PATH-SETUP-TYPE-TLV-FORMAT" />. The TLV type is 28. Its Reserved field
MUST be set to zero. The one-byte PST field contains the PST as defined for the
PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV.</t>

<t>The absence of the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV is equivalent to a PATH-SETUP-TYPE
TLV with a PST value of 0 (Path is set up using the RSVP-TE signaling protocol). A PCEP speaker MAY omit the TLV if the
PST is RSVP-TE. If the RP or SRP object contains more than one
PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV, only the first TLV MUST be processed, and the rest MUST be ignored.</t>

<t>If a PCEP speaker does not recognize the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV, it will
ignore the TLV in accordance with <xref target="RFC5440"/> and use
RSVP-TE to set up the path.</t>

</section> <!-- Path-setup-type-tlv -->

<section anchor="Operation" title="Operation">

<t>During the PCEP initialization phase, if a PCEP speaker receives a PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV from its peer, it MUST assume that the peer supports only the PSTs listed in the TLV.  If the PCEP speaker and its peer have no PSTs in common, then the PCEP speaker MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type = 21 (Invalid traffic engineering path setup type) and Error-value = 2 (Mismatched path setup type) and close the PCEP session.</t>

<t>If the peer has sent no PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY TLV, then the PCEP speaker MUST infer that the peer supports path setup using at least RSVP-TE.  The PCEP speaker MAY also infer that the peer supports other path setup types, but the means of inference are outside the scope of this document.</t>

<t>When a PCC sends a PCReq message to a PCE <xref target="RFC5440"/>, it
MUST include the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV in the RP object, unless the intended
PST is RSVP-TE (in which case it MAY omit the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV).
If the PCE is
capable of expressing the path in a format appropriate to the intended PST, it
MUST use the appropriate ERO format in the PCRep message.</t>


<t>When a PCE sends a PCRep message to a PCC <xref target="RFC5440"/>, it MUST
  include the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV in the RP object, unless the PST is
  RSVP-TE (in which case it MAY omit the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV).
If the PCE does
not support the intended PST, it MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type =
21 (Invalid traffic engineering path setup type) and Error-value = 1
(Unsupported path setup type) and close the PCEP session. If the PSTs
corresponding to the PCReq and PCRep messages do not match, the PCC MUST send
a PCErr message with Error-Type = 21 (Invalid traffic engineering path setup
type) and Error-value = 2 (Mismatched path setup type) and close the PCEP
session.</t>


<t>When a stateful PCE sends a PCUpd message <xref target="RFC8231"/> or a
PCInitiate message <xref target="RFC8281"/> to a PCC, 
it MUST include the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV
  in the SRP object, unless the intended PST is RSVP-TE (in which case
  it MAY omit the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV).  
If the PCC does not
support the PST associated with the PCUpd or PCInitiate message, it MUST send
a PCErr message with Error-Type = 21 (Invalid traffic engineering path setup
type) and Error-value = 1 (Unsupported path setup type) and close the PCEP
session.</t>

<t>When a PCC sends a PCRpt message to a stateful PCE <xref
target="RFC8231"/>, it
MUST include the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV in the SRP object, unless the
PST is RSVP-TE (in which case it MAY omit the PATH-SETUP-TYPE TLV).
The PCC MUST include the SRP object in the PCRpt message if the PST is
not RSVP-TE, even when the SRP-ID-number is the reserved value of
0x00000000. If the PCRpt message is triggered by a PCUpd or PCInitiate
message, then the PST that the PCC indicates in the PCRpt message MUST match
the PST
that the stateful PCE intended in the PCUpd or PCInitiate message. If it does not
match, then the PCE MUST send a PCErr message with Error-Type = 21 (Invalid
traffic engineering path setup type) and Error-value = 2 (Mismatched path
setup type) and close the PCEP session.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Management" title="Manageability Considerations">

<t>This document generalizes PCEP to allow path setup methods other than
RSVP-TE to be used by the network (but does not define any new path setup
types besides RSVP-TE). It is possible that, in a given network, multiple path
setup methods will be used. It is also possible that not all devices will
support the same set of path setup methods. Managing networks that combine
multiple path setup methods may therefore raise some challenges from a
configuration and observability point of view.</t>


<t>Each document that defines a new path setup type in the "PCEP Path Setup
Types" registry (<xref target="PCEP-Setup-Type-Registry"/>) must include a
Manageability Considerations section. The Manageability Considerations section must explain how operators
can manage PCEP with the new path setup type. It must address the following
questions, which are generally applicable when working with multiple path
setup types in PCEP.

  <list style="symbols">
    <t>What are the criteria for when devices will use the new path setup type in PCEP, and how can the operator control this?</t>
    <t>How can the network be migrated to the new path setup type, and are
    there any backwards-compatibility issues that operators need to be aware
    of?</t>

    <t>Are paths set up using the new path setup type intended to coexist with other paths over the long term, and if so, how is this situation managed with PCEP?</t>
    <t>How can operators verify the correct operation of PCEP in the network with respect to the new path setup type? Which fault conditions must be reported to the operators?</t>
    <t>Are there any existing management interfaces (such as YANG models) that must be extended to model the operation of PCEP in the network with respect to the new path setup type?</t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>See <xref target="RFC5706"/> for further guidance on how to write
Manageability Considerations sections in Standards Track documents.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440"/> and <xref
target="RFC8281"/> are applicable to this specification. No additional
security measure is required.</t>

<t>Note that if the security mechanisms of <xref target="RFC5440"/> and <xref
target="RFC8281"/> are not used, then the protocol described in this document
could be attacked in the following new way.  An attacker, using a TCP
man-in-the-middle attack, could inject error messages into the PCEP session
when a particular PST is (or is not) used.  Doing this could
potentially force the use of a specific PST, which may allow the attacker to
subsequently attack a weakness in that PST.</t>


</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<section anchor="PCEP-TLV-Type" title="Additions to PCEP TLV Type Indicators Registry">

<t>IANA has allocated the following code points in the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" registry.
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  Value    Description                   Reference
  -----    --------------------------    ---------
  28       PATH-SETUP-TYPE               RFC 8408
  34       PATH-SETUP-TYPE-CAPABILITY    RFC 8408
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section anchor="PCEP-Setup-Type-Registry" title="New PCEP Path Setup Types Registry">

<t>IANA has created a new sub-registry within the "Path Computation Element
Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry called "PCEP Path Setup Types". The
allocation policy for this new registry is IETF Review <xref target="RFC8126"/>. This new registry
contains the following value:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  Value    Description                   Reference
  -----    --------------------------    ---------
  0        Path is set up using the      RFC 8408
           RSVP-TE signaling protocol
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section anchor="PCEP-Error-Object" title="Additions to PCEP-ERROR Object Error Types and Values Registry">

<t>IANA has allocated the following code points in the "PCEP-ERROR Object
Error Types and Values" registry.

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
 Error-Type  Meaning                                        Reference
 ----------  -------------------------------------------    ---------
    10       Reception of an invalid object                 RFC 5440

              Error-value = 11: Malformed object            RFC 8408

    21       Invalid traffic engineering path setup type    RFC 8408

              Error-value = 0: Unassigned                   RFC 8408
              Error-value = 1: Unsupported path setup type  RFC 8408
              Error-value = 2: Mismatched path setup type   RFC 8408
]]></artwork></figure>

</t>

</section>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281.xml"?>
</references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"?>
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4657.xml"?>
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5706.xml"?>
     <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"?>

<!-- draft-ietf-pce-segment-routing-11 exists (expired)  -->

<reference anchor='PCEP-EXTENSIONS'>
<front>
<title>PCEP Extensions for Segment Routing</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Henderickx' fullname='Wim Henderickx'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Hardwick' fullname='Jonathan Hardwick'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-pce-segment-routing-11' />

</reference>


   </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgement" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

<t>We would like to thank Marek Zavodsky for valuable comments.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors" numbered="no">

      <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
      <t>The following people contributed to this document:
      <list style="empty">
	      <t>- Jan Medved</t>
	      <t>- Edward Crabbe</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
    </section>


</back>

</rfc>
