<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2464 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2464.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3610 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3610.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3633 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3972 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3972.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4193 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4862 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4903 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4903.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4941 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4944 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4944.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5535 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5535.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6282 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6282.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6775 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6775.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7136 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7136.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7217 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7217.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7668 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7668.xml">


<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6lo-privacy-considerations SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6lo-privacy-considerations.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6lo-backbone-router SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6lo-backbone-router.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8105"
     category="std" 
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 over DECT ULE">Transmission of IPv6 Packets over
    Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT)
    Ultra Low Energy (ULE)</title>

    <author fullname="Peter B. Mariager" initials="P.M." surname="Mariager">
      <organization abbrev="RTX A/S">RTX A/S</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Stroemmen 6</street>

          <code>DK-9400 Noerresundby</code>

          <country>Denmark</country>
        </postal>

        <email>pm@rtx.dk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jens Toftgaard Petersen" initials="J.T.P." role="editor"
            surname="Petersen">
      <organization abbrev="RTX A/S">RTX A/S</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Stroemmen 6</street>

          <code>DK-9400 Noerresundby</code>

          <country>Denmark</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jtp@rtx.dk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zach Shelby" initials="Z.S." surname="Shelby">
      <organization abbrev="ARM">ARM</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>150 Rose Orchard</street>

          <code>San Jose, CA 95134</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zach.shelby@arm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Marco van de Logt" initials="M.L." surname="van de Logt">
      <organization>Bosch Sensortec GmbH</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gerhard-Kindler-Str. 9</street>

          <code>72770 Reutlingen</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>marco.vandelogt@bosch-sensortec.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dominique Barthel" initials="D" surname="Barthel">
      <organization>Orange Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>28 chemin du Vieux Chene</street>

          <code>38243 Meylan</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dominique.barthel@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2017"/>

    <workgroup>6Lo Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT) Ultra Low Energy
      (ULE) is a low-power air interface technology that is proposed by the
      DECT Forum and is defined and specified by ETSI.</t>

      <t>The DECT air interface technology has been used worldwide in
      communication devices for more than 20 years. It has primarily been used
      to carry voice
      for cordless telephony but has also been deployed for data-centric
      services.</t>

      <t>DECT ULE is a recent addition to the DECT interface
      primarily intended for low-bandwidth, low-power applications such as
      sensor devices, smart meters, home automation, etc. As the DECT ULE interface inherits many of the capabilities from DECT, it
      benefits from operation that is long-range and interence-free,
      worldwide-reserved frequency band, low silicon prices, and maturity. There is an
      added value in the ability to communicate with IPv6 over DECT ULE, such
      as for Internet of Things applications.</t>

      <t>This document describes how IPv6 is transported over DECT ULE using
     IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Network (6LoWPAN) techniques.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT) is a standard 
	  series <xref target="EN300.175-part1-7"/> specified
      by ETSI, and CAT-iq (Cordless Advanced Technology - internet and quality)
      is a set of product certification and interoperability profiles <xref target="CAT-iq"/>
      defined by DECT Forum. DECT Ultra Low Energy (DECT ULE or just ULE) is an air interface
      technology building on the key fundamentals of traditional DECT/CAT-iq
      but with specific changes to significantly reduce the power consumption
      at the expense of data throughput. DECT ULE devices with requirements on power
      consumption, as specified by ETSI in <xref target="TS102.939-1"/> and
      <xref target="TS102.939-2"/>,
      will operate on special power-optimized silicon but can connect to a
      DECT Gateway supporting traditional DECT/CAT-iq for cordless telephony
      and data as well as the ULE extensions.</t> 
	  <t>DECT terminology has
      two major role definitions: the Portable Part (PP) is the power-constrained device while the Fixed Part (FP) is the Gateway or base
      station. This FP may be connected to the Internet. An example of a use
      case for DECT ULE is a home-security sensor transmitting small amounts
      of data (few bytes) at periodic intervals through the FP but that is able to
      wake up upon an external event (e.g., a break-in) and communicate with the FP.
      Another example incorporating both DECT ULE and traditional
      CAT-iq telephony would be a pendant (brooch) for the elderly that generally transmits
      periodic status messages to a care provider using very little battery,
      but in the event of an emergency, the elderly person can establish a voice
      connection through the pendant to an alarm service. It is expected that
      DECT ULE will be integrated into many residential gateways, as many of
      these already implement DECT CAT-iq for cordless telephony. DECT ULE
      can be added as a software option for the FP.</t>
      <t>It is desirable to
      consider IPv6 for DECT ULE devices due to the large address space and
      well-known infrastructure. This document describes how IPv6 is used on
      DECT ULE links to optimize power while maintaining the many benefits of
      IPv6 transmission. <xref target="RFC4944"/>, <xref target="RFC6282"/>,
      and <xref target="RFC6775"/> specify the
      transmission of IPv6 over IEEE 802.15.4. DECT ULE has many
      characteristics similar to those of IEEE 802.15.4, but it also has differences.
      A subset of mechanisms defined for transmission of IPv6 over IEEE
      802.15.4 can be applied to the transmission of IPv6 on DECT ULE
      links.</t>

      <t>This document specifies how to map IPv6 over DECT ULE inspired by
      <xref target="RFC4944"/>, <xref target="RFC6282"/>, <xref
      target="RFC6775"/>, and <xref target="RFC7668"/>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Notation">

        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terms Used">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
6CO      6LoWPAN Context Option [RFC6775]
6BBR     6loWPAN Backbone Router
6LBR     6LoWPAN Border Router, as defined in [RFC6775]. 
         The DECT Fixed Part has this role.
6LN      6LoWPAN Node as defined in [RFC6775]. 
         The DECT Portable Part has this role
6LoWPAN  IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Network
AES128   Advanced Encryption Standard with a key size of 128 bits
API      Application Programming Interface
ARO      Address Registration Option [RFC6775]
CAT-iq   Cordless Advanced Technology - internet and quality
CID      Context Identifier [RFC6775]
DAC      Destination Address Compression
DAD      Duplicate Address Detection [RFC4862]
DAM      Destination Address Mode
DHCPv6   Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 [RFC3315]
DLC      Data Link Control
DSAA2    DECT Standard Authentication Algorithm #2
DSC      DECT Standard Cipher
DSC2     DECT Standard Cipher #2
FDMA     Frequency-Division Multiple Access
FP       DECT Fixed Part; the Gateway
GAP      Generic Access Profile
IID      Interface Identifier
IPEI     International Portable Equipment Identity; DECT identity
MAC-48   48-bit global unique MAC address managed by IEEE
MAC      Media Access Control
MTU      Maximum Transmission Unit
NBMA     Non-Broadcast Multi-Access
ND       Neighbor Discovery [RFC4861] [RFC6775]
PDU      Protocol Data Unit
PHY      Physical Layer
PMID     Portable MAC Identity; DECT identity
PP       DECT Portable Part; typically the sensor node (6LN)
PVC      Permanent Virtual Circuit
RFPI     Radio Fixed Part Identity; DECT identity
SAC      Source Address Compression
SAM      Source Address Mode
TDD      Time Division Duplex
TDMA     Time-Division Multiple Access
TPUI     Temporary Portable User Identity; DECT identity
UAK      User Authentication Key; DECT master security key
ULA      Unique Local Address [RFC4193]
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="DECT Ultra Low Energy">
      <t>DECT ULE is a low-power air interface technology that is designed to
      support both circuit-switched services, such as voice communication,
      and packet-mode data services at a modest data rate. This document is
      only addressing the packet-mode data service of DECT ULE.</t>

      <section title="The DECT ULE Protocol Stack">
        <t>The DECT ULE Protocol Stack contains a PHY layer operating at
        frequencies in the 1880 - 1920 MHz frequency band depending on the
        region and uses a symbol rate of 1.152 Mbaud. Radio bearers are
        allocated by use of FDMA/TDMA/TDD techniques.</t>

        <t>In its generic network topology, DECT is defined as a cellular
        network technology. However, the most common configuration is a star
        network with a single FP defining the network with a number of PPs
        attached. The MAC layer supports both traditional DECT circuit mode 
		operation, as this is used for services like discovery, pairing, 
		security features, etc., and it supports new ULE packet-mode operation. 
		The circuit-mode features have been reused from DECT.
		</t>

        <t>The DECT ULE device can switch to the ULE mode of operation, 
        utilizing the new ULE MAC layer features. The DECT ULE Data Link
        Control (DLC) provides multiplexing as well as segmentation and
        reassembly for larger packets from layers above. The DECT ULE layer
        also implements per-message authentication and encryption. The DLC
        layer ensures packet integrity and preserves packet order, but
        delivery is based on best effort.</t>

        <t>The current DECT ULE MAC layer standard supports low-bandwidth data
        broadcast. However, this document is not considering usage of the DECT
        ULE MAC layer broadcast service for IPv6 over DECT ULE.</t>

        <t>In general, communication sessions can be initiated from both the FP side
        and the PP side. Depending on power-down modes employed in the PP, latency
        may occur when initiating sessions from the FP side. MAC layer
        communication can take place using either connection-oriented packet
        transfer with low overhead for short sessions or connection-oriented bearers including media reservation. The MAC layer
        autonomously selects the radio-spectrum positions that are available
        within the band and can rearrange these to avoid interference. The MAC
        layer has built-in retransmission procedures in order to improve
        transmission reliability.</t>

        <t>The DECT ULE device will typically incorporate an Application
        Programming Interface (API), as well as common elements known as
        Generic Access Profiles (GAPs), for enrolling into the network. The DECT
        ULE Stack establishes a Permanent Virtual Circuit (PVC) for the
        application layers and provides support for a range of different
        application protocols. The application protocol is negotiated
        between the PP and FP when the PVC communication service is
        established. <xref target="TS102.939-1"/> defines this negotiation and specifies an
	Application Protocol Identifier set to 0x06 for 6LoWPAN.

 This document 
        defines the behavior of that application protocol.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="DECT_ULE_Protocol" title="DECT ULE
	  Protocol Stack">
            <artwork>
           +----------------------------------------+ 
           |          Application Layers            | 
           +----------------------------------------+ 
           | Generic Access     |     ULE Profile   |
           |       Profile      |                   |
           +----------------------------------------+ 
           | DECT/Service API   | ULE Data API      | 
           +--------------------+-------------------+ 
           | LLME  | NWK (MM,CC)|                   | 
           +--------------------+-------------------+ 
           | DECT DLC           | DECT ULE DLC      | 
           +--------------------+-------------------+ 
           |                MAC Layer               | 
           +--------------------+-------------------+ 
           |                PHY Layer               | 
           +--------------------+-------------------+ 
                 (C-plane)             (U-plane)
</artwork>
          </figure><xref target="DECT_ULE_Protocol"/> shows the DECT ULE Stack divided into the
        Control Plane (C-plane) and User Data Plane (U-plane), to the left and to the right,
        respectively. The shown entities in the Stack are the Physical
        Layer (PHY), Media Access Control (MAC) Layer, Data Link Control (DLC)
        Layer, and Network Layer (NWK), along with following subcomponents: Lower-Layer
        Management Entity (LLME), Mobility Management (MM), and Call Control (CC).
        Above there are the typical Application Programmers Interface (API)
        and application-profile-specific layers.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section anchor="link_layer_roles_topology" title="Link Layer Roles and Topology">
        <t>An FP is assumed to be less constrained than a PP. Hence, in the
        primary scenario, the FP and PP will act as 6LBR and a 6LN, respectively.
        This document only addresses this primary scenario, and all other scenarios 
        with different roles of an FP and PP are out of scope.</t>

        <t>In DECT ULE, at the link layer, the communication only takes place
        between an FP and a PP. An FP is able to handle multiple simultaneous
        connections with a number of PPs. Hence, in a DECT ULE network using
        IPv6, a radio hop is equivalent to an IPv6 link and vice versa (see
	<xref target="subnets_ICS"/>).
        <figure anchor="DECT_ULE_star" title="DECT ULE Star Topology">
            <artwork>
    [DECT ULE PP]-----\                 /-----[DECT ULE PP]
                       \               /
    [DECT ULE PP]-------+[DECT ULE FP]+-------[DECT ULE PP]
                       /               \
    [DECT ULE PP]-----/                 \-----[DECT ULE PP]
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>A significant difference between IEEE 802.15.4 and DECT ULE is that
        the former supports both star and mesh topology (and requires a
        routing protocol), whereas DECT ULE in its primary configuration does
        not support the formation of multihop networks at the link layer. In
        consequence, the mesh header defined in <xref target="RFC4944"/> is not used in DECT ULE networks.</t>

        <t>DECT ULE repeaters are considered to operate transparently in the DECT protocol 
		domain and are outside the scope of this document.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section anchor="addressing_model" title="Addressing Model">
        <t>Each DECT PP is assigned an IPEI during manufacturing. This
        identity has the size of 40 bits and is globally unique within DECT addressing space 
		and can be used to constitute the MAC address used to derive the IID for
        link-local address.</t>

        <t>During a DECT location registration procedure, the FP assigns a 20-bit TPUI to a PP. 
		The FP creates a unique mapping between the assigned TPUI and the IPEI of each PP.
		This TPUI is used for addressing (Layer 2) in messages between
		the FP and PP.
		Although the TPUI is temporary by definition, many implementations assign the
        same value repeatedly to any given PP, hence it seems not suitable for
	construction of the IID
		(see <xref target="RFC8065"/>).</t>

        <t>Each DECT FP is assigned an RFPI during manufacturing. This identity
        has the size of 40 bits and is globally unique within DECT addressing space and can be
        used to constitute the MAC address used to derive the IID for
        link-local address.</t>

        <t>Optionally, each DECT PP and DECT FP can be assigned a unique (IEEE)
        MAC-48 address in addition to the DECT identities to be used by the
        6LoWPAN. During the address registration of non-link-local addresses
        as specified by this document, the FP and PP can use such MAC-48 to
        construct the IID. 
		However, as these addresses are considered as being permanent, 
		such a scheme is NOT RECOMMENDED as per <xref target="RFC8065"/>.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="MTU Considerations">
        <t>Ideally, the DECT ULE FP and PP may generate data that fits into a
        single MAC layer packet (38 octets) for periodically transferred
        information, depending on application. However, IP packets may be much
        larger. The DECT ULE DLC procedures natively support segmentation and
        reassembly and provide any MTU size below 65536 octets. The default MTU
        size defined in DECT ULE <xref target="TS102.939-1"/> is 500 octets. In order to
        support complete IPv6 packets, the DLC layer of DECT ULE SHALL, per this
        specification, be configured with an MTU size of 1280 octets, 
		hence <xref target="RFC4944"/> fragmentation/reassembly is not required.</t>

        <t>It is important to realize that the usage of larger packets will be
        at the expense of battery life, as a large packet inside the DECT ULE
        Stack will be fragmented into several or many MAC layer packets, each
        consuming power to transmit/receive. 
		The increased MTU size does not change the MAC layer packet and PDU size.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Additional Considerations">
        <t>The DECT ULE standard allows the PP to be DECT-registered (bound) to multiple
        FP and to roam between them. These FP and their 6LBR functionalities can operate either individually or 
		connected through a Backbone Router as per <xref target="BACKBONE-ROUTER"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Specification of IPv6 over DECT ULE">
      <t>Before any IP-layer communications can take place over DECT ULE,
      DECT-ULE-enabled nodes such as 6LNs and 6LBRs have to find each other and
      establish a suitable link layer connection. The obtain-access-rights
      registration and location registration procedures are documented by ETSI
      in the specifications <xref target="EN300.175-part1-7"/>, <xref target="TS102.939-1"/>, and
      <xref target="TS102.939-2"/>.</t>

      <t>DECT ULE technology sets strict requirements for low power
      consumption and, thus, limits the allowed protocol overhead. 6LoWPAN
      standards <xref target="RFC4944"/>, <xref target="RFC6775"/>, and <xref target="RFC6282"/> provide useful
      functionality for reducing overhead that can be applied to DECT ULE.
      This functionality comprises link-local IPv6 addresses and stateless
      IPv6 address autoconfiguration, Neighbor Discovery, and header
      compression.</t>

      <t>The ULE 6LoWPAN adaptation layer can run directly on this U-plane DLC
      layer. <xref target="IPv6_over_DECT_ULE_Stack"/> illustrates an IPv6 over DECT ULE Stack.</t>

      <t>Because DECT ULE in its primary configuration does not
      support the formation of multihop networks at the link layer, the mesh
      header defined in <xref target="RFC4944"/> for mesh under routing MUST NOT be used. In
      addition, the role of a 6LoWPAN Router (6LR) is not defined per this specification.</t>

      <section title="Protocol Stack">
        <t>In order to enable data transmission over DECT ULE, a
        Permanent Virtual Circuit (PVC) has to be configured and opened
	between the FP and PP.
        This is done by setting up a DECT service call between the PP and FP. In the DECT protocol domain, the PP
        SHALL specify the &lt;&lt;IWU-ATTRIBUTES&gt;&gt; in a service-change
        (other) message before sending a service-change (resume) message as
        defined in <xref target="TS102.939-1"/>. 
	The &lt;&lt;IWU-ATTRIBUTES&gt;&gt; SHALL
        set the ULE Application Protocol Identifier to 0x06 and
	the MTU size to 1280 octets or larger.
 The FP sends a
        service-change-accept (resume) that MUST contain a valid paging descriptor.
        The PP MUST listen to paging messages from the FP according to the information 
        in the received paging descriptor. Following this, transmission of IPv6 packets can start.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="IPv6_over_DECT_ULE_Stack" title="IPv6 over DECT ULE
	  Stack">
            <artwork>                  +-------------------+
                  |    UDP/TCP/other  |
                  +-------------------+
                  |       IPv6        |
                  +-------------------+
                  |6LoWPAN adapted to |
                  |    DECT ULE       |
                  +-------------------+
                  |  DECT ULE DLC     |
                  +-------------------+
                  |  DECT ULE MAC     |
                  +-------------------+
                  |  DECT ULE PHY     |
                  +-------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Link Model">
        <t>The general model is that IPv6 is Layer 3 and DECT ULE MAC and DECT
	ULE DLC are Layer 2. DECT ULE already implements fragmentation and reassembly
        functionality; hence, the fragmentation and reassembly function described in <xref target="RFC4944"/>
        MUST NOT be used.</t>

		
		<t>After the FPs and PPs have connected at the DECT ULE level,
        the link can be considered up and IPv6 address configuration and
        transmission can begin. The 6LBR ensures address collisions do not
        occur.</t>

        <t>Per this specification, the IPv6 header compression format
        specified in <xref target="RFC6282"/> MUST be used. 

The IPv6 payload length can be derived from the ULE DLC packet length.
The possibly elided IPv6 address can be reconstructed from the lower layer
address (see <xref target="header_compression_section"/>).</t>

        <t>Due to the DECT ULE star topology (see <xref target="link_layer_roles_topology"/>), each PP
        has a separate link to the FP; thus, the PPs cannot directly
        hear one another and cannot talk to one another.
		As discussed in <xref target="RFC4903"/>, conventional usage 
		of IPv6 anticipates IPv6 subnets spanning a single
		link at the link layer. In order to avoid the complexity of
		implementing a 
		separate subnet for each DECT ULE link, a Multi-Link Subnet
		model <xref target="RFC4903"/> has been chosen, 
		specifically Non-Broadcast Multi-Access (NBMA) at Layer 2.  
		Because of this, link-local multicast communications can
		happen only within a single DECT ULE connection; thus, 6LN-to-6LN
		communications using link-local addresses are not possible. 6LNs
		connected to the same 6LBR have to communicate with each other 
		utilizing the shared prefix used on the subnet. The 6LBR forwards packets sent
		by one 6LN to another.</t>

        <t/>

        <section anchor="stateless_address" title="Stateless Address Autoconfiguration">
          <t>At network interface initialization, both 6LN and 6LBR SHALL
          generate and assign IPv6 link-local addresses to the DECT ULE network interfaces
          <xref target="RFC4862"/> based on the DECT device addresses
          (see <xref target="addressing_model"/>) that were used for establishing the underlying
          DECT ULE connection.</t>

          <t>The DECT device addresses IPEI and RFPI MUST be used to derive
          the IPv6 link-local 64-bit Interface Identifiers (IIDs) for 6LN and
          6LBR, respectively.</t>

          <t>The rule for deriving IIDs from DECT device addresses is as
          follows: the DECT device addresses that consist of 40 bits
          each MUST be expanded with leading zero bits to form 48-bit
          intermediate addresses. The most significant bit in this newly formed
          48-bit intermediate address is set to one for addresses derived from
          the RFPI and set to zero for addresses derived from the IPEI. 64-bit
	  IIDs are derived from these intermediate 48-bit addresses
          following the guidance in Appendix A of <xref target="RFC4291"/>. 
		  However, because DECT and IEEE address spaces are different, 
		  this intermediate address cannot be considered to be unique
		  within an IEEE address space.
		  In the derived IIDs, the Universal/Local (U/L)
          bit (7th bit) will be zero, which indicates that derived IIDs are not
          globally unique, see <xref target="RFC7136"/>. For example, from RFPI=11.22.33.44.55,
          the derived IID is 80:11:22:ff:fe:33:44:55; from
          IPEI=01.23.45.67.89, the derived IID is 00:01:23:ff:fe:45:67:89.</t>

		  <t>Global uniqueness of an IID in link-local addresses is not required as they 
		  should never be leaked outside the subnet domain.</t>
		  
          <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC4291"/>, the IPv6 link-local address is formed by
          appending the IID to the prefix FE80::/64, as shown in <xref target="IPv6_DECT_ULE"/>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="IPv6_DECT_ULE" title="IPv6 Link-Local Address in
	    DECT ULE">
              <artwork>
             10 bits       54 bits            64 bits
          +----------+-----------------+----------------------+
          |1111111010|       zeros     | Interface Identifier |
          +----------+-----------------+----------------------+
</artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>A 6LN MUST join the all-nodes multicast address.</t>

          <t>After link-local address configuration, 6LN sends Router
          Solicitation messages as described in Section 6.3.7 of <xref
	  target="RFC4861"/> and Section 5.3 of  <xref target="RFC6775"/>.</t>

          <t>For non-link-local addresses, 6LNs SHOULD NOT be configured to
          use IIDs derived from a MAC-48 device address or DECT device
          addresses. Alternative schemes such as Cryptographically Generated
          Addresses (CGAs) <xref target="RFC3972"/>, privacy extensions <xref target="RFC4941"/>, Hash-Based
          Addresses (HBAs) <xref target="RFC5535"/>, DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315"/>, or static,
          semantically opaque addresses <xref target="RFC7217"/> SHOULD be used by default.
          See also <xref target="RFC8065"/> for guidance of needed 
          entropy in IIDs and the recommended lifetime of used IIDs.
          When generated IIDs are not globally unique, Duplicate Address
	  Detection (DAD) <xref target="RFC4862"/> MUST be used.
          In situations where deployment constraints require the device's 
          address to be embedded in the IID, the 6LN MAY form a 64-bit IID
          by utilizing the MAC-48 device address or DECT device addresses.
          The non-link-local addresses that a 6LN generates MUST be registered with
          6LBR as described in <xref target="neighbor_discovery"/>.</t>

          <t>The means for a 6LBR to obtain an IPv6 prefix for numbering the
          DECT ULE network is out of scope of this document, but a prefix can be, for
          example, assigned via DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation <xref target="RFC3633"/> or
          using IPv6 Unicast Unique Local Addresses (ULAs) <xref target="RFC4193"/>. Due to
          the link model of the DECT ULE, the 6LBR MUST set the "on-link" (L) flag
          to zero in the Prefix Information Option <xref target="RFC4861"/>. This will
          cause 6LNs to always send packets to the 6LBR, including the case
          when the destination is another 6LN using the same prefix.</t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="neighbor_discovery" title="Neighbor Discovery">
          <t>"Neighbor Discovery Optimization for IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless
          Personal Area Networks (6LoWPANs)" <xref target="RFC6775"/> describes the Neighbor
          Discovery approach as adapted for use in several 6LoWPAN topologies,
          including the mesh topology. As DECT ULE does not support mesh networks,
          only those aspects of <xref target="RFC6775"/> that apply to star topology are considered. </t>

          <t>The following aspects of the Neighbor Discovery optimizations
          <xref target="RFC6775"/> are applicable to DECT ULE 6LNs:<list style="numbers">

          <t>For sending Router Solicitations and processing Router
          Advertisements the DECT ULE 6LNs MUST, respectively, follow Sections
          5.3 and 5.4 of the <xref target="RFC6775"/>.</t>

          <t>A DECT ULE 6LN MUST NOT register its link-local address. 
		  Because the IIDs used in link-local addresses are derived from DECT addresses, 
		  there will always exist a unique mapping between link-local
	  and Layer 2 addresses.</t>
		  
		  <t>A DECT ULE 6LN MUST register its non-link-local addresses with the
          6LBR by sending a Neighbor Solicitation (NS) message with the
          Address Registration Option (ARO) and process the Neighbor
          Advertisement (NA) accordingly. The NS with the ARO option MUST be
          sent irrespective of the method used to generate the IID.</t></list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Unicast and Multicast Address Mapping">
          <t>The DECT MAC layer broadcast service is considered inadequate for
          IP multicast because it does not support the MTU size required by IPv6.</t>

          <t>Hence, traffic is always unicast between two DECT ULE nodes. Even
          in the case where a 6LBR is attached to multiple 6LNs, the 6LBR
          cannot do a multicast to all the connected 6LNs. If the 6LBR needs
          to send a multicast packet to all its 6LNs, it has to replicate the
          packet and unicast it on each link. However, this may not be
          energy efficient and particular care should be taken if the FP is
          battery-powered. To further conserve power, the 6LBR MUST keep track
          of multicast listeners at DECT ULE link-level granularity, and it
          MUST NOT forward multicast packets to 6LNs that have not registered
          for multicast groups the packets belong to. In the opposite
          direction, a 6LN can only transmit data to or through the 6LBR.
          Hence, when a 6LN needs to transmit an IPv6 multicast packet, the
          6LN will unicast the corresponding DECT ULE packet to the 6LBR. The
          6LBR will then forward the multicast packet to other 6LNs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Header Compression" anchor="header_compression_section">
          <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC6282"/>, which specifies the
          compression format for IPv6 datagrams on top of IEEE 802.15.4, header compression is
          REQUIRED in this document as the basis for IPv6 header compression
          on top of DECT ULE. All headers MUST be compressed according to encoding formats as described in 
          <xref target="RFC6282"/>. The DECT ULE's star topology structure,
          ARO and 6CO, can be exploited in order to provide a mechanism for
          address compression. The following text describes the principles of
          IPv6 address compression on top of DECT ULE.</t>

          <section title="Link-Local Header Compression">
            <t>In a link-local communication terminated at 6LN and 6LBR, both
            the IPv6 source and destination addresses MUST be elided since
            the used IIDs map uniquely into the DECT link end-point addresses.
            A 6LN or 6LBR that receives a PDU containing an IPv6 packet can
            infer the corresponding IPv6 source address. For the unicast type of
            communication considered in this paragraph, the following settings
            MUST be used in the IPv6 compressed header: CID=0, SAC=0, SAM=11,
            DAC=0, and DAM=11.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Non-link-local Header Compression">
            <t>To enable efficient header compression, the 6LBR MUST include the
            6LoWPAN Context Option (6CO) <xref target="RFC6775"/> for all prefixes the 6LBR
            advertises in Router Advertisements for use in stateless address
            autoconfiguration.</t>

            <t>When a 6LN transmits an IPv6 packet to a destination using
            global unicast IPv6 addresses, if a context is defined for the
            prefix of the 6LNs global IPv6 address, the 6LN MUST indicate this
            context in the corresponding source fields of the compressed IPv6
            header as per Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC6282"/> and MUST fully elide the latest registered IPv6
            source address. For this, the 6LN MUST use the following settings
            in the IPv6 compressed header: CID=1, SAC=1, and SAM=11. In this case,
            the 6LBR can infer the elided IPv6 source address since 1) the
            6LBR has previously assigned the prefix to the 6LNs and 2) the
            6LBR maintains a Neighbor Cache that relates the device address
            and the IID of the corresponding PP. 
			If a context is defined for
            the IPv6 destination address, the 6LN MUST also indicate this
            context in the corresponding destination fields of the compressed
            IPv6 header and MUST elide the prefix of the destination IPv6
            address. For this, the 6LN MUST set the DAM field of the
            compressed IPv6 header as CID=1, DAC=1, and DAM=01 or DAM=11. Note
            that when a context is defined for the IPv6 destination address,
            the 6LBR can infer the elided destination prefix by using the
            context.</t>

            <t>When a 6LBR receives an IPv6 packet having a global unicast IPv6
            address and the destination of the packet is a 6LN, if a context
            is defined for the prefix of the 6LN's global IPv6 address, the
            6LBR MUST indicate this context in the corresponding destination
            fields of the compressed IPv6 header and MUST fully elide the IPv6
            destination address of the packet if the destination address is the 
			latest registered by the 6LN for the indicated context. 
            For this, the 6LBR MUST set the DAM field of the IPv6 compressed
            header as DAM=11. CID and DAC MUST be set to CID=1 and DAC=1. If a
            context is defined for the prefix of the IPv6 source address, the
            6LBR MUST indicate this context in the source fields of the
            compressed IPv6 header and MUST elide that prefix as well. For
            this, the 6LBR MUST set the SAM field of the IPv6 compressed
            header as CID=1, SAC=1, and SAM=01 or SAM=11.</t>

            <t/>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="subnets_ICS" title="Subnets and Internet Connectivity Scenarios">
        <t>In the DECT ULE star topology (see <xref target="link_layer_roles_topology"/>), each PP
        has a separate link to the FP, and the FP acts as an IPv6
        router rather than a link layer switch. A Multi-Link Subnet model
	<xref target="RFC4903"/> has been chosen, 
		specifically Non-Broadcast Multi-Access (NBMA) at Layer 2,
		as is further illustrated in <xref target="DECT_ULE_network"/>. The 6LBR forwards packets sent
		by one 6LN to another.
		In a typical scenario, the DECT ULE network is connected to the
        Internet as shown in the <xref target="DECT_ULE_network"/>. In this scenario, the DECT ULE
        network is deployed as one subnet using one /64 IPv6 prefix.  
		The 6LBR acts as a router and forwards packets between 6LNs to and
        from Internet. </t>
        <figure anchor="DECT_ULE_network" title="DECT ULE Network Connected to
	  the Internet">
          <artwork>
                       6LN
                        \               ____________
                         \             /            \
                 6LN ---- 6LBR ------ |  Internet    |
                         /             \____________/
                        /
                       6LN

             &lt;--  One subnet --&gt;
             &lt;--   DECT ULE  --&gt;
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>In some scenarios, the DECT ULE network may transiently or
        permanently be an isolated network as shown in the <xref target="isolated_DECT_ULE"/>. In this
        case, the whole DECT ULE network consists of a single subnet with
        multiple links, where 6LBR is routing packets between 6LNs.</t>

        <figure anchor="isolated_DECT_ULE" title="Isolated DECT ULE Network">
          <artwork>
                      6LN      6LN
                       \      /
                        \    /
                 6LN --- 6LBR --- 6LN
                        /    \
                       /      \
                      6LN      6LN

                 &lt;----  One subnet ----&gt;
                 &lt;------ DECT ULE -----&gt;
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>In the isolated network scenario, communications between 6LN and
        6LBR can use IPv6 link-local methodology, but for communications
        between different PP, the FP has to act as 6LBR, number the network
        with a ULA prefix <xref target="RFC4193"/>, and route packets between
	the PP.</t>
        
        <t>In other more advanced systems scenarios with multiple FPs and 6LBR, 
        each DECT ULE FP constitutes a wireless cell. The
        network can be configured as a Multi-Link Subnet in which the 6LN can operate 
        within the same /64 subnet prefix in multiple cells as shown in the
	<xref target="Multiple_DECT_ULE"/>.
        The FPs in such a scenario should behave as Backbone Routers (6BBR) as defined 
        in <xref target="BACKBONE-ROUTER"/>.</t>
        <figure anchor="Multiple_DECT_ULE" title="Multiple DECT ULE Cells in a
	  Single Multi-link Subnet">
          <artwork>
                        ____________
                       /            \
                      |  Internet    |
                       \____________/
                             |
                             |
                             |
                             |
                 6BBR/       |        6BBR/
        6LN ---- 6LBR -------+------- 6LBR ---- 6LN
                /  \                   /  \
               /    \                 /    \
              6LN   6LN              6LN   6LN

  &lt;------------------ One subnet ------------------&gt;
  &lt;-- DECT ULE Cell --&gt;       &lt;-- DECT ULE Cell --&gt;
</artwork>
        </figure>
        
        
      </section>
    </section>
<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
</section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The secure transmission of circuit mode services in DECT is based on the
      DSAA2 and DSC/DSC2 specifications developed by ETSI Technical Committee (TC) DECT and the ETSI
      Security Algorithms Group of Experts (SAGE).</t>

      <t>DECT ULE communications are secured at the link layer (DLC) by
      encryption and per-message authentication through CCM (Counter with
      Cipher Block Chaining Message Authentication Code (CBC-MAC)) mode similar to <xref target="RFC3610"/>. The underlying algorithm for providing
      encryption and authentication is AES128.</t>

      <t>The DECT ULE pairing procedure generates a master User Authentication Key
      (UAK). During the location registration procedure, or when the permanent
      virtual circuits are established, the session security keys are
      generated. Both the master authentication key and session security keys are 
	  generated by use of the DSAA2 algorithm <xref target="EN300.175-part1-7"/>, which uses 
	  AES128 as the underlying algorithm.
	  Session security keys may be renewed regularly. The generated
      security keys (UAK and session security keys) are individual for each
      FP-PP binding; hence, all PPs in a system have different security keys.
      DECT ULE PPs do not use any shared encryption key.</t>
	  
	  <t>Even though DECT ULE offers link layer security, it is still recommended to use 
	  secure transport or application protocols above 6LoWPAN.</t>

      <t>From the privacy point of view, the IPv6 link-local address configuration
      described in <xref target="stateless_address"/> only reveals information about the 6LN to the
      6LBR that the 6LBR already knows from the link layer connection. For
      non-link-local IPv6 addresses, by default, a 6LN SHOULD use a randomly
      generated IID, for example, as discussed in <xref target="STABLE-IPv6"/>, 
      or use alternative schemes such as Cryptographically Generated
      Addresses (CGAs) <xref target="RFC3972"/>, privacy extensions <xref target="RFC4941"/>, Hash-Based
      Addresses (HBAs, <xref target="RFC5535"/>), or static, semantically opaque addresses
      <xref target="RFC7217"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ETSI" title="ETSI Considerations">
      <t>ETSI is standardizing a list of known application-layer protocols
      that can use the DECT ULE permanent virtual circuit packet data service.
      Each protocol is identified by a unique known identifier, which is
      exchanged in the service-change procedure as defined in <xref target="TS102.939-1"/>.
      The IPv6/6LoWPAN as described in this document is considered to be an
      application-layer protocol on top of DECT ULE. In order to provide
      interoperability between 6LoWPAN / DECT ULE devices, a common protocol
      identifier for 6LoWPAN is standardized by ETSI.</t>

      <t>The ETSI DECT ULE Application Protocol Identifier is set to
      0x06 for 6LoWPAN <xref target="TS102.939-1"/>.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC3633;

      &RFC4193;

      &RFC4861;

      &RFC4862;

      &RFC4941;

      &RFC4944;

      &RFC6282;

      &RFC4291;

      &RFC6775;

      &RFC7136;

      <reference anchor="EN300.175-part1-7"
                 target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/300100_300199/30017501/02.06.01_60/en_30017501v020601p.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT); Common
          Interface (CI); Part 1: Overview</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="ETSI">ETSI</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2015"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="European Standard," value="ETSI EN 300 175-1, V2.6.1"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS102.939-1"
                 target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102900_102999/10293901/01.02.01_60/ts_10293901v010201p.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT); Ultra
          Low Energy (ULE); Machine to Machine Communications; Part 1: Home
          Automation Network (phase 1)</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="ETSI">ETSI</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="Technical Specification," value="ETSI TS 102 939-1, V1.2.1"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS102.939-2"
                 target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102900_102999/10293902/01.01.01_60/ts_10293902v010101p.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT); Ultra
          Low Energy (ULE); Machine to Machine Communications; Part 2: Home
          Automation Network (phase 2)</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="ETSI">ETSI</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="Technical Specification," value="ETSI TS 102 939-2, V1.1.1"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="CAT-iq"
                 target="http://www.dect.org/userfiles/Public/DF_CAT-iq%20at%20a%20Glance.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>CAT-iq at a Glance</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="DECTforum">DECT Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      &RFC3315;

      &RFC3610;

      &RFC3972;

      &RFC4903;
	  
      &RFC5535;

      &RFC7217;

      &RFC7668;

      
	  
<!--draft-ietf-6lo-privacy-considerations-04:pub'd as RFC 8065 -->

<reference anchor='RFC8065' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8065'>
<front>
<title>Privacy Considerations for IPv6 Adaptation-Layer Mechanisms</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This document discusses how a number of privacy threats apply to technologies designed for IPv6 over various link layer protocols, and provides advice to protocol designers on how to address such threats in adaptation layer specifications for IPv6 over such links.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8065' />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8065"/>
</reference>



<!--draft-ietf-6man-default-iids-16: I-D Exists-->	  

<reference anchor='STABLE-IPv6'>
<front>
<title>Recommendation on Stable IPv6 Interface Identifiers</title>

<author initials='F' surname='Gont' fullname='Fernando Gont'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Cooper' fullname='Alissa Cooper'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='LIU' fullname='Shucheng LIU'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September'  year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This document changes the recommended default IID generation
scheme for cases where SLAAC is used to generate a stable IPv6 address.  It
recommends using the mechanism specified in RFC7217 in such cases, and
recommends against embedding stable link layer addresses in IPv6 Interface Identifiers.  It formally updates RFC2464, RFC2467, RFC2470, RFC2491, RFC2492, RFC2497, RFC2590, RFC3146, RFC3572, RFC4291, RFC4338, RFC4391, RFC5072, and RFC5121.  This document does not change any existing recommendations concerning the use of temporary addresses as specified in RFC 4941.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-6man-default-iids-16' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-6man-default-iids-16.txt' />
</reference>

<!--draft-ietf-6lo-backbone-router-03: I-D Exists -->
<reference anchor='BACKBONE-ROUTER'>
<front>
<title>IPv6 Backbone Router</title>

<author initials='P' surname='Thubert' fullname='Pascal Thubert'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This specification proposes an update to IPv6 Neighbor Discovery, to enhance the operation of IPv6 over wireless links that exhibit lossy multicast support, and enable a large degree of scalability by splitting the broadcast domains.  A higher speed backbone federates multiple wireless links to form a large MultiLink Subnet.  Backbone Routers acting as Layer-3 Access Point route packets to registered nodes, where an classical Layer-2 Access Point would bridge. Conversely, wireless nodes register to the Backbone Router to setup routing services in a fashion that is essentially similar to a classical Layer-2 association.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-6lo-backbone-router-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-6lo-backbone-router-03.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>
<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>We are grateful to the members of the IETF 6lo working group; this
document borrows liberally from their work.</t>

<t>Ralph Droms, Samita Chakrabarti, Kerry Lynn, Suresh Krishnan, Pascal
Thubert, Tatuya Jinmei, Dale Worley, and Robert Sparks have provided valuable
feedback for this document.</t>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
