<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<rfc number="8637" ipr="trust200902" category="info" consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="PCE-ACTN">Applicability of the Path Computation Element (PCE) to&nbsp;the&nbsp;Abstraction&nbsp;and&nbsp;Control&nbsp;of&nbsp;TE&nbsp;Networks&nbsp;(ACTN)</title>
    <author initials="D" surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560066</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Young Lee" initials="Y" surname="Lee">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5340 Legacy Drive, Suite 173</street>
          <city>Plano</city>
          <region>TX</region>
          <code>75024</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>younglee.tx@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D" fullname="Daniele Ceccarelli" surname="Ceccarelli">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Torshamnsgatan,48</street>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniele.ceccarelli@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
<date year="2019" month="July" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>PCE, ACTN</keyword>
    <abstract>
   <t> 
      Abstraction and Control of TE Networks (ACTN) refers to the set of
      virtual network (VN) operations needed to orchestrate, control, and
      manage large-scale multidomain TE networks so as to facilitate network
      programmability, automation, efficient resource sharing, and end-to-end
      virtual service-aware connectivity and network function virtualization
      services.</t>
   <t>The Path Computation Element (PCE) is a component, application, or
   network node that is capable of computing a network path or route based on
   a network graph and applying computational constraints.  The PCE serves
   requests from Path Computation Clients (PCCs) that communicate with it over
   a local API or using the Path Computation Element Communication Protocol
   (PCEP).</t>
   <t>This document examines the applicability of PCE to the ACTN framework. </t>    
   </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">

   <t> 
  Abstraction and Control of TE Networks (ACTN) <xref target="RFC8453"/>
  refers to the set of virtual network (VN) operations needed to orchestrate,
  control, and manage large-scale multidomain TE networks so as to facilitate
  network programmability, automation, efficient resource sharing, and
  end-to-end virtual service-aware connectivity and network function
  virtualization services.</t>
   <t>The Path Computation Element (PCE) <xref target="RFC4655"/> is a
   component, application, or network node that is capable of computing a
   network path or route based on a network graph and applying computational
   constraints.  The PCE serves requests from Path Computation Clients (PCCs)
   that communicate with it over a local API or using the Path Computation
   Element Communication Protocol (PCEP).
   </t>
   <t>This document examines the PCE and ACTN architecture and describes how PCE architecture
   is applicable to ACTN. It also lists the PCEP extensions that are needed to use PCEP as an ACTN interface. 
   This document also identifies any gaps in PCEP that exist at the time of publication of this document.</t>
   <t>Further, ACTN, stateful Hierarchical PCE (H-PCE) <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/>, and PCE as a central
   controller (PCECC) <xref target="RFC8283"/> are based on the same basic hierarchy     
   framework and are thus compatible with each other.</t>
   
</section>
    <section title="Background Information" toc="default">
    <section title="Path Computation Element (PCE)" toc="default">
   <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) <xref target="RFC5440"/> provides
   mechanisms for Path Computation Clients (PCCs) to request a Path Computation Element (PCE) <xref target="RFC4655"/> to perform path
   computations.</t>
   
   <t>The ability to compute shortest constrained TE LSPs in Multiprotocol
   Label Switching (MPLS) and Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) networks across
   multiple domains has been identified as a key motivation for PCE
   development.</t>
   
   <t>A stateful PCE <xref target="RFC8231"/> is capable of considering, for the purposes of
   path computation, not only the network state in terms of links and
   nodes (referred to as the Traffic Engineering Database or TED), but
   also the status of active services (previously computed paths),
   and currently reserved resources, stored in the Label Switched
   Paths Database (LSP-DB).</t>


   <t><xref target="RFC8051"/> describes general considerations for
   a stateful PCE deployment and examines its applicability and
   benefits as well as its challenges and limitations through a number
   of use cases.</t>

   <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> describes a set of extensions to PCEP to
   provide stateful control.  A stateful PCE has access to not only the
   information carried by the network's Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP),
   but also the set of active paths and their reserved resources for its
   computations.  The additional state allows the PCE to compute
   constrained paths while considering individual LSPs and their
   interactions.  <xref target="RFC8281"/> describes the setup,
   maintenance, and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the stateful PCE
   model.</t>

   <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> also describes the active stateful PCE.
   The active PCE functionality allows a PCE to reroute an existing
   LSP or make changes to the attributes of an existing LSP, or a PCC to delegate
   control of specific LSPs to a new PCE.</t>

   
   <section title="Role of PCE in SDN" toc="default">
   <t>Software-Defined Networking (SDN) <xref target="RFC7149"/> refers to a separation between the control elements
   and the forwarding components so that software running in a
   centralized system, called a controller, can act to program the
   devices in the network to behave in specific ways. A required 
   element in an SDN architecture is a component that plans
   how the network resources will be used and how the devices will be
   programmed.  It is possible to view this component as performing
   specific computations to place flows within the network given
   knowledge of the availability of network resources, how other
   forwarding devices are programmed, and the way that other flows are
   routed.  It is concluded in <xref target="RFC7399"/> that this is the same function that a PCE
   might offer in a network operated using a dynamic control plane.
   This is the function and purpose of a PCE, and the way that
   a PCE integrates into a wider network control system including SDN is
   presented in Application-Based Network Operation (ABNO) <xref target="RFC7491"/>.
   </t>
    
   
   </section>
   <section title="PCE in Multidomain and Multilayer Deployments" toc="default">
   <t>Computing paths across large multidomain environments
   requires special computational components and cooperation between
   entities in different domains capable of complex path computation.
   The PCE provides an architecture and a set of functional components 
   to address this problem space. A PCE may be used to compute 
   end-to-end paths across multidomain
   environments using a per-domain path computation technique <xref target="RFC5152"/>.
   The Backward-Recursive PCE-based path computation (BRPC) mechanism
   <xref target="RFC5441"/> defines a PCE-based path computation procedure to compute
   interdomain-constrained  MPLS and
   GMPLS TE networks. However, per-domain technique assumes that the
   sequence of domains to be crossed from source to destination is
   known, either fixed by the network operator or obtained by other
   means.  BRPC can work best with a known domain sequence, and it will
   also work nicely with a small set of interconnected domains.
   However, it doesn't work well for a large set of interconnected
   domains.</t>
   <t><xref target="RFC6805"/> describes a Hierarchical PCE (H-PCE)
   architecture that can be used for computing end-to-end paths for
   interdomain MPLS Traffic Engineering (TE) and GMPLS Label Switched
   Paths (LSPs) when the domain sequence is not known.  
   Within the Hierarchical PCE (H-PCE) architecture, 
   the Parent PCE (P-PCE) is used to compute a multidomain
   path based on the domain connectivity information.  A Child PCE
   (C-PCE) may be responsible for a single domain or multiple domains;
   it is used to compute the intradomain path based on its domain
   topology information.</t>
   
   <t><xref target="PCE-HPCE"/> states the considerations for stateful PCEs in
   Hierarchical PCE architecture.  In particular, the behavior changes and
   adds to the existing stateful PCE mechanisms (including PCE-initiated
   LSP setup and active PCE usage) in the context of networks using the H-PCE
   architecture.</t>
   

   <t><xref target="RFC5623"/> describes a framework for applying the PCE-based
   architecture to interlayer (G)MPLS TE. It provides
   suggestions for the deployment of PCE in support of multilayer
   networks.  It also describes the
   relationship between PCE and a functional component in charge of the
   control and management of the Virtual Network Topology (VNT) <xref target="RFC5212"/> called the VNT Manager (VNTM).</t>
   
   </section>
   <section title="Relationship to PCE-Based Central Control" toc="default">
       <t><xref target="RFC8283"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a central
   controller (PCECC); it further examines the motivations and applicability for PCEP as a
   southbound interface (SBI) and introduces the implications for the
   protocol. Section 2.1.3 of <xref target="RFC8283"/>
   describes a hierarchy of PCE-based controllers as per the PCE Hierarchy
   Framework defined in <xref target="RFC6805"/>. </t>
    </section>
   </section>
   <section title="Abstraction and Control of TE Networks (ACTN)" toc="default">
   <t><xref target="RFC8453"/> describes the high-level ACTN requirements and
   the architecture model for ACTN, including the entities Customer Network
   Controller (CNC), Multidomain Service Coordinator (MDSC), and Provisioning
   Network Controller (PNC) and their interfaces.</t>
 
  <t>The ACTN reference architecture is shown in <xref target="fig_actn"/>, which is reproduced here from <xref target="RFC8453"/> for convenience. <xref target="RFC8453"/> remains the definitive reference for the ACTN architecture. As depicted in <xref target="fig_actn"/>, the ACTN architecture identifies a three-tier hierarchy.</t>

<!-- [rfced] Figure 1 uses "SBI"; would you like to add "SBI - Southbound
Interface" below the figure (under CMI and MPI)? 
Alternatively, in the preceding section, would you like to add "(SBI)" 
so that it reads "southbound interface (SBI)"?
-->

                <figure title="ACTN Hierarchy"
             suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height="" anchor="fig_actn">
            <artwork><![CDATA[


           +---------+           +---------+           +---------+
           |   CNC   |           |   CNC   |           |   CNC   |
           +---------+           +---------+           +---------+
                     \                |                /
                      \               |               /
Boundary  =============\==============|==============/============
Between                 \             |             /
Customer &               -------      | CMI  -------
Network Operator                \     |     /
                              +---------------+
                              |     MDSC      |
                              +---------------+
                                /     |     \
                    ------------      | MPI  -------------
                   /                  |                   \
              +-------+          +-------+             +-------+
              |  PNC  |          |  PNC  |             |  PNC  |
              +-------+          +-------+             +-------+
                  | SBI            /   |                /   \
                  |               /    | SBI           /     \
              ---------        -----   |              /       \
             (         )      (     )  |             /         \
             - Control -     ( Phys. ) |            /        -----
            (  Plane    )     ( Net )  |           /        (     )
           (  Physical   )     -----   |          /        ( Phys. )
            (  Network  )            -----      -----       ( Net )
             -         -            (     )    (     )       -----
             (         )           ( Phys. )  ( Phys. )
              ---------             ( Net )    ( Net )
                                     -----      -----

CMI - (CNC-MDSC Interface)
MPI - (MDSC-PNC Interface)
SBI - (Southbound Interface)
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

   <t>There are two interfaces with respect to the MDSC: one north of the
   MDSC (the CNC-MDSC Interface (CMI)), and one south (the MDSC-PNC
   Interface (MPI)).  A hierarchy of MDSCs is possible with a recursive
   MPI interface.</t>
   <t><xref target="RFC8454"/> provides an information model
   for ACTN interfaces.</t>
   </section>
   </section>

   
          
    
<section title="Architectural Considerations" toc="default">
    <t>The ACTN architecture <xref target="RFC8453"/>
    is based on the hierarchy and recursiveness of controllers. It defines 
    three types of controllers (depending on the functionalities they implement).
    The main functionalities are: 
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>Multidomain coordination</t>
    <t>Abstraction</t>
    <t>Customer mapping/translation</t>
    <t>Virtual service coordination</t>
    </list>
    </t>
    <t>Section 3 of <xref target="RFC8453"/> describes these functions.</t>
   
    <t>It should be noted that this document lists all possible ways in which PCE could be used
    for each of the above functions, but all functions are not required to be implemented via PCE. Similarly,
   this document presents the ways in which PCEP could be used as the
   communications medium between functional components. Operators 
   may choose to use the PCEP for multidomain coordination via stateful H-PCE
   but alternatively use Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF) <xref target="RFC6241"/>, RESTCONF <xref target="RFC8040"/>, or BGP - Link State (BGP-LS) <xref target="RFC7752"/> to get access to the topology and support abstraction function.</t>
   
    <section title="Multidomain Coordination via Hierarchy" toc="default" anchor="sec_hpce">

<t>
    With the definition of domain being everything that is under the control
    of the single logical controller, as per <xref target="RFC8453"/>, it is
    needed both to have a control entity that oversees the specific aspects of
    the different domains and to build a single abstracted end-to-end network
    topology in order to coordinate end-to-end path computation and
    path/service provisioning.
    
	</t>
	<t>The MDSC in ACTN framework realizes this function by coordinating 
	the per-domain PNCs in a hierarchy of controllers. It also needs to detach 
	from the underlying network technology and express customer concerns by
	business needs.</t>
	<t><xref target="RFC6805"/> and <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/> 
	describe a hierarchy of PCEs with the Parent PCE coordinating multidomain path 
	computation function between Child PCEs. It is easy to see how these 
	principles align, and thus how the stateful H-PCE architecture can be used to realize ACTN.</t>
	<t>The per-domain stitched LSP in the Hierarchical stateful PCE
	architecture, described in Section 3.3.1 of <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/>,
	is well suited for multidomain coordination function. This includes
	domain sequence selection, End-to-End (E2E) path computation, and
	controller-initiated (PCE-initiated) path setup and reporting.  This
	is also applicable to multilayer coordination in case of IP+optical
	networks.
	</t>
	<t><xref target="PCE-STATE-SYNC"/> describes the procedures to allow a
   stateful communication between PCEs for various use cases. The
   procedures and extensions are also applicable to Child and
   Parent PCE communication and are thus useful for ACTN as well.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Abstraction" toc="default" anchor="sec_topo">
    <t>To realize ACTN, an abstracted view of the underlying network resources
    needs to be built.  This includes global network-wide abstracted topology
    based on the underlying network resources of each domain. This also
    includes abstract topology created as per the customer service
    connectivity requests and represented as a VN slice allocated to each
    customer. </t>
    
    <t>In order to compute and provide optimal paths, PCEs require an accurate
    and timely Traffic Engineering Database (TED).  Traditionally, this TED
    has been obtained from a link-state (LS) routing protocol supporting
    traffic engineering extensions. PCE may construct its TED by participating
    in the IGP (<xref target="RFC3630"/> and <xref target="RFC5305"/> for
    MPLS-TE; <xref target="RFC4203"/> and <xref target="RFC5307"/> for
    GMPLS). An alternative is offered by BGP-LS <xref target="RFC7752"/>.</t>
   <t>In case of H-PCE <xref target="RFC6805"/>, the Parent PCE needs to 
   build the domain topology map of the child domains and
   their interconnectivity. <xref target="RFC6805"/> and <xref target="PCE-INTER-AREA"/>
   suggest that BGP-LS could be used as a "northbound" TE advertisement from 
   the Child PCE to the Parent PCE.</t>
   <t><xref target="PCEP-LS"/> proposes another approach for learning and maintaining
   the Link-State and TE information as an alternative to IGPs and BGP flooding, using PCEP itself. 
   The Child PCE can use this mechanism to transport Link-State and
   TE information from Child PCE to a Parent PCE using PCEP.

   </t>
   <t>In ACTN, there is a need to control the level of abstraction based on
   the deployment scenario and business relationship between the controllers.
   The mechanism used to disseminate information from the PNC (Child PCE) to
   the MDSC (Parent PCE) should support abstraction.  <xref target="RFC8453"/>
   describes a few alternative approaches of abstraction. The resulting
   abstracted topology can be encoded using the PCEP-LS mechanisms <xref
   target="PCEP-LS"/> and its optical network extension <xref
   target="PCEP-OPTICAL"/>.  PCEP-LS is an attractive option when the operator
   would wish to have a single control-plane protocol (PCEP) to achieve ACTN
   functions. </t>
   
   <t><xref target="RFC8453"/> discusses two ways to build abstract topology from an MDSC standpoint
   with interaction with PNCs. The primary method is called automatic generation of abstract topology by configuration. With this 
   method, automatic generation is based on the abstraction/summarization of
   the whole domain by the PNC and its advertisement on the MPI. The secondary method is called 
   on-demand generation of supplementary topology via Path Compute
   Request/Reply. This method may be needed to obtain further complementary information such as 
   potential connectivity from Child PCEs in order to facilitate an end-to-end path provisioning.
   PCEP is well suited to support both methods.</t>
    </section>
	<section title="Customer Mapping" toc="default">
    <t>In ACTN, there is a need to map customer virtual network (VN) requirements into 
    a network provisioning request to the PNC. That is, the
        customer requests/commands are mapped by the MDSC into network provisioning requests
        that can be sent to the PNC. Specifically, the MDSC provides mapping and
        translation of a customer's service request into a set of
        parameters that are specific to a network type and technology
        such that the network configuration process is made possible.</t>

    <t><xref target="RFC8281"/> describes the setup, maintenance, and
   teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the stateful PCE model, without
   the need for local configuration on the PCC, thus allowing for a
   dynamic network that is centrally controlled and deployed.  To
   instantiate or delete an LSP, the PCE sends the Path Computation LSP
   Initiate Request (PCInitiate) message to the PCC.  As described in 
   <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/>, for interdomain LSP in 
   Hierarchical PCE architecture, the initiation
   operations can be carried out at the Parent PCE. In this case, after
   Parent PCE finishes the E2E path computation, it can send the
   PCInitiate message to the Child PCE; the Child PCE
   further propagates the initiate request to the Label Switching Router (LSR). The customer request
   is received by the MDSC (Parent PCE), and, based on the business logic, 
   global abstracted topology, network conditions, and local policy, the 
   MDSC (Parent PCE) translates this into a per-domain LSP initiation request that a 
   PNC (Child PCE) can understand and act on. This can be done via the PCInitiate message.</t>
   <t>PCEP extensions for associating opaque policy between PCEP peer <xref target="ASSOC-POLICY"/>
   can be used.</t> 
   
  
    </section>
	<section title="Virtual Service Coordination" toc="default" anchor="sec_vno">
    <t>Virtual service coordination
        function in ACTN incorporates customer service-related
        information into the virtual network service operations in order to
        seamlessly operate virtual networks while meeting customers'
        service requirements. </t>

	<t><xref target="PCEP-VN"/> describes the 
	need for associating a set of LSPs with a VN "construct" to
   facilitate VN operations in PCE architecture. This association
   allows the PCEs to identify which LSPs belong to a certain VN. </t>

<!-- [rfced] We are having trouble understanding the following sentence. 
How might we clarify?

Original:
   This is to make sure that the overall optimization and SLA 
   of the VN rather than of a single LSP.

Perhaps:
   This is to ensure the optimization of the overall VN rather
   than of a single LSP.

Or:
   This is to ensure optimization and SLA attainment for the VN 
   rather than for a single LSP.
-->
   <t>This association based on VN is useful for various optimizations at the
   VN level, which can be applied to all the LSPs that are part of the VN
   slice. During path computation, the impact of a path for an LSP is compared
   against the paths of other LSPs in the VN. This is to ensure optimization
   and SLA attainment for the VN rather than for a single LSP. Similarly,
   during reoptimization, advanced path computation algorithms and
   optimization techniques can be considered for all the LSPs belonging to a
   VN/customer and optimize them all together.
</t>


    </section>
</section>
<section title="Interface Considerations" toc="default">
<t>As per <xref target="RFC8453"/>, 
to allow virtualization and multidomain coordination, the network
   has to provide open, programmable interfaces in which customer
   applications can create, replace, and modify virtual network
   resources and services in an interactive, flexible, and dynamic
   fashion while having no impact on other customers. The two ACTN 
   interfaces are as follows:
   <list style="symbols">
   <t>The CNC-MDSC Interface (CMI) is an interface
        between a Customer Network Controller and a Multidomain
        Service Coordinator. It requests the creation of the network
        resources, topology, or services for the applications. The
        MDSC may also report potential network
        topology availability if queried for current capability from
        the Customer Network Controller.</t>
   <t>The MDSC-PNC Interface (MPI) is an interface
        between a Multidomain Service Coordinator and a Provisioning
        Network Controller. It communicates the creation request, if
        required, of new connectivity of bandwidth changes in the
        physical network via the PNC. In multidomain environments,
        the MDSC needs to establish multiple MPIs, one for each PNC, as
        there are multiple PNCs responsible for its domain
control.</t></list></t>    

    <t>In the case of a hierarchy of MDSCs, the MPI is applied recursively. 
   From an abstraction point of view, the top-level MDSC, which
   interfaces the CNC, operates on a higher level of abstraction (i.e.,
   less granular level) than the lower-level MDSCs.</t>     
   
   <t>PCEP is especially suitable on the MPI as it meets the requirement
   and the functions as set out in the ACTN framework 
   <xref target="RFC8453"/>. Its recursive nature is well suited 
   via the multilevel hierarchy of PCE. PCEP can also be applied to the CMI as the 
   CNC can be a path computation client while the MDSC can be a path 
   computation server. <xref target="sec_real"/> describes how PCE and PCEP could help 
   realize ACTN on the MPI.</t>
   
</section>
<section title="Realizing ACTN with PCE (and PCEP)" toc="default" anchor="sec_real">
<t>As per the example in <xref target="F1"/>, there are 4 domains, 
each with their own PNC and MDSC on top. The PNC and MDSC need PCE as 
an important function. The PNC (or Child PCE) already uses PCEP to communicate to
the network device. It can utilize the PCEP as the MPI to communicate
between controllers too.</t>
             <figure title="ACTN with PCE"
             suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height="" anchor="F1">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                          ******  
                ..........*MDSC*.............................. 
             .            ****** ..                   MPI    .
          .                .        .                        .
       .                   .          .                      .
     .                    .             .                    .
    .                    .                .                  .
   .                    .                  .                 .
  .                    .                    .                .
  v                    v                    v                .
******               ******               ******             .    
*PNC1*               *PNC2*               *PNC4*             .
******               ******               ******             .
+---------------+    +---------------+    +---------------+  .
|A              |----|               |----|              C|  .
|               |    |               |    |               |  .
|DOMAIN 1       |----|DOMAIN 2       |----|DOMAIN 4       |  .
+------------B13+    +---------------+    +B43------------+  .
                \                         /                  .
                 \   ******              /                   .
                  \  *PNC3*<............/.....................
                   \ ******            /
                    \+---------------+/
                     B31           B34
                     |               |
                     |DOMAIN 3      B|
                     +---------------+


MDSC -> Parent PCE
PNC  -> Child  PCE
MPI  -> PCEP            
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
    <t><list style="symbols">      
    <t>Building Domain Topology at MDSC: PNC (or Child PCE) needs to have the
    TED to compute the path in its domain. 
    As described in <xref target="sec_topo"/>, it can learn the topology 
    via IGP or BGP-LS. PCEP-LS is also a proposed mechanism to carry link state and 
    traffic engineering information within PCEP. A mechanism to carry abstracted
    topology while hiding technology-specific information between PNC and MDSC is
    described in <xref target="PCEP-LS"/>. At the end of this 
    step, the MDSC (or Parent PCE) has the abstracted topology from each of its PNCs 
    (or Child PCE). This could be as simple as a domain topology map as described 
    in <xref target="RFC6805"/>, or it can have full topology information of all
    domains. The latter is not scalable, and thus, an abstracted topology of each domain
    interconnected by interdomain links is the most common case.
    <list style="symbols">      
        <t>Topology Change: When the PNC learns of any topology change, the PNC needs 
        to decide if the change needs to be notified to the MDSC. This is dependent on 
        the level of abstraction between the MDSC and the PNC.</t>
        </list>
    </t>
    <t>VN Instantiate: When an MDSC is requested to instantiate a VN, the minimal information 
    that is required would be a VN identifier and a set of end points. Various path 
    computation, setup constraints, and objective functions may also be provided.
    In PCE terms, a VN Instantiate can be considered as a set of paths belonging to the same VN. 
    As described in <xref target="sec_vno"/> and <xref target="PCEP-VN"/>,
    the VN association can help in identifying the set of paths that belong to a VN. 
    The rest of the information, like the endpoints, constraints, and objective function (OF), is 
    already defined in PCEP in terms of a single path.
        <list style="symbols">      
        <t>Path Computation: As per the example in <xref target="F1"/>, the VN
        instantiate requires two end-to-end paths between (A in Domain 1 to B
        in Domain 3) and (A in Domain 1 to C in Domain 4). The MDSC (or Parent
        PCE) triggers the end-to-end path computation for these two
        paths. MDSC can do path computation based on the abstracted domain
        topology that it already has, or it may use the H-PCE procedures
        (<xref target="sec_hpce"/>) using the PCReq and PCRep messages to get
        the end-to-end path with the help of the Child PCEs (PNC).  Either
        way, the resultant E2E paths may be broken into per-domain paths.</t>
        <t>A-B: (A-B13,B13-B31,B31-B) </t>
        <t>A-C: (A-B13,B13-B31,B31-B34,B34-B43,B43-C)</t>
        <t>Per-Domain Path Instantiation: Based on the above path computation,
        MDSC can issue the path instantiation request to each PNC via
        PCInitiate message (see <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/> and <xref
        target="PCEP-VN"/>).  A suitable stitching mechanism would be used to
        stitch these per-domain LSPs.  One such mechanism is described in
        <xref target="PCE-INTERDOMAIN"/>, where PCEP is extended to support
        stitching in stateful H-PCE context.
        </t>

        <t>Per-Domain Path Report: Each PNC should report the status of the
        per-domain LSP to the MDSC via PCRpt message, as per the hierarchy of
        stateful PCEs (<xref target="PCE-HPCE"/>). The status of the end-to-end
        LSP (A-B and A-C) is made up when all the per-domain LSPs are reported
        up by the PNCs.</t>
        <t>Delegation: It is suggested that the per-domain LSPs are delegated to
        respective PNCs so that they can control the path and attributes based
        on the conditions of each domain network.</t>
        <t>State Synchronization: The state needs to be synchronized between
        the Parent PCE and Child PCE. The mechanism described in <xref
        target="PCE-STATE-SYNC"/> can be used.</t>
        </list></t>
   <t>VN Modify: MDSC is requested to modify a VN, for example, the bandwidth
   for VN is increased. This may trigger path computation at MDSC as described
   in the previous step and can trigger an update to an existing
   per-intradomain path (via PCUpd message) or the creation (or deletion) of
   a per-domain path (via PCInitiate message). As described in <xref
   target="PCE-HPCE"/>, this should be done in make-before-break fashion.</t>
   <t>VN Delete: MDSC is requested to delete a VN, in this case, based on the E2E paths, and 
   the resulting per-domain paths need to be removed (via PCInitiate message).</t>
   <t>VN Update (based on network changes): Any change in the per-domain LSP
   is reported to the MDSC (via PCRpt message) as per <xref target="PCE-HPCE"/>. 
   This may result in changes in the E2E path or VN status. This may also trigger a reoptimization
   leading to a new per-domain path, an update to an existing path, or the deletion of the path.</t>
   <t>VN Protection: The VN protection/restoration requirements need to be applied to each E2E path
   as well as each per-domain path. The MDSC needs to play a crucial role in coordinating the 
   right protection/restoration policy across each PNC. The existing protection/restoration mechanism
   of PCEP can be applied on each path.   </t>
   <t>In case a PNC generates an abstract topology towards the MDSC, the PCInitiate/PCUpd messages from the 
   MDSC to a PNC will contain a path with abstract nodes and links. A PNC would need to take that as an 
   input for path computation to get a path with physical nodes and links. Similarly, a PNC would convert 
   the path received from the device (with physical nodes and links) into an abstract path (based on the
   abstract topology generated before with abstract nodes and links) and report it to the MDSC.</t>
   </list></t>
</section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default" anchor="sec_iana">
    <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>    
    </section>  
    
   
    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
    <t>Various security considerations for PCEP are described in <xref
    target="RFC5440" /> and <xref target="RFC8253"/>. Security considerations
    as stated in Sections 10.1, 10.6, and 10.7 of <xref target="RFC5440"/>
    continue to apply on PCEP when used as an ACTN interface. Further, this
    document lists various extensions of PCEP that are applicable; each of
    them specify various security considerations that continue to apply
    here.</t>

    <t>The ACTN framework described in <xref target="RFC8453"/> defines key
    components and interfaces for managed traffic-engineered networks. It also
    lists various security considerations such as request and control of
    resources, confidentially of the information, and availability of function,
    which should be taken into consideration. </t>

   <t>As per <xref target="RFC8453"/>, securing the request and
   control of resources, confidentiality of the information, and
   availability of function should all be critical security
   considerations when deploying and operating ACTN platforms.
   From a security and reliability perspective, ACTN may encounter many
   risks such as malicious attack and rogue elements attempting to
   connect to various ACTN components (with PCE being one of them). 
   Furthermore, some ACTN
   components represent a single point of failure and threat vector, and
   must also manage policy conflicts and eavesdropping of communication
   between different ACTN components.
   <xref target="RFC8453"/> further states that all protocols used to realize the ACTN
   framework should have rich security features, and customer,
   application, and network data should be stored in encrypted data
   stores. When PCEP is used as an ACTN interface, the security of PCEP 
   provided by 
   Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/>, as per the recommendations
   and best current practices in <xref target="RFC7525"/> (unless
   explicitly set aside in <xref target="RFC8253"/>), is used.</t>  
 



   <t>As per <xref target="RFC8453"/>, regarding the MPI, a PKI-based
   mechanism is suggested, such as building a TLS or HTTPS connection between
   the MDSC and PNCs, to ensure trust between the physical network layer
   control components and the MDSC.  Which MDSC the PNC exports topology
   information to, and the level of detail (full or abstracted), should also
   be authenticated, and specific access restrictions and topology views
   should be configurable and/or policy based. When PCEP is used in MPI, the
   security functions, as per <xref target="RFC8253"/>, are used to fulfill
   these requirements.</t>

   <t>As per <xref target="RFC8453"/>, regarding the CMI, suitable
   authentication and authorization of each CNC connecting to the MDSC
   will be required. If PCEP is used in CMI, the security functions, as per 
   <xref target="RFC8253"/>, can be used to support peer authentication, message encryption, and
   integrity checks.</t>

    </section>    
        
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4655.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5440.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6805.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8453.xml" ?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3630.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4203.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5152.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5212.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5305.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5307.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5441.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5623.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6241.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7149.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7399.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7491.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7525.xml" ?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7752.xml" ?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8040.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8051.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8231.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8253.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8283.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8454.xml"?>

<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-stateful-hpce"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCE-HPCE'>
<front>
<title>Hierarchical Stateful Path Computation Element (PCE).</title>
<author initials='D' surname='Dhody' fullname='Dhruv Dhody'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Young Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Ceccarelli' fullname='Daniele Ceccarelli'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Shin' fullname='Jongyoon Shin'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='King' fullname='Daniel King'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='June' year='2019' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-pce-stateful-hpce-10' />
</reference>

	     
<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-inter-area-as-applicability"?>; In Last Call -->

<reference anchor='PCE-INTER-AREA'>
<front>
<title>Applicability of the Path Computation Element to Interarea and Inter-AS MPLS and GMPLS Traffic Engineering</title>

<author initials='D' surname='King' fullname='Daniel King'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Zheng' fullname='Haomian Zheng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' year='2018' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-pce-inter-area-as-applicability-07' />
</reference>


<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.dhodylee-pce-pcep-ls"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCEP-LS'>
<front>
<title>PCEP Extension for Distribution of Link-State and TE Information.</title>

<author initials='D' surname='Dhody' fullname='Dhruv Dhody'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Young Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ceccarelli' fullname='Daniele Ceccarelli'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='15' year='2019' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-dhodylee-pce-pcep-ls-13' />
</reference>

<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCEP-OPTICAL'>
<front>
<title>PCEP Extension for Distribution of Link-State and TE information for Optical Networks</title>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Young Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Zheng' fullname='Haomian Zheng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ceccarelli' fullname='Daniele Ceccarelli'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Wang' fullname='Wei Wang'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Park' fullname='Peter Park'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Yoon' fullname='Bin Yeong Yoon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='1' year='2019' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical-07' />
</reference>


<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.leedhody-pce-vn-association"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCEP-VN'>
<front>
<title>Path Computation Element communication Protocol (PCEP) extensions for
Establishing Relationships between sets of LSPs and Virtual Networks</title>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Young Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='X' surname='Zhang' fullname='Xian Zhang'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ceccarelli' fullname='Daniele Ceccarelli'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2019' />

</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-leedhody-pce-vn-association-08' />
</reference>

<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.litkowski-pce-state-sync?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCE-STATE-SYNC'>
<front>
<title>Inter Stateful Path Computation Element (PCE) Communication Procedures.</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Li' fullname='Cheng Li'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='H' surname='Zheng' fullname='Haomian Zheng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='8' year='2019' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-litkowski-pce-state-sync-05' />
</reference>

<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-policy"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='ASSOC-POLICY'>
<front>
<title>Path Computation Element communication Protocol extension for associating Policies and LSPs</title>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Hardwick' fullname='Jonathan Hardwick'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Negi' fullname='Mahendra Negi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='3' year='2019' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-pce-association-policy-05' />
</reference>

<!-- <?rfc include="reference.I-D.dugeon-pce-stateful-interdomain"?>; I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor='PCE-INTERDOMAIN'>
<front>
<title>PCEP Extension for Stateful Interdomain Tunnels</title>

<author initials='O' surname='Dugeon' fullname='Olivier Dugeon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Meuric' fullname='Julien Meuric'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Y' surname='Lee' fullname='Young Lee'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Ceccarelli' fullname='Daniele Ceccarelli'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='4' year='2019' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-dugeon-pce-stateful-interdomain-02' />
</reference>

     <reference anchor="EXP" target="https://zenodo.org/record/832904">
        <front>
            <title>Experimental Validation of the ACTN architecture for flexi-grid optical networks using Active Stateful Hierarchical PCEs</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Casellas" fullname="R. Casellas">
                <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Vilalta" fullname="R. Vilalta">
                <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Martinez" fullname="R. Martinez">
                <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Munoz" fullname="R. Munoz">
                <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="H." surname="Zheng" fullname="H. Zheng">
                <organization />
            </author>
            <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
                <organization />
            </author>


            <date month="July" year="2017" />
        </front>   
        <seriesInfo name="19th International Conference on 
Transparent Optical Networks" value="(ICTON)" />
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.5281/zenodo.832903"/>    
</reference>

    </references>
    <section title="Additional Information" toc="default">
      <t>In the paper <xref target="EXP"/>, the application of the ACTN architecture is
      presented to demonstrate the control of a multidomain flexi-grid optical
      network by proposing, adopting, and extending:
<list style="symbols">
<t>the Hierarchical active stateful PCE architectures and protocols</t>
<t>the PCEP protocol to support efficient and incremental link-state
topological reporting, known as PCEP-LS</t>
<t>the per-link partitioning of the optical spectrum based on variable-sized
allocated frequency slots enabling network sharing and virtualization</t>
<t>the use of a model-based interface to dynamically request the instantiation
of virtual networks for specific clients/tenants.</t></list> </t>
<t>The design and implementation of the test bed are reported in order to
validate the approach.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" toc="default" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Jonathan Hardwick for the inspiration behind this document. 
      Further thanks to Avantika for her comments with suggested text. </t>
      <t>Thanks to Adrian Farrel and Daniel King for their substantial reviews.</t>
      <t>Thanks to Yingzhen Qu for RTGDIR review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to Rifaat Shekh-Yusef for SECDIR review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to Meral Shirazipour for GENART review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to Roman Danyliw and Barry Leiba for IESG review comments.</t>
      <t>Thanks to Deborah Brungard for being the responsible AD.</t>  
    </section>
    
  </back>
</rfc>
