<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc number="8256" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Hitless Path Segment Monitoring">Requirements for Hitless
    MPLS Path Segment Monitoring</title>

    <author fullname="Alessandro D'Alessandro" initials="A." surname="D'Alessandro">
      <organization>Telecom Italia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Reiss Romoli, 274</street>

          <city>Torino</city>

          <region/>

          <code>10148</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>alessandro.dalessandro@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>
  
    
    <author fullname="Loa Andersson" initials="L." surname="Andersson">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>loa@pi.nu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
 

    <author fullname="Satoshi Ueno" initials="S." surname="Ueno">
      <organization>NTT Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
        
          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>ueno@nttv6.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>
 
    <author fullname="Kaoru Arai" initials="K." surname="Arai">
      <organization>NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
        
          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>arai.kaoru@lab.ntt.co.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>
      
    <author fullname="Yoshinori Koike" initials="Y." surname="Koike">
      <organization>NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
        
          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>y.koike@vcd.nttbiz.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
    
      <t>
      One of the most important Operations, Administration, and Maintenance
      (OAM) capabilities for transport-network operation is fault
      localization.  An in-service, on-demand path segment monitoring function of a
      transport path is indispensable, particularly when the service monitoring function is activated only between endpoints.  However, the
      current segment monitoring approach defined for MPLS (including the MPLS
      Transport Profile (MPLS-TP)) in RFC 6371 "Operations, Administration,
      and Maintenance Framework for MPLS-Based Transport Networks" has
      drawbacks.  This document provides an analysis of the existing MPLS-TP
      OAM mechanisms for the path segment monitoring and provides requirements
      to guide the development of new OAM tools to support Hitless Path
      Segment Monitoring (HPSM).
      </t>
      
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      
    <t>
     According to the MPLS-TP OAM requirements <xref target="RFC5860"/>,
     mechanisms MUST be available for alerting service providers of faults or
     defects that affect their services.  In addition, to ensure that faults
     or service degradation can be localized, operators need a function to
     diagnose the detected problem.  Using end-to-end monitoring for this
     purpose is insufficient in that an operator will not be able to localize
     a fault or service degradation accurately.
    </t>
        
    <t>
     A segment monitoring function that can focus on a specific segment of a
     transport path and that can provide a detailed analysis is indispensable
     to promptly and accurately localize the fault.  A function for monitoring
     path segments has been defined to perform this task for MPLS-TP. However,
     as noted in the MPLS-TP OAM Framework <xref target="RFC6371"/>, the
     current method for segment monitoring of a transport path has
     implications that hinder the usage in an operator network.
    </t>
        
    <t>
     After elaborating on the problem statement for the
     path segment monitoring function as it is currently defined, this
     document provides requirements for an on-demand path segment monitoring
     function without traffic disruption. Further works are required to
     evaluate how proposed requirements match with current MPLS architecture
     and to identify possible solutions.
    </t>
        
     </section>
     
     <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      
 <t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
   <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
   appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
       
       <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
         <t>
			<list style="empty">
      
			   
			<t> 
			HPSM - Hitless Path Segment Monitoring
			</t>
         
			<t>
			LSP - Label Switched Path
			</t>
         
			 <t>
			  LSR - Label Switching Router
			 </t>     
         
			 <t>
			  ME - Maintenance Entity
			 </t>
         
			 <t>
			  MEG - Maintenance Entity Group
			 </t>
         
			 <t>
			  MEP - Maintenance Entity Group End Point
			 </t>     
         
			 <t>
			  MIP - Maintenance Entity Group Intermediate Point
			 </t> 
         
			 <t>
			  OTN - Optical Transport Network
			 </t>     
			      
			 <t>
			  TCM - Tandem Connection Monitoring
			 </t>
 
			 <t>
			 SPME - Sub-Path Maintenance Element
			 </t>  
         
			</list> 
         </t>
       </section>
       
       
     </section>
    
    
<section anchor="problem" title="Problem Statement">
<t>A Sub-Path Maintenance Element (SPME) function to monitor (and to protect
and/or manage) MPLS-TP network segments is defined in <xref
target="RFC5921"/>.  The SPME is defined between the edges of the segment of a
transport path that needs to be monitored, protected, or managed. SPME is
created by stacking the shim header (MPLS header), according to <xref
target="RFC3031"/>; it is defined as the segment where the header is
stacked. OAM messages can be initiated at the edge of the SPME. They can be
sent to the peer edge of the SPME or to a MIP along the SPME by setting the
TTL value of the Label Stack Entry (LSE) and interface identifier value at the
corresponding hierarchical LSP level in case of a per-node model.
		  </t>
      
 <t>
			   According to Section 3.8 of <xref
			   target="RFC6371"/>, MPLS-TP segment monitoring
			   should satisfy two network objectives:
			<list style="format (N%d)">
			
<t>
					The monitoring and maintenance of
					current transport paths has to be
					conducted in-service without traffic
					disruption.
				</t>
				
				<t>
					Segment monitoring must not modify the
					forwarding of the segment portion of
					the transport path.  </t></list></t>
					<t> The SPME function that is defined
					in <xref target="RFC5921"/> has the
					following drawbacks:
 
			       	<list style="format (P%d)"><t> It increases
			       	network management complexity, because a new
			       	sub-layer and new MEPs and MIPs have to be
			       	configured for the SPME.
				</t>
				
				 <t>Original conditions of the path change.
				 </t>
				 
				<t>
				  The client traffic over a transport path is disrupted if
				  the SPME is configured on-demand.
				</t>
				
			 </list>
		  
		  </t>
       
		<t>
	           Problem (P1) is related to the management of each
	           additional sub-layer required for segment monitoring in an
	           MPLS-TP network.  When an SPME is applied to administer
	           on-demand OAM functions in MPLS-TP networks, a rule for
	           operationally differentiating those SPMEs will be required
	           at least within an administrative domain. This forces
	           operators to implement at least an additional layer into
	           the management systems that will only be used for on-demand
	           path segment monitoring.  From the perspective of
	           operation, increasing the number of managed layers and
	           managed addresses/identifiers is not desirable in view of
	           keeping the management systems as simple as
	           possible. Moreover, using the currently defined methods,
	           on-demand setting of SPMEs causes problems (P2) and (P3)
	           due to additional label stacking.
		</t>
	      
		<t>

Problem (P2) arises because the MPLS-exposed label value and MPLS frame length
change.  The monitoring function should monitor the status without changing
any condition of the target segment or of the target transport path. Changing
the settings of the original shim header should not be allowed, because this
change corresponds to creating a new segment of the original transport path
that differs from the original one.  When the conditions of the path change,
the measured values or observed data will also change.  This may make the
monitoring meaningless because the result of the measurement would no longer
reflect the performance of the connection where the original fault or
degradation occurred.  As an example, setting up an on-demand SPME will result
in the LSRs within the monitoring segment only looking at the added (stacked)
labels and not at the labels of the original LSP.  This means that problems
stemming from incorrect (or unexpected) treatment of labels of the original
LSP by the nodes within the monitored segment cannot be identified when
setting up SPME.  This might include hardware problems during label lookup,
misconfiguration, etc.  Therefore, operators have to pay extra attention to
correctly setting and checking the label values of the original LSP in the
configuration.  Of course, the reverse of this situation is also possible; for
example, an incorrect or unexpected treatment of SPME labels can result in
false detection of a fault where no problem existed originally.
        </t>
      
		<t><xref target="Figure-1"/> shows an example of SPME settings. In the figure,
 "X" is the label value of the original path expected at the tail end of node
 D.  "210" and "220" are label values allocated for SPME. The label values of
 the original path are modified as are the values of the stacked labels.  As
 shown in <xref target="Figure-1"/>, SPME changes both the length of MPLS
 frames and the label value(s). In particular, performance monitoring
 measurements (e.g., Delay Measurement and Packet Loss Measurement) are
 sensitive to these changes. As an example, increasing the packet length may
 impact packet loss due to MTU settings;  modifying the label stack may introduce packet loss, or it may fix
packet loss depending on the configuration status. Such changes influence packet
 delay, too, even if, from a practical point of view, it is likely that only a
 few services will experience a practical impact.
			</t>
              <t><figure anchor="Figure-1" title="SPME Settings Example">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
 
   (Before SPME settings)
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
     A--100--B--110--C--120--D--130--E  <= transport path
    MEP                             MEP

   (After SPME settings)
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
     A--100--B-----------X---D--130--E  <= transport path
    MEP                             MEP 
              210--C--220               <= SPME
            MEP'          MEP'
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
 <t>
			Problem (P3) can be avoided if the operator sets SPMEs
			in advance and maintains them until the end of life of
			a transport path: but this does not support on-demand.
			Furthermore, SMPEs cannot be set arbitrarily because
			overlapping of path segments is limited to nesting
			relationships.  As a result, possible SPME
			configurations of segments of an original transport
			path are limited due to the characteristic of the SPME
			shown in <xref target="Figure-1"/>, even if SPMEs are
			preconfigured.
		</t>
	  	  
 <t>
       	Although the make-before-break procedure in the survivability document
       	<xref target="RFC6372"/> supports configuration for monitoring
       	according to the framework document <xref target="RFC5921"/>, without
       	traffic disruption the configuration of an SPME is not possible
       	without violating the network objective (N2).  These concerns are
       	described in Section 3.8 of <xref target="RFC6371"/>.
      </t>
      
 <t>
        Additionally, the make-before-break approach typically relies on a
        control plane and requires additional functionalities for a management
        system to properly support SPME creation and traffic switching from
        the original transport path to the SPME.
      </t>
      
 <t>As an example, the old and new transport resources (e.g., LSP tunnels)
 might compete with each other for resources that they have in common.
 Depending on availability of resources, this competition can cause admission
 control to prevent the new LSP tunnel from being established as this
 bandwidth accounting deviates from the traditional (non-control plane)
 management-system operation.  While SPMEs can be applied in any network
 context (single-domain, multi-domain, single-carrier, multi-carrier, etc.),
 the main applications are in inter-carrier or inter-domain segment monitoring
 where they are typically preconfigured or pre-instantiated.  SPME
 instantiates a hierarchical path (introducing MPLS-label stacking) through
 which OAM packets can be sent.  The SPME monitoring function is also mainly
 important for protecting bundles of transport paths and the carriers' carrier
 solutions within an administrative domain.
       </t>
      
 <t> 		
			The analogy for SPME in other transport technologies
			is Tandem Connection Monitoring (TCM). TCM is used in
			Optical Transport Networks (OTNs) and Ethernet
			transport networks.  It supports on-demand but does
			not affect the path.  For example, in OTNs, TCM allows
			the insertion and removal of performance monitoring
			overhead within the frame at intermediate points in
			the network. It is done such that their insertion and
			removal do not change the conditions of the path.
			Though, as the OAM overhead is part of the frame
			(designated overhead bytes), it is constrained to a
			predefined number of monitoring segments.
      </t>
      
      <t>
			To summarize: the problem statement is that the
			current sub-path maintenance based on a hierarchical
			LSP (SPME) is problematic for preconfiguration in
			terms of increasing the number of managed objects by
			layer stacking and identifiers/addresses.  An
			on-demand configuration of SPME is one of the possible
			approaches for minimizing the impact of these issues.
			However, the current procedure is unfavorable because
			the on-demand configuration for monitoring changes the
			condition of the original monitored path.  To avoid or
			minimize the impact of the drawbacks discussed above,
			a more efficient approach is required for the
			operation of an MPLS-TP transport network.  A
			monitoring mechanism, named "Hitless Path Segment
			Monitoring" (HPSM), supporting on-demand path segment
			monitoring without traffic disruption is needed.
      </t>
     

    </section>
    
    
    <section anchor="requirement" title="Requirements for HPSM">
	
   <t>
	   In the following sections, mandatory (M) and optional (O)
	   requirements for the HPSM function are listed.
   </t>
   
    <section anchor="back-comp" title="Backward Compatibility">
  
 <t>
			HPSM would be an additional OAM tool that would not
			replace SPME. As such:

			<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
				<t hangText="(M1)">HPSM MUST be compatible with the usage of SPME.
				</t>
				
				<t hangText="(O1)">HPSM SHOULD be applicable at the SPME layer too.
				</t>
				
				<t hangText="(M2)">HPSM MUST support both the
					per-node and per-interface model as
					specified in <xref target="RFC6371"/>. 
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
	</section>
  
   <section anchor="seg-mon" title="Non-Intrusive Segment Monitoring">
 <t>
		One of the major problems of legacy SPME highlighted in <xref
		target="problem"/> is that it may not monitor the original
		path and it could disrupt service traffic when set up on
		demand.
	   
	      <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
 <t hangText="(M3)">HPSM MUST NOT change the original conditions of the
 transport path (e.g., the length of MPLS frames, the exposed label values,
 etc.).
			</t>
		
 <t hangText="(M4)">HPSM MUST support on-demand provisioning without traffic
 disruption.
			</t>
		
         </list>

	</t>
    </section>
	  	   
	   
	<section anchor="multi" title="Monitoring Multiple Segments">
 <t>
			Along a transport path, there may be the need to
			support monitoring multiple segments simultaneously.
	   
			 <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
 <t hangText="(M5)">HPSM MUST support configuration of multiple monitoring
 segments along a transport path.
				</t>
			</list>		
		</t>	
		
		<t>	<figure anchor="Figure-2" title="Multiple HPSM Instances Example"> <artwork><![CDATA[
   ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
  |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
  | A |   | B |   | C |   | D |   | E |
   ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   MEP                              MEP <= ME of a transport path
    *------* *----*  *--------------* <=three HPSM monit. instances
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

 
    </section>
   
	   
   <section anchor="multi-level" title="Monitoring Single and Multiple Levels">
  
	   <t>
		  HPSM would apply mainly for on-demand diagnostic purposes.
		  With the currently defined approach, the most serious
		  problem is that there is no way to locate the degraded
		  segment of a path without changing the conditions of the
		  original path.  Therefore, as a first step, a single-level,
		  single-segment monitoring not affecting the monitored path
		  is required for HPSM. Monitoring simultaneous segments on
		  multiple levels is the most powerful tool for accurately
		  diagnosing the performance of a transport path. However, in
		  the field, a single- level, multiple-segment approach would be less complex for
		  management and operations.
	   
   
			<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
				<t hangText="(M6)">HPSM MUST support single-level segment monitoring.  
				</t>
				
				<t hangText="(O2)">HPSM MAY support multi-level segment monitoring. 
				</t>
				
			</list>
		</t>

   	<t> 
		<figure anchor="Figure-3" title="Multi-Level HPSM Example"> <artwork><![CDATA[
   ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
  |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
  | A |   | B |   | C |   | D |   | E |
   ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   MEP                             MEP <= ME of a transport path
           *-----------------*         <=On-demand HPSM level 1
             *-------------*           <=On-demand HPSM level 2
                   *-*                 <=On-demand HPSM level 3

      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

   </section>
   
   <section anchor="pro-active" title="HPSM and End-to-End Proactive Monitoring Independence">
    
 <t>There is a need for simultaneously using existing end-to-end proactive
 monitoring and on-demand path segment monitoring.  Normally, the on-demand
 path segment monitoring is configured on a segment of a maintenance entity of
 a transport path.  In such an environment, on-demand single-level monitoring
 should be performed without disrupting the proactive monitoring of the
 targeted end-to-end transport path to avoid affecting monitoring of user
 traffic performance.
    </t>
   
   <t>
	<list style="empty">
 <t>(M7) HPSM MUST support the capability of being operated concurrently to,
 and independently of, the OAM function on the end-to-end path.
		</t>
      
    </list>   
   </t>
    
         <t><figure anchor="Figure-4" title="Independence between Proactive End-to-End Monitoring and On-Demand HPSM">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
 |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
 | A |   | B |   | C |   | D |   | E |
  ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
  MEP                             MEP <= ME of a transport path
    +-----------------------------+   <= Proactive end-to-end mon.
          *------------------*        <= On-demand HPSM
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>  
   </section>
 
   <section anchor="arbitrary" title="Monitoring an Arbitrary Segment">
 <t>The main objective for on-demand path segment monitoring is to diagnose the
 fault locations.  A possible realistic diagnostic procedure is to fix one
 endpoint of a segment at the MEP of the transport path under observation and
 progressively change the length of the segments. It is, therefore, possible
 to monitor all the paths, step-by-step, with a granularity that depends on
 equipment implementations.  For example, <xref target="Figure-5"/> shows the
 case where the granularity is at the interface level (i.e., monitoring is at
 each input interface and output interface of each piece of equipment).

   </t>
       
    <t><figure anchor="Figure-5" title="Localization of a Defect by
					Consecutive On-Demand Path Segment Monitoring Procedure">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
   | A |   | B |   | C |   | D |   | E |
    ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
    MEP                             MEP <= ME of a transport path
      +-----------------------------+   <= Proactive end-to-end mon.
      *-----*                           <= 1st on-demand HPSM
      *-------*                         <= 2nd on-demand HPSM
           |                                |
           |                                |
      *-----------------------*         <= 4th on-demand HPSM
      *-----------------------------*   <= 5th on-demand HPSM
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>  
 <t>Another possible scenario is depicted in <xref target="Figure-6"/>.  In
 this case, the operator wants to diagnose a transport path starting at a
 transit node because the end nodes (A and E) are located at customer sites
 and consist of small boxes supporting only a subset of OAM functions.  In
 this case, where the source entities of the diagnostic packets are limited to
 the position of MEPs, on-demand path segment monitoring will be ineffective
 because not all the segments can be diagnosed (e.g., segment monitoring HPSM
 3 in <xref target="Figure-6"/> is not available, and it is not possible to
 determine the fault location exactly).
   </t>
   
   <t>
	<list style="empty">
 <t>(M8) It SHALL be possible to provision HPSM on an arbitrary segment of a
 transport path.
		</t>
    </list>   
   </t>
   
   <t><figure anchor="Figure-6" title="HPSM Configuration at Arbitrary Segments">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
           ---     ---     ---
   ---    |   |   |   |   |   |    ---
  | A |   | B |   | C |   | D |   | E |
   ---     ---     ---     ---     ---
   MEP                             MEP <= ME of a transport path
     +-----------------------------+   <= Proactive end-to-end mon.
     *-----*                           <= On-demand HPSM 1
           *-----------------------*   <= On-demand HPSM 2
           *---------*                 <= On-demand HPSM 3
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>  
   
   </section>
   
   <section anchor="fault" title="Fault while HPSM Is Operational">
 <t>Node or link failures may occur while HPSM is active.  In this case, if no
 resiliency mechanism is set up on the subtended transport path, there is no
 particular requirement for HPSM.  If the transport path is protected, the
 HPSM function may monitor unintended segments.  The following
 examples are provided for clarification.

   </t>
 <t>Protection scenario A is shown in <xref target="Figure-7"/>.  In this
 scenario, a working LSP and a protection LSP are set up.  HPSM is activated
 between nodes A and E.  When a fault occurs between nodes B and C, the
 operation of HPSM is not affected by the protection switch and continues on
 the active LSP.
   </t>   
            <t><figure anchor="Figure-7" title="Protection Scenario A">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
   A - B - C - D - E - F
     \               /
       G - H - I - L

   Where:
   - end-to-end LSP: A-B-C-D-E-F
   - working LSP:    A-B-C-D-E-F
   - protection LSP: A-G-H-I-L-F
   - HPSM:           A-E
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>  
 <t>
	   Protection scenario B is shown in <xref target="Figure-8"/>.  The
	   difference with scenario A is that only a portion of the transport
	   path is protected.  In this case, when a fault occurs between nodes
	   B and C on the working sub-path B-C-D, traffic will be switched to
	   protection sub- path B-G-H-D.  Assuming that OAM packet termination
	   depends only on the TTL value of the MPLS label header, the target
	   node of the HPSM changes from E to D due to the difference of hop
	   counts between the working path route (A-B-C-D-E: 4 hops) and
	   protection path route (A-B-G-H-D-E: 5 hops). In this case, the
	   operation of HPSM is affected.
   </t>   
                  <t><figure anchor="Figure-8" title="Protection Scenario B ">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
       A - B - C - D - E - F
             \     /
              G - H

   - end-to-end LSP:      A-B-C-D-E-F
   - working sub-path:    B-C-D
   - protection sub-path: B-G-H-D
   - HPSM:                A-E
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>  
  <t>
   	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
        <t hangText="(M9)">The HPSM SHOULD avoid monitoring an unintended
		  segment when one or more failures occur.
		</t>
    </list>   
 </t>

 <t> There are potentially different solutions to satisfy such a requirement.
 A possible solution may be to suspend HPSM monitoring until network
 restoration takes place.  Another possible approach may be to compare the
 node/interface ID in the OAM packet with that at the node reached at TTL
 termination and, if this does not match, a suspension of HPSM monitoring
 should be triggered. The above approaches are valid in any circumstance, both
 for protected and unprotected networks LSPs.  These examples should not be
 taken to limit the design of a solution.
   </t>
		  
		  
   </section>

   <section anchor="manage" title="HPSM Manageability">
 <t>
       From a managing perspective, increasing the number of managed layers
       and managed addresses/identifiers is not desirable in view of keeping
       the management systems as simple as possible.
   </t>
   
   <t>
      	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
			<t hangText="(M10)">HPSM SHOULD NOT be based on additional transport layers (e.g., hierarchical LSPs).
			</t>
         
 <t hangText="(M11)">The same identifiers used for MIPs and/or MEPs SHOULD be
 applied to maintenance points for the HPSM when they are instantiated in the
 same place along a transport path.
			</t>

 <t>Maintenance points for the HPSM may be different from the functional
 components of MIPs and MEPs as defined in the OAM framework document <xref
 target="RFC6371"/>. Investigating potential solutions for satisfying HPSM
 requirements may lead to identifying new functional components; these
 components need to be backward compatible with MPLS architecture.  Solutions
 are outside the scope of this document.
			</t>
        </list>   
    </t>
   
   </section>      
   
   <section anchor="point" title="Supported OAM Functions">
 <t>
	   A maintenance point supporting the HPSM function has to be able to
	   generate and inject OAM packets. OAM functions that may be
	   applicable for on-demand HPSM are basically the on-demand
	   performance monitoring functions that are defined in the OAM
	   framework document <xref target="RFC6371"/>.  The "on-demand"
	   attribute is typically temporary for maintenance operation.
   </t>
   
   <t>
      	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
			<t hangText="(M12)">HPSM MUST support Packet Loss and Packet Delay measurement.
			</t>
        </list> 
		
	</t>
	
 <t>These functions are normally only supported at the endpoints of a
 transport path.  If a defect occurs, it might be quite hard to locate the
 defect or degradation point without using the segment monitoring function.
 If an operator cannot locate or narrow down the cause of the fault, it is
 quite difficult to take prompt actions to solve the problem.
	</t>
	
 <t>
	   Other on-demand monitoring functions (e.g., Delay Variation
	   measurement) are desirable but not as necessary as the functions
	   mentioned above.
	</t>
	
	<t>
	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
 <t hangText="(O3)">HPSM MAY support Packet Delay variation, Throughput
 measurement, and other performance monitoring and fault management functions.
		</t>
    </list> 
	</t>	
 <t>   
	Support of out-of-service on-demand performance-management functions
	(e.g., Throughput measurement) is not required for HPSM.
    	</t>

   </section>      
   </section>
   
   <section anchor="summary" title="Summary">
   
 <t>
	A new HPSM mechanism is required to provide on-demand path segment
	monitoring without traffic disruption.  It shall meet the two network
	objectives described in Section 3.8 of <xref target="RFC6371"/> and
	summarized in <xref target="problem"/> of this document.
 
   </t>
   
 <t>
	   The mechanism should minimize the problems described in <xref
	   target="problem"/>, i.e., (P1), (P2), and (P3).
   </t>
   
 <t>
		The solution for the on-demand path segment monitoring without
		traffic disruption needs to cover both the per-node model and
		the per-interface model specified in <xref target="RFC6371"/>.
 
   </t>
   
 <t>
		The on-demand path segment monitoring without traffic disruption
		solution needs to support on-demand Packet Loss Measurement
		and Packet Delay Measurement functions and optionally other
		performance monitoring and fault management functions (e.g.,
		Throughput measurement, Packet Delay variation measurement,
		Diagnostic test, etc.).
  
   </t>
   
   </section>
   
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    
 <t>
	Security is a significant requirement of the MPLS Transport Profile.
	This document provides a problem statement and requirements to guide
	the development of new OAM tools to support HPSM. Such new tools must
	follow the security considerations provided in OAM Requirements for
	MPLS-TP in <xref target="RFC5860"/>.
    </t>
    
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
    <t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
    
    </section>    
	
    
  </middle>

  <back>
 
    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3031"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5860"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
      
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">  
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5921"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6371"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6372"?>
      
    </references>
	<section anchor="contribute" title="Contributors" numbered="no">
    
    <t>Manuel Paul
<vspace blankLines="0" />Deutsche Telekom  AG
<vspace blankLines="0" />
	</t>
	<t>Email: manuel.paul@telekom.de
     </t>
    
       
    </section>   
	
	
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
  
   <t>
   The authors would also like to thank Alexander Vainshtein, Dave
   Allan, Fei Zhang, Huub van Helvoort, Malcolm Betts, Italo Busi,
   Maarten Vissers, Jia He, and Nurit Sprecher for their comments and
   enhancements to the text.
   </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
