<?xml version='1.0' encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="no" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="8457"
     category="std"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev='IMAP "Important" Keyword and Attribute'>
      IMAP "$Important" Keyword and "\Important" Special-Use Attribute
    </title>

    <author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='Barry Leiba' role='editor'>
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 646 827 0648</phone>
        <email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
        <uri>http://internetmessagingtechnology.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="September" year="2018"/>
    <area>ART</area>
    <keyword>IMAP attributes</keyword>

    <abstract><t>
      RFC 6154 created an IMAP special-use LIST extension and defined an
      initial set of attributes.  This document defines a new attribute,
      "\Important", and establishes a new IANA registry for IMAP folder
      attributes, which include the attributes defined in RFCs 5258, 3501, and 6154.
      This document also defines a new IMAP keyword, "$Important", and registers it in the registry
      defined in RFC 5788.
    </t></abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        The Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) specification <xref target="RFC3501"/> defines the use of message keywords, and an "IMAP Keywords" registry is created in <xref target="RFC5788"/>.  <xref target="RFC6154"/> defines an extension to the IMAP LIST command for special-use mailboxes.  The extension allows servers to provide extra information (attributes) about the purpose of a mailbox and defines an initial set of special-use attributes.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does the following:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            defines a new message keyword, "$Important", to apply to messages that are considered important for the user by some externally defined criteria;
          </t>
          <t>
            registers the "$Important" keyword in the "IMAP Keywords" registry;
          </t>
          <t>
            defines a new special-use attribute, "\Important", to designate a
	    mailbox that will hold messages that are considered important for
	    the user by some externally defined criteria; and 
          </t>
          <t>
            creates a registry for IMAP mailbox attributes and registers the new attribute and those defined in <xref target="RFC5258"/>, <xref target="RFC3501"/>, and <xref target="RFC6154"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>
          In the examples used in this document, "C:" indicates lines sent by a client that is connected
          to a server, and "S:" indicates lines sent by the server to the client.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ImpKwd" title='Definition of the "$Important" Message Keyword'>
      <t>
        The "$Important" keyword is a signal that a message is likely
        important to the user.  The keyword is generally expected to be set
        automatically by the system based on available signals (such as who
        the message is from, who else the message is addressed to, evaluation
        of the subject or content, or other heuristics).  While the keyword also
        can be set by the user, that is not expected to be the primary usage.
      </t>
      <t>
        This is distinct from the "\Flagged" system flag in two ways:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            "$Important" carries a meaning of general importance, as
            opposed to follow-up or urgency.  It is meant to be used for a form of
            triage, with "\Flagged" remaining as a designation of special attention,
            need for follow-up, or time sensitivity.  In particular, the sense of
            "$Important" is that other messages that are "like this one" according to
            some server-applied heuristics will also be considered "$Important".
          </t>
          <t>
            The setting of "$Important" is expected to be based at least
            partly on heuristics (generally set automatically by the server), whereas
            "\Flagged" is only intended to be set by the user with some sort of
            "flag this message" or "put a star on this message" interface.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definition of the 'Important' Mailbox Attribute">
      <t>
        The "\Important" mailbox attribute is a signal that the mailbox
	contains messages that are likely important to the user.  In an
	implementation that also supports the "$Important" keyword, this
	special use is likely to represent a virtual mailbox collecting
	messages (from other mailboxes) that are marked with the "$Important"
	keyword.  In other implementations, the system might automatically put
	messages there based on the same sorts of heuristics that are noted
	for the "$Important" keyword (see <xref target="ImpKwd"/>).  

The distinctions between "\Important" and "\Flagged" for mailboxes are similar to those between "$Important" and "\Flagged" for messages.
      </t>
      <section title="Formal Syntax">
        <t>
          The following syntax specification adds to the one in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC6154"/> using Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) as described in <xref target="RFC5234" />.
          Be sure to see the ABNF notes at the beginning of Section 9 of <xref target="RFC3501"/>.
          <figure><artwork>
    use-attr      =/  "\Important"
          </artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examples">
        <section title="Example of a LIST Response">
          <t>
            In the following example, the mailbox called "Important Messages" is the one designated with the "\Important" attribute.
            <figure><artwork>
   C: t1 LIST "" "Imp*"
   S: * LIST (\HasNoChildren \Important) "/" "Important Messages"
   S: * LIST (\HasNoChildren) "/" "Imported Wine"
   S: t1 OK Success
            </artwork></figure>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title='Examples of Creating a New Mailbox Using "\Important"'>
          <t>
            In the following example, the mailbox called "Important Messages" is created
            with the "\Important" attribute on a server that advertises the
            "CREATE-SPECIAL-USE" capability string.
            <figure><artwork>
   C: t1 CREATE "Important Messages" (USE (\Important))
   S: t1 OK Mailbox created
            </artwork></figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            The following example is similar to the previous one, but the server is
            not able to assign the "\Important" attribute to the new mailbox.
            <figure><artwork>
   C: t1 CREATE "Important Messages" (USE (\Important))
   S: t1 NO [USEATTR] An \Important mailbox already exists
            </artwork></figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            The following example is similar to the previous one, but the server does not
            support this extension.
            <figure><artwork>
   C: t1 CREATE "Important Messages" (USE (\Important))
   S: t1 NO [USEATTR] Mailbox not created; unsupported use \Important
            </artwork></figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            In both of the failure-mode examples, the "USEATTR" response code lets the
            client know that the problem is in the "USE" parameters.
            Note that the same response code is given in both cases, and
            the human-readable text is the only way to tell the difference.
            That text is not parsable by the client (it can only be logged and/or reported
            to the user).
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="impl" title="Implementation Notes">
      <t>
        This section is non-normative and is intended to describe the intended (and current as of
        this publication) usage of "$Important" in contrast with "\Flagged" on a message.
      </t>
      <t>
        On the server:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            "\Flagged" is set or cleared in response to an explicit command from the client.
          </t>
          <t>
            "$Important" is set via a heuristic process performed by the server
	    and usually involves analysis of header fields, what mailbox the message
            is filed in, perhaps message content, attachments, and such.  It may
            then be set or cleared in response to an explicit command from the
            client, and the server may use that to adjust the heuristics in the
            future.  It's also possible that the server will re-evaluate this and
            make a message "$Important" later if the user accesses the message
            frequently, for example.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        On the client:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Typically, an icon such as a flag or a star (or an indication, such
            as red or bold text) is associated with "\Flagged", and the UI provides
            a way for the user to turn that icon or indication on or off.
            Manipulation of this results in a command to the server.
          </t>
          <t>
            Typically, a lesser indication is used for "$Important".  The client
            might or might not provide the user with a way to manipulate it.  If
            it does, manipulation results in a command to the server.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations in Section 7 of <xref target="RFC6154"/> apply equally to this extension, in particular, "Conveying special-use information to a client exposes a small bit of extra information that could be of value to an attacker."  Moreover, identifying important messages or a place where important messages are kept could give an attacker a strategic starting point.  If the algorithm by which messages are determined to be important is well known, still more information is exposed -- perhaps, for example, there is an implication that the senders of these messages are particularly significant to the mailbox owner, and perhaps that is information that should not be made public.
      </t>
      <t>
        As noted in RFC 6154, it is wise to protect the IMAP channel from
	passive eavesdropping and to defend against unauthorized discernment
	of the identity of a user's "\Important" mailbox or of a user's
	"$Important" messages.  See Section 11 of <xref target="RFC3501"/> for
        security considerations about using the IMAP STARTTLS command to protect the IMAP channel.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        IANA has completed three actions, which are specified in the sections below:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            registration of the "$Important" keyword;
          </t>
          <t>
            creation of a new "IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes" registry; and
          </t>
          <t>
            registration of initial entries in the "IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes" registry.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title='Registration of the "$Important" Keyword'>
        <t>
          IANA has registered the "$Important" keyword in the "IMAP Keywords" registry, as follows, using the template in <xref target="RFC5788"/>.
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
            <t hangText="IMAP keyword name:">
              $Important
            </t>
            <t hangText="Purpose (description):">
              The "$Important" keyword is a signal that a message is likely important to the user.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Private or Shared on a server:">
              PRIVATE
            </t>
            <t hangText="Is it an advisory keyword or may it cause an automatic action:">
              <vspace/>
              Advisory (but see the reference for details).
            </t>
            <t hangText="When/by whom the keyword is set/cleared:">
              The keyword can be set by the user, or automatically by the system based on available signals (such as who the message is from, who else the message is addressed to, evaluation of the subject or content, or other heuristics).
            </t>
            <t hangText="Related keywords:">
              None (see the reference for the related mailbox name attribute).
            </t>
            <t hangText="Related IMAP capabilities:">
              None.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Security considerations:">
              See <xref target="sec"/> of RFC 8457.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Published specification:">
              RFC 8457
            </t>
            <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">
              <vspace/>
              IETF Applications and Real-Time Area &lt;art@ietf.org&gt;
            </t>
            <t hangText="Intended usage:">
              COMMON
            </t>
            <t hangText="Owner/Change controller:">
              IESG
            </t>
            <t hangText="Note:">
              None.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Creation of the IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes Registry">
        <t>
          IANA has created a new registry in the group "Internet
	  Message Access Protocol (IMAP)".  It is called
	  "IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes", and it has two references:
	  "RFC 3501, Section 7.2.2", and "RFC 8457, Section 6".
          This registry will be shared with the JSON Meta Application Protocol (JMAP) for Mail
          <xref target="JMAP-MAIL"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The registry entries contain the following fields:
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Attribute Name</t>
            <t>Description</t>
            <t>Reference</t>
            <t>Usage Notes</t>
          </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA keeps this list in alphabetical order by Attribute Name, which is registered without the initial backslash ("\").  The names are generally registered with initial
          capital letters but are treated as case-insensitive US-ASCII strings.
        </t>
        <t>
          The "Usage Notes" field is free-form US-ASCII text that will normally be empty
          (and is empty if it's not specified in the registration request).
          It is intended to hold things such as "not used by JMAP" and "JMAP only".
          The field is for human use, and there is no need for a registry of strings that
          may appear here.  
        </t>

        <t>
          The registration policy for the new registry is listed as "IETF Review" or "Expert Review" <xref target="RFC8126"/>, and new registrations will be accepted in one of two ways:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              For registrations requested in an IETF consensus document, the
	      registration policy will be IETF Review, and the request will be
	      made in the IANA Considerations section of the document, which gives the requested values for each of the fields.
            </t>
            <t>
              For other registrations, the policy will be Expert Review policy (see <xref target="DEinst"/>), and the request will be made by sending email to IANA asking for a new IMAP Mailbox Name Attribute and giving the requested values for each of the fields.
              While a formal specification is not required, the reference document should provide
              a description of the proposed attribute sufficient for building interoperable
              implementations.  

An Informational RFC (submitted, for example, through the IETF or Independent stream) is a fine way to publish a reference document
              (see also <xref target="DEinst"/>).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <section anchor="DEinst" title="Instructions to the Designated Expert">
          <t>
            The expert reviewer, who will be designated by the IESG, is
	    expected to provide only a general review of the requested
	    registration, checking that the reference and description are
	    adequate for understanding the intent of the registered attribute.
	    Efforts should also be made to generalize the intent of an
	    attribute so that multiple implementations with the same
	    requirements may reuse existing attributes.  Except for this
	    check, this is intended to be very close to a
	    first come first served policy, and the expert should not block
	    serious registration requests with a reasonable reference.  The
	    reference may be to any form of documentation, including a web
	    page, but consideration should be given to providing one that is
	    expected to be long-lived and stable.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Initial Entries for the IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes Registry">
        <t>The registry initially contains these entries:
        <figure><artwork>
+===============+===================================+===========+
| Attribute     | Description                       | Reference |
| Name          |                                   |           |
+===============+===================================+===========+
| All           | All messages                      | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Archive       | Archived messages                 | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Drafts        | Messages that are working drafts  | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Flagged       | Messages with the \Flagged flag   | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| HasChildren   | Has accessible child mailboxes    | [RFC5258] | *
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| HasNoChildren | Has no accessible child mailboxes | [RFC5258] | *
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Important     | Messages deemed important to user |  RFC 8457 |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Junk          | Messages identified as Spam/Junk  | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Marked        | Server has marked the mailbox as  | [RFC3501] | *
|               | "interesting"                     |           |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| NoInferiors   | No hierarchy under this name      | [RFC3501] | *
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| NonExistent   | The mailbox name doesn't actually | [RFC5258] | *
|               | exist                             |           |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Noselect      | The mailbox is not selectable     | [RFC3501] | *
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Remote        | The mailbox exists on a remote    | [RFC5258] | *
|               | server                            |           |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Sent          | Sent mail                         | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Subscribed    | The mailbox is subscribed to      | [RFC5258] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Trash         | Messages the user has discarded   | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Unmarked      | No new messages since last select | [RFC3501] | *
+===============+===================================+===========+
        </artwork></figure>
          The rows marked with "*" at the end have their Usage Notes field
          set to "not used by JMAP".
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3501" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6154" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126" ?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5258" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5788" ?>

<!--draft-ietf-jmap-mail-07: I-D Exists -->
<reference anchor='JMAP-MAIL'>
<front>
<title>JMAP for Mail</title>

<author initials='N' surname='Jenkins' fullname='Neil Jenkins'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Newman' fullname='Chris Newman'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='August' year='2018' />

<abstract><t>This document specifies a data model for synchronising email data with a server using JMAP.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-jmap-mail-07' />

</reference>
    </references>

<section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
<t>The following author was an original contributor to this document in
addition to the editor.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
Eric "Iceman"
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
Google
<vspace blankLines="0"/>
Email: iceman@google.com
</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
