<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2328 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5340 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5340.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6987 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6987.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4203 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4203.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4915 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4915.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7684 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7684.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8042 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8042.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7752 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7752.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6845 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6845.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4577 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4577.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5817 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5817.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5329 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5329.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4552 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3630 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"> 
<!ENTITY RFC8362 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8362.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" number="8379" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
<front>
<title abbrev="OSPF Graceful Link Shutdown">OSPF Graceful Link Shutdown</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Hegde" fullname="Shraddha Hegde">
<organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Embassy Business Park</street>
<city>Bangalore</city>
<region>KA</region>
<code>560093</code>
<country>India</country>
</postal>
<email>shraddha@juniper.net</email>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Sarkar" fullname="Pushpasis Sarkar">
<organization>Arrcus, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>pushpasis.ietf@gmail.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<author fullname="Hannes Gredler" initials="H." surname="Gredler">
<organization>RtBrick Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>hannes@rtbrick.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<author fullname="Mohan Nanduri" initials="M." surname="Nanduri">
<organization>ebay Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2025 Hamilton Avenue</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>98052</code>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
<email>mnanduri@ebay.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<author fullname="Luay Jalil" initials="L." surname="Jalil">
<organization>Verizon</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>luay.jalil@verizon.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<date month="April" year="2018"/>

<area>Routing</area>
<workgroup>Open Shortest Path First IGP</workgroup>
<keyword>MPLS</keyword>
<keyword>IGP</keyword>
<keyword>OSPF</keyword>

<abstract>
<t> When a link is being prepared to be taken out of service, the traffic
needs to be diverted from both ends of the link. 
 Increasing the metric to the highest value on one side of the link
is not sufficient to divert the traffic flowing in the other direction.</t> 

<t>It is useful for the routers in an OSPFv2 or OSPFv3 routing domain to be able to
advertise a link as being in a graceful-shutdown state to indicate impending
maintenance activity on the link. This information can be used by the network
devices to reroute the traffic effectively. 
 </t>
<t>This document describes the protocol extensions to disseminate
graceful-link-shutdown information in OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.</t>
</abstract>

</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction" anchor='intro'>

<t>This document describes a mechanism for gracefully taking a link out of service 
while allowing it to be used if no other path is available. It also provides a
mechanism to divert the traffic from both directions of the link.
 </t>

<t>Many OSPFv2 or OSPFv3 deployments run on overlay networks provisioned by
means of pseudowires or L2 circuits. Prior to devices in the underlying
network going offline for maintenance, it is useful to divert the traffic away
from the node before maintenance is actually performed. Since the nodes in
the underlying network are not visible to OSPF, the existing stub-router
mechanism described in <xref target="RFC6987"/> cannot be used.  
In a service provider's network, there may be many CE-to-CE connections that
run over a single PE.  It is cumbersome to change the metric
on every CE-to-CE connection in both directions. This document provides a
mechanism to change the metric of the link on the remote side and also use the
link as a last-resort link if no alternate paths are available. An application
specific to this use case is described in detail in <xref
target="overlay_network"/>.</t> 


 <t>
This document provides mechanisms to advertise graceful-link-shutdown state in
the flexible encodings provided by
"OSPFv2 Prefix/Link Attribute Advertisement" <xref target="RFC7684"/> and the
E-Router-LSA <xref target="RFC8362"/> for OSPFv3. 
Throughout this document, OSPF is used when the text applies to both
OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.  OSPFv2 or OSPFv3 is used when the text is
specific to one version of the OSPF protocol.
</t>


<section title="Requirements Language">
<t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" /> <xref target="RFC8174" />
      when, and only when, they 
      appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Motivation" anchor='Motivation'>

<t>The motivation of this document is to reduce manual intervention during
maintenance activities. The following objectives help to accomplish this in a
range of deployment scenarios.</t> 
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t> Advertise impending maintenance activity so that traffic from both directions 
can be diverted away from the link.</t>
<t> Allow the solution to be backward compatible so that nodes that do not
understand the new advertisement do not cause routing loops.</t>

<t> Advertise the maintenance activity to other nodes in the network so that
Label Switched Path (LSP) ingress routers/controllers can learn about the
impending maintenance activity and apply specific policies to reroute the LSPs
for deployments based on Traffic Engineering (TE).</t> 

<t> Allow the link to be used as a last-resort link to prevent traffic
disruption when alternate paths are not available.</t> 

</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title='Flooding Scope'>
<t>The graceful-link-shutdown information is flooded in an area-scoped
Extended Link Opaque LSA <xref target='RFC7684'/> for OSPFv2 and in an
E-Router-LSA for OSPFv3 <xref target="RFC8362"/>. The Graceful-Link-Shutdown
sub-TLV MAY be processed by the head-end nodes or the controller as described
in the <xref target="applications"/>. The procedures for processing the
Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV are described in <xref target="procedures"/>. 
 </t>

</section>

<section title='Protocol Extensions' anchor='protocol-sub-tlvs'>

<section title='OSPFv2 Graceful-Link-Shutdown Sub-TLV'> 
<t>The Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV identifies the link as being gracefully
shutdown. It is advertised in the Extended Link TLV  of the Extended Link
Opaque LSA as defined in <xref target='RFC7684'/>.

<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="OSPFv2-graceful-link-shutdown-sub-TLV" title="Graceful-Link-Shutdown Sub-TLV for OSPFv2">
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |              Type             |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines="1" />

Type: 7 
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: 0
<vspace blankLines="1" />

<vspace blankLines="1" />
</t>
</section>

<section title='Remote IPv4 Address Sub-TLV' anchor='remote-ipv4-addr'>

<t>This sub-TLV specifies the IPv4 address of the remote endpoint on the
link. It is advertised in the Extended Link TLV as defined in <xref
target='RFC7684'/>. This sub-TLV is optional and MAY be advertised in an
area-scoped Extended Link Opaque LSA to identify the link when there are
multiple parallel links between two nodes.  

<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="remote-ipv4-addr-sub-tlv" title="Remote IPv4 Address Sub-TLV">
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |              Type             |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                     Remote IPv4 Address                       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines="1" />

Type: 8
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: 4
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Value: Remote IPv4 address. The remote IPv4 address is used to identify a
particular link on the remote side when there are 
multiple parallel links between two nodes.
<vspace blankLines="1" />
</t>
</section>

<section title='Local/Remote Interface ID Sub-TLV' anchor='local-remote-interface-id'>


<t>This sub-TLV specifies Local and Remote Interface IDs. It is advertised in
the Extended Link TLV as defined in <xref target='RFC7684'/>. This sub-TLV is
optional and MAY be advertised in an area-scoped Extended Link Opaque LSA 
to identify the link when there are multiple parallel unnumbered links between two nodes. 
The Local Interface ID is generally readily available.
One of the mechanisms to obtain the Remote Interface ID is described in <xref target='RFC4203'/>.

<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="local-remote-interface-id-sub-tlv" title="Local/Remote Interface ID Sub-TLV">
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |              Type             |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                     Local Interface ID                        |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                     Remote Interface ID                       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines="1" />

Type: 9
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: 8
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Value: 4 octets of the Local Interface ID followed by 4 octets of the Remote Interface ID.
<vspace blankLines="1" />
</t>
</section>

<section title='OSPFv3 Graceful-Link-Shutdown Sub-TLV'>
<t> 
The Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV is carried in the Router-Link TLV as
defined in <xref target="RFC8362"/> for OSPFv3. The Router-Link TLV contains
the Neighbor Interface ID and can uniquely identify the link on the remote
node. 

<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="OSPFv3-graceful-link-shutdown-TLV" title="Graceful-Link-Shutdown Sub-TLV for OSPFv3">
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |              Type             |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
</artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Type: 8
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: 0
</t>
</section>


<section title='BGP-LS Graceful-Link-Shutdown TLV'>
<t>BGP-LS as defined in <xref target="RFC7752"/> is a mechanism that distributes
network information to the 
external entities using the BGP routing protocol. Graceful link shutdown is
important link information that the external entities  
can use for various use cases as defined in <xref target="applications"/>. BGP
Link Network Layer Reachability Information (NLRI) is used to carry the link
information. 
A new TLV called "Graceful-Link-Shutdown" is defined to describe the link
attribute corresponding to graceful-link-shutdown state. 
The TLV format is as described in Section 3.1 of <xref
target="RFC7752"/>. There is no Value field, and the Length field is set to
zero for this TLV. 

<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="BGPLS-graceful-link-shutdown-TLV" title="Graceful-Link-Shutdown TLV for BGP-LS">
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |              Type             |             Length            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
</artwork>
</figure>
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Type: 1121
<vspace blankLines="1" />
Length: 0
</t>

</section>

<section title='Distinguishing Parallel Links'>
<t> 
<vspace blankLines="2" />
<figure anchor="parallel_links" title="Parallel Links">
<artwork>
    
                 ++++++++++I.w            I.y+++++++++++
                 |Router A|------------------|Router B | 
                 |        |------------------|         |
                 ++++++++++I.x            I.z+++++++++++
</artwork>
</figure>

Consider two routers, A and B, connected with two parallel
point&nbhy;to&nbhy;point interfaces. I.w and I.x represent the interface
address on Router A's side, and I.y and I.z represent interface addresses on
Router B's side.  

The Extended Link Opaque LSA as defined in <xref target="RFC7684"/>
describes links using Link Type, Link ID, and Link Data. For example, a link
with the address I.w is described as below on Router A. 
<list>
<t>Link Type = Point-to-point</t>
<t>Link ID = Router ID of B</t>
<t>Link Data = I.w</t>
</list>

A third node (controller or head-end) in the network cannot distinguish the
interface on Router B, which is connected to this particular Interface on Router A based on the link
information described above. The interface with address  I.y or I.z could be chosen
due to this ambiguity. In such cases, a Remote IPv4 Address sub-TLV should be
originated and added to the Extended Link TLV. The use cases as described in
<xref target="applications"/> require controller or head-end nodes to
interpret the graceful&nbhy;link&nbhy;shutdown information and hence the need
for the Remote IPv4 Address sub-TLV. I.y is carried in the Extended Link TLV,
which unambiguously identifies the interface on the remote side. The OSPFv3
Router-Link TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8362"/> contains an Interface
ID and a neighbor's Interface ID, which can uniquely identify connecting the
interface on the remote side; hence, OSPFv3 does not require a separate remote
IPv6 address to be advertised along with the OSPFv3 Graceful-Link-Shutdown
sub-TLV. 
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title='Elements of Procedure' anchor='procedures'>
<t>As defined in  <xref target="RFC7684"/>, every link on the node will have a
separate Extended Link Opaque LSA. 

 The node that has the link to be taken out of service 
MUST advertise the Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV in the Extended Link TLV of the
Extended Link Opaque LSA for OSPFv2, as defined in <xref target="RFC7684"/>,
and in the Router-Link TLV of E-Router-LSA for OSPFv3. 
The Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV indicates that the link identified by the
 sub-TLV is subjected to maintenance.</t>
 
<t>For the purposes of changing the metric OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 Router-LSAs need
to be reoriginated.  To change the Traffic Engineering metric, TE Opaque LSAs in OSPFv2 <xref
target="RFC3630"/> and Intra-area-TE-LSAs in OSPFv3 <xref target="RFC5329"/> need to be reoriginated.</t> 

<t>The graceful-link-shutdown information is advertised as a property of the
link and is flooded through the area. This information can be used by ingress
routers or controllers to take special actions. An application specific to
this use case is described in  <xref target="controller_TE"/>.</t> 

<t> When a link is ready to carry traffic, the Graceful-Link-Shutdown
sub&nbhy;TLV MUST be removed from the Extended Link TLV/Router-Link TLV, and
the corresponding LSAs MUST be readvertised. Similarly, the metric MUST be set
to original values, and the corresponding LSAs MUST be readvertised.</t>

 <t> The procedures described in this document may be used to divert the
 traffic away from the link in scenarios other than link-shutdown or
 link-replacement activity.</t>  

<t>The precise action taken by the remote node at the other end of the link
identified for graceful-shutdown depends on the link type.</t>

<section title='Point-to-Point Links'>
<t>The node that has the link to be taken
   out of service MUST set the metric of the link to MaxLinkMetric (0xffff)
   and reoriginate its Router-LSA.  
   The Traffic Engineering metric of the link SHOULD be set to 
   (0xffffffff), and the node SHOULD reoriginate the corresponding TE Link
   Opaque LSAs. When a Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV is received for a
   point-to-point link, the remote node MUST identify the local link that
   corresponds to the graceful-shutdown link and set its metric to
   MaxLinkMetric (0xffff), and the remote node MUST reoriginate its Router-LSA
   with the changed metric. When TE is enabled, the Traffic Engineering metric
   of the link SHOULD be set to (0xffffffff) and follow the procedures in
   <xref target="RFC5817"/>. Similarly, the remote node SHOULD set the
Traffic Engineering metric of the link to 0xffffffff and SHOULD reoriginate
the TE Link Opaque LSA for the link with the new value.</t> 
 
 <t> The Extended Link Opaque LSAs and the Extended Link TLV are not scoped
 for multi-topology <xref target="RFC4915"/>. In multi-topology deployments
 <xref target="RFC4915"/>, the Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV advertised in an
 Extended Link Opaque LSA corresponds to all the topologies that include the
 link. 
 
 The receiver node SHOULD change the metric in the reverse direction for all
 the topologies that include the remote link and 
 reoriginate the Router-LSA as defined in <xref target="RFC4915"/>.</t>
 
 <t>When the originator of the Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV purges the
 Extended Link Opaque LSA or reoriginates it without the
 Graceful&nbhy;Link&nbhy;Shutdown sub-TLV, the remote node must reoriginate
 the appropriate LSAs with the metric and TE metric values set to their
 original values.</t> 
 
</section>

<section title='Broadcast/NBMA Links'>
<t>Broadcast or Non-Broadcast Multi-Access (NBMA) networks in OSPF are
represented by a star topology where the Designated Router (DR) is the central
point to which all other routers on the broadcast or NBMA network logically
connect.  As a result, routers on the broadcast or NBMA network advertise only
their adjacency to the DR.  Routers that do not act as DRs do not form or
advertise adjacencies with each other. For the broadcast links, the
MaxLinkMetric on the remote link cannot be changed since all the neighbors are
on same link. Setting the link cost to MaxLinkMetric would impact all paths that traverse any of the neighbors connected on that broadcast link. </t>

<t> The node that has the link to be taken out of service MUST set the metric
of the link to MaxLinkMetric (0xffff) and reoriginate the Router-LSA. The
Traffic Engineering metric of the link SHOULD be set to (0xffffffff), and the
node SHOULD reoriginate the corresponding TE Link Opaque LSAs. For a broadcast
link, the two-part metric as described in <xref target="RFC8042"/> is
used. The node originating the Graceful&nbhy;Link&nbhy;Shutdown sub-TLV MUST
set the metric in the Network&nbhy;to&nbhy;Router Metric sub-TLV to
MaxLinkMetric (0xffff) for OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 and reoriginate the corresponding
LSAs. The nodes that receive the two-part metric should follow the procedures
described in <xref target="RFC8042"/>. The backward-compatibility procedures
described in <xref target="RFC8042"/> should be followed to ensure loop-free routing. 
</t>
</section>

<section anchor='point_to_pont' title='Point-to-Multipoint Links'>
   <t> Operation for the point-to-multipoint (P2MP) links is similar to the
   point-to-point links. When a Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV is received for
   a point-to-multipoint link, the remote node MUST identify the neighbor that
   corresponds to the graceful-shutdown link and set its metric to
   MaxLinkMetric (0xffff). The remote node MUST reoriginate the Router-LSA
   with the changed metric for the corresponding neighbor.</t> 
</section>

<section title='Unnumbered Interfaces'>
   <t> Unnumbered interfaces do not have a unique IP address and borrow their
   address from other interfaces.   
   <xref target="RFC2328"/> describes procedures to handle unnumbered
   interfaces in the context of the Router-LSA.  
   We apply a similar procedure to the Extended Link TLV advertising the
   Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV in order to handle unnumbered interfaces.
 
   The Link-Data field in the Extended Link TLV includes the Local Interface
   ID instead of the IP address. The Local/Remote Interface ID sub-TLV MUST be
   advertised when there are multiple parallel unnumbered interfaces between
   two nodes. One of the mechanisms to obtain the Interface ID of the remote
   side is defined in  <xref target="RFC4203"/>. </t> 
</section>

<section title='Hybrid Broadcast and P2MP Interfaces'>
   <t> Hybrid Broadcast and P2MP interfaces represent a broadcast network
   modeled as P2MP interfaces. <xref target="RFC6845"/> describes procedures
   to handle these interfaces. Operation for the Hybrid interfaces is similar
   to operation for the P2MP interfaces. When a Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV
   is received for a hybrid link, the remote node MUST identify the neighbor
   that corresponds to the graceful-shutdown link and set its metric to
   MaxLinkMetric (0xffff). All the remote nodes connected to the originator
   MUST reoriginate the Router-LSA with the changed metric for the
   neighbor.</t> 
</section>    
</section>


    
<section title='Backward Compatibility'>
   <t> The mechanisms described in the document are fully backward compatible.
    It is required that the node adverting the Graceful&nbhy;Link&nbhy;Shutdown sub-TLV as
    well as the node at the remote end of the graceful-shutdown link support the
    extensions described herein for the traffic to be diverted from the 
    graceful-shutdown link. If the remote node doesn't support the capability, 
    it will still use the graceful-shutdown link, but there are no other adverse 
    effects. In the case of broadcast links using two-part metrics, the 
    backward-compatibility procedures as described in <xref target="RFC8042"/> are 
    applicable.</t>

</section>

<section title='Applications' anchor='applications'>
<section anchor="overlay_network" title='Overlay Network'> 


 <t>Many service providers offer L2 services to a customer connecting different locations. 
 The customer's IGP protocol creates a seamless private network
(overlay network) across the locations for the customer.
Service providers want to offer graceful-shutdown functionality when the PE
device is taken out for maintenance. 
 There can be large number of customers attached to a PE node, and the remote
 endpoints for these L2 attachment circuits  
are spread across the service provider's network. Changing the metric for all
corresponding L2 circuits in both directions is a tedious and error-prone
process. The graceful-link-shutdown feature simplifies the process by
increasing the metric on the CE-CE overlay link  so that traffic 
in both directions is diverted away from the PE undergoing maintenance.
The graceful-link-shutdown feature allows the link to be used as a last-resort
link so that traffic is not disrupted when alternate paths are not available.</t>

<figure anchor="overlay_network_dgm" title="Overlay Network">
<artwork>
                  ------PE3---------------PE4------CE3
                /                           \          
              /                               \       
           CE1---------PE1----------PE2---------CE2
                                    \                 
                                     \                
                                      ------CE4

CE: Customer Edge
PE: Provider Edge
</artwork>
</figure>

<t> In the example shown in <xref target="overlay_network_dgm"/>,
 when the PE1 node is going out of service for maintenance, a service provider
 sets the PE1 to stub-router state and communicates the pending maintenance
 action to the overlay customer networks. The mechanisms used 
to communicate between PE1 and CE1 is outside the scope of this document. CE1
sets the graceful-link-shutdown state on its links connecting CE3, CE2, and
CE4, changes the metric to MaxLinkMetric, and reoriginates the corresponding
LSA. The remote end of the link at CE3, CE2, and CE4 also set the metric on
the link to MaxLinkMetric, and the traffic from both directions gets diverted
away from PE1.</t> 
</section>

<section anchor="controller_TE" title='Controller-Based Deployments'>  


<t>In controller-based deployments where the controller participates in the
IGP protocol, the controller can also receive the
graceful&nbhy;link&nbhy;shutdown information as a warning that link
maintenance is imminent. Using this information, the controller can find
alternate paths for traffic that uses the affected link. The controller can
apply various policies and reroute the LSPs away from the link undergoing
maintenance. If there are no alternate paths satisfying the constraints, the
controller might temporarily relax those constraints and put the service on a
different path. Increasing the link metric alone does not specify the
maintenance activity as the metric could increase in events such as LDP-IGP
synchronization. An explicit indication from the router using the
Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV is needed to inform the controller or head-end
routers. </t> 

 <figure anchor="TE_deployments" title="Controller-Based Traffic Engineering">
<artwork>
                           _____________
                          |             |
            --------------| Controller  |--------------
            |             |____________ |             |
            |                                         |
            |--------- Primary Path ------------------|
            PE1---------P1----------------P2---------PE2
                        |                  |
                        |                  |
                        |________P3________|      
                    
                           Alternate Path

</artwork>
</figure>
<t>In the above example, the PE1->PE2 LSP
 is set up to satisfy a constraint of 10 Gbps bandwidth on each link. The
 links P1->P3 and P3->P2 have only 1 Gbps capacity, and there is no alternate
 path satisfying the bandwidth constraint of 10 Gbps. When the P1->P2 link is
 being prepared for maintenance, the controller receives the
 graceful-link-shutdown information, as there is no alternate path available
 that satisfies the constraints, and the controller chooses a path that is
 less optimal and temporarily sets up an alternate path via P1->P3->P2. 
 Once the traffic is diverted, the P1->P2 link can be taken out of service for
maintenance/upgrade.</t> 
</section>
<section anchor="L3VPN" title='L3VPN Services and Sham Links'> 

 <t>Many service providers offer Layer 3 Virtual Private Network (L3VPN)
 services to customers, and CE-PE links run OSPF <xref target="RFC4577"/>. 
  When the PE is taken out of service for maintenance, all the links on the PE
  can be set to graceful&nbhy;link&nbhy;shutdown state, which will guarantee 
  that the traffic to/from dual-homed CEs gets diverted.
 The interaction between OSPF and BGP is outside the scope of this document. A
 mechanism based on <xref target="RFC6987"/> with summaries and externals that
 are advertised with high metrics could also be used to achieve the same
 functionality when implementations support high metrics advertisement for
 summaries and externals.</t> 

<t> Another useful use case is when ISPs provide sham-link services to
customers <xref target="RFC4577"/>. When the PE goes out of service for
maintenance, all sham links on the PE can be set to graceful-link-shutdown
state, and traffic can be diverted from both ends without having to touch the
configurations on the remote end of the sham links.</t> 
</section>

<section anchor="Hub_and_spoke" title='Hub and Spoke Deployment'> 


<t>OSPF is largely deployed in Hub and Spoke deployments with a large number
of Spokes connecting to the Hub. It is a general practice to deploy 
multiple Hubs with all Spokes connecting to these  Hubs to achieve
redundancy. The mechanism defined in <xref target="RFC6987"/> can be used to
divert the Spoke-to-Spoke traffic from the overloaded Hub router. The traffic
that flows from Spokes via the Hub into an external network may not be
diverted in certain scenarios. When a Hub node goes down for maintenance, 
all links on the Hub can be set to graceful-link-shutdown state, and traffic 
gets diverted from the Spoke sites as well without having to make
configuration changes on the Spokes.</t> 

</section>
</section>

<section title='Security Considerations' anchor='sec-con'>
<t> This document utilizes the OSPF packets and LSAs described in 
<xref target="RFC2328"/> , <xref target="RFC3630"/>, <xref target="RFC5329"/>,
and <xref target="RFC5340"/>. The authentication procedures described in <xref
target="RFC2328"/> for OSPFv2 and <xref target="RFC4552"/> for OSPFv3 are
applicable to this document as well. This document does not introduce any
further security issues other than those discussed in <xref target="RFC2328"/>
and <xref target="RFC5340"/>. 
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">


<t>IANA has registered the following in the "OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV
Sub-TLVs" registry: 
<list>
<t>7 - Graceful-Link-Shutdown Sub-TLV</t>
<t>8 - Remote IPv4 Address Sub-TLV</t>
<t>9 - Local/Remote Interface ID Sub-TLV</t>
</list>
</t>
 
<t>IANA has registered the following value in the "OSPFv3 Extended-LSA
Sub-TLVs" registry:
<list>
<t>8 - Graceful-Link-Shutdown sub-TLV</t>
</list>
</t>
    
<t>IANA has registered the following value in the "BGP-LS Node Descriptor,
Link Descriptor, Prefix Descriptor, and Attribute TLVs" registry <xref
target="RFC7752"/>": 
<list>
<t>1121 - Graceful-Link-Shutdown TLV</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>

</middle>
<back>

<references title='Normative References'>

&RFC7684;
&RFC8042;
&RFC7752;
&RFC6845;
&RFC2119;
&RFC6987;
&RFC2328;
&RFC5340;
&RFC5329;
&RFC3630;
&RFC5817;
&RFC8174;
&RFC8362;

</references>
<references title='Informative References'>

&RFC4203;
&RFC4915;
&RFC4577;
&RFC4552;

</references>

<section title='Acknowledgements' numbered='no'>
<t>Thanks to Chris Bowers for valuable input and edits to the document.
Thanks to Jeffrey Zhang, Acee Lindem, and Ketan Talaulikar for their input.
Thanks to Karsten Thomann for careful review and input on the applications
where graceful link shutdown is useful.</t>

<t> Thanks to Alia Atlas, Deborah Brungard, Alvaro Retana, Andrew G. Malis,
and Tim Chown for their valuable input.</t> 
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
