<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  ]>



<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902" number="8629" >

<front>
<title abbrev="DLEP Multi-Hop Extension">Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Multi-Hop Forwarding Extension</title>
   <author initials='B.' surname="Cheng" fullname='Bow-Nan Cheng'>
    <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
        <street>244 Wood Street</street>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <region>MA</region>
        <code>02421-6426</code>
      </postal>
       <email>bcheng@ll.mit.edu</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger' role='editor'>
    <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
    <address>
       <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
    </address>
    </author>

<date year="2019" month="July" />


  <abstract>
<t>
  This document defines an extension to the Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) that enables
  the reporting and control of multi-hop forwarding by DLEP-capable
  modems.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="sec-1" title="Introduction">
<t>
  The Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) is defined in <xref
  target="RFC8175"/>. It provides the exchange of link-related control
  information between a modem and a router. DLEP defines a base set of
  mechanisms as well as support for possible extensions.  This document
  defines one such extension.
</t>
<t>
  Some modem technologies support mobile ad hoc network (MANET)
  forwarding where connectivity to destinations is provided via
  forwarding in intermediate modems. This document refers to forwarding
  by intermediate modems as "multi-hop forwarding".
  DLEP Destination Messages can be used to report
  such reachable destinations (see <xref target="RFC8175"/>), but do
  not provide any information related to the number or capacity of the
  hops.  The extension defined in this document enables modems to inform
  routers when multi-hop forwarding is being used and allows routers
  to request that modems change multi-hop forwarding behavior. The
  extension defined in this document is referred to as "Multi-Hop
  Forwarding", where each modem that transmits/sends data to reach a
  particular destination is counted as a hop.
</t>
<t>
  It is important to note that the use of the Hop Control mechanism
  defined in this document can result in connectivity changes and even loss of
  the ability to reach one or more destinations.  The defined mechanism
  will report such connectivity changes, but the details of what a
  router does or how it reacts to such are out scope of this document.
</t>
<t>
  This document defines a new DLEP Extension Type Value in <xref
  target="sec-ext-type"/>, which indicates the use of the
  extension, and three new DLEP Data Items in <xref
  target="sec-data-items"/>.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-1.1" title="Key Words">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-ext-type" title="Extension Usage and Identification">
<t>
   The use of the Multi-Hop Forwarding Extension SHOULD be configurable.
   Per  <xref target="RFC8175"/>, to indicate that the extension is to
be used, an implementation
   includes the Multi-Hop Forwarding Extension Type Value in the
   Extensions Supported Data Item. The Extensions Supported Data Item is
   sent and processed according to <xref target="RFC8175"/>.
</t>
<t>
  The Multi-Hop Forwarding Extension Type Value is 1 (see <xref
  target="sec-iana"/>).
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-data-items" title="Extension Data Items">
<t>
   Three data items are defined by this extension. The Hop Count Data
   Item is used by a modem to provide the number of modem hops
   traversed to reach a particular destination.  The Hop Control Data
   Item is used by a router to request that a modem alter connectivity
   to a particular destination.  The Suppress Forwarding Data Item is
   used by a router to request that a modem disable multi-hop forwarding
   on either a device or destination basis.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-di-hcount" title="Hop Count">
<t>
  The Hop Count Data Item is used by a modem to indicate the number of
  modems that transmit/send data to reach a particular destination,
  i.e., hops, between the modem and a specific destination.  

In other words, each hop represents a transmission, and the number of hops is
equal to the number of transmissions required to go from a router's connected
modem to the destination's connected modem.  The minimum number of hops is 1,
which represents transmission to destinations that are directly reachable via
the router's locally connected modem.
</t>
<t>
  The data item also contains an indication of when a destination that
  currently has a hop count of greater than one (1) could be made
  directly reachable by a modem, e.g., by reaiming an antenna.
</t>
<t>
  The Hop Count Data Item SHOULD be carried in the Destination Up,
  Destination Update, Destination Announce Response, and Link
  Characteristics Response Messages when the Hop Count to a destination
  is greater than one (1).
</t>
<t>
  A router receiving a Hop Count Data Item can use this information in
  its forwarding and routing decisions, but specific use is out of scope
  of this document.  When using this extension, the absence of the Hop Count Data Item MUST be
  interpreted by the router as a Hop Count value of one (1).
</t>
<t>
  The format of the Hop Count Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |P|  Reserved   |   Hop Count   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">21</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">2</t>
    <t hangText="P:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The P-bit indicates that a destination is potentially directly
      reachable. When the P-bit is set, the router MAY request a direct
      link to the associated destination using the Hop Control Data Item
      described below. This field MUST be ignored when the value
      contained in the Hop Count field is one (1).
    </t>

    <t hangText="Reserved:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The Reserved field MUST be set to zero by the sender (a modem) and ignored by the
      receiver (a router).
    </t>
    <t hangText="Hop Count:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The Hop Count is an unsigned 8-bit integer indicating the number of modem hops
      required (i.e., number of times a packet will be transmitted) to
      reach the destination indicated in the message.  The special value
      of 255 (0xFF) is used to indicate that the number of hops is an
      unknown number greater than one (1).  This field MUST contain a
      value of at least one (1) if the associated destination is
      reachable.
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      A value of zero (0) is used to indicate that the processing of a Hop
      Control action (see <xref target="sec-di-hcontrol"/>) has resulted
      in the destination no longer being reachable.  A zero value MUST NOT
      be used in any message other than a Link Characteristics Response
      Message.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-di-hcontrol" title="Hop Control">
<t>
  The Hop Control Data Item is used by a router to request a change in
  connectivity to a particular destination or to perform multi-hop processing
  on a device-wide basis. A router can request that a multi-hop-reachable
  destination be changed to a single-hop destination.  A router can also
  indicate that the modem terminates a previous direct connectivity request to a
  particular destination.
</t>
<t>
  The Hop Control Data Item MAY be carried in a Session Update Message
  sent by a router when the control applies to the whole device, or a Link
  Characteristics Request Message when the control applies to a
  particular destination.
</t>
<t>
  A modem that receives the Hop Control Data Item in a Link Characteristics
  Request Message SHOULD take whatever actions are needed to make the change
  indicated by the data item for the associated destination Media Access
  Control (MAC) address. Once the change is made, fails, or is rejected, the
  modem MUST respond with a Link Characteristics Response Message containing
  an updated Hop Count Data Item.  Note that other destinations can be
  impacted as a result of the change, and such changes are reported in
  Destination Down and Destination Update Messages.  The modem MUST notify the
  router of each destination that is not identified in the Link
  Characteristics Response Message and is no longer reachable via a
  Destination Down Message.  The modem MUST also notify the router of each
  impacted destination that is not identified in the Link Characteristics
  Response Message via a Destination Update Message.
</t>
<t>
  Failures may occur for multiple reasons, for example, the transmission
  characteristics of the link don't support the one-hop connection at
  the time of the request. Requests can be rejected by local policy.
</t>

<t>
  A modem that receives the Hop Control Data Item in a Session Update Message
  SHOULD take whatever actions are needed to make the change indicated by the
  data item for all known destinations.  Once the change is made, fails, or is
  rejected, the modem MUST respond with a Session Update Response Message with
  an appropriate Status Code.  The destination-specific impact of processing
  a Hop Control Data Item in a Session Update Message is provided via
  Destination Down and Destination Update Messages.  The modem MUST notify the
  router of each destination that is no longer reachable via a Destination
  Down Message. The modem MUST notify the router of any changes in Hop Counts
  via Destination Update Messages.
</t>
<t>
  The format of the Hop Control Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |       Hop Control Actions     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">22</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">2</t>
    <t hangText="Hop Control Actions:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The Hop Control Actions field is an unsigned 16-bit value with the following meaning:
      </t>
  </list>
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_hc" title="Hop Control Actions Values">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol><ttcol>Action</ttcol>
        <c>0</c> <c>Reset</c>
        <c>1</c> <c>Terminate</c>
        <c>2</c> <c>Direct Connection</c>
        <c>3</c> <c>Suppress Forwarding</c>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </texttable>

<section anchor="sec-di-hc-r" title="Reset">
  <t>
    The Reset Action requests that the default behavior be restored.
    When received in a Session Update Message, a modem MUST
    clear all control actions that have previously been processed on a
    device-wide basis and revert to its configured behavior.  When
    received in a Link Characteristics Request Message, a modem MUST clear all
    control actions that have previously been processed for the
    destination indicated in the message.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-di-hc-t" title="Terminate">
  <t>
    The Terminate Action is only valid on a per-destination basis and MUST NOT
    be sent in a Session Update Message. It indicates that a direct connection
    is no longer needed with the destination identified in the message. This
    request has no impact on multi-hop destinations and may fail even in a
    single-hop case, i.e., it can result in the Hop Count to the destination not
    being impacted by the processing of the request.
  </t>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-di-hc-dc" title="Direct Connection">
  <t>
    The Direct Connection Action is only valid on a per-destination basis and
    MUST NOT be sent in a Session Update Message.  It indicates
    that the modem SHOULD attempt to establish a direct connection with
    the destination identified in the message.  This action SHOULD only
    be sent for destinations for which the Hop Count is both greater than 1
    and has the P-Bit set in the previously received Hop Count Data
    Item.  Results of the request for the destination identified in the
    message are provided as described above.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-di-hc-sf" title="Suppress Forwarding">
<t>
  The Suppress Forwarding Action is used by a router to indicate to
  its peer that multi-hop forwarding performed by the modem is to be
  suppressed.  A router can request that multi-hop forwarding be
  suppressed on a device-wide or destination-specific basis.
</t>
<t>
  A modem that receives the Suppress Forwarding Data Item in a Session
  Update Message MUST suppress multi-hop forwarding on a device-wide
  basis. This means that data traffic originating from the modem's peer
  router SHALL only be sent by the modem to destinations that are one
  modem hop away, and that any data traffic received by the modem from
  another modem that is not destined to the peer router SHALL be
  dropped. The impact on destination hop counts are provided to the
  router by the modem as described above.
</t>
<t>
  A modem that receives the Suppress Forwarding Data Item in a Link
  Characteristics Request Message MUST suppress multi-hop forwarding for
  only the destination indicated in the message.  This means that data
  traffic originating from the modem's peer router SHALL be sent by the
  modem to the destination indicated in the Link Characteristics Request
  Message only when it is one modem hop away.  Notably, data traffic
  received by the modem from another modem can be forwarded by the modem
  per its normal processing.  Results are provided as described above.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-sec" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   The extension defined in this document enables the reporting and control of
   forwarding information by DLEP-capable modems.  The extension does not
   inherently introduce any additional vulnerabilities above those documented
   in <xref target="RFC8175"/>.  The approach taken to security in that
   document applies equally when running the extension defined in this
   document.
</t>
<t>
  The extension does define one mechanism that is worth particular
  note.  It includes a Hop Control mechanism (see <xref
  target="sec-di-hcontrol"/>) that is similar to the Link
  Characteristics Request Message defined in <xref target="RFC8175"/> in
  that it can impact the set of destinations reported as reachable.
  With the Link Characteristics Request Message, this risk is implicit.
  With the Hop Control mechanism defined in this document, it is more
  likely.  From a security perspective, implementations should be aware
  of this increased risk and may choose to implement additional
  configuration control mechanisms to ensure that the Hop Control
  mechanism is only used under conditions intended by the network
  operator.
</t>
<t>
   Implementations of the extension defined in this document MUST support
   configuration of TLS usage, as described in <xref target="RFC8175"/>,
   in order to protect configurations where injection attacks are
   possible, i.e., when the link between a modem and router is not
   otherwise protected.
</t>
 
<t>
  Note that this extension does allow a compromised or impersonating
  modem to suppress transmission by the router or a switch that
  interconnects the modem and router.  Similar attacks are
  generally possible for DLEP, for example, an impersonating modem may
  cause a session reset or cause a compromised modem to simply
  drop all traffic destined to, or sent by, a router.  <xref
  target="RFC8175"/> defines the use of TLS to protect against the
  impersonating attacker.
</t>

</section>


<section anchor="sec-iana" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
  As described below, IANA has assigned 3 values to registries defined by <xref
  target="RFC8175"/> and created a new registry. 
</t>
<section anchor="sec-iana-ext" title="Extension Type Value">
<t>
  IANA has registered the following new value in the Specification Required
  range of the
  "Extension Type Values" registry within the
  "Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Parameters" registry. 
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_et" title="Requested Extension Type Value">
  <preamble></preamble>
  <ttcol>Code</ttcol> <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    <c>1</c> <c>Multi-Hop Forwarding</c>
    <postamble></postamble>
    </texttable>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-iana-di" title="Data Item Values">
<t>
  IANA has registered the following 2 values in the Specification                         
  Required range of the "Data Item Type Values" registry within the "Dynamic
  Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Parameters" registry. 
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_di" title="Requested Data Item Values">
  <preamble></preamble>
  <ttcol>Type Code</ttcol> <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    <c>21</c> <c>Hop Count</c>
    <c>22</c> <c>Hop Control</c>
    <postamble></postamble>
    </texttable>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-iana-hca" title="Hop Control Actions Registry">
  <t>
    IANA has created the "Hop Control Actions Values"
    registry within the "Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Parameters"
    registry. 

   The following table provides initial registry values and the registration
   procedures <xref target="RFC8126"/> that apply:
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_iana_hca" title="Hop Control Actions Values">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol><ttcol>Action/Policy</ttcol>
        <c>0</c> <c>Reset</c>
        <c>1</c> <c>Terminate</c>
        <c>2</c> <c>Direct Connection</c>
        <c>3</c> <c>Suppress Forwarding</c>
        <c>4-65519</c>     <c>Specification Required</c>
        <c>65520-65534</c> <c>Private Use</c>
        <c>65535</c>       <c>Reserved</c>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </texttable>
</section>
</section>
</middle>

<?rfc needLines="20"?>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8175"?>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>

</references>
<?rfc needLines="100"?>
<section numbered="no" title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>
    Helpful comments were received from members of the MANET working
    group, including Henning Rogge, Victoria Pritchard, and David
    Wiggins.
  </t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
