<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2869 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2869.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc number="8354" 
     category="info" 
     submissionType="IETF" 
     consensus="yes"
     ipr="trust200902" >
  <front>

    <title abbrev="Use Cases for IPv6 SPRING">Use Cases for IPv6 Source
    Packet Routing in Networking (SPRING)</title>

    <author fullname="John Brzozowski" initials="J." surname="Brzozowski">
      <organization abbrev="">Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <email>john_brzozowski@cable.comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Leddy" initials="J." surname="Leddy">
      <organization abbrev="">Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <email>John_Leddy@cable.comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." surname="Filsfils">
      <organization abbrev="">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Brussels</city>

          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roberta Maglione" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Maglione">
      <organization abbrev="">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Torri Bianche 8</street>

          <city>Vimercate</city>

          <code>20871</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>robmgl@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mark Townsley" initials="M." surname="Townsley">
      <organization abbrev="">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>townsley@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2018"/>

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Spring</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Source Packet Routing in Networking (SPRING) architecture
      describes how Segment Routing can be used to steer packets through an
      IPv6 or MPLS network using the source routing paradigm. This document
      illustrates some use cases for Segment Routing in an IPv6-only
      environment.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Source Packet Routing in Networking (SPRING) architecture leverages
      the source routing paradigm. An ingress node steers a packet by
      including a controlled set of instructions, called segments, in the
      SPRING header. The SPRING architecture is described in <xref
      target="SEGMENT-ROUTING"/>. This document illustrates
      some use cases for SPRING / Segment Routing in an IPv6-only
      environment.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="use-cases" title="IPv6 SPRING Use Cases">
      <t>The use cases described in this section do not constitute an
      exhaustive list of all the possible scenarios: this section only
      includes some of the most common envisioned deployment models for
      Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6).</t>

      <t>In addition to the use cases described in this document, all the
      SPRING use cases <xref target="RFC7855"/> are also applicable to the
      SRv6 data plane.</t>

      <section anchor="Home" title="SPRING in the Small Office  ">
        <t>An IPv6-enabled Small Office, Home Office (SOHO) provides ample globally routed
        IP addresses for all devices in the SOHO. An IPv6 small office with
        multiple egress points and associated provider-assigned prefixes will,
        in turn, provide multiple IPv6 addresses to hosts. A small office
        performing source and destination routing <xref
        target="PA-MULTIHOMING"/> will ensure that
        packets exit the SOHO at the appropriate egress based on the
        associated delegated prefix for that link.</t>

        <t>A SPRING-enabled SOHO provides the ability to steer traffic into a
        specific path from end hosts in the SOHO or from a customer edge router in the SOHO.
        If the selection of the source-routed path is
        enabled at the customer edge router, that router is responsible for
        classifying traffic and steering it into the correct path. If hosts in
        the SOHO have explicit source selection rules, classification can be
        based on the source address or associated network egress point, thus avoiding
        the need for implicit classification techniques based on Deep Packet
	Inspection (DPI). If the
        traffic is steered into a specific path by the host itself, it is
        important to know which networks can interpret the SPRING header. This
        information can be provided as part of the host configuration as a
        property of the configured IP address.</t>

        <t>The ability to steer traffic to an appropriate egress or utilize a
        specific type of media (e.g., low power, Wi-Fi, wired, femtocell,
        Bluetooth, Multimedia over Coax Alliance (MoCA), HomePlug, etc.) within the home itself are obvious
        cases that may be of interest to an application running within a
        SOHO.</t>

        <t>Steering to a specific egress point may be useful for a number of
        scenarios, including:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>regulatory compliance;</t>

            <t>performance of a particular service associated with a
	    particular link;</t>

            <t>cost imposed due to data caps or per-byte charges;</t>

            <t>distinguishing between personal vs. work traffic in homes with
	    one or more teleworkers; and</t>

            <t>provision of specific services by one ISP vs. another.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Information included in the SPRING header, whether imposed by the
        end host itself, a customer edge router, or within the access network
        of the ISP, may be of use at the far ends of the data communication as
        well. For example, an application running on an end host with
        application support in a data center can utilize the SPRING header as
        a channel to include information that affects its treatment within the
        data center itself, which allows for application-level steering and
        load balancing without relying upon implicit
	application-classification techniques at the edge of the data center. Further, as more
        and more application traffic is encrypted, the ability to extract (and
        include in the SPRING header) just enough information to enable the
        network and data center to load balance and steer traffic
        appropriately becomes more and more important.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Access" title="SPRING in the Access Network">
        <t>Access networks deliver a variety of types of traffic from the
        service provider's network to the home environment and from the home
        towards the service provider's network.</t>

        <t>For bandwidth management or related purposes, the service provider
        may want to associate certain types of traffic to specific physical or
        logical downstream capacity pipes.</t>

        <t>This mapping is not the same thing as classification and
        scheduling. 

   In the cable access network, these pipes are represented at
   the Data-Over-Cable Service Interface Specification <xref target="DOCSIS"/> layer as
   different service flows, which are better identified as distinct
   data links. As such, creating this separation allows an operator to differentiate
        between different types of content and perform a variety of differing
        functions on these pipes, such as byte capping, regulatory compliance
        functions, and billing.</t>

        <t>In a cable operator's environment, these downstream pipes could be
        a DOCSIS <xref target="DOCSIS"/> service flow, a service group, or a specific Quadrature Amplitude Modulation (QAM) as in Annex B of <xref target="ITU.J83"/>.</t>

        <t>Similarly, the operator may want to map traffic from the home sent
        towards the service provider's network to specific upstream capacity
        pipes. Information carried in a packet's SPRING header could provide
        the target pipe for this specific packet. The access device would not
        need to know specific details about the packet to perform this
        mapping; instead, the access device would only need to know the
        interpretation of the SPRING header and how to map it to the target
        pipe.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="DC" title="SPRING in Data Center">
        <t>Some data center operators are transitioning their data center
        infrastructure from IPv4 to native IPv6 only, in order to cope with
        IPv4 address depletion and to achieve larger scale. In such an
	environment, source routing (as enabled by SRv6) can
        be used to steer traffic across specific paths through the network.
        The specific path may also include a given function that one or more nodes
        in the path are requested to perform.</t>

        <t>Additionally, one of the fundamental requirements for data center
        architecture is to provide scalable, isolated tenant networks. In such
        scenarios, Segment Routing can be used to build a construct to steer
	the traffic across that specific path and to identify specific nodes,
        tenants, and functions.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="CDN" title="SPRING in Content Delivery Networks">
        <t>The rise of online video applications and new, video-capable IP
        devices has led to an explosion of video traffic traversing network
        operator infrastructures. In the drive to reduce the capital and
        operational impact of the massive influx of online video traffic, as
        well as to extend traditional TV services to new devices and screens,
        network operators are increasingly turning to Content Delivery
        Networks (CDNs).</t>

        <t>Several studies showed the benefits of connecting caches in a
        hierarchical structure following the hierarchical nature of the
        Internet. In a cache hierarchy, one cache establishes peering
        relationships with its neighbor caches. There are two types of
        relationships: parent and sibling. A parent cache is essentially one
        level up in a cache hierarchy. A sibling cache is on the same level.
        Multiple levels of hierarchy are commonly used in order to build an
        efficient cache architecture.</t>

        <t>In an environment where each single cache system can be uniquely
        identified by its own IPv6 address, a list containing a sequence of
        the caches in a hierarchy can be built. At each node (cache) in the
        list, the presence of the requested content is checked. If the
        requested content is found at the cache (a cache hits scenario), the
        sequence ends even if there are more nodes in the list; otherwise, the
        next element in the list (the next node/cache) is examined.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="core" title="SPRING in Core Networks  ">
        <t>While the overall amount of traffic offered to the network
        continues to grow, and considering that multiple types of traffic with
        different characteristics and requirements are quickly converging over
        a single network architecture, the network operators are starting to
        face new challenges.</t>

        <t>Some operators are currently building, or plan to build in the near
        future, an IPv6-only native infrastructure for their core network.
        These operators are also looking at the possibility to set up an
        explicit path based on the IPv6 source address for specific types of
        traffic in order to efficiently use their network infrastructure. In
	the case of IPv6, some operators are currently assigning or plan to assign
        IPv6 prefix(es) to their IPv6 customers based on regions/geography,
        thus the subscriber's IPv6 prefix could be used to identify the region
        where the customer is located. In such an environment, the IPv6 source
        address could be used by the edge nodes of the network to steer
        traffic and forward it through a specific path other than the optimal
        path.</t>

        <t>The need to set up a source-based path that goes through some specific
        middle/intermediate points in the network may be related to different
        requirements: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The operator may want to be able to use some high-bandwidth
            links for a specific type of traffic (like video) and thus avoid the need
            for overdimensioning all the links of the network;</t>

            <t>The operator may want to be able to set up a specific path for
            delay-sensitive applications;</t>

            <t>The operator may have the need to be able to select one (or
            multiple) specific exit point(s) at peering points when different
            peering points are available;</t>

            <t>The operator may have the need to be able to set up a
	    source-based path for specific services in order to be able to reach some
            servers hosted in some facilities that are not always reachable through the
            optimal path; or</t>

            <t>The operator may need to be able to provision
            guaranteed disjoint paths (a so-called "dual-plane network") for
            diversity purposes.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>All these scenarios would require a form of traffic engineering
        capabilities in an IPv6-only network environment.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="seccons" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document presents use cases to be considered by the SPRING
      architecture and potential IPv6 extensions. As such, it does not
      introduce any security considerations. However, there are a number of
      security concerns with source routing at the IP layer <xref
      target="RFC5095"/>. It is expected that any solution that addresses
      these use cases also addresses any security concerns.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7855"?>
</references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5095'?>

      <reference anchor="DOCSIS"
                 target="http://www.cablelabs.com/news/new-generation-of-docsis-technology/">
        <front>
          <title>New Generation of DOCSIS Technology</title>

          <author><organization>CableLabs</organization></author>

          <date month="October" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ITU.J83"
                 target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-J.83/en">
        <front>
          <title>Digital multi-programme systems for television, sound and data services or cable distribution</title>

          <author><organization>ITU-T</organization></author>

          <date month="December" year="2007"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="J.83"/>
      </reference>

<reference anchor='SEGMENT-ROUTING'>
<front>
<title>Segment Routing Architecture</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Previdi' fullname='Stefano Previdi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Ginsberg' fullname='Les Ginsberg'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Decraene' fullname='Bruno Decraene'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shakir' fullname='Rob Shakir'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='January' year='2018' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-15"/>
</reference>


<!--draft-ietf-rtgwg-enterprise-pa-multihoming-03: I-D Exists-->

<reference anchor='PA-MULTIHOMING'>
<front>
<title>Enterprise Multihoming using Provider-Assigned Addresses without Network Prefix Translation: Requirements and Solution</title>

<author initials='F' surname='Baker' fullname='Fred Baker'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Bowers' fullname='Chris Bowers'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Linkova' fullname='J. Linkova'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' year='2018' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-rtgwg-enterprise-pa-multihoming-03' />

</reference>
    </references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="no">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Brian Field, Robert Raszuk, Wes
      George, Eric Vyncke, Fred Baker, John G.&nbsp;Scudder, Adrian Farrel,
      Alvaro Retana, Bruno Decraene, and Yakov Rekhter for their valuable
      comments and inputs to this document.</t>
</section>

<section title="Contributors" anchor="contributors" numbered="no">
<t>Many people contributed to this document.  The authors of this
document would like to thank and recognize them and their
contributions.  These contributors provided invaluable concepts and
content for this document's creation.</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Ida Leung
Independent

Email: ida@brumund.ca


Stefano Previdi
Cisco Systems
Via Del Serafico, 200
Rome  00142
Italy

Email: stefano@previdi.net


Christian Martin
Arista Networks

Email: cmartin@arista.com
]]></artwork></figure>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
