<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6879 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6879.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7010 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7010.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6463 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6463.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6275 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7077 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7077.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3007 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3007.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6058 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6058.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4283 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4283.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4283 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml">
]> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?> 
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="8191" ipr="trust200902" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes"> 

<front> 
<title abbrev="PMIPv6 HNP Renumbering">Home Network Prefix Renumbering in Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6)</title>
 
 <author fullname="Zhiwei Yan" initials="Z.W." surname="Yan"> 
<organization>CNNIC</organization> <address> <postal> <street>No.4 South 4th 
Street, Zhongguancun</street> <code>100190</code> <city>Beijing</city> 
<country>China</country> </postal> <email>yan@cnnic.cn</email> </address> 
</author>

<author fullname="Jong-Hyouk Lee" initials="J.-H." surname="Lee">
<organization>Sangmyung University</organization> <address>	<postal> <street>31, Sangmyeongdae-gil, Dongnam-gu</street> <code>31066</code> <city>Cheonan</city> <country>Republic of Korea</country>
</postal>	<email>jonghyouk@smu.ac.kr</email> </address>	</author>

<author fullname="Xiaodong Lee" initials="X.D." surname="Lee">
<organization>CNNIC</organization> <address> <postal>
<street>No.4 South 4th Street, Zhongguancun</street> <code>100190</code>
<city>Beijing</city> <country>China</country>	</postal> <email>xl@cnnic.cn</email>
</address> </author>

<date month="August" year="2017"/> 
<area>Internet Area</area> 
<workgroup>DMM Working Group</workgroup>

<keyword>PMIPv6</keyword> 
<keyword>HNP renumbering</keyword>
<keyword>LMA handover</keyword>

<abstract> 				
<t>In the basic Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) specification, a Mobile Node (MN)
is assigned with a Home Network Prefix (HNP) during its initial attachment, and
the MN configures its Home Address (HoA) with the HNP. During the movement of
the MN, the HNP remains unchanged to keep ongoing communications associated
with the HoA. However, the current PMIPv6 specification does not specify
related operations when HNP renumbering has occurred (e.g., due to change of
service provider or site topology, etc.). In this document, a solution
to support HNP renumbering is proposed, as an optional extension of the
PMIPv6 specification.  </t> </abstract>

</front> 

<middle>

	<section title="Introduction"> 				<t>At the time of writing, network
	managers prefer Provider-Independent (PI) addressing for
	IPv6 to attempt to minimize the need for future possible
	renumbering. However, a widespread use of PI addresses will cause
	Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) scaling problems <xref target="RFC7010"
	/>. It is thus desirable to develop tools and practices that make IPv6
	renumbering a simpler process to reduce demand for IPv6 PI space <xref
	target="RFC6879" />. 

   In this document, we aim to support HNP renumbering
   when the HNP in PMIPv6 <xref target="RFC5213" /> is not a PI prefix.

 </t>


<section title="Requirements Language">
  <t> 
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
   "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
   described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
   appear in all capitals, as shown here.
  </t> 
</section>

</section>

<section title="Usage Scenarios"> 	  <t> There are a number of reasons why HNP renumbering support in PMIPv6 is useful, and some scenarios are identified below: </t> 
			<t>
			<list style="format Scenario %d:">
				<t>the HNP set used by a PMIPv6
				service provider is assigned by a different
				Internet Service Provider (ISP), and then HNP
				renumbering MAY occur if the PMIPv6 service
				provider switches to a different ISP. </t> 
                                <t>multiple Local Mobility Anchors
				(LMAs) MAY be deployed by the same PMIPv6
				service provider, and then each LMA MAY serve
				for a specific HNP set. 

      In this case, the HNP of an MN MAY change
      if the serving LMA is changed to another LMA that does
      not inherit the assigned HNP set <xref target="RFC6463"/>. </t> 

<t>PMIPv6 HNP
				renumbering MAY be caused by the rebuilding of
				the network architecture as the companies
				split, merge, grow, relocate, or
				reorganize. For example, the PMIPv6 service
				provider MAY reorganize its network
				topology. </t>
			</list>
			</t>
			<t> In Scenario 1, we assume that only the HNP is
			renumbered, while the serving LMA remains unchanged;
			this is the basic scenario considered in this
			document. In Scenarios 2 and 3, more
			complex situations MAY result; for example, HNP
			renumbering MAY occur due to the switchover of a serving LMA.	</t>
			<t> In the Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) protocol, when an HNP
			changes, the Home Agent (HA) will actively notify its
			MN about the new prefix, and then the renumbering of
			the Home Network Address (HoA) can be well supported
			<xref target="RFC6275" />. In basic PMIPv6, the PMIPv6
			binding is triggered by a Mobile Access Gateway (MAG),
			which detects the attachment of the MN. A scheme is
			also needed for the LMA to immediately initiate the
			PMIPv6 binding state refreshment during the HNP
			renumbering process. Although this issue is also
			mentioned in Section 6.12 of <xref target="RFC5213"
			/>, the related solution has not been specified. 
			 </t> 
			 </section>

			 <section title="HNP Renumbering Procedure">
			 <t>
				 When HNP renumbering happens in PMIPv6, the
				 LMA MUST notify the MAG about the new HNP,
				 and then the MAG MUST announce the new HNP to
				 the attached MN accordingly. Also, the LMA
				 and the MAG MUST update the routing states
				 for the HNP and the related addresses. To
				 support this procedure, <xref
				 target="RFC7077" /> can be adopted; it specifies an asynchronous update from the LMA to the MAG about specific session parameters. This document considers the following two cases:
			 </t>

<t>
(1) HNP is renumbered under the same LMA
</t>
<t>
In this case, the LMA remains unchanged as in Scenarios 1 and 3. The 
steps are shown in <xref target="fig:procedure"/>.
</t>
			
<figure anchor="fig:procedure" title="Signaling Call Flow for HNP Renumbering">
<artwork><![CDATA[
    +-----+                +-----+                +-----+
    | MN  |                | MAG |                | LMA |
    +-----+                +-----+                +-----+
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |           Allocate new HNP
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |<------------- UPN ---|
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |                      |
      |<-----RA/DHCP --------|                      |
      |                      |                      |
    Address configuration    |                      |
      |                      |                      |
      |            Update binding & routing states  |
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |--- UPA ------------->|
      |                      |                      |
      |                      |     Update binding & routing states
      |                      |                      |
]]></artwork>
</figure>
			
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
When a PMIPv6 service provider renumbers the HNP set under the same LMA, the serving LMA SHOULD initiate the HNP renumbering operation. The LMA allocates a new HNP for the related MN.
</t>
<t>
The LMA sends the Update Notification (UPN) message to the MAG to update the
HNP information. If the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) is used to
allocate the address, the DHCP infrastructure MUST also be notified about the new HNP.
</t>
<t>
Once the MAG receives this UPN message, it recognizes that the related MN has the new HNP. Then, the MAG MUST notify the MN about the new HNP with a Router Advertisement (RA) message or allocate a new address within the new HNP through a DHCP procedure.
</t>
<t>
After the MN obtains the HNP information through the RA message, it deletes the old HoA and configures a new HoA with the newly allocated HNP.
</t>
<t>
When the new HNP is announced or the new address is configured to the MN
successfully, the MAG MUST update the related binding and routing
states. Then, the MAG sends back the Update Notification Acknowledgement (UPA)
message to the LMA for the notification of successful update of the HNP,
related binding state, and routing state. Then, the LMA updates the routing
and binding information corresponding to the MN in order to replace the old HNP with the new one.
</t>
</list>
</t>
			 
<t>
(2) HNP renumbering is caused by the LMA switchover
</t>
<t>
Since the HNP is assigned by the LMA, HNP renumbering MAY be caused by the LMA switchover, as in Scenarios 2 and 3.
</t>
<t>
The LMA information is the basic configuration information of the MAG. When
the LMA changes, the related profile SHOULD be updated by the service
provider. 


In this way, the MAG initiates the binding registration to the MN's new LMA as specified in
<xref target="RFC5213" />. When HNP renumbering is caused in this case,
the new HNP information is sent by the LMA during the new binding
procedure. Accordingly, the MAG withdraws the old HNP of the MN and announces
the new HNP to the MN, similar to the case when the HNP is renumbered under the same LMA.
</t>
</section>
	 
<section title="Session Connectivity">
<t>
HNP renumbering MAY cause the disconnection of the ongoing communications of the MN. Basically, there are two modes to manage the session connectivity during HNP renumbering.
</t> 
	 		 <t>
<list style="format (%d)">


<t>Soft mode
			 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				 The LMA will temporarily maintain the state
				 of the old HNP during the HNP renumbering
				 (after the UPA reception) in order to
				 redirect the packets to the MN before the MN
				 reconnects the ongoing session and notifies
				 the Correspondent Node (CN) about its new HoA. This mode is aiming to reduce packet loss during HNP renumbering, but the binding state corresponding to the old HNP SHOULD be marked, for example, as transient binding <xref target="RFC6058" />. Also, the LMA MUST stop broadcasting the routing information about the old HNP if the old HNP is no longer anchored at this LMA.
			 </t>
			 <t>
Hard mode
			 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
			 If HNP renumbering happens with the switchover of the LMA, hard mode is RECOMMENDED to keep the protocol simple. In this mode, the LMA deletes the binding state of the old HNP after it receives the UPA message from the MAG, and the LMA silently discards the packets destined to the old HNP.
			 </t></list></t>
	 		 </section>
	 
			 <section title="Message Format">
<t>
<list style="format (%d)">
			 <t>
			 UPN message
			 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
			 In the UPN message sent from the LMA to the MAG, the
			 notification reason is set to 2
			 (UPDATE-SESSION-PARAMETERS). 


   Besides, the HNP
   Option <xref target="RFC5213" /> containing the new HNP and the Mobile Node
   Identifier Option <xref target="RFC4283" /> (which identifies the MN) are contained
   as Mobility Options of UPN. 


 The order of the HNP Option and Mobile Node Identifier Option in the UPN message is not mandated here.
			 </t>
			 <t>
			 UPA message
			<vspace blankLines="1"/>
			 
			 The MAG sends this message in order to acknowledge
			 that it has received an UPN message with the (A) flag
			 set and to indicate the status after processing the
			 message. 


   If the MAG did not successfully renumber the HNP, which is required in
   the UPN message, the UPA message has the Status Code set to 128
   (FAILED-TO-UPDATE-SESSION-PARAMETERS), and the subsequent operation of
   the LMA is PMIPv6 service provider specific.

			 </t>
			 <t>
			 RA message
			 

			 	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
				 When the RA message is used by the MAG to
				 advise the new HNP, it contains two Prefix Information Options <xref target="RFC4861" /> <xref target="RFC4862" />. In the first Prefix Information Option, the old HNP is carried, and the related Preferred Lifetime is set to 0. In the second Prefix Information Option, the new HNP is carried with the Valid Lifetime, and Preferred Lifetime set to larger than 0.
			 </t>
			 <t>
			 DHCP message
			 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				 When the DHCP is used in PMIPv6 to configure
				 the addresses for the MN, new IPv6 address or
				 addresses (e.g., the HoA) will be generated
				 based on the new HNP, and the related DHCP
				 procedure is also triggered by the reception
				 of the UPN message <xref target="RFC3315"/>.
			 </t>
			 </list></t>
	     </section>
	     
		 <section title="Other Issues"> <t> In order to maintain the
		 reachability of the MN, the Domain Name System (DNS) resource
		 record corresponding to this MN MAY need to be updated when
		 the HNP of the MN changes <xref target="RFC3007" />. However, this is beyond the scope of this document. </t> </section>


			<section title="Security Considerations"> <t> The UPN and UPA messages in this
			document MUST be protected using end-to-end security
			association(s) offering integrity and data origin
			authentication as specified in <xref
			target="RFC5213"/> and <xref target="RFC7077"/>. </t>
			<t> When HNP renumbering is triggered, a new HNP
			SHOULD be allocated to the MN. The LMA MUST follow the
			procedure of PMIPv6 to make sure that only an
			authorized HNP can be assigned for the MN. In this
			way, the LMA is ready to be the topological anchor point
			of the new HNP, which is for that MN's
			exclusive use.</t> 

<t>
   Per <xref target="RFC4862" />, if the Valid Lifetime in a Prefix Information Option is set to
less than 2 hours in an unauthenticated RA, it is ignored.

   Thus, when the old HNP that is being deprecated is included in an RA from
   the MAG, the Valid Lifetime SHOULD be set to 2 hours (and the Preferred
   Lifetime set to 0) for an unauthenticated RA. 

 However, if the legality of the signaling messages exchanged between MAG and
 MN can be guaranteed, it MAY be acceptable to also set the Valid Lifetime to
 0 for an unauthenticated RA.</t></section>


<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6463" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6275" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7077" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3007" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4283" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174" ?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6058" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6879" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7010" ?>
</references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>
The work of Jong-Hyouk Lee was supported by 'The Cross-Ministry Giga KOREA Project' grant from the Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Planning, Korea.
</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
