<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8588" ipr="trust200902" category="std">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SHAKEN">Personal Assertion Token (PaSSporT) Extension for Signature-based Handling of Asserted information using toKENs (SHAKEN)</title>

    <author initials="C." surname="Wendt" fullname="Chris Wendt">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>
          <city>Philadelphia, PA  19103</city>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>chris-ietf@chriswendt.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Barnes" fullname="Mary Barnes">
      <organization>iconectiv</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mary.ietf.barnes@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2019" month="May"/>

    <area>ART</area>
    <workgroup>STIR</workgroup>


<keyword>SIP</keyword>
<keyword>Telephone Identity</keyword>
<keyword>Authenticated Identity</keyword>
<keyword>VoIP SPAM</keyword> 
<keyword>Robocall</keyword>


    <abstract>

<t>This document extends the Personal Assertion Token (PASSporT), which is a
token object that conveys cryptographically signed information about the
participants involved in communications.  
   The extension is defined based on the "Signature-based Handling
   of Asserted information using toKENs (SHAKEN)" specification by the
   ATIS/SIP Forum IP-NNI Task Group.  It provides both (1) a specific
   set of levels of confidence in the correctness of the originating
   identity of a call originated in a SIP-based telephone network as
   well as (2) an identifier that allows the Service
   Provider (SP) to uniquely identify the origin of the call within its
   network. 
</t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>The Signature-based Handling of Asserted information using toKENs (SHAKEN)
<xref target="ATIS-1000074"/> specification defines a framework for using
Secure Telephone Identity Revisited (STIR) protocols including the Personal
Assertion Token (PASSporT) <xref target="RFC8225"/>, SIP Authenticated
Identity Management <xref target="RFC8224"/>, and the STIR certificate
framework <xref target="RFC8226"/> for implementing the cryptographic
validation of an authorized originator of telephone calls using SIP.  Because
the current telephone network contains traffic originated from both VoIP and
TDM/SS7 (Time Division Multiplexing / Signaling System 7), there are many scenarios that need to be accounted for where PASSporT signatures may represent either direct or indirect call origination scenarios.  The SHAKEN  <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/> specification defines levels of attestation of the origination of the call as well as an origination identifier that can help create a unique association between the origin of a particular call to the point in the VoIP or TDM telephone network the call came from to identify, for example, either a customer or class of service that call represents.  This document specifies these values as claims to extend the base set of PASSporT claims.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

<t>In addition, the following terms are used in this document:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Verified association: Typically defined as an authenticated relationship between a customer and a device that initiated a call on behalf of that customer, for example, a subscriber account with a specific SIM card or set of SIP credentials.</t>
  <t>PASSporT: Defined in <xref target="RFC8225"/> is a JSON Web Token <xref target="RFC7519"/> defined specifically for securing the identity of an initiator of personal communication.  This document defines a specific extension to PASSporT.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="overview-of-shaken-passport-extension" title='Overview of
  "shaken" PASSporT Extension'>

<t>The SHAKEN framework is designed to use PASSporT <xref target="RFC8225"/>
as a method of asserting the caller's telephone identity.  In addition
to the PASSporT base claims, there are two additional claims that have been
defined for the needs of a service provider to signal information beyond just
the telephone identity. First, in order to help bridge the transition of the
state of the current telephone network (which has calls with no authentication
and non-SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> signaling not compatible with the use of
PASSporT and Secure Telephone Identity (STI) in general), there is an
attestation claim.  This provides three levels of attestation: a
full attestation when the service provider can fully attest to the calling
identity, a partial attestation when the service provider originated a
telephone call but cannot fully attest to the calling identity, and a gateway
attestation, which is the lowest level of attestation and represents the
service provider receiving a call from a telephone gateway that does not
support PASSporT or STI.</t>

<t>The second claim is a unique origination identifier that should be used by
the service provider to identify different sources of telephone calls to
support a traceback mechanism that can be used for enforcement and
identification of a source of illegitimate calls.</t>

<t>The use of the compact form of PASSporT is not specified in this document
and is not specified for use in SHAKEN <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/>.</t>

<t>The next two sections define these new claims.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="attest" title='PASSporT "attest" Claim'>

<t>This indicator allows for both identifying the service provider that is
vouching for the call as well as clearly indicating what information the
service provider is attesting to.  The "attest" claim can be one of the
following three values: 'A', 'B', or 'C'. These values correspond to 'Full
Attestation', 'Partial Attestation', and 'Gateway Attestation',
respectively. See <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/> for the definitions of these
three levels of attestation.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="origid" title='PASSporT "origid" Claim'>

<t>The purpose of the "origid" claim is described in <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/>.
The value of "origid" claim is a Universally Unique Identifier (UUID) as defined in <xref target="RFC4122"/>. Please refer to <xref target="privacy"/> for a discussion of the privacy considerations around the use of this value.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="example-shaken-passport" title='Example "shaken" PASSporT'>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Protected Header
{
   "alg":"ES256",
   "typ":"passport",
   "ppt":"shaken",
   "x5u":"https://cert.example.org/passport.cer"
}
Payload
{
   "attest":"A"
   "dest":{"tn":["12155550131"]}
   "iat":"1443208345",
   "orig":{"tn":"12155550121"},
   "origid":"123e4567-e89b-12d3-a456-426655440000"
}
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="using-shaken-in-sip" title='Using "shaken" in SIP'>

<t>
   The use of the "shaken" PASSporT type and the "attest" and "origid"
   claims for SIP is formally defined in <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/> using the SIP
   <xref target="RFC3261"/> Identity header field defined in <xref target="RFC8224"/>.
</t>

</section>
<section anchor="order-of-claim-keys" title="Order of Claim Keys">

<t>The order of the claim keys MUST follow the rules of Section 9 of <xref
target="RFC8225"/>; the claim keys MUST appear in lexicographic
order. Therefore, the claim keys discussed in this document appear in the
PASSporT Payload in the following order:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>attest</t>
  <t>dest</t>
  <t>iat</t>
  <t>orig</t>
  <t>origid</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This document defines a new PASSporT <xref target="RFC8225"/> extension. The considerations related to the security of the PASSporT object itself are the same as those described in <xref target="RFC8225"/>.</t>

<t><xref target="RFC8224"/> defines how to compare the values of the "dest", "orig", and
"iat" claims against fields in a SIP message containing a PASSporT as part of validating that request.  The values of the new "attest" and "origid" claims added by this extension are not used in such a validation step. They are not compared to fields in the SIP message. Instead, they simply carry additional information from the signer to the consumer of the PASSporT. This new information shares the same
integrity protection and non-repudiation properties as the base claims in the PASSporT.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">

<t>As detailed in Section 26 of <xref target="RFC3261"/>, SIP messages inherently carry identifying information of the caller and callee. The addition of STIR cryptographically attests that the signing party vouches for the information given about the callee, as is discussed in the Privacy Considerations of <xref target="RFC8224"/>.</t>

<t>SHAKEN <xref target="ATIS-1000074"/> furthermore adds an "origid" value to the STIR PASSporT, which is an opaque unique identifier representing an element on the path of a given SIP request. This identifier is generated by an originating telephone service provider to identify where within their network (e.g. a gateway or particular service element) a call was initiated; "origid" can facilitate forensic analysis of call origins when identifying and stopping bad actors trying to spoof identities or make fraudulent calls.</t>

<t>The opacity of the "origid" claim value is intended to minimize exposure of
information about the origination of calls labeled with an "origid" value. It
is therefore RECOMMENDED that implementations generate a unique "origid" value
per call in such a way that only the generator of the "origid" can determine
when two "origid" values represent the same or different elements. If deployed
systems instead use a common or related "origid" for service elements in their
network, the potential for discovering patterns through correlation of those
calls exists. This could allow a recipient of calls to, for instance, learn
that a set of callers are using a particular service or coming through a
common gateway. It is expected that SHAKEN PASSporTs are shared only within an
<xref target="RFC3324"/> trust domain and will be stripped before calls exit
that trust domain, but this information still could be used by analytics on
intermediary and terminating systems to reveal information that could include
geographic location and even device-level information, depending on how the
"origid" is generated.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<section anchor="json-web-token-claims" title="JSON Web Token claims">

<t>IANA has added two new claims to the "JSON Web Token Claims" registry as defined in <xref target="RFC7519"/>.</t>

<figure><artwork>
Claim Name: attest
Claim Description: Attestation level as defined in SHAKEN framework
Change Controller: IESG
Specification Document(s): RFC 8588

Claim Name: origid
Claim Description: Originating Identifier as defined in SHAKEN 
   framework
Change Controller: IESG
Specification Document(s): RFC 8588
</artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="passport-types" title="PASSporT Types">

<t>IANA has added a new entry in the "Personal
Assertion Token (PASSporT) Extensions" registry for the type "shaken", which is
specified in this document.</t>

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

<reference  anchor="RFC8224" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8224'>
<front>
<title>Authenticated Identity Management in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'><organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Jennings' fullname='C. Jennings'><organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'><organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Wendt' fullname='C. Wendt'><organization /></author>
<date year='2018' month='February' />
<abstract><t>The baseline security mechanisms in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) are inadequate for cryptographically assuring the identity of the end users that originate SIP requests, especially in an interdomain context.  This document defines a mechanism for securely identifying originators of SIP requests.  It does so by defining a SIP header field for conveying a signature used for validating the identity and for conveying a reference to the credentials of the signer.</t><t>This document obsoletes RFC 4474.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8224'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8224'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC8225" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8225'>
<front>
<title>PASSporT: Personal Assertion Token</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Wendt' fullname='C. Wendt'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'><organization /></author>
<date year='2018' month='February' />
<abstract><t>This document defines a method for creating and validating a token that cryptographically verifies an originating identity or, more generally, a URI or telephone number representing the originator of personal communications.  The Personal Assertion Token, PASSporT, is cryptographically signed to protect the integrity of the identity of the originator and to verify the assertion of the identity information at the destination.  The cryptographic signature is defined with the intention that it can confidently verify the originating persona even when the signature is sent to the destination party over an insecure channel.  PASSporT is particularly useful for many personal-communications applications over IP networks and other multi-hop interconnection scenarios where the originating and destination parties may not have a direct trusted relationship.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8225'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8225'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC8226" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8226'>
<front>
<title>Secure Telephone Identity Credentials: Certificates</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Turner' fullname='S. Turner'><organization /></author>
<date year='2018' month='February' />
<abstract><t>In order to prevent the impersonation of telephone numbers on the Internet, some kind of credential system needs to exist that cryptographically asserts authority over telephone numbers.  This document describes the use of certificates in establishing authority over telephone numbers, as a component of a broader architecture for managing telephone numbers as identities in protocols like SIP.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8226'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8226'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC4122" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4122'>
<front>
<title>A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Leach' fullname='P. Leach'><organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Mealling' fullname='M. Mealling'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Salz' fullname='R. Salz'><organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='July' />
<abstract><t>This specification defines a Uniform Resource Name namespace for UUIDs (Universally Unique IDentifier), also known as GUIDs (Globally Unique IDentifier).  A UUID is 128 bits long, and can guarantee uniqueness across space and time.  UUIDs were originally used in the Apollo Network Computing System and later in the Open Software Foundation\'s (OSF) Distributed Computing Environment (DCE), and then in Microsoft Windows platforms.</t><t>This specification is derived from the DCE specification with the kind permission of the OSF (now known as The Open Group).  Information from earlier versions of the DCE specification have been incorporated into this document.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4122'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC4122'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor="RFC7519" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7519'>
<front>
<title>JSON Web Token (JWT)</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Jones' fullname='M. Jones'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Bradley' fullname='J. Bradley'><organization /></author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Sakimura' fullname='N. Sakimura'><organization /></author>
<date year='2015' month='May' />
<abstract><t>JSON Web Token (JWT) is a compact, URL-safe means of representing claims to be transferred between two parties.  The claims in a JWT are encoded as a JSON object that is used as the payload of a JSON Web Signature (JWS) structure or as the plaintext of a JSON Web Encryption (JWE) structure, enabling the claims to be digitally signed or integrity protected with a Message Authentication Code (MAC) and/or encrypted.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7519'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7519'/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="ATIS-1000074" target="https://access.atis.org/apps/group_public/download.php/32237/ATIS-1000074.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Signature-based Handling of Asserted information using toKENs (SHAKEN)</title>
    <author >
      <organization>ATIS/SIP Forum IP-NNI Task Group</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2017" month="January"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

<reference  anchor="RFC3261" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3261'>
<front>
<title>SIP: Session Initiation Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Rosenberg' fullname='J. Rosenberg'><organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'><organization /></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Camarillo' fullname='G. Camarillo'><organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Johnston' fullname='A. Johnston'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='J. Peterson'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Sparks' fullname='R. Sparks'><organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='M. Handley'><organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Schooler' fullname='E. Schooler'><organization /></author>
<date year='2002' month='June' />
<abstract><t>This document describes Session Initiation Protocol (SIP), an application-layer control (signaling) protocol for creating, modifying, and terminating sessions with one or more participants.  These sessions include Internet telephone calls, multimedia distribution, and multimedia conferences.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3261'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3261'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor="RFC3324" target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3324'>
<front>
<title>Short Term Requirements for Network Asserted Identity</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Watson' fullname='M. Watson'><organization /></author>
<date year='2002' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3324'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3324'/>
</reference>

  </references>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

<t>The authors would like to thank those that helped review and contribute to
this document including specific contributions from Jon Peterson, Russ
Housley, Robert Sparks, and Andrew Jurczak.  The authors would like to
acknowledge the work of the ATIS/SIP Forum IP&nbhy;NNI Task Force to develop the
concepts behind this document.</t>

</section>

</back>
</rfc>

