<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="8280" category="info" submissionType="IRTF" consensus="yes">

   <front>
     <title abbrev="Human Rights Protocol Considerations">Research into Human Rights Protocol Considerations</title>

     <author initials="N." surname="ten Oever" fullname="Niels ten Oever">
       <organization>ARTICLE 19</organization>
       <address>
         <email>mail@nielstenoever.net</email>
       </address>
     </author>

     <author initials="C.J.N." surname="Cath" fullname="Corinne Cath">
       <organization>Oxford Internet Institute</organization>
       <address>
         <email>corinnecath@gmail.com</email>
       </address>
     </author>

     <date year="2017" month="October"/>

     <workgroup>Human Rights Protocol Considerations</workgroup>

     <abstract>
<t>This document aims to propose guidelines for human rights considerations,
similar to the work done on the guidelines for privacy considerations
(RFC 6973). The other parts of this document explain the background of the
guidelines and how they were developed.</t>

<t>This document is the first milestone in a longer-term research effort.
It has been reviewed by the Human Rights Protocol Considerations (HRPC)
Research Group and also by individuals from outside the research group.
</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>"There's a freedom about the Internet: As long as we accept the
rules of sending packets around, we can send packets containing
anything to anywhere." <xref target="Berners-Lee"/></t>

<t>"The Internet isn't value-neutral, and neither is the IETF."
<xref target="RFC3935"/></t>

<t>The ever-growing interconnectedness of the Internet and society increases
the impact of the Internet on the lives of individuals. Because of this, the
design and development of the Internet infrastructure also have a growing
impact on society. This has led to a broad recognition that human rights <xref
target="UDHR"/> <xref target="ICCPR"/> <xref target="ICESCR"/> have a role in
the development and management of the Internet <xref target="UNGA2013"/> <xref
target="NETmundial"/>. It has also been argued that the Internet should be
strengthened as an enabling environment for human rights <xref
target="Brown"/>.</t>

<t>This document aims to (1) expose the relationship between protocols and
human rights, (2)&nbsp;propose possible guidelines to protect the Internet
as an enabling environment for human rights in future protocol development, in
a manner similar to the work done for privacy considerations <xref
target="RFC6973"/>, and (3)&nbsp;increase the awareness, in both the human
rights community and the technical community, of the importance of the
technical workings of the Internet and its impact on human rights.</t>

<t>Document authors who want to apply this work to their own can go
directly to
<xref target="model-for-developing-human-rights-protocol-considerations"/>
of this document.</t>

<t>Open, secure, and reliable connectivity is necessary (although not
sufficient) to exercise human rights such as freedom of expression and freedom
of association <xref target="FOC"/>, as defined in the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights <xref target="UDHR"/>. The purpose of the Internet is to be a
global network of networks that provides unfettered connectivity to all users,
and for any content <xref target="RFC1958"/>. This objective of stimulating
global connectivity contributes to the Internet's role as an enabler of human
rights. The Internet has given people a platform to exchange opinions and
gather information; it has enabled people of different backgrounds and
genders to participate in the public debate; it has also allowed people to
congregate and organize. Next to that, the strong commitment to security <xref
target="RFC1984"/> <xref target="RFC3365"/> and privacy <xref
target="RFC6973"/> <xref target="RFC7258"/> in the Internet's architectural
design contributes to the strengthening of the Internet as an
enabling environment for human rights. One could even argue that the Internet
is not only an enabler of human rights but that human rights lie at the base
of, and are ingrained in, the architecture of the networks that make up the
Internet. Internet connectivity increases the capacity for individuals to
exercise their rights; the core of the Internet -- its architectural design --
is therefore closely intertwined with the human rights framework <xref
target="CathFloridi"/>. The quintessential link between the Internet's
infrastructure and human rights has been argued by many. <xref
target="Bless1"/>, for instance, argues that "to a certain extent, the
Internet and its protocols have already facilitated the realization of human
rights, e.g., the freedom of assembly and expression. In contrast, measures
of censorship and pervasive surveillance violate fundamental human rights."
<xref target="DeNardis15"/> argues that "Since the first hints of Internet
commercialization and internationalization, the IETF has supported strong
security in protocol design and has sometimes served as a force resisting
protocol-enabled surveillance features." By doing so, the IETF enabled the
manifestation of the right to privacy, through the Internet's
infrastructure. Additionally, access to freely available information gives
people access to knowledge that enables them to help satisfy other human
rights; as such, the Internet increasingly becomes a precondition for human
rights rather than a supplement.</t>

<t>Human rights can be in conflict with each other, such as the right to
freedom of expression and the right to privacy. In such cases, the different
affected rights need to be balanced. To do this, it is crucial that the
impacts on rights are clearly documented in order to mitigate potential
harm. This research aims to ultimately contribute to making that process
tangible and practical for protocol developers. Technology can never be
fully equated with a human right. Whereas a specific technology might be a
strong enabler of a specific human right, it might have an adverse impact on
another human right. In this case, decisions on design and deployment need to
take this into account.</t>

 <t>The open nature of the initial technical design and its open standards, as
 well as developments like open source, fostered freedom of communication.
 What emerged was a network of networks that could enable everyone to connect
 and to exchange data, information, and code.  For many, enabling such
 connections became a core value. However, as the scale and the
 commercialization of the Internet grew, topics like access, rights, and
 connectivity have been forced to compete with other values. Therefore,
 important characteristics of the Internet that enable human rights might be
 degraded if they're not properly defined, described, and protected as
 such. Conversely, not protecting characteristics that enable human rights
 could also result in (partial) loss of functionality and connectivity,
 along with other inherent parts of the Internet's architecture of
 networks. New protocols, particularly those that upgrade the core
 infrastructure of the network, should be designed to continue to enable
 fundamental human rights.</t>

 <t>The IETF has produced guidelines and procedures to ensure and galvanize the
 privacy of individuals and security of the network in protocol
 development. This document aims to explore the possibility of developing
 similar procedures for guidelines for human rights considerations to
 ensure that protocols developed in the IETF do not have an adverse impact on
 the realization of human rights on the Internet. By carefully considering
 the answers to the questions posed in <xref
 target="model-for-developing-human-rights-protocol-considerations"/> of
 this document, document authors should be (1)&nbsp;able to produce a
 comprehensive analysis that can serve as the basis for discussion on
 whether the protocol adequately protects against specific human rights
 threats and (2)&nbsp;potentially stimulated to think about alternative
 design choices.</t>

 <t>This document was developed within the framework of the Human Rights
 Protocol Considerations (HRPC) Research Group, based on discussions on
 the HRPC mailing list (<xref target="research-group-information"/>);
 this document was also extensively discussed during HRPC sessions. This
 document has received eleven in-depth reviews on the mailing list, and it
 received many comments from inside and outside the IRTF and IETF
 communities.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="vocabulary-used" title="Vocabulary Used">

 <t>In the discussion of human rights and Internet architecture, concepts
 developed in computer science, networking, law, policy-making, and advocacy
 are coming together <xref target="Dutton"/> <xref target="Kaye"/>
 <xref target="Franklin"/> <xref target="RFC1958"/>. The same concepts might
 have a very different meaning and implications in other areas of expertise. In
 order to foster a constructive interdisciplinary debate and minimize
 differences in interpretation, the following glossary is provided. It builds
 as much as possible on existing definitions; when definitions were not
 available in IETF documents, definitions were taken from other
 Standards Development Organizations (SDOs) or academic literature.
 </t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
   <t hangText='Accessibility:'>
   "Full Internet Connectivity", as described in <xref target="RFC4084"/>,
   to provide unfettered access to the Internet.</t>
   <t>The design of protocols, services, or implementations that provide an
   enabling environment for people with disabilities.</t>
   <t>The ability to receive information available on the Internet.</t>
   <t hangText='Anonymity:'>
   The condition of an identity being unknown or concealed <xref
   target="RFC4949"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Anonymous:'>
   A state of an individual in which an observer or attacker cannot identify
   the individual within a set of other individuals (the anonymity set) <xref
   target="RFC6973"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Authenticity:'>
   The property of being genuine and able to be verified and be trusted <xref
   target="RFC4949"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Blocking:'>
   The practice of preventing access to resources in the aggregate <xref
   target="RFC7754"/>. Both blocking and filtering can be implemented at the
   level of "services" (web hosting or video streaming, for example) or at the
   level of particular "content" <xref target="RFC7754"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Censorship:'>
   Technical mechanisms, including both blocking and filtering, that certain
   political or private actors around the world use to block or degrade
   Internet traffic. For further details on the various elements of Internet
   censorship, see <xref target="Hall"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Censorship resistance:'>
   Methods and measures to mitigate Internet censorship.</t>
   <t hangText='Confidentiality:'>
   The property that data is not disclosed to system entities unless they have
   been authorized to know the data <xref target="RFC4949"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Connectivity:'>
   The extent to which a device or network is able to reach other devices or
   networks to exchange data. The Internet is the tool for providing global
   connectivity <xref target="RFC1958"/>. Different types of connectivity are
   further specified in <xref target="RFC4084"/>.</t>
   <t>The end-to-end principle, interoperability, distributed architecture,
   resilience, reliability, and robustness in combination constitute the
   enabling factors that result in connectivity to, and on, the Internet.</t>
   <t hangText='Content agnosticism:'>
   Treating network traffic identically regardless of content.</t>
   <t hangText='Decentralized:'>
   Implementation or deployment of standards, protocols, or systems without
   one single point of control.</t>
   <t hangText='End-to-end principle:'>
   The principle that application-specific functions should not be embedded
   into the network and thus stay at the endpoints. In many cases, especially
   when dealing with failures, the right decisions can only be made with the
   corresponding application-specific knowledge, which is available at
   endpoints not in the network.</t>
   <t>The end-to-end principle is one of the key architectural guidelines of
   the Internet. The argument in favor of the end&nbhy;to&nbhy;end approach
   to system design is laid out in the fundamental papers by Saltzer, Reed, and
   Clark <xref target="Saltzer"/> <xref target="Clark"/>. In these papers,
   the authors argue in favor of radical simplification: system designers
   should only build the essential and shared functions into the network, as
   most functions can only be implemented at network endpoints. Building
   features into the network for the benefit of certain applications will come
   at the expense of others. As such, in&nbsp;general system designers should
   attempt to steer clear of building anything into the network that is not a
   bare necessity for its functioning. Following the end&nbhy;to&nbhy;end
   principle is crucial for innovation, as it makes innovation at the edges
   possible without having to make changes to the network, and it protects the
   robustness of the network. <xref target="RFC2775"/> further elaborates on
   various aspects of end-to-end connectivity.</t>
   <t hangText='Federation:'>
   The possibility of connecting autonomous and possibly centralized systems
   into a single system without a central authority.</t>
   <t hangText='Filtering:'>
   The practice of preventing access to specific resources within an aggregate
   <xref target="RFC7754"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Heterogeneity:'>"The Internet is characterized by heterogeneity
   on many levels: devices and nodes, router scheduling algorithms and queue
   management mechanisms, routing protocols, levels of multiplexing,
   protocol versions and implementations, underlying link layers
   (e.g., point-to-point, multi-access links, wireless, FDDI, etc.),
   in the traffic mix and in the levels of congestion at different
   times and places. Moreover, as the Internet is composed of autonomous
   organizations and internet service providers, each with their own
   separate policy concerns, there is a large heterogeneity of administrative
   domains and pricing structures." <xref target="FIArch"/>
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   As a result, per <xref target="FIArch"/>, the heterogeneity principle
   proposed in <xref target="RFC1958"/> needs to be supported by design.</t>
   <t hangText='Human rights:'>
   Principles and norms that are indivisible, interrelated, unalienable,
   universal, and mutually reinforcing.  Human rights have been
   codified in national and international bodies of law. The Universal
   Declaration of Human Rights <xref target="UDHR"/> is the most well-known
   document in the history of human rights. The aspirations from
   <xref target="UDHR"/> were later codified into treaties such as the
   International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights <xref
   target="ICCPR"/> and the International Covenant on Economic, Social
   and Cultural Rights <xref target="ICESCR"/>, after which signatory
   countries were obliged to reflect them in their national bodies of law.
   There is also a broad recognition that not only states have obligations
   vis&nbhy;a&nbhy;vis human rights, but non&nbhy;state actors do as well.</t>
   <t hangText='Integrity:'>
   The property that data has not been changed, destroyed, or lost in an
   unauthorized or accidental manner <xref target="RFC4949"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Internationalization (i18n):'>
   The practice of making protocols, standards, and implementations usable in
   different languages and scripts (see <xref target="localization"/>
   ("Localization")).</t>
   <t>"In the IETF, 'internationalization' means to add or improve the handling
   of non&nbhy;ASCII text in a protocol" <xref target="RFC6365"/>.</t>
   <t>A different perspective, more appropriate to protocols that are designed
   for global use from the beginning, is the definition used by the World Wide
   Web Consortium (W3C) <xref target="W3Ci18nDef"/>: "Internationalization is
   the design and development of a product, application or document content
   that enables easy localization for target audiences that vary in culture,
   region, or language."</t>
   <t>Many protocols that handle text only handle one charset (US&nbhy;ASCII),
   or they leave the question of encoding up to local guesswork (which leads,
   of course, to interoperability problems) <xref target="RFC3536"/>. If
   multiple charsets are permitted, they must be explicitly identified <xref
   target="RFC2277"/>.  Adding non&nbhy;ASCII text to a protocol allows the
   protocol to handle more scripts, hopefully all scripts in use in the world.
   In today's world, that is normally best accomplished by allowing
   Unicode encoded in UTF-8 only, thereby shifting conversion issues away from
   ad&nbsp;hoc choices.</t>
   <t hangText='Interoperable:'>
   A property of a documented standard or protocol that allows different
   independent implementations to work with each other without any restriction
   on functionality.</t>
   <t hangText='Localization (l10n):'>
   The practice of translating an implementation to make it functional in a
   specific language or for users in a specific locale
   (see <xref target="internationalization"/> ("Internationalization")).</t>
   <t>(cf.&nbsp;<xref target="RFC6365"/>): The process of adapting an
   internationalized application platform or application to a specific cultural
   environment.  In localization, the same semantics are preserved while the
   syntax may be changed <xref target="FRAMEWORK"/>.</t>
   <t>Localization is the act of tailoring an application for a different
   language, script, or culture.  Some internationalized applications can
   handle a wide variety of languages.  Typical users only understand a small
   number of languages, so the program must be tailored to interact with users
   in just the languages they know. The major work of localization is
   translating the user interface and documentation.  Localization involves not
   only changing the language interaction but also other relevant changes,
   such as display of numbers, dates, currency, and so on.  The better
   internationalized an application is, the easier it is to localize it for a
   particular language and character-encoding scheme.</t>

   <t hangText='Open standards:'>
   Conform with <xref target="RFC2026"/>, which states the following:
   "Various national and international standards bodies, such as ANSI, ISO,
   IEEE, and ITU&nbhy;T, develop a variety of protocol and service
   specifications that are similar to Technical Specifications defined here.
   National and international groups also publish 'implementors' agreements'
   that are analogous to Applicability Statements, capturing a body of
   implementation-specific detail concerned with the practical application of
   their standards.  All of these are considered to be 'open external
   standards' for the purposes of the Internet Standards Process."</t> 
   <t hangText='Openness:'>
   Absence of centralized points of control -- "a feature that is assumed to
   make it easy for new users to join and new uses to unfold" <xref
   target="Brown"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Permissionless innovation:'>
   The freedom and ability to freely create and deploy new protocols on top of
   the communications constructs that currently exist.</t>
   <t hangText='Privacy:'>
   The right of an entity (normally a person), acting on its own behalf, to
   determine the degree to which it will interact with its environment,
   including the degree to which the entity is willing to share its personal
   information with others <xref target="RFC4949"/>.</t>
   <t>The right of individuals to control or influence what information related
   to them may be collected and stored, and by whom and to whom that
   information may be disclosed.</t>
   <t>Privacy is a broad concept relating to the protection of individual or
   group autonomy and the relationship between an individual or group and
   society, including government, companies, and private individuals. It is
   often summarized as "the right to be left alone", but it encompasses a wide
   range of rights, including protections from intrusions into family and home
   life, control of sexual and reproductive rights, and communications secrecy.
   It is commonly recognized as a core right that underpins human dignity and
   other values such as freedom of association and freedom of speech.</t>
   <t>The right to privacy is also recognized in nearly every national
   constitution and in most international human rights treaties. It has been
   adjudicated upon by both international and regional bodies. The right to
   privacy is also legally protected at the national level through provisions
   in civil and/or criminal codes.</t>
   <t hangText='Reliability:'>
   Ensures that a protocol will execute its function consistently
   as described and function without unexpected results. A system that is
   reliable degenerates gracefully and will have a documented way to announce
   degradation. It also has mechanisms to recover from failure gracefully and,
   if applicable, allow for partial healing <xref target="dict"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Resilience:'>
   The maintaining of dependability and performance in the face of
   unanticipated changes and circumstances <xref target="Meyer"/>.</t>
   <t hangText='Robustness:'>
   The resistance of protocols and their implementations to errors, and
   resistance to involuntary, legal, or malicious attempts to disrupt their
   modes of operation <xref target="RFC760"/> <xref target="RFC791"/> <xref
   target="RFC793"/> <xref target="RFC1122"/>. Or, framed more positively,
   a system can provide functionality consistently and without errors despite
   involuntary, legal, or malicious attempts to disrupt its mode of
   operation.</t>
   <t hangText='Scalability:'>
   The ability to handle increased or decreased system parameters (number of
   end systems, users, data flows, routing entries, etc.) predictably within
   defined expectations. There should be a clear definition of its scope and
   applicability. The limits of a system's scalability should be
   defined. Growth or shrinkage of these parameters is typically considered by
   orders of magnitude.</t>

   <t hangText='Strong encryption / cryptography:'>
   Used to describe a cryptographic algorithm that would require a large
   amount of computational power to defeat it <xref target="RFC4949"/>. In
   the modern usage of the definition of "strong encryption", this refers to
   an amount of computing power currently not available, not even to major
   state-level actors.</t>

   <t hangText='Transparency:'>
   In this context, linked to the comprehensibility of a protocol in relation
   to the choices it makes for users, protocol developers, and implementers,
   and to its outcome.</t>
   <t>Outcome transparency is linked to the comprehensibility of the effects
   of a protocol in relation to the choices it makes for users, protocol
   developers, and implementers, including the comprehensibility of possible
   unintended consequences of protocol choices (e.g., lack of authenticity may
   lead to lack of integrity and negative externalities).</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="research-questions" title="Research Questions">

 <t>The Human Rights Protocol Considerations (HRPC) Research Group in the
 Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) embarked on its mission to answer the
 following two questions, which are also the main two questions that this
 document seeks to answer:</t>

 <t><list style="numbers">
   <t>How can Internet protocols and standards impact human rights,
   by either enabling them or creating a restrictive environment?</t>
   <t>Can guidelines be developed to improve informed and transparent
   decision&nbhy;making about the potential impact of protocols on
   human rights?</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="literature-and-discussion-review" title="Literature and Discussion Review">

 <t>Protocols and standards are regularly seen as merely performing technical
 functions. However, these protocols and standards do not exist outside of
 their technical context, nor do they exist outside of their political,
 historical, economic, legal, or cultural context. This is best exemplified
 by the way in which some Internet processes and protocols have become part and
 parcel of political processes and public policies: one only has to look at the
 IANA transition, <xref target="RFC7258"/> ("Pervasive Monitoring Is an
 Attack"), or global innovation policy, for concrete examples
 <xref target="DeNardis15"/>. According to <xref target="Abbate"/>,
 "protocols are politics by other means." This statement would probably not
 garner IETF consensus, but it nonetheless reveals that protocols are
 based on decision&nbhy;making, most often by humans. In this process, the
 values and ideas about the role that a particular technology should perform
 in society are embedded into the design. Often, these design decisions are
 partly "purely technical" and partly inspired by a certain world view of how
 technology should function that is inspired by personal, corporate, and
 political views. Within the community of IETF participants, there is a
 strong desire to solve technical problems and to minimize engagement with
 political processes and non&nbhy;protocol-related political issues.</t>

 <t>Since the late 1990s, a burgeoning group of academics and practitioners
 researched questions surrounding the societal impact of protocols, as well
 as the politics of protocols. These studies vary in focus and scope: some
 focus on specific standards <xref target="Davidson-etal"/> <xref
 target="Musiani"/>; others look into the political, legal, commercial, or
 social impact of protocols <xref target="BrownMarsden"/> <xref
 target="Lessig"/> <xref target="Mueller"/>; and yet others look at how the
 engineers' personal set of values get translated into technology <xref
 target="Abbate"/> <xref target="CathFloridi"/> <xref target="DeNardis15"/>
 <xref target="WynsbergheMoura"/>.</t>

 <t>Commercial and political influences on the management of the Internet's
 infrastructure are well documented in the academic literature and will thus
 not be discussed here; see <xref target="Benkler"/>,
 <xref target="Brown-etal"/>, <xref target="DeNardis15"/>,
 <xref target="Lessig"/>, <xref target="Mueller"/>, and
 <xref target="Zittrain"/>. It is sufficient to say that the IETF community
 consistently tries to push back against the standardization of surveillance
 and certain other issues that negatively influence an end&nbsp;user's
 experience of, and trust in, the Internet <xref target="DeNardis14"/>. The
 role that human rights play in engineering, infrastructure maintenance, and
 protocol design is much less clear.</t>

 <t>It is very important to understand how protocols and standards impact
 human rights, in particular because SDOs are increasingly becoming venues
 where social values (like human rights) are discussed, although often from a
 technological point of view. These SDOs are becoming a new focal point for
 discussions about "values by design" and the role of technical engineers in
 protecting or enabling human rights <xref target="Brown-etal"/> <xref
 target="Clark-etal"/> <xref target="DeNardis14"/> <xref target="CathFloridi"/>
 <xref target="Lessig"/> <xref target="Rachovitsa"/>.</t>

 <t>In the academic literature, five clear positions can be discerned in
 relation to the role of human rights in protocol design and how to account for
 these human rights in protocol development: Clark et&nbsp;al.&nbsp;<xref
 target="Clark-etal"/> argue that there is a need to design "for variation in
 outcome -- so that the outcome can be different in different places, and the
 tussle takes place within the design (...)" [as] "Rigid designs will be broken;
 designs that permit variation will flex under pressure and survive." They
 hold that human rights should not be hard-coded into protocols for
 three reasons: First, the rights in the UDHR are not absolute. Second,
 technology is not the only tool in the tussle over human rights. And last but
 not least, it is dangerous to make promises that can't be kept. The open
 nature of the Internet will never, they argue, be enough to fully protect
 individuals' human rights.</t>

 <t>Conversely, Brown et al.&nbsp;<xref target="Brown-etal"/> state that "some
 key, universal values -- of which the UDHR is the most legitimate expression --
 should be baked into the architecture at design time." They argue that design
 choices have offline consequences and are able to shape the power positions
 of groups or individuals in society. As such, the individuals making these
 technical decisions have a moral obligation to take into account the impact of
 their decisions on society and, by extension, human rights.
 Brown et al.&nbsp;recognize that values and the implementation of human
 rights vary across the globe. Yet they argue that all members of the United
 Nations have found "common agreement on the values proclaimed in the
 Universal Declaration of Human Rights. In looking for the most legitimate set
 of global values to embed in the future Internet architectures, the UDHR has
 the democratic assent of a significant fraction of the planet's population,
 through their elected representatives."</t>

 <t>The main disagreement between these two academic positions lies mostly in
 the question of whether (1)&nbsp;a particular value system should be
 embedded into the Internet's architectures or (2)&nbsp;the architectures
 need to account for a varying set of values.</t>

 <t>A third position, which is similar to that of Brown et&nbsp;al., is
 taken by <xref target="Broeders"/>, in which Broeders argues that "we must
 find ways to continue guaranteeing the overall integrity and functionality of
 the public core of the Internet." He argues that the best way to do this
 is by declaring the backbone of the Internet -- which includes the TCP/IP
 protocol suite, numerous standards, the Domain Name System (DNS), and routing
 protocols -- a common public good. This is a different approach than those of
 <xref target="Clark-etal"/> and <xref target="Brown-etal"/> because Broeders
 does not suggest that social values should (or should not) be explicitly coded
 into the Internet, but rather that the existing infrastructure should be seen
 as an entity of public value.</t>

 <t>Bless and Orwat <xref target="Bless2"/> represent a fourth position. They
 argue that it is too early to make any definitive claims but that there is a
 need for more careful analysis of the impact of protocol design choices on
 human rights. They also argue that it is important to search for solutions
 that "create awareness in the technical community about impact of design
 choices on social values" and "work towards a methodology for co-design of
 technical and institutional systems."</t>

 <t>Berners-Lee and Halpin <xref target="BernersLeeHalpin"/> represent a
 fifth position. They argue that the Internet could lead to even newer
 capacities, and these capacities may over time be viewed as new kinds of
 rights. For example, Internet access may be viewed as a human right in and of
 itself if it is taken to be a precondition for other rights, even if it could
 not have been predicted at the time that the UDHR was written (after the end
 of World War&nbsp;II).</t>

 <t>It is important to contextualize the technical discussion with the academic
 discussions on this issue. The academic discussions are also important to
 document, as they inform the position of the authors of this document. The
 research group's position is that hard-coding human rights into protocols is
 complicated and changes with the context. At this point, it is difficult
 to say whether or not hard-coding human rights into protocols is wise or
 feasible. Additionally, there are many human rights, but not all are
 relevant for information and communications technologies (ICTs). A partial
 catalog (with references to sources) of human rights related to ICTs can be
 found in <xref target="Hill2014"/>. It is, however, important to make
 conscious and explicit design decisions that take into account the human
 rights protocol considerations guidelines developed below. This will
 contribute to the understanding of the impact that protocols can have on human
 rights, for both developers and users. In addition, it contributes to
 (1)&nbsp;the careful consideration of the impact that a specific protocol
 might have on human rights and (2)&nbsp;the dissemination of the practice of
 documenting protocol design decisions related to human rights.
 </t>

 <t>Pursuant to the principle of constant change, because the function and
 scope of the Internet evolve, so does the role of the IETF in developing
 standards. Internet Standards are adopted based on a series of criteria,
 including high technical quality, support by community consensus, and their
 overall benefit to the Internet. The latter calls for an assessment of the
 interests of all affected parties and the specifications' impact on the
 Internet's users. In this respect, the effective exercise of the human rights
 of the Internet users is a relevant consideration that needs to be appreciated
 in the standardization process insofar as it is directly linked to the
 reliability and core values of the Internet <xref target="RFC1958"/>
 <xref target="RFC2775"/> <xref target="RFC3439"/>
 <xref target="RFC3724"/>.</t>

 <t>This document details the steps taken in the research into human rights
 protocol considerations by the HRPC Research Group to clarify the relationship
 between technical concepts used in the IETF and human rights. This document
 sets out some preliminary steps and considerations for engineers to take into
 account when developing standards and protocols.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="methodology" title="Methodology">

 <t>Mapping the relationship between human rights, protocols, and architectures
 is a new research challenge that requires a good amount of interdisciplinary
 and cross-organizational cooperation to develop a consistent methodology.</t>

 <t>The methodological choices made in this document are based on the
 political-science-based method of discourse analysis and ethnographic research
 methods <xref target="Cath"/>. This work departs from the assumption that
 language reflects the understanding of concepts. Or, as <xref target="Jabri"/>
 holds, policy documents are "social relations represented in texts where the
 language contained within these texts is used to construct meaning and
 representation." This process happens in society <xref target="Denzin"/> and
 manifests itself in institutions and organizations <xref target="King"/>,
 exposed using the ethnographic methods of semi-structured interviews and
 participant observation. Or, in non&nbhy;academic language, the way the
 language in IETF/IRTF documents describes and approaches the issues they are
 trying to address is an indication of the underlying social assumptions and
 relationships of the engineers to their engineering. By reading and analyzing
 these documents, as well as interviewing engineers and participating in the
 IETF/IRTF working groups, it is possible to distill the relationship between
 human rights, protocols, and the Internet's infrastructure as it pertains to
 the work of the IETF.</t>
 <t>The discourse analysis was operationalized using qualitative and
 quantitative means. The first step taken by the authors and contributors was
 reading RFCs and other official IETF documents. The second step was the use of
 a Python-based analyzer, using the "Bigbang" tool, adapted by Nick Doty
 <xref target="Doty"/>, to scan for the concepts that were identified as
 important architectural principles (distilled on the initial reading and
 supplemented by the interviews and participant observation). Such a
 quantitative method is very precise and speeds up the research process <xref
 target="Ritchie"/>. But this tool is unable to understand "latent meaning"
 <xref target="Denzin"/>. In order to mitigate these issues of automated
 word-frequency-based approaches and to get a sense of the "thick meaning"
 <xref target="Geertz"/> of the data, a second qualitative analysis of the data
 set was performed. These various rounds of discourse analysis were used to
 inform the interviews and further data analysis. As such, the initial rounds of
 quantitative discourse analysis were used to inform the second rounds of
 qualitative analysis. The results from the qualitative interviews were again
 used to feed new concepts into the quantitative discourse analysis. As such,
 the two methods continued to support and enrich each other.</t>

 <t>The ethnographic methods of the data collection and processing allowed the
 research group to acquire the data necessary to "provide a holistic
 understanding of research participants' views and actions" <xref
 target="Denzin"/> that highlighted ongoing issues and case studies where
 protocols impact human rights. The interview participants were selected
 through purposive sampling <xref target="Babbie"/>, as the research group was
 interested in getting a wide variety of opinions on the role of human rights
 in guiding protocol development. This sampling method also ensured that
 individuals with extensive experience working at the IETF in various roles
 were targeted. The interviewees included individuals in leadership positions
 (Working Group (WG) chairs, Area Directors (ADs)), "regular participants",
 and individuals working for specific entities (corporate, civil society,
 political, academic) and represented various backgrounds, nationalities, and
 genders.</t>

 <section anchor="data-sources" title="Data Sources">

 <t>In order to map the potential relationship between human rights and
 protocols, the HRPC Research Group gathered data from three specific
 sources:</t>

 <section anchor="discourse-analysis-of-rfcs" title="Discourse Analysis of RFCs">
 <t>To start addressing the issue, a mapping exercise analyzing Internet
 infrastructure and protocol features vis-a-vis their possible impact on
 human rights was undertaken. Therefore, research on (1)&nbsp;the
 language used in current and historic RFCs and (2)&nbsp;information
 gathered from mailing-list discussions was undertaken to expose core
 architectural principles, language, and deliberations on the human rights
 of those affected by the network.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="interviews-with-members-of-the-ietf-community" title="Interviews with Members of the IETF Community">
 <t>Over 30 interviews with the current and past members of the Internet
 Architecture Board (IAB), current and past members of the Internet Engineering
 Steering Group (IESG), chairs of selected working groups, and RFC authors
 were done at the IETF&nbsp;92 meeting in Dallas in March&nbsp;2015 to get an
 insider's understanding of how they view the relationship (if any) between
 human rights and protocols, and how this relationship plays out in their work.
 Several of the participants opted to remain anonymous. If you are interested
 in this data set, please contact the authors of this document.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="participant-observation-in-working-groups" title="Participant Observation in Working Groups">
 <t>By participating in various working groups, in person at IETF meetings,
 and on mailing lists, information about the IETF's day&nbhy;to&nbhy;day
 workings was gathered, from which general themes, technical concepts, and use
 cases about human rights and protocols were extracted. This process started
 at the IETF&nbsp;91 meeting in Honolulu and continues today.</t>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="data-analysis-strategies" title="Data Analysis Strategies">

 <t>The data above was processed using three consecutive strategies: mapping
 protocols related to human rights, extracting concepts from these protocols,
 and creation of a common glossary (detailed under <xref
 target="vocabulary-used" />). Before going over these strategies, some
 elaboration on the process of identifying technical concepts as they relate to
 human rights is needed:</t>

 <section anchor="identifying-qualities-of-technical-concepts-that-relate-to-human-rights" title="Identifying Qualities of Technical Concepts That Relate to Human Rights">

 <section anchor="mapping-protocols-and-standards-to-human-rights" title="Mapping Protocols and Standards to Human Rights">
 <t>By combining data from the three data sources named above, an extensive
 list of protocols and standards that potentially enable the Internet as a tool
 for freedom of expression and association was created. In order to determine
 the enabling (or inhibiting) features, we relied on direct references in the
 RFCs as related to such impacts, as well as input from the community. Based
 on this analysis, a list of RFCs that describe standards and protocols that
 are potentially closely related to human rights was compiled.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="extracting-concepts-from-selected-rfcs" title="Extracting Concepts from Selected RFCs">
 <t>The first step was to identify the protocols and standards that are
 related to human rights and to create an environment that enables human rights.
 For that, we needed to focus on specific technical concepts that underlie
 these protocols and standards. Based on this list, a number of technical
 concepts that appeared frequently were extracted and used to create a second
 list of technical terms that, when combined and applied in different
 circumstances, create an enabling environment for exercising human rights on
 the Internet.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="building-a-common-vocabulary-of-technical-concepts-that-impact-human-rights" title="Building a Common Vocabulary of Technical Concepts That Impact Human Rights">
 <t>While interviewing experts, investigating RFCs, and compiling technical
 definitions, several concepts of convergence and divergence were identified.
 To ensure that the discussion was based on a common understanding of terms and
 vocabulary, a list of definitions was created. The definitions are based on
 the wording found in various IETF documents; if the definitions were not
 available therein, definitions were taken from other SDOs or academic
 literature, as indicated in <xref target="vocabulary-used"/>.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="translating-human-rights-concepts-into-technical-definitions" title="Translating Human Rights Concepts into Technical Definitions">
 <t>The previous steps allowed for the clarification of relationships between
 human rights and technical concepts. The steps taken show how the research
 process "zoomed in", from compiling a broad list of protocols and standards
 that relate to human rights to extracting the precise technical concepts that
 make up these protocols and standards, in order to understand the relationship
 between the two. This subsection presents the next step: translating human
 rights to technical concepts by matching the individual components of the
 rights to the accompanying technical concepts, allowing for the creation of a
 list of technical concepts that, when partially combined, can create an
 enabling environment for human rights.</t>

 </section>
 <section
     anchor="list-technical-terms-that-when-partially-combined-can-create-an-enabling-environment-for-human-rights"
     title="List of Technical Terms That, When Partially Combined, Can Create an Enabling Environment for Human Rights">
 <t>Based on the prior steps, the following list of technical terms was
 drafted. When partially combined, this list can create an enabling
 environment for human rights, such as freedom of expression and freedom of
 association.</t>

<figure anchor="fig1" title="Relationship between Architectural Principles and Enabling Features for User Rights">
<artwork><![CDATA[
  Architectural principles                    Enabling features
    and system properties                        for user rights

                   /------------------------------------------------\
                   |                                                |
 +=================|=============================+                  |
 =                 |                             =                  |
 =                 |           End-to-end        =                  |
 =                 |          Reliability        =                  |
 =                 |           Resilience        =  Access as       |
 =                 |        Interoperability     =   human right    |
 =    Good enough  |          Transparency       =                  |
 =     principle   |       Data minimization     =                  |
 =                 |  Permissionless innovation  =                  |
 =    Simplicity   |     Graceful degradation    =                  |
 =                 |          Connectivity       =                  |
 =                 |      Heterogeneity support  =                  |
 =                 |                             =                  |
 =                 |                             =                  |
 =                 \------------------------------------------------/
 =                                               =
 +===============================================+
]]></artwork></figure>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="relating-human-rights-to-technical-concepts" title="Relating Human Rights to Technical Concepts">

 <t>The technical concepts listed in the steps above have been grouped
 according to their impact on specific rights, as mentioned in the
 interviews done at IETF&nbsp;92 as well as the study of literature
 (see <xref target="literature-and-discussion-review"/> ("Literature and
 Discussion Review") above).</t>

 <t>This analysis aims to assist protocol developers in better understanding
 the roles that specific technical concepts have with regard to their
 contribution to an enabling environment for people to exercise their human
 rights.</t>

 <t>This analysis does not claim to be a complete or exhaustive mapping of all
 possible ways in which protocols could potentially impact human rights, but
 it presents a mapping of initial concepts based on interviews and on
 discussion and review of the literature.</t>

<figure anchor="fig2" title="Relationship between Specific Technical Concepts with Regard to Their Contribution to an Enabling Environment for People to Exercise Their Human Rights">
<artwork><![CDATA[
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Technical Concepts    | Rights Potentially Impacted             |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Connectivity          |                                         |
| Privacy               |                                         |
| Security              |                                         |
| Content agnosticism   | Right to freedom of expression          |
| Internationalization  |                                         |
| Censorship resistance |                                         |
| Open standards        |                                         |
| Heterogeneity support |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Anonymity             |                                         |
| Privacy               |                                         |
| Pseudonymity          | Right to non-discrimination             |
| Accessibility         |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Content agnosticism   |                                         |
| Security              | Right to equal protection               |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Accessibility         |                                         |
| Internationalization  | Right to political participation        |
| Censorship resistance |                                         |
| Connectivity          |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Open standards        |                                         |
| Localization          | Right to participate in cultural life,  |
| Internationalization  |    arts, and science, and               |
| Censorship resistance | Right to education                      |
| Accessibility         |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Connectivity          |                                         |
| Decentralization      |                                         |
| Censorship resistance | Right to freedom of assembly            |
| Pseudonymity          |    and association                      |
| Anonymity             |                                         |
| Security              |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
| Reliability           |                                         |
| Confidentiality       |                                         |
| Integrity             | Right to security                       |
| Authenticity          |                                         |
| Anonymity             |                                         |
|                       |                                         |
+-----------------------+-----------------------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

 </section>
 <section
 anchor="map-cases-of-protocols-implementations-and-networking-paradigms-that-adversely-impact-human-rights-or-are-enablers-thereof"
 title="Mapping Cases of Protocols, Implementations, and Networking Paradigms That Adversely Impact Human Rights or Are Enablers Thereof">

 <t>Given the information above, the following list of cases of protocols,
 implementations, and networking paradigms that either adversely impact or
 enable human rights was formed.</t>

 <t>It is important to note that the assessment here is not a general
 judgment on these protocols, nor is it an exhaustive listing of all the
 potential negative or positive impacts on human rights that these protocols
 might have. When these protocols were conceived, there were many criteria to
 take into account. For instance, relying on a centralized service can be bad
 for freedom of speech (it creates one more control point, where censorship
 could be applied), but it may be a necessity if the endpoints are not
 connected and reachable permanently. So, when we say "protocol X has feature
 Y, which may endanger freedom of speech," it does not mean that protocol X is
 bad, much less that its authors were evil. The goal here is to show, with
 actual examples, that the design of protocols has practical consequences for
 some human rights and that these consequences have to be considered in the
 design phase.</t>

 <section anchor="ipv4" title="IPv4">

 <t>The Internet Protocol version 4 (IPv4), also known as "Layer 3" of the
 Internet and specified with a common encapsulation and protocol header, is
 defined in <xref target="RFC791"/>. The evolution of Internet communications
 led to continued development in this area, "encapsulated" in the development
 of version 6 (IPv6) of the protocol <xref target="RFC8200"/>. In spite of
 this updated protocol, we find that 23&nbsp;years after the specification of
 IPv6 the older IPv4 standard continues to account for a sizable majority of
 Internet traffic. Most of the issues discussed here (Network Address
 Translators (NATs) are a major exception; see
 <xref target="address-translation-and-mobility"/> ("Address Translation and
 Mobility")) are valid for IPv4 as well as IPv6.</t>

 <t>The Internet was designed as a platform for free and open communication,
 most notably encoded in the end-to-end principle, and that philosophy is also
 present in the technical implementation of IP <xref target="RFC3724"/>.
 While the protocol was designed to exist in an environment where intelligence
 is at the end hosts, it has proven to provide sufficient information that a
 more intelligent network core can make policy decisions and enforce
 policy-based traffic shaping, thereby restricting the communications of end
 hosts. These capabilities for network control and for limitations on freedom
 of expression by end hosts can be traced back to the design of IPv4, helping
 us to understand which technical protocol decisions have led to harm to
 this human right. A feature that can harm freedom of expression as well as
 the right to privacy through misuse of IP is the exploitation of the public
 visibility of the host pairs for all communications and the corresponding
 ability to differentiate and block traffic as a result of that metadata.
 </t>

 <section anchor="network-visibility-of-source-and-destination" title="Network Visibility of Source and Destination">

 <t>The IPv4 protocol header contains fixed location fields for both the
 source IP address and destination IP address <xref target="RFC791"/>. These
 addresses identify both the host sending and the host receiving each message;
 they also allow the core network to understand who is talking to whom
 and to practically limit communication selectively between pairs of
 hosts. Blocking of communication based on the pair of source and destination
 is one of the most common limitations on the ability for people to communicate
 today <xref target="CAIDA"/> and can be seen as a restriction of the ability
 for people to assemble or to consensually express themselves.</t>

 <t>Inclusion of an Internet-wide identified source in the IP header
 is&nbsp;not the only possible design, especially since the protocol is most
 commonly implemented over Ethernet networks exposing only link&nbhy;local
 identifiers <xref target="RFC894"/>.</t>

 <t>A variety of alternative designs do exist, such as the Accountable and
 Private Internet Protocol <xref target="APIP"/> and High-speed Onion Routing
 at the Network Layer (HORNET) <xref target="HORNET"/> as well as
 source routing. The latter would allow the sender to choose a predefined
 (safe) route and spoofing of the source IP address, which are technically
 supported by IPv4, but neither are considered good practice on the Internet
 <xref target="Farrow"/>. While projects like <xref target="TorProject"/>
 provide an alternative implementation of anonymity in connections, they have
 been developed in spite of the IPv4 protocol design.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="address-translation-and-mobility" title="Address Translation and Mobility">

 <t>A major structural shift in the Internet that undermined the protocol
 design of IPv4, and significantly reduced the freedom of end users to
 communicate and assemble, was the introduction of network address
 translation <xref target="RFC3022"/>. Network address translation is a process
 whereby organizations and autonomous systems connect two networks by
 translating the IPv4 source and destination addresses between them. This
 process puts the router performing the translation in a privileged position,
 where it is predetermined which subset of communications will be translated.
 </t>

 <t>This process of translation has widespread adoption despite promoting a
 process that goes against the stated end-to-end process of the underlying
 protocol <xref target="NATusage"/>. In contrast, the proposed mechanism to
 provide support for mobility and forwarding to clients that may move --
 encoded instead as an option in IP <xref target="RFC5944"/> -- has failed
 to gain traction. In this situation, the compromise made in the design
 of the protocol resulted in a technology that is not coherent with the
 end-to-end principles and thus creates an extra possible hurdle for freedom of
 expression in its design, even though a viable alternative  exists. There is a
 particular problem surrounding NATs and Virtual Private Networks (VPNs)
 (as well as other connections used for privacy purposes), as NATs sometimes
 cause VPNs not to work.</t>
 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="dns" title="DNS">

 <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) <xref target="RFC1035"/> provides service
 discovery capabilities and provides a mechanism to associate human-readable
 names with services. The DNS is organized around a set of independently
 operated "root servers" run by organizations that function in line with
 ICANN's policy by answering queries for which organizations have been
 delegated to manage registration under each Top-Level Domain (TLD). The DNS is
 organized as a rooted tree, and this brings up political and social concerns
 over control.  TLDs are maintained and determined by ICANN. These
 namespaces encompass several classes of services. The initial namespaces,
 including ".com" and ".net", provide common spaces for expression of ideas,
 though their policies are enacted through US-based companies. Other
 namespaces are delegated to specific nationalities and may impose limits
 designed to focus speech in those forums, to both (1)&nbsp;promote speech from
 that nationality and (2)&nbsp;comply with local limits on expression and social
 norms. Finally, the system has recently been expanded with additional generic
 and sponsored namespaces -- for instance, ".travel" and ".ninja" -- that are
 operated by a range of organizations that may independently determine their
 registration policies. This new development has both positive and negative
 implications in terms of enabling human rights. Some individuals argue that it
 undermines the right to freedom of expression because some of these new
 generic TLDs have restricted policies on registration and particular rules on
 hate speech content. Others argue that precisely these properties are positive
 because they enable certain (mostly minority) communities to build safer
 spaces for association, thereby enabling their right to freedom of
 association. An often-mentioned example is an application like
 .gay&nbsp;<xref target="CoE"/>.</t>

 <t>As discussed in <xref target="RFC7626"/>, DNS has significant privacy
 issues. Most notable is the lack of encryption to limit the visibility of
 requests for domain resolution from intermediary parties, and a limited
 deployment of DNSSEC to provide authentication, allowing the client to know
 that they received a correct, "authoritative" answer to a query.  In
 response to the privacy issues, the IETF DNS Private Exchange (DPRIVE) Working
 Group is developing mechanisms to provide confidentiality to DNS transactions,
 to address concerns surrounding pervasive monitoring <xref
 target="RFC7258"/>.</t>

 <t>Authentication through DNSSEC creates a validation path for records. This
 authentication protects against forged or manipulated DNS data. As such,
 DNSSEC protects directory lookups and makes it harder to hijack a
 session. This is important because interference with the operation of the DNS
 is currently becoming one of the central mechanisms used to block access to
 websites. This interference limits both the freedom of expression of the
 publisher to offer their content and the freedom of assembly for clients to
 congregate in a shared virtual space. Even though DNSSEC doesn't prevent
 censorship, it makes it clear that the returned information is not the
 information that was requested; this contributes to the right to security and
 increases trust in the network. It is, however, important to note that DNSSEC
 is currently not widely supported or deployed by domain name registrars,
 making it difficult to authenticate and use correctly.</t>

 <section anchor="removal-of-records" title="Removal of Records">

 <t>There have been a number of cases where the records for a domain are
 removed from the name system due to political events. Examples of this removal
 include the "seizure" of wikileaks <xref target="BBC-wikileaks"/> and the
 names of illegally operating gambling operations by the United States
 Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) unit. In the first case, a US court
 ordered the registrar to take down the domain. In the second, ICE compelled
 the US-based registry in charge of the .com TLD to hand ownership of those
 domains over to the US government.  The same technique has been used in Libya
 to remove sites in violation of "our Country's Law and Morality (which) do not
 allow any kind of pornography or its promotion." &nbsp;<xref target="techyum"/></t>

 <t>At a protocol level, there is no technical auditing for name ownership, as
 in alternate systems like Namecoin <xref target="Namecoin"/>. As a result,
 there is no ability for users to differentiate seizure from the legitimate
 transfer of name ownership, which is purely a policy decision made by
 registrars. While DNSSEC addresses the network distortion events described
 below, it does not tackle this problem.</t>

 <t>(Although we mention alternative techniques, this is not a comparison of DNS
 with Namecoin: the latter has its own problems and limitations. The idea here
 is to show that there are several possible choices, and they have consequences
 for human rights.)</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="distortion-of-records" title="Distortion of Records">

 <t>The most common mechanism by which the DNS is abused to limit freedom of
 expression is through manipulation of protocol messages by the network. One
 form occurs at an organizational level, where client computers are instructed
 to use a local DNS resolver controlled by the organization. The DNS resolver
 will then selectively distort responses rather than request the authoritative
 lookup from the upstream system. The second form occurs through the use of
 Deep Packet Inspection (DPI), where all DNS protocol messages are inspected by
 the network and objectionable content is distorted, as can be observed in
 Chinese networks.</t>

 <t>A notable instance of distortion occurred in Greece <xref
 target="Ververis"/>, where a study found evidence of both (1)&nbsp;DPI to
 distort DNS replies and (2)&nbsp;more excessive blocking of content than
 was legally required or requested (also known as "overblocking").
 Internet Service Providers (ISPs), obeying a governmental order, prevented
 clients from resolving the names of domains, thereby prompting this
 particular blocking of systems there.</t>

 <t>At a protocol level, the effectiveness of these attacks is made possible by
 a lack of authentication in the DNS protocol. DNSSEC provides the ability to
 determine the authenticity of responses when used, but it is not regularly
 checked by resolvers. DNSSEC is not effective when the local resolver for a
 network is complicit in the distortion -- for instance, when the resolver
 assigned for use by an ISP is the source of injection. Selective distortion of
 records is also made possible by the predictable structure of DNS messages,
 which makes it computationally easy for a network device to watch all passing
 messages even at high speeds, and the lack of encryption, which allows the
 network to distort only an objectionable subset of protocol
 messages. Specific distortion mechanisms are discussed further in <xref
 target="Hall"/>.</t>

 <t>Users can switch to another resolver -- for instance, a public
 resolver. The distorter can then try to block or hijack the connection to
 this resolver. This may start an arms race, with the user switching to secured
 connections to this alternative resolver <xref target="RFC7858"/> and the
 distorter then trying to find more sophisticated ways to block or hijack the
 connection. In some cases, this search for an alternative, non&nbhy;disrupting
 resolver may lead to more centralization because many people are switching
 to a few big commercial public resolvers.</t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="injection-of-records" title="Injection of Records">

 <t>Responding incorrectly to requests for name lookups is the most common
 mechanism that in-network devices use to limit the ability of end users to
 discover services. A deviation that accomplishes a similar objective and
 may be seen as different from a "freedom of expression" perspective is the
 injection of incorrect responses to queries. The most prominent example of
 this behavior occurs in China, where requests for lookups of sites deemed
 inappropriate will trigger the network to return a false response, causing the
 client to ignore the real response when it subsequently arrives <xref
 target="greatfirewall"/>. Unlike the other network paradigms discussed above,
 injection does not stifle the ability of a server to announce its name;
 it instead provides another voice that answers sooner. This is effective
 because without DNSSEC, the protocol will respond to whichever answer is
 received first, without listening for subsequent answers.</t>
 </section>
 </section>

 <section anchor="http" title="HTTP">

 <t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) version 1.1 <xref target="RFC7230"/>
 <xref target="RFC7231"/> <xref target="RFC7232"/> <xref target="RFC7233"/>
 <xref target="RFC7234"/> <xref target="RFC7235"/> <xref target="RFC7236"/>
 <xref target="RFC7237"/> is a request-response application protocol developed
 throughout the 1990s. HTTP factually contributed to the exponential growth of
 the Internet and the interconnection of populations around the world. Its
 simple design strongly contributed to the fact that HTTP has become the
 foundation of most modern Internet platforms and communication systems, from
 websites to chat systems and computer-to-computer applications. In its
 manifestation in the World Wide Web, HTTP radically revolutionized the course
 of technological development and the ways people interact with online content
 and with each other.</t>

 <t>However, HTTP is also a fundamentally insecure protocol that doesn't
 natively provide encryption properties. While the definition of the Secure
 Sockets Layer (SSL) <xref target="RFC6101"/>, and later of Transport Layer
 Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC5246"/>, also happened during the 1990s, the
 fact that HTTP doesn't mandate the use of such encryption layers by developers
 and service providers was one of the reasons for a very late adoption of
 encryption. Only in the middle of the 2000s did we observe big ISPs,
 such as Google, starting to provide encrypted access to their
 web services.</t>

 <t>The lack of sensitivity and understanding of the critical importance
 of securing web traffic incentivized certain (offensive) actors to
 develop, deploy, and utilize interception systems at large and to
 later launch active injection attacks, in order to swipe large amounts
 of data and compromise Internet-enabled devices. The commercial availability
 of systems and tools to perform these types of attacks also led to a number of
 human rights abuses that have been discovered and reported over the years.</t>

 <t>Generally, we can identify traffic interception
 (<xref target="traffic-interception"/>) and
 traffic manipulation (<xref target="traffic-manipulation"/>) as the two most
 problematic attacks that can be performed against applications employing a
 cleartext HTTP transport layer. That being said, the IETF is taking steady
 steps to move to the encrypted version of HTTP, HTTP Secure (HTTPS).</t>

 <t>While this is commendable, we must not lose track of the fact that
 different protocols, implementations, configurations, and networking paradigms
 can intersect such that they (can be used to) adversely impact human
 rights. For instance, to facilitate surveillance, certain countries will
 throttle HTTPS connections, forcing users to switch to (unthrottled) HTTP 
 <xref target="Aryan-etal"/>.</t>

 <section anchor="traffic-interception" title="Traffic Interception">

 <t>While we are seeing an increasing trend in the last couple of years to
 employ SSL/TLS as a secure traffic layer for HTTP-based applications, we are
 still far from seeing a ubiquitous use of encryption on the World Wide
 Web. &nbsp;It is important to consider that the adoption of SSL/TLS is also a
 relatively recent phenomenon. Email providers such as riseup.net were the
 first to enable SSL by default. Google did not introduce an option for its
 Gmail users to navigate with SSL until 2008 <xref target="Rideout"/> and turned
 TLS on by default later, in 2010 <xref target="Schillace"/>. It took an
 increasing amount of security breaches and revelations on global surveillance
 from Edward Snowden before other mail service providers followed suit. For
 example, Yahoo did not enable SSL/TLS by default on its webmail services
 until early 2014 <xref target="Peterson"/>.</t>

 <t>TLS itself has been subject to many attacks and bugs; this situation
 can be attributed to some fundamental design weaknesses, such as lack of a
 state machine (which opens a vulnerability for triple handshake attacks)
 and flaws caused by early US government restrictions on cryptography, leading
 to cipher-suite downgrade attacks (Logjam attacks). These vulnerabilities are
 being corrected in TLS&nbsp;1.3 <xref target="Bhargavan"/> <xref
 target="Adrian"/>.</t>

 <t>HTTP upgrading to HTTPS is also vulnerable to having an attacker remove the
 "s" in any links to HTTPS URIs from a web page transferred in cleartext over
 HTTP -- an attack called "SSL Stripping" <xref target="sslstrip"/>. Thus, for
 high-security use of HTTPS, IETF standards such as HTTP Strict Transport
 Security (HSTS) <xref target="RFC6797"/>, certificate pinning <xref
 target="RFC7469"/>, and/or DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities
 (DANE) <xref target="RFC6698"/> should be used.</t>

 <t>As we learned through Snowden's revelations, intelligence agencies have
 been intercepting and collecting unencrypted traffic at large for many
 years. There are documented examples of such mass&nbhy;surveillance programs
 with the Government Communications Headquarters's (GCHQ's) Tempora
 <xref target="WP-Tempora"/> and the National Security Agency's (NSA's)
 XKeyscore <xref target="Greenwald"/>. Through these programs, the NSA and
 the GCHQ have been able to swipe large amounts of data, including email and
 instant messaging communications that have been transported in the clear
 for years by providers unsuspecting of the pervasiveness and scale of
 governments' efforts and investment in global mass-surveillance capabilities.
 </t>
 <t>However, similar mass interception of unencrypted HTTP communications is
 also often employed at the national level by some democratic countries, by
 exercising control over state-owned ISPs and through the use of commercially
 available monitoring, collection, and censorship equipment. Over the last few
 years, a lot of information has come to public attention on the role and scale
 of a surveillance industry dedicated to developing different types of
 interception gear, making use of known and unknown weaknesses in existing
 protocols <xref target="RFC7258"/>. We have several records of such equipment
 being sold and utilized by some regimes in order to monitor entire segments of
 a population, especially at times of social and political distress, uncovering
 massive human rights abuses. For example, in 2013, the group Telecomix revealed
 that the Syrian regime was making use of Blue Coat products in order to
 intercept cleartext traffic as well as to enforce censorship of unwanted
 content <xref target="RSF"/>. Similarly, in 2011, it was found that the
 French technology firm Amesys provided the Gadhafi government with equipment
 able to intercept emails, Facebook traffic, and chat messages at a
 country-wide level <xref target="WSJ"/>. The use of such systems, especially
 in the context of the Arab Spring and of civil uprisings against the
 dictatorships, has caused serious concerns regarding significant human rights
 abuses in Libya.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="traffic-manipulation" title="Traffic Manipulation">

 <t>The lack of a secure transport layer under HTTP connections not only
 exposes users to interception of the content of their communications but
 is more and more commonly abused as a vehicle for actively compromising
 computers and mobile devices. If an HTTP session travels in the clear over the
 network, any node positioned at any point in the network is able to perform
 man-in-the-middle attacks; the node can observe, manipulate, and hijack the
 session and can modify the content of the communication in order to trigger
 unexpected behavior by the application generating the traffic. For example, in
 the case of a browser, the attacker would be able to inject malicious code in
 order to exploit vulnerabilities in the browser or any of its plugins.
 Similarly, the attacker would be able to intercept, add malware to, and
 repackage binary software updates that are very commonly downloaded in the
 clear by applications such as word processors and media players. If the HTTP
 session were encrypted, the tampering of the content would not be possible,
 and these network injection attacks would not be successful.</t>

 <t>While traffic manipulation attacks have long been known, documented, and
 prototyped, especially in the context of Wi&nbhy;Fi and LAN networks, in
 the last few years we have observed an increasing investment in the
 production and sale of network injection equipment that is both commercially
 available and deployed at scale by intelligence agencies.</t>

 <t>For example, we learned from some of the documents provided by Edward
 Snowden to the press that the NSA has constructed a global network injection
 infrastructure, called "QUANTUM", able to leverage mass surveillance in order
 to identify targets of interest and subsequently task man-on-the-side
 attacks to ultimately compromise a selected device. Among other attacks, the
 NSA makes use of an attack called "QUANTUMINSERT" <xref target="Haagsma"/>,
 which intercepts and hijacks an unencrypted HTTP communication and forces the
 requesting browser to redirect to a host controlled by the NSA instead of
 the intended website. Normally, the new destination would be an exploitation
 service, referred to in Snowden documents as "FOXACID", which would attempt
 to execute malicious code in the context of the target's browser. The Guardian
 reported in 2013 that the NSA has, for example, been using these techniques to
 target users of the popular anonymity service Tor <xref
 target="Schneier"/>. The German Norddeutscher Rundfunk (NDR) reported in
 2014 that the NSA has also been using its mass&nbhy;surveillance capabilities
 to identify Tor users at large <xref target="Appelbaum"/>.
 </t>

 <t>Recently, similar capabilities used by Chinese authorities have been
 reported as well in what has been informally called the "Great Cannon" <xref
 target="Marcak"/>, which raised numerous concerns on the potential curb on
 human rights and freedom of speech due to the increasingly tighter control
 of Chinese Internet communications and access to information.</t>

 <t>Network injection attacks are also made widely available to state actors
 around the world through the commercialization of similar, smaller-scale
 equipment that can be easily acquired and deployed at a country-wide
 level. Certain companies are known to have network injection gear within their
 products portfolio <xref target="Marquis-Boire"/>. The technology devised and
 produced by some of them to perform network traffic manipulation attacks on
 HTTP communications is even the subject of a patent application in the United
 States <xref target="Googlepatent"/>. Access to offensive technologies
 available on the commercial lawful interception market has led to human rights
 abuses and illegitimate surveillance of journalists, human rights defenders,
 and political activists in many countries around the world <xref
 target="Collins"/>. While network injection attacks haven't been the subject
 of much attention, they do enable even unskilled attackers to perform silent
 and very resilient compromises, and unencrypted HTTP remains one of the main
 vehicles.</t>

 <t>There is a new version of HTTP, called "HTTP/2" <xref target="RFC7540"/>,
 which aims to be largely backwards compatible while also offering new options
 such as data compression of HTTP headers, pipelining of requests, and
 multiplexing multiple requests over a single TCP connection. In addition
 to decreasing latency to improve page-loading speeds, it also facilitates more
 efficient use of connectivity in low-bandwidth environments, which in turn
 enables freedom of expression; the right to assembly; the right to political
 participation; and the right to participate in cultural life, arts, and
 science. <xref target="RFC7540"/> does not mandate TLS or any other form of
 encryption, nor does it support opportunistic encryption even though
 opportunistic encryption is now addressed in <xref target="RFC8164"/>.</t>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="xmpp" title="XMPP">

 <t>The Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP), specified in <xref
 target="RFC6120"/>, provides a standard for interactive chat messaging
 and has evolved to encompass interoperable text, voice, and video chat. The
 protocol is structured as a federated network of servers, similar to email,
 where users register with a local server that acts on their behalf to cache
 and relay messages. This protocol design has many advantages, allowing servers
 to shield clients from denial of service and other forms of retribution for
 their expression; it is also designed to avoid central entities that could
 control the ability to communicate or assemble using the protocol.</t>

 <t>Nonetheless, there are plenty of aspects of the protocol design of XMPP
 that shape the ability for users to communicate freely and to assemble
 via the protocol.</t>

 <section anchor="user-identification" title="User Identification">

 <t>The XMPP specification <xref target="RFC6120"/> dictates that clients
 are identified with a resource (&lt;node@domain/home&gt; /
 &lt;node@domain&wj;/work&gt;) to distinguish the conversations to
 specific devices. While the protocol does not specify that the resource must
 be exposed by the client's server to remote users, in practice this has become
 the default behavior. In doing so, users can be tracked by remote friends and
 their servers, who are able to monitor the presence of not just the user
 but of each individual device the user logs in with. This has proven to be
 misleading to many users <xref target="Pidgin"/>, since many clients only
 expose user-level rather than device-level presence. Likewise, user
 invisibility so that communication can occur while users don't notify all
 buddies and other servers of their availability is not part of the formal
 protocol and has only been added as an extension within the XML stream rather
 than enforced by the protocol.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="surveillance-of-communication" title="Surveillance of Communication">

 <t>XMPP specifies the standard by which communications channels may be
 encrypted, but it does not provide visibility to clients regarding
 whether their communications are encrypted on each link. In particular, even
 when both clients ensure that they have an encrypted connection to their XMPP
 server to ensure that their local network is unable to read or disrupt the
 messages they send, the protocol does not provide visibility into the
 encryption status between the two servers. As such, clients may be subject to
 selective disruption of communications by an intermediate network that
 disrupts communications based on keywords found through DPI. While many
 operators have committed to only establishing encrypted links from their
 servers in recognition of this vulnerability, it remains impossible for users
 to audit this behavior, and encrypted connections are not required by the
 protocol itself <xref target="XMPP-Manifesto"/>.</t>

 <t>In particular, Section 13.14 of the XMPP specification <xref
 target="RFC6120"/> explicitly acknowledges the existence of a downgrade attack
 where an adversary controlling an intermediate network can force the
 inter&nbhy;domain federation between servers to revert to a non&nbhy;encrypted
 protocol where selective messages can then be disrupted.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="group-chat-limitations" title="Group Chat Limitations">

 <t>Group chat in XMPP is defined as an extension within the XML
 specification of XMPP (https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0045.html).
 However, it is not encoded or required at a protocol level and is not
 uniformly implemented by clients.</t>

 <t>The design of multi-user chat in XMPP suffers from extending a
 protocol that was not designed with assembly of many users in mind. In
 particular, in the federated protocol provided by XMPP, multi-user communities
 are implemented with a distinguished "owner" who is granted control over the
 participants and structure of the conversation.</t>

 <t>Multi-user chat rooms are identified by a name specified on a specific
 server, so that while the overall protocol may be federated, the ability for
 users to assemble in a given community is moderated by a single server. That
 server may block the room and prevent assembly unilaterally, even between two
 users, neither of whom trust or use that server directly.</t>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="peer-to-peer" title="Peer-to-Peer">

 <t>Peer-to-Peer (P2P) is a distributed network architecture <xref
 target="RFC5694"/> in which all the participant nodes can be responsible for
 the storage and dissemination of information from any other node (see
 <xref target="RFC7574"/>, an IETF standard that discusses a P2P
 architecture called the "Peer&nbhy;to-Peer Streaming Peer Protocol" (PPSPP)).
 A P2P network is a logical overlay that lives on top of the physical network
 and allows nodes (or "peers") participating in it to establish contact and
 exchange information directly with each other. The implementation of a P2P
 network may vary widely: it may be structured or unstructured, and it may
 implement stronger or weaker cryptographic and anonymity properties. While
 its most common application has traditionally been file-sharing (and other
 types of content delivery systems), P2P is a popular architecture for
 networks and applications that require (or encourage) decentralization. Prime
 examples include Bitcoin and other proprietary multimedia applications.
 </t>

 <t>In a time of heavily centralized online services, P2P is regularly
 described as an alternative, more democratic, and resistant option that
 displaces structures of control over data and communications and delegates all
 peers to be equally responsible for the functioning, integrity, and security
 of the data. While in principle P2P remains important to the design
 and development of future content distribution, messaging, and publishing
 systems, it poses numerous security and privacy challenges that are mostly
 delegated to individual developers to recognize, analyze, and solve in each
 implementation of a given P2P network.</t>

 <section anchor="network-poisoning" title="Network Poisoning">

 <t>Since content, and sometimes peer lists, are safeguarded and distributed
 by their members, P2P networks are prone to what are generally defined as
 "poisoning attacks". Poisoning attacks might be aimed directly at the data
 that is being distributed, for example, (1)&nbsp;by intentionally corrupting
 the data, (2)&nbsp;at the index tables used to instruct the peers where to
 fetch the data, or (3)&nbsp;at routing tables, with an attempt to provide
 connecting peers with lists of rogue or nonexistent peers, with the intention
 to effectively cause a denial of service on the network.</t>
 </section>
 <section anchor="throttling" title="Throttling">

 <t>P2P traffic (and BitTorrent in particular) represents a significant
 percentage of global Internet traffic <xref target="Sandvine"/>, and it has
 become increasingly popular for ISPs to perform throttling of customers' lines
 in order to limit bandwidth usage <xref target="torrentfreak1"/> and,
 sometimes, probably as an effect of the ongoing conflict between copyright
 holders and file-sharing communities <xref target="wikileaks"/>. Such
 throttling undermines the end-to-end principle.</t>

 <t>Throttling the P2P traffic makes some uses of P2P networks ineffective;
 this throttling might be coupled with stricter inspection of users' Internet
 traffic through DPI techniques, possibly posing additional security and
 privacy risks.</t>
 </section>
 <section anchor="tracking-and-identification" title="Tracking and Identification">

 <t>One of the fundamental and most problematic issues with traditional
 P2P networks is a complete lack of anonymization of their users. For
 example, in the case of BitTorrent, all peers' IP addresses are openly
 available to the other peers. This has led to ever&nbhy;increasing
 tracking of P2P and file-sharing users <xref target="ars"/>. As the
 geographical location of the user is directly exposed, as could also be his
 identity, the user might become a target of additional harassment and attacks
 of a physical or legal nature. For example, it is known that in Germany
 law firms have made extensive use of P2P and file-sharing tracking systems
 in order to identify downloaders and initiate legal actions looking for
 compensations <xref target="torrentfreak2"/>.</t>

 <t>It is worth noting that there are some varieties of P2P networks that
 implement cryptographic practices and that introduce anonymization of their
 users. Such implementations may be proved to be successful in resisting
 censorship of content and tracking of network peers. A prime example is
 Freenet <xref target="freenet1"/>, a free software application that is
 (1)&nbsp;designed to make it significantly more difficult to identify users
 and content and (2)&nbsp;dedicated to fostering freedom of speech online
 <xref target="freenet2"/>.
 </t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="sybil-attacks" title="Sybil Attacks">

 <t>In open-membership P2P networks, a single attacker can pretend to be many
 participants, typically by creating multiple fake identities of whatever kind
 the P2P network uses <xref target="Douceur"/>.  Attackers can use Sybil
 attacks to bias choices that the P2P network makes collectively to the
 attacker's advantage, e.g., by making it more likely that a particular data
 item (or some threshold of the replicas or shares of a data item) is assigned
 to attacker-controlled participants.  If the P2P network implements any
 voting, moderation, or peer-review-like functionality, Sybil attacks may be
 used to "stuff the ballots" to benefit the attacker.  Companies and
 governments can use Sybil attacks on discussion-oriented P2P systems for
 "astroturfing" or creating the appearance of mass grassroots support for some
 position where in reality there is none. It is important to know that there
 are no known complete, environmentally sustainable, and fully distributed
 solutions to Sybil attacks, and routing via "friends" allows users to be
 de&nbhy;anonymized via their social graph. It is important to note that Sybil
 attacks in this context (e.g., astroturfing) are relevant to more than P2P
 protocols; they are also common on web-based systems, and they are
 exploited by governments and commercial entities.
 </t>

 <t>Encrypted P2P and anonymous P2P networks have already emerged. They provide
 viable platforms for sharing material <xref target="Tribler"/>, publishing
 content anonymously, and communicating securely <xref
 target="Bitmessage"/>. These platforms are not perfect, and more research
 needs to be done. If adopted at large, well-designed and resistant P2P
 networks might represent a critical component of a future secure and
 distributed Internet, enabling freedom of speech and freedom of information
 at&nbsp;scale.</t>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="virtual-private-networks" title="Virtual Private Networks">

 <t>The VPNs discussed here are point-to-point connections that enable
 two computers to communicate over an encrypted tunnel. There are
 multiple implementations and protocols used in the deployment of VPNs, and
 they generally diversify by encryption protocol or particular requirements,
 most commonly in proprietary and enterprise solutions. VPNs are commonly used
 to (1)&nbsp;enable some devices to communicate through peculiar network
 configurations, (2)&nbsp;use some privacy and security properties in order to
 protect the traffic generated by the end user, or both. VPNs have also
 become a very popular technology among human rights defenders, dissidents,
 and journalists worldwide to avoid local monitoring and eventually also to
 circumvent censorship. VPNs are often debated among human rights defenders
 as a potential alternative to Tor or other anonymous networks. Such
 comparisons are misleading, as some of the privacy and security properties of
 VPNs are often misunderstood by less tech&nbhy;savvy users and could
 ultimately lead to unintended problems.</t>

 <t>As VPNs have increased in popularity, commercial VPN providers have started
 growing as businesses and are very commonly picked by human rights defenders
 and people at risk, as they are normally provided with an easy-to-use service
 and, sometimes, even custom applications to establish the VPN tunnel. Not
 being able to control the configuration of the network, let alone the
 security of the application, assessing the general privacy and security state
 of common VPNs is very hard. Such services have often been discovered to be
 leaking information, and their custom applications have been found to be
 flawed. While Tor and similar networks receive a lot of scrutiny from the
 public and the academic community, commercial or non&nbhy;commercial VPNs are
 far less analyzed and understood <xref target="Insinuator"/> <xref
 target="Alshalan-etal"/>, and it might be valuable to establish some standards
 to guarantee a minimal level of privacy and security to those who need them
 the most.</t>

 <section anchor="no-anonymity-against-vpn-provider" title="No Anonymity against VPN Providers">

 <t>One of the common misconceptions among users of VPNs is the level of
 anonymity that VPNs can provide. This sense of anonymity can be betrayed by a
 number of attacks or misconfigurations of the VPN provider. It is important to
 remember that, in contrast to Tor and similar systems, VPNs were not
 designed to provide anonymity properties. From a technical point of view, a
 VPN might leak identifiable information or might be the subject of correlation
 attacks that could expose the originating address of a connecting user. Most
 importantly, it is vital to understand that commercial and
 non&nbhy;commercial VPN providers are bound by the law of the jurisdiction in
 which they reside or in which their infrastructure is located, and they might
 be legally forced to turn over data of specific users if legal investigations
 or intelligence requirements dictate so. In such cases, if the VPN providers
 retain logs, it is possible that a user's information could be provided to
 the user's adversary and lead to his or her identification.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="logging" title="Logging">

 <t>Because VPNs are point-to-point connections, the service providers are in
 fact able to observe the original location of connecting users, and they are
 able to track at what time they started their session and, eventually, also to
 which destinations they're trying to connect. If the VPN providers retain logs
 for a long enough time, they might be forced to turn over the relevant data or
 they might be otherwise compromised, leading to the same data getting
 exposed. A clear log-retention policy could be enforced, but considering that
 countries enforce different levels of data-retention policies, VPN providers
 should at least be transparent regarding what information they store and for
 how long it is being kept.</t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="rd-party-hosting" title="Third-Party Hosting">
 <t>VPN providers very commonly rely on third parties to provision the
 infrastructure that is later going to be used to run VPN endpoints. For
 example, they might rely on external dedicated server providers or on
 uplink providers. In those cases, even if the VPN provider itself isn't
 retaining any significant logs, the information on connecting users might
 be retained by those third parties instead, introducing an additional
 collection point for the adversary.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="ipv6-leakage" title="IPv6 Leakage">

 <t>Some studies proved that several commercial VPN providers and applications
 suffer from critical leakage of information through IPv6 due to improper
 support and configuration <xref target="PETS2015VPN"/>. This is generally
 caused by a lack of proper configuration of the client's IPv6 routing
 tables. Considering that most popular browsers and similar applications have
 been supporting IPv6 by default, if the host is provided with a functional
 IPv6 configuration, the traffic that is generated might be leaked if the VPN
 application isn't designed to manipulate such traffic properly.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="dns-leakage" title="DNS Leakage">

 <t>Similarly, VPN services that aren't handling DNS requests and aren't
 running DNS servers of their own might be prone to DNS leaking that might not
 only expose sensitive information on the activity of a user but could also
 potentially lead to DNS hijacking attacks and subsequent compromises.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="traffic-correlation" title="Traffic Correlation">

 <t>Some VPN implementations appear to be particularly vulnerable to
 identification and collection of key exchanges that, some Snowden documents
 revealed, are systematically collected and stored for future reference. The
 ability of an adversary to monitor network connections at many different
 points over the Internet can allow them to perform traffic correlation
 attacks and identify the origin of certain VPN traffic by cross-referencing
 the connection time of the user to the endpoint and the connection time of the
 endpoint to the final destination. These types of attacks, although very
 expensive and normally only performed by very resourceful adversaries, have
 been documented <xref target="SPIEGEL"/> to be already in practice, and
 they could completely nullify the use of a VPN and ultimately expose the
 activity and the identity of a user at risk.</t>

 </section>
 </section>
 <section anchor="http-status-code-451" title="HTTP Status Code 451">

 <t>"Every Internet user has run into the '404 Not Found' Hypertext Transfer
 Protocol (HTTP) status code when trying, and failing, to access a particular
 website" <xref target="Cath"/>. It is a response status that the server sends
 to the browser when the server cannot locate the URL. "403 Forbidden" is
 another example of this class of code signals that gives users information
 about what is going on. In the "403" case, the server can be reached but is
 blocking the request because the user is trying to access content forbidden
 to them, typically because some content is only for identified users, based
 on a payment or on special status in the organization. Most of the time, 403
 is sent by the origin server, not by an intermediary. If a firewall prevents
 a government employee from accessing pornography on a work computer, it does
 not use 403.</t>

 <t>As surveillance and censorship of the Internet are becoming more
 commonplace, voices were raised at the IETF to introduce a new status code
 that indicates when something is not available for "legal reasons" (like
 censorship):</t>

 <t>The 451 status code would allow server operators to operate with greater
 transparency in circumstances where issues of law or public policy affect
 their operation. This transparency may be beneficial to both (1)&nbsp;these
 operators and (2)&nbsp;end&nbsp;users <xref target="RFC7725"/>.</t>

 <t>The status code is named "451" in reference to both Bradbury's famous
 novel "Fahrenheit 451" and to 451 degrees Fahrenheit (the temperature at
 which some claim book paper autoignites).</t>

 <t>During the IETF&nbsp;92 meeting in Dallas, there was discussion about the
 usefulness of 451. The main tension revolved around the lack of an apparent
 machine-readable technical use of the information. The extent to which 451
 is just "political theatre" or whether it has a concrete technical use was
 heatedly debated. Some argued that "the 451 status code is just a status code
 with a response body"; others said it was problematic because "it brings law
 into the picture." Still others argued that it would be useful for
 individuals or for organizations like the "Chilling Effects" project that
 are crawling the Web to get an indication of censorship (IETF discussion
 on 451 -- author's field notes, March 2015). There was no outright
 objection during the Dallas meeting against moving forward on status code 451,
 and on December 18, 2015, the IESG approved "An HTTP Status Code to Report
 Legal Obstacles" (now <xref target="RFC7725"/>) for publication. HTTP status
 code 451 is now an IETF-approved HTTP status code that signals when resource
 access is denied as a consequence of legal demands.</t>

 <t>What is interesting about this particular case is that not only technical
 arguments but also the status code's outright potential political use for
 civil society played a substantial role in shaping the discussion and the
 decision to move forward with this technology.</t>

 <t>It is nonetheless important to note that HTTP status code 451 is not a
 solution to detect all occasions of censorship. A large swath of Internet
 filtering occurs in the network, at a lower level than HTTP, rather than
 at the server itself. For these forms of censorship, 451 plays a limited role,
 as typical censoring intermediaries won't generate it. Besides technical
 reasons, such filtering regimes are unlikely to voluntarily inject a 451 status
 code. The use of 451 is most likely to apply in the case of cooperative, legal
 versions of content removal resulting from requests to providers. One can
 think of content that is removed or blocked for legal reasons, like copyright
 infringement, gambling laws, child abuse, etc. Large Internet companies
 and search engines are constantly asked to censor content in various
 jurisdictions. &nbsp;451 allows this to be easily discovered -- for instance,
 by initiatives like the Lumen Database.</t>

 <t>Overall, the strength of 451 lies in its ability to provide transparency by
 giving the reason for blocking and giving the end&nbsp;user the ability to
 file a complaint. It allows organizations to easily measure censorship in an
 automated way and prompts the user to access the content via another path
 (e.g., Tor, VPNs) when (s)he encounters the 451 status code.</t>

 <t>Status code 451 impacts human rights by making censorship more transparent
 and measurable. It increases transparency by signaling the existence of
 censorship (instead of a much broader HTTP error message such as HTTP status
 code 404) as well as providing details of the legal restriction, which legal
 authority is imposing it, and to what class of resources it applies. This
 empowers the user to seek redress.</t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="ddos-attacks" title="DDoS Attacks">
 <t>Many individuals, including IETF engineers, have argued that DDoS attacks
 are fundamentally against freedom of expression. Technically, DDoS attacks
 are attacks where one host or multiple hosts overload the bandwidth or
 resources of another host by flooding it with traffic or making
 resource-intensive requests, causing it to temporarily stop being available
 to users. One can roughly differentiate three types of DDoS attacks:</t>

 <t><list style="numbers">
 <t>volume-based attacks (which aim to make the host unreachable by using up
 all its bandwidth; often-used techniques are UDP floods and ICMP floods)</t>
 <t>protocol attacks (which aim to use up actual server resources;
 often&nbhy;used techniques are SYN floods, fragmented packet attacks,
 and "ping of death" <xref target="RFC4949"/>)</t>
 <t>application-layer attacks (which aim to bring down a server, such as a web
 server)</t>
</list></t>

 <t>DDoS attacks can thus stifle freedom of expression and complicate the
 ability of independent media and human rights organizations to exercise their
 right to (online) freedom of association, while facilitating the ability of
 governments to censor dissent.  When it comes to comparing DDoS attacks to
 protests in offline life, it is important to remember that only a limited
 number of DDoS attacks solely involved willing participants. In the
 overwhelming majority of cases, the clients are hacked hosts of unrelated
 parties that have not consented to being part of a DDoS (for exceptions, see
 Operation Ababil <xref target="Ababil"/> or the Iranian Green Movement's
 DDoS campaign at election time <xref target="GreenMovement"/>). In addition,
 DDoS attacks are increasingly used as an extortion tactic.</t>

 <t>All of these issues seem to suggest that the IETF should try to ensure that
 their protocols cannot be used for DDoS attacks; this is consistent with the
 long-standing IETF consensus that DDoS is an attack that protocols should
 mitigate to the extent they can <xref target="BCP72"/>. Decreasing the
 number of vulnerabilities in protocols and (outside of the IETF) the number
 of bugs in the network stacks of routers or computers could address this
 issue. The IETF can clearly play a role in bringing about some of these
 changes, but the IETF cannot be expected to take a positive stance on
 (specific) DDoS attacks or to create protocols that enable some attacks and
 inhibit others. What the IETF can do is critically reflect on its role in the
 development of the Internet and how this impacts the ability of people to
 exercise their human rights, such as freedom of expression.</t>
 </section>
 </section>
 </section>
 </section>

 <section anchor="model-for-developing-human-rights-protocol-considerations" title="Model for Developing Human Rights Protocol Considerations">

 <t>This section outlines a set of human rights protocol considerations for
 protocol developers. It provides questions that engineers should ask
 themselves when developing or improving protocols if they want to understand
 their impact on human rights. It should, however, be noted that the impact of
 a protocol cannot be solely deduced from its design; its usage and
 implementation should also be studied to form a full assessment of
 the impact of the protocol on human rights.</t>

 <t>The questions are based on the research performed by the HRPC Research
 Group. This research was documented prior to the writing of these
 considerations. The research establishes that human rights relate to standards
 and protocols; it also offers a common vocabulary of technical concepts that
 impact human rights and how these technical concepts can be combined to ensure
 that the Internet remains an enabling environment for human rights. With this,
 a model for developing human rights protocol considerations has taken
 shape.</t>

 <section anchor="human-rights-threats" title="Human Rights Threats">
 <t>Human rights threats on the Internet come in a myriad of forms. Protocols
 and standards can either harm or enable the right to freedom of expression;
 the right to non&nbhy;discrimination; the right to equal protection;
 the right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science; the right to
 freedom of assembly and association; and the right to security. An
 end&nbsp;user who is denied access to certain services, data, or websites may
 be unable to disclose vital information about malpractice on the part of a
 government or other authority. A person whose communications are monitored may
 be prevented from exercising their right to freedom of association or
 participation in political processes <xref target="Penney"/>. In a worst-case
 scenario, protocols that leak information can lead to physical danger. A
 realistic example to consider is when, based on information gathered by state
 agencies through information leakage in protocols, individuals perceived
 as threats to the state are subjected to torture, extrajudicial killings,
 or detention.</t>

 <t>This section details several "common" threats to human rights, indicating
 how each of these can lead to harm to, or violations of, human rights.
 It also presents several examples of how these threats to human rights
 materialize on the Internet. This threat modeling is inspired by <xref
 target="RFC6973"/> ("Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols"),
 which is based on security threat analysis. This method is by no means a
 perfect solution for assessing human rights risks in Internet protocols and
 systems; it is, however, the best approach currently available. Certain
 specific human rights threats are indirectly considered in Internet protocols
 as part of their security considerations <xref target="BCP72"/>, but privacy
 guidelines <xref target="RFC6973"/> or reviews, let alone the assessments of
 the impact of protocols on human rights, are not standardized or
 implemented.</t>

 <t>Many threats, enablers, and risks are linked to different rights. This is
 not surprising if one takes into account that human rights are interrelated,
 interdependent, and indivisible. Here, however, we're not discussing all
 human rights, because not all human rights are relevant to ICTs in general
 and to protocols and standards in particular <xref target="Bless1"/>:

<list>
 <t>The main
 source of the values of human rights is the International Bill of Human Rights
 that is composed of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights <xref
 target="UDHR"/> along with the International Covenant on Civil and Political
 Rights <xref target="ICCPR"/> and the International Covenant on Economic,
 Social and Cultural Rights <xref target="ICESCR"/>. In the light of several
 cases of Internet censorship, the Human Rights Council Resolution 20/8 was
 adopted in 2012 <xref target="UNHRC2016"/>, affirming "... that the same
 rights that people have offline must also be protected online ..." &nbsp;In
 2015, the Charter of Human Rights and Principles for the Internet <xref
 target="IRP"/> was developed and released. According to these documents, some
 examples of human rights relevant for ICT systems are human dignity (Art. 1
 UDHR), non&nbhy;discrimination (Art. 2), rights to life, liberty and security
 (Art. 3), freedom of opinion and expression (Art. 19), freedom of assembly and
 association (Art. 20), rights to equal protection, legal remedy, fair trial,
 due process, presumed innocent (Art. 7-11), appropriate social and
 international order (Art. 28), participation in public affairs (Art.&nbsp;21),
 participation in cultural life, protection of intellectual property
 (Art. 27), and privacy (Art. 12).</t>
</list>
 </t>

 <t>A partial catalog of human rights related to ICTs,
 including economic rights, can be found in <xref target="Hill2014"/>.</t>

 <t>This is by no means an attempt to exclude specific rights or prioritize
 some rights over others. If other rights seem relevant, please contact the
 authors of this document.</t>

 </section>

 <section anchor="guidelines-for-human-rights-considerations" title="Guidelines for Human Rights Considerations">
 <t>This section provides guidance for document authors in the form of a
 questionnaire about protocols and their (potential) impact. The questionnaire
 may be useful at any point in the design process, particularly after document
 authors have developed a high-level protocol model as described in <xref
 target="RFC4101"/>. These guidelines do not seek to replace any existing
 referenced specifications; rather, they contribute to them and look at the
 design process from a human rights perspective.</t>

 <t>Protocols and Internet Standards might benefit from a documented discussion
 of potential human rights risks arising from potential misapplications of the
 protocol or technology described in the RFC in question. This might be coupled
 with an Applicability Statement for that RFC.</t>

 <t>Note that the guidance provided in this section does not recommend specific
 practices. The range of protocols developed in the IETF is too broad to make
 recommendations about particular uses of data or how human rights might be
 balanced against other design goals.  However, by carefully considering the
 answers to the following questions, document authors should be able to produce
 a comprehensive analysis that can serve as the basis for discussion on
 whether the protocol adequately takes specific human rights threats into
 account. This guidance is meant to help the thought process of a human rights
 analysis; it does not provide specific directions for how to write a human
 rights protocol considerations section (following the example set in <xref
 target="RFC6973"/>), and the addition of a human rights protocol
 considerations section has also not yet been proposed. In considering these
 questions, authors will need to be aware of the potential of technical
 advances or the passage of time to undermine protections.  In general,
 considerations of rights are likely to be more effective if they are
 considered given a purpose and specific use cases, rather than as abstract
 absolute goals.</t>

 <section anchor="connectivity" title="Connectivity">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Does your protocol add application-specific functions to intermediary
 nodes?</t>
 <t>Could this functionality be added to end nodes instead of intermediary
 nodes?</t>
 <t>Is your protocol optimized for low bandwidth and high-latency
 connections?</t>
 <t>Could your protocol also be developed in a stateless manner?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 The end-to-end principle <xref target="Saltzer"/> holds that "the
 intelligence is end to end rather than hidden in the network" <xref
 target="RFC1958"/>. The end-to-end principle is important for the robustness
 of the network and innovation. Such robustness of the network is crucial to
 enabling human rights like freedom of expression.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 Middleboxes (which can be content delivery networks, firewalls, NATs, or
 other intermediary nodes that provide "services" other than routing)
 serve many legitimate purposes. But the protocols guiding them can influence
 individuals' ability to communicate online freely and privately. The potential
 for abuse, intentional and unintentional censoring, and limiting
 permissionless innovation -- and thus, ultimately, the impact of middleboxes
 on the Internet as a place of unfiltered, unmonitored freedom of speech -- is
 real.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Did you have a look at the guidelines in Section&nbsp;7 of
 <xref target="RFC6973"/> ("Privacy Considerations for Internet
 Protocols")?</t>
 <t>Could your protocol in any way impact the confidentiality of
 protocol metadata?</t>
 <t>Could your protocol counter traffic analysis?</t>
 <t>Could your protocol improve data minimization?</t>
 <t>Does your document identify potentially sensitive data logged by your
 protocol and/or for how long that data needs to be retained for
 technical reasons?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 "Privacy" refers to the right of an entity (normally a person), acting on its
 own behalf, to determine the degree to which it will interact with its
 environment, including the degree to which the entity is willing to share its
 personal information with others <xref target="RFC4949"/>. If a protocol
 provides insufficient privacy protection, it may have a negative impact on
 freedom of expression as users self&nbhy;censor for fear of surveillance
 or find themselves unable to express themselves freely.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 See <xref target="RFC6973"/>.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="content-agnosticism" title="Content Agnosticism">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>If your protocol impacts packet handling, does it use user data (packet
 data that is not included in the header)?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol make decisions based on the payload of the packet?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol prioritize certain content or services over others
 in the routing process?</t>
 <t>Is the protocol transparent about the prioritization that is made
 (if any)?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 "Content agnosticism" refers to the notion that network traffic is treated
 identically regardless of payload, with some exceptions when it comes to
 effective traffic handling -- for instance, delay-tolerant or
 delay-sensitive packets based on the header.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 Content agnosticism prevents payload-based discrimination against
 packets. This is important because changes to this principle can lead to a
 two-tiered Internet, where certain packets are prioritized over others based
 on their content. Effectively, this would mean that although all users are
 entitled to receive their packets at a certain speed, some users become
 more equal than others.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to equal protection</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="security" title="Security">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Did you have a look at <xref target="BCP72"/> ("Guidelines for
 Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations")?</t>
 <t>Have you found any attacks that are somewhat related to your protocol
 yet considered out of scope for your document?
 </t>

 <t>Would these attacks be pertinent to the features of the Internet
 that enable human rights (as described throughout this document)?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 Most people speak of security as if it were a single monolithic property of a
 protocol or system; however, upon reflection one realizes that it is clearly
 not true. Rather, security is a series of related but somewhat independent
 properties. Not all of these properties are required for every application.
 Since communications are carried out by systems and access to systems is
 through communications channels, these goals obviously interlock, but they
 can also be independently provided <xref target="BCP72"/>.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 See <xref target="BCP72"/>.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to security</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>

 <section anchor="internationalization" title="Internationalization">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Does your protocol have text strings that have to be understood or entered
 by humans?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol allow Unicode? If so, do you accept texts in one
 charset (which must be UTF-8) or several (which is dangerous for
 interoperability)?</t>
 <t>If character sets or encodings other than UTF-8 are allowed, does your
 protocol mandate proper tagging of the charset?</t>
 <t>Did you have a look at <xref target="RFC6365"/>?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 "Internationalization" refers to the practice of making protocols, standards,
 and implementations usable in different languages and scripts (see
 <xref target="localization"/> ("Localization")). "In the IETF,
 'internationalization' means to add or improve the handling of non&nbhy;ASCII
 text in a protocol" <xref target="RFC6365"/>.</t>
 <t>A different perspective, more appropriate to protocols that are designed
 for global use from the beginning, is the definition used by the W3C
 <xref target="W3Ci18nDef"/>: "Internationalization is the design and
 development of a product, application or document content that enables easy
 localization for target audiences that vary in culture, region,
 or language."</t>

 <t>Many protocols that handle text only handle one charset (US&nbhy;ASCII),
 or they leave the question of what coded character set (CCS) and encoding
 are used up to local guesswork (which leads, of course, to
 interoperability problems) <xref target="RFC3536"/>. If multiple charsets
 are permitted, they must be explicitly identified <xref target="RFC2277"/>.
 Adding non&nbhy;ASCII text to a protocol allows the protocol to handle more
 scripts, hopefully all scripts in use in the world.  In today's world,
 that is normally best accomplished by allowing Unicode encoded in UTF-8
 only.</t>

 <t>In the current IETF policy <xref target="RFC2277"/>, internationalization
 is aimed at user-facing strings, not protocol elements, such as the verbs used
 by some text-based protocols. (Do note that some strings, such as identifiers,
 are both content and protocol elements.) If the Internet wants to be a
 global network of networks, the protocols should work with languages other
 than English and character sets other than Latin characters. It is therefore
 crucial that at least the content carried by the protocol can be in any
 script and that all scripts are treated equally.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Example:">
 See <xref target="localization"/> ("Localization").</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to political participation</t>
   <t>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="censorship-resistance" title="Censorship Resistance">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Does this protocol introduce new identifiers or reuse existing identifiers
 (e.g., Media Access Control (MAC) addresses) that might be associated with
 persons or content?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol make it apparent or transparent when access to a
 resource is restricted?</t>
 <t>Can your protocol contribute to filtering in such a way that it could be
 implemented to censor data or services?  If so, could your protocol be
 designed to ensure that this doesn't happen?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 "Censorship resistance" refers to the methods and measures to prevent Internet
 censorship.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 When IPv6 was developed, embedding a MAC address into unique IP addresses
 was discussed. This makes it possible, per <xref target="RFC4941"/>, for
 "eavesdroppers and other information collectors to identify
 when different addresses used in different transactions actually
 correspond to the same node." This is why privacy extensions for
 stateless address autoconfiguration in IPv6 <xref target="RFC4941"/>
 have been introduced.</t>

 <t>Identifiers of content exposed within a protocol might be used to
 facilitate censorship, as in the case of application-layer-based censorship,
 which affects protocols like HTTP. Denial or restriction of access can be
 made apparent by the use of status code 451, thereby allowing server operators
 to operate with greater transparency in circumstances where issues of law or
 public policy affect their operation <xref target="RFC7725"/>.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to political participation</t>
   <t>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="open-standards" title="Open Standards">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Is your protocol fully documented in such a way that it could be easily
 implemented, improved, built upon, and/or further developed?</t>
 <t>Do you depend on proprietary code for the implementation, running,
 or further development of your protocol?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol favor a particular proprietary specification
 over technically equivalent and competing specification(s) -- for instance,
 by making any incorporated vendor specification "required" or "recommended"
 <xref target="RFC2026"/>?</t>
 <t>Do you normatively reference another standard that is not available
 without cost (and could you possibly do without it)?</t>
 <t>Are you aware of any patents that would prevent your standard from being
 fully implemented <xref target="RFC6701"/> <xref target="RFC8179"/>?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 The Internet was able to be developed into the global network of networks
 because of the existence of open, non&nbhy;proprietary standards <xref
 target="Zittrain"/>. They are crucial for enabling interoperability. Yet, open
 standards are not explicitly defined within the IETF. On the subject, <xref
 target="RFC2026"/> states the following: "Various national and
 international standards bodies, such as ANSI, ISO, IEEE, and ITU-T,
 develop a variety of protocol and service specifications that are similar
 to Technical Specifications defined" at the IETF. "National and
 international groups also publish 'implementors' agreements' that are
 analogous to Applicability Statements, capturing a body of
 implementation-specific detail concerned with the practical application of
 their standards.  All of these are considered to be 'open external standards'
 for the purposes of the Internet Standards Process." Similarly, <xref
 target="RFC3935"/> does not define open standards but does emphasize the
 importance of "open process": any interested person can participate in the
 work, know what is being decided, and make his or her voice heard on the
 issue. Part of this principle is the IETF's commitment to making its
 documents, WG mailing lists, attendance lists, and meeting minutes publicly
 available on the Internet.</t>

 <t>Open standards are important, as they allow for permissionless innovation,
 which in turn is important for maintaining the freedom and ability to freely
 create and deploy new protocols on top of the communications constructs that
 currently exist. It is at the heart of the Internet as we know it, and to
 maintain its fundamentally open nature, we need to be mindful of the need for
 developing open standards.</t>

 <t>All standards that need to be normatively implemented should be freely
 available and should provide reasonable protection against patent infringement
 claims, so that it can also be implemented in open-source or free
 software. Patents have often held back open standardization or have been used
 against those deploying open standards, particularly in the domain of
 cryptography <xref target="Newegg"/>. An exemption is sometimes made when a
 protocol that normatively relies on specifications produced by other SDOs that
 are not freely available is standardized. Patents in open standards or in
 normative references to other standards should have a patent disclosure <xref
 target="notewell"/>, royalty-free licensing <xref target="patentpolicy"/>, or
 some other form of reasonable protection. Reasonable patent protection should
 include, but is not limited to, cryptographic primitives.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 <xref target="RFC6108"/> describes a system deployed by Comcast, an ISP,
 for providing critical end&nbhy;user notifications to web browsers. Such a
 notification system is being used to provide almost&nbhy;immediate
 notifications to customers, such as warning them that their traffic exhibits
 patterns that are indicative of malware or virus infection. There are other
 proprietary systems that can perform such notifications, but those systems
 utilize Deep Packet Inspection (DPI) technology.  In contrast to DPI,
 <xref target="RFC6108"/> describes a system that does not rely upon DPI
 and is instead based on open IETF standards and open-source applications.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="heterogeneity-support" title="Heterogeneity Support">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Does your protocol support heterogeneity by design?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol allow for multiple types of hardware?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol allow for multiple types of application protocols?</t>
 <t>Is your protocol liberal in what it receives and handles?</t>
 <t>Will your protocol remain usable and open if the context changes?</t>
 <t>Does your protocol allow well-defined extension points? If so, do
 these extension points allow for open innovation?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 <xref target="FIArch"/> notes the following: "The Internet is characterized by
 heterogeneity on many levels: devices and nodes, router scheduling algorithms
 and queue management mechanisms, routing protocols, levels of multiplexing,
 protocol versions and implementations, underlying link layers (e.g.,
 point-to-point, multi-access links, wireless, FDDI, etc.), in the traffic mix
 and in the levels of congestion at different times and places. Moreover, as
 the Internet is composed of autonomous organizations and internet service
 providers, each with their own separate policy concerns, there is a large 
 heterogeneity of administrative domains and pricing structures." As a result,
 as also noted in <xref target="FIArch"/>, the heterogeneity principle proposed
 in <xref target="RFC1958"/> needs to be supported by design.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 Heterogeneity is inevitable and needs to be supported by design. For example,
 multiple types of hardware must be allowed for transmission speeds differing
 by at least seven orders of magnitude, various computer word lengths, and hosts
 ranging from memory-starved microprocessors up to massively parallel
 supercomputers. As noted in <xref target="RFC1958"/>, "Multiple types of
 application protocol must be allowed for, ranging from the simplest such as
 remote login up to the most complex such as distributed databases."</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
   <t>Right to political participation</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="anonymity" title="Anonymity">

 <t>Question:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Did you have a look at <xref target="RFC6973"/> ("Privacy Considerations
 for Internet Protocols"), especially Section&nbsp;6.1.1 of that
 document?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 "Anonymity" refers to the condition of an identity being unknown or concealed
 <xref target="RFC4949"/>. Even though full anonymity is hard to achieve, it is
 a non&nbhy;binary concept. Making pervasive monitoring and tracking harder is
 important for many users as well as for the IETF <xref target="RFC7258"/>.
 Achieving a higher level of anonymity is an important feature for many
 end&nbsp;users, as it allows them different degrees of privacy online.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 Protocols often expose personal data; it is therefore important to
 consider ways to mitigate the obvious impacts on privacy. A protocol that uses
 data that could help identify a sender (items of interest) should be protected
 from third parties. For instance, if one wants to hide the source/destination
 IP addresses of a packet, the use of IPsec in tunneling mode (e.g., inside a
 VPN) can help protect against third parties likely to eavesdrop packets
 exchanged between the tunnel endpoints.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to political participation</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
   <t>Right to security</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="pseudonymity" title="Pseudonymity">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Have you considered <xref target="RFC6973"/> ("Privacy Considerations for
 Internet Protocols"), especially Section&nbsp;6.1.2 of that document?</t>
 <t>Does the protocol collect personally derived data?</t>
 <t>Does the protocol generate or process anything that can be, or that can
 be tightly correlated with, personally identifiable information?</t>
 <t>Does the protocol utilize data that is personally derived, i.e.,
 derived from the interaction of a single person or from their device or
 address?</t>
 <t>Does this protocol generate personally derived data?  If so, how will
 that data be handled?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 Pseudonymity -- the ability to use a persistent identifier that is not
 immediately linked to one's offline identity -- is an important feature for
 many end&nbsp;users, as it allows them different degrees of disguised identity
 and privacy online.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 When designing a standard that exposes personal data, it is important to
 consider ways to mitigate the obvious impacts. While pseudonyms cannot
 easily be reverse-engineered -- for example, some early approaches
 used such techniques as simple hashing of IP addresses that could
 in turn be easily reversed by generating a hash for each potential
 IP address and comparing it to the pseudonym -- limiting the exposure
 of personal data remains important.</t>

 <t>"Pseudonymity" means using a pseudonym instead of one's "real" name. There
 are many reasons for users to use pseudonyms -- for instance, to hide their
 gender; protect themselves against harassment; protect their families'
 privacy; frankly discuss sexuality; or develop an artistic or journalistic
 persona without retribution from an employer, (potential) customers, or social
 surroundings <xref target="geekfeminism"/>. The difference between anonymity
 and pseudonymity is that a pseudonym is often persistent. "Pseudonymity is
 strengthened when less personal data can be linked to the pseudonym; when the
 same pseudonym is used less often and across fewer contexts; and when
 independently chosen pseudonyms are more frequently used for new actions
 (making them, from an observer's or attacker's perspective, unlinkable)."
 <xref target="RFC6973"/></t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="accessibility" title="Accessibility">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Is your protocol designed to provide an enabling environment for people who
 are not able-bodied?</t>
 <t>Have you looked at the W3C Web Accessibility Initiative
 <xref target="W3CAccessibility"/> for examples and guidance?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 The Internet is fundamentally designed to work for all people, whatever their
 hardware, software, language, culture, location, or physical or mental
 ability. When the Internet meets this goal, it is accessible to people with a
 diverse range of hearing, movement, sight, and cognitive abilities
 <xref target="W3CAccessibility"/>. Sometimes, in the design of protocols,
 websites, web technologies, or web tools, barriers that exclude people from
 using the Web are created.</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 The HTML protocol as defined in <xref target="HTML5"/> specifically requires
 that (with a few exceptions) every image must have an "alt" attribute to
 ensure that images are accessible for people that cannot themselves decipher
 non&nbhy;text content in web pages.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
   <t>Right to education</t>
   <t>Right to political participation</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="localization" title="Localization">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Does your protocol uphold the standards of internationalization?</t>
 <t>Have you taken any concrete steps towards localizing your protocol for
 relevant audiences?</t>
 </list></t>

 <t><list style="hanging">
 <t hangText="Explanation:">
 Per <xref target="W3Ci18nDef"/>, "Localization refers to the adaptation of a
 product, application or document content to meet the language, cultural and
 other requirements of a specific target market (a 'locale')." It is also
 described as the practice of translating an implementation to make it
 functional in a specific language or for users in a specific locale
 (see <xref target="internationalization"/> ("Internationalization")).</t>

 <t hangText="Example:">
 The Internet is a global medium, but many of its protocols and products are
 developed with a certain audience in mind; this audience often shares
 particular characteristics like knowing how to read and write in ASCII and
 knowing English. This limits the ability of a large part of the world's online
 population to use the Internet in a way that is culturally and linguistically
 accessible. An example of a protocol that has taken into account the view that
 individuals like to have access to data in their native language can be found
 in <xref target="RFC5646"/>; such a protocol would label the information
 content with an identifier for the language in which it is written and
 would allow information to be presented in more than one language.</t>
 </list></t>

 <t>Impacts:</t>

 <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Right to non-discrimination</t>
   <t>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</t>
   <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
 </list></t>

 </section>
 <section anchor="decentralization" title="Decentralization">

 <t>Questions:</t>
 <t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Can your protocol be implemented without one single point of control?</t>
 <t>If applicable, can your protocol be deployed in a federated manner?</t>
 <t>What is the potential for discrimination against users of
 your protocol?</t>
 <t>Can your protocol be used to negatively implicate users (e.g.,
 incrimination, accusation)?</t>
<t>Does your protocol create additional centralized points of control?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
Decentralization is one of the central technical concepts of the architecture
of networks and is embraced as such by the IETF <xref target="RFC3935"/>. It
refers to the absence or minimization of centralized points of control --
"a feature that is assumed to make it easy for new users to join and new
uses to unfold" <xref target="Brown"/>. It also reduces issues surrounding
single points of failure and distributes the network such that it continues to
function if one or several nodes are disabled. With the commercialization of
the Internet in the early 1990s, there has been a slow trend toward moving
away from decentralization, to the detriment of any technical benefits
that having a decentralized Internet otherwise provides.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
The bits traveling the Internet are increasingly susceptible to monitoring and
censorship, from both governments and ISPs, as well as third (malicious)
parties. The ability to monitor and censor is further enabled by increased
centralization of the network, creating central infrastructure points that
can be tapped into. The creation of P2P networks and the development of
voice-over-IP protocols using P2P technology in combination with a distributed
hash table (DHT) for scalability are examples of how protocols can preserve
decentralization <xref target="Pouwelse"/>.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="reliability" title="Reliability">

<t>Questions:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Is your protocol fault tolerant?</t>
<t>Does your protocol degrade gracefully?</t>
<t>Can your protocol resist malicious degradation attempts?</t>
<t>Do you have a documented way to announce degradation?</t>
<t>Do you have measures in place for recovery or partial healing
from failure?</t>
<t>Can your protocol maintain dependability and performance in the face of
unanticipated changes or circumstances?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
Reliability ensures that a protocol will execute its function consistently,
be error resistant as described, and function without unexpected results. A
system that is reliable degenerates gracefully and will have a documented way
to announce degradation.  It also has mechanisms to recover from failure
gracefully and, if applicable, to allow for partial healing. It is important
here to draw a distinction between random degradation and malicious
degradation. Many current attacks against TLS, for example, exploit TLS's
ability to gracefully degrade to older cipher suites; from a functional
perspective, this ability is good, but from a security perspective, it can
be very bad. As with confidentiality, the growth of the Internet and fostering
innovation in services depend on users having confidence and trust <xref
target="RFC3724"/> in the network. For reliability, it is necessary that
services notify users if packet delivery fails. In the case of real-time
systems, the protocol needs to safeguard timeliness in addition to providing
reliable delivery.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
In the modern IP stack structure, a reliable transport layer requires an
indication that transport processing has successfully completed, such as
the indication given by TCP's ACK message <xref target="RFC793"/> and not
simply an indication from the IP layer that the packet arrived.  Similarly, an
application-layer protocol may require an application-specific acknowledgement
that contains, among other things, a status code indicating the disposition of
the request (see <xref target="RFC3724"/>).</t>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to security</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="confidentiality" title="Confidentiality">

<t>Questions:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Does this protocol expose information related to identifiers or data?
If so, does it do so to each of the other protocol entities (i.e.,
recipients, intermediaries, and enablers) <xref target="RFC6973"/>?</t>
<t>What options exist for protocol implementers to choose to limit the
information shared with each entity?</t>
<t>What operational controls are available to limit the information shared
with each entity?</t>
<t>What controls or consent mechanisms does the protocol define or require
before personal data or identifiers are shared or exposed via the protocol?
If no such mechanisms or controls are specified, is it expected that control
and consent will be handled outside of the protocol?</t>
<t>Does the protocol provide ways for initiators to share different pieces of
information with different recipients?  If not, are there mechanisms that
exist outside of the protocol to provide initiators with such control?</t>
<t>Does the protocol provide ways for initiators to limit which information is
shared with intermediaries?  If not, are there mechanisms that exist outside
of the protocol to provide users with such control?</t>
<t>Is it expected that users will have relationships that govern the use of
the information (contractual or otherwise) with those who operate these
intermediaries?</t>
<t>Does the protocol prefer encryption over cleartext operation?</t>
<t>Does the protocol provide ways for initiators to express individuals'
preferences to recipients or intermediaries with regard to the collection,
use, or disclosure of their personal data?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
"Confidentiality" refers to keeping a user's data secret from unintended
listeners <xref target="BCP72"/>. The growth of the Internet depends on users
having confidence that the network protects their personal data <xref
target="RFC1984"/>.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
Protocols that do not encrypt their payload make the entire content of the
communication available to the idealized attacker along their
path <xref target="RFC7624"/>. Following the advice in <xref
target="RFC3365"/>, most such protocols have a secure variant that encrypts
the payload for confidentiality, and these secure variants are seeing
ever-wider deployment. A noteworthy exception is DNS <xref target="RFC1035"/>,
as DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033"/> does not have confidentiality as a
requirement. This implies that, in the absence of changes to the protocol as
presently under development in the IETF's DNS Private Exchange (DPRIVE)
Working Group, all DNS queries and answers generated by the activities of any
protocol are available to the attacker. When store-and-forward protocols are
used (e.g., SMTP <xref target="RFC5321"/>), intermediaries leave this data
subject to observation by an attacker that has compromised these
intermediaries, unless the data is encrypted end to end by the
application-layer protocol or the implementation uses an encrypted store for
this data <xref target="RFC7624"/>.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to privacy</t>
  <t>Right to security</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="integrity" title="Integrity">

<t>Questions:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Does your protocol maintain, assure, and/or verify the accuracy of
payload data?</t>
<t>Does your protocol maintain and assure the consistency of data?</t>
<t>Does your protocol in any way allow the data to be (intentionally or
unintentionally) altered?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
"Integrity" refers to the maintenance and assurance of the accuracy and
consistency of data to ensure that it has not been (intentionally or
unintentionally) altered.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
Integrity verification of data is important for preventing vulnerabilities
and attacks such as man-in-the-middle attacks. These attacks happen when a
third party (often for malicious reasons) intercepts a communication between
two parties, inserting themselves in the middle and changing the content of
the data. In practice, this looks as follows:<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
  <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne forges and sends a message to Bob, impersonating Alice.</t>
  <t>Bob cannot see that the data from Alice was altered by Corinne.</t>
  <t>Corinne intercepts and alters the communication as it is sent between
  Alice and Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne is able to control the communication content.</t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to security</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="authenticity" title="Authenticity">

<t>Questions:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Do you have sufficient measures in place to confirm the truth of
   an attribute of an entity or of a single piece of data?</t>
<t>Can attributes get garbled along the way (see <xref target="security"/>
("Security"))?</t>
<t>If relevant, have you implemented IPsec, DNSSEC, HTTPS, and other
standard security best practices?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
Authenticity ensures that data does indeed come from the source it claims to
come from. This is important for preventing (1)&nbsp;certain attacks or
(2)&nbsp;unauthorized access to, and use of, data.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
Authentication of data is important for preventing vulnerabilities and attacks
such as man-in-the-middle attacks. These attacks happen when a third party
(often for malicious reasons) intercepts a communication between two parties,
inserting themselves in the middle and posing as both parties. In practice,
this looks as follows:</t>
</list></t>

<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<t><list>
  <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob.</t>
  <t>Alice sends data to Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne intercepts the data sent to Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne reads and alters the message to Bob.</t>
  <t>Bob cannot see that the data did not come from Alice
     but instead came from Corinne.</t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<t>When there is proper authentication, the scenario would be as follows:</t>

  <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob.</t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
  <t>Alice sends data to Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne intercepts the data sent to Bob.</t>
  <t>Corinne reads and alters the message to Bob.</t>
  <t>Bob can see that the data did not come from Alice
     but instead came from Corinne.</t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to privacy</t>
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to security</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="adaptability" title="Adaptability">

<t>Questions:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Is your protocol written in such a way that it would be easy for other
protocols to be developed on top of it or to interact with&nbsp;it?</t>
<t>Does your protocol impact permissionless innovation (see <xref target="connectivity"/> ("Connectivity") above)?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
Adaptability is closely interrelated with permissionless innovation; both
maintain the freedom and ability to freely create and deploy new protocols on
top of the communications constructs that currently exist. Permissionless
innovation is at the heart of the Internet as we know it. To maintain the
Internet's fundamentally open nature and ensure that it can continue to
develop, we need to be mindful of the impact of protocols on maintaining or
reducing permissionless innovation.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
WebRTC generates audio and/or video data. In order to ensure that WebRTC can
be used in different locations by different parties, it is important that
standard JavaScript APIs be developed to support applications from different
voice service providers. Multiple parties will have similar capabilities;
in order to ensure that all parties can build upon existing standards, these
standards need to be adaptable and allow for permissionless innovation.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to education</t>
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="outcome-transparency" title="Outcome Transparency">

<t>Question:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>Are the effects of your protocol fully and easily comprehensible,
including with respect to unintended consequences of protocol choices?</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Explanation:">
Certain technical choices may have unintended consequences.</t>

<t hangText="Example:">
Lack of authenticity may lead to lack of integrity and negative
externalities; spam is an example. Lack of data that could be used
for billing and accounting can lead to so-called "free" arrangements that
obscure the actual costs and distribution of the costs -- for example,
(1)&nbsp;the barter arrangements that are commonly used for Internet
interconnection and (2)&nbsp;the commercial exploitation of personal data for
targeted advertising, which is the most common funding model for the so-called
"free" services such as search engines and social networks.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Impacts:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Right to freedom of expression</t>
  <t>Right to privacy</t>
  <t>Right to freedom of assembly and association</t>
  <t>Right to access to information</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>As this document discusses research, there are no security
considerations.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="research-group-information" title="Research Group Information">
<t>The discussion list for the IRTF Human Rights Protocol Considerations
Research Group is located at the email address
&lt;hrpc@ietf.org&gt;. Information on the group and information on how
to subscribe to the list are provided at
&lt;https://www.irtf.org/mailman/listinfo/hrpc&gt;.</t>

<t>Archives of the list can be found at 
&lt;https://www.irtf.org/mail&nbhy;archive/web/hrpc/current/index.html&gt;.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Informative References'>

<reference  anchor='RFC760' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc760'>
<front>
<title>DoD standard Internet Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
<date year='1980' month='January' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='760'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0760'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='RFC791' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc791'>
<front>
<title>Internet Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
<date year='1981' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='5'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='791'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0791'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='RFC793' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc793'>
<front>
<title>Transmission Control Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
<date year='1981' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='7'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='793'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0793'/>
</reference>

<reference  anchor='RFC894' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc894'>
<front>
<title>A Standard for the Transmission of IP Datagrams over Ethernet Networks</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Hornig' fullname='C. Hornig'><organization /></author>
<date year='1984' month='April' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='41'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='894'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0894'/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1122"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1958"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1984"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2026"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2277"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2775"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3022"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3365"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3439"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3536"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3724"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3935"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4084"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4101"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4941"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4949"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5321"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5646"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5694"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5944"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6101"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6108"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6120"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6365"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6698"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6701"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6797"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6973"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7230"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7231"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7232"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7233"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7234"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7235"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7236"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7237"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7258"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7469"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7540"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7574"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7624"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7626"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7725"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7754"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7858"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8164"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8179"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8200"?>

<reference anchor="IRP" target="http://internetrightsandprinciples.org/site/campaign/">
  <front>
    <title>10&nbsp;Internet Rights &amp; Principles</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Internet Rights and Principles Dynamic Coalition</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2017"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="UNHRC2016"
           target="http://ap.ohchr.org/documents/alldocs.aspx?doc_id=20340">
  <front>
    <title>The promotion, protection and enjoyment of human rights on the Internet</title>
    <author >
      <organization>United Nations Human Rights Council</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Resolution" value="A/HRC/32/L.20"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="UNGA2013"
   target="https://documents-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/LTD/N13/576/77/PDF/N1357677.pdf?OpenElement">
  <front>
    <title>UN General Assembly Resolution "The right to privacy in the digital age" (A/C.3/68/L.45)</title>
    <author >
      <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="NETmundial" target="http://netmundial.br/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/NETmundial-Multistakeholder-Document.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>NETmundial Multistakeholder Statement</title>
    <author >
      <organization>NETmundial</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="UDHR" target="http://www.un.org/en/universal-declaration-human-rights/index.html">
  <front>
    <title>The Universal Declaration of Human Rights</title>
    <author >
      <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1948"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ICESCR" target="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/CESCR.aspx">
  <front>
    <title>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</title>
    <author >
      <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1966"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="CAIDA" target="http://www.caida.org/publications/papers/2014/outages_censorship/outages_censorship.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Analysis of Country-wide Internet Outages Caused by Censorship</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Dainotti">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Squarcella">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Aben">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Claffy">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Chiesa">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Russo">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Pescape">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2013"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/TNET.2013.2291244"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TorProject" target="https://www.torproject.org/">
  <front>
    <title>Anonymity Online</title>
    <author fullname="The Tor Project">
      <organization>The Tor Project</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2006"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="NATusage" target="http://www.icsi.berkeley.edu/pubs/networking/NATusage11.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>NAT usage in Residential Broadband networks</title>
    <author initials="G." surname="Maier">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="F." surname="Schneider">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Feldmann">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="PAM: International Conference on Passive and Active
     Network Measurement" value="Lecture Notes in Computer Science,
     Volume&nbsp;6579, Springer, Berlin and Heidelberg"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-642-19260-9_4"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BBC-wikileaks" target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7250916.stm">
  <front>
    <title>Whistle-blower site taken offline</title>
    <author >
      <organization>BBC</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2008"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="techyum" target="http://techyum.com/2010/10/official-vb-ly-link-shortener-seized-by-libyan-government/">
  <front>
    <title>Official - vb.ly Link Shortener Seized by Libyan Government</title>
    <author fullname="Violet">
      <organization>Violet</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2010"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Ververis" target="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/foci15/foci15-paper-ververis-update.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Understanding Internet Censorship Policy: The Case of Greece</title>
    <author initials="V." surname="Ververis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Kargiotakis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Filasto">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Fabian">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Alexandros">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2015"/>
  </front>
    <seriesInfo name="5th USENIX Workshop on Free and Open Communications"
        value="on the Internet (FOCI) '15"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-hall-censorship-tech (Expired) -->
<reference anchor="Hall">
  <front>
    <title>A Survey of Worldwide Censorship Techniques</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Hall">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Aaron">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Jones">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="Feamster">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-hall-censorship-tech-04"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="greatfirewall" target="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/foci14/foci14-anonymous.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Towards a Comprehensive Picture of the Great Firewall's DNS Censorship</title>
    <author fullname="Anonymous">
      <organization>Anonymous</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2014"/>
  </front>
    <seriesInfo name="4th USENIX Workshop on Free and Open Communications"
        value="on the Internet (FOCI) '14"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="torrentfreak1" target="https://torrentfreak.com/is-your-isp-messing-with-bittorrent-traffic-find-out-140123/">
  <front>
    <title>Is Your ISP Messing With BitTorrent Traffic? &nbsp;Find Out</title>
    <author initials="E." surname="Van der Sar">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="wikileaks" target="https://wikileaks.org/sony/docs/05/docs/Anti-Piracy/CDSA/EANTC-Survey-1.5-unsecured.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Market Survey: Detection &amp; Filtering Solutions to Identify File Transfer of Copyright Protected Content for Warner Bros. and movielabs</title>
    <author initials="T." surname="Sladek">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Broese">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ars" target="http://arstechnica.com/uncategorized/2007/10/p2p&nbhy;researchers-use-a-blocklist-or-you-will-be-tracked-100-of-the-time/">
  <front>
    <title>P2P researchers: use a blocklist or you will be tracked... 100% of the time</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Anderson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2007"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="torrentfreak2" target="https://torrentfreak.com/lawyers-sent-109000-piracy-threats-in-germany-during-2013-140304/">
  <front>
    <title>Lawyers Sent 109,000 Piracy Threats in Germany During 2013</title>
    <author fullname="Andy">
      <organization>Andy</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="freenet1" target="https://freenetproject.org/whatis.html">
  <front>
    <title>What is Freenet?</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Freenet</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="n.d."/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="freenet2" target="https://freenetproject.org/pages/about.html">
  <front>
    <title>The Philosophy behind Freenet</title>
    <author initials="I" surname="Clarke" fullname="Ian Clarke">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="n.d."/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Bitmessage" target="https://bitmessage.org/wiki/Main_Page">
  <front>
    <title>Bitmessage Wiki</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Bitmessage</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2017"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Tribler" target="https://www.tribler.org/about.html">
  <front>
    <title>About Tribler</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Delft University of Technology, Department EWI/PDS/Tribler</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="PETS2015VPN" target="http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~hamed/papers/PETS2015VPN.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>A Glance through the VPN Looking Glass: IPv6 Leakage and DNS Hijacking in Commercial VPN clients</title>
    <author initials="V.C." surname="Perta">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M.V." surname="Barbera">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Tyson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Haddadi">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Mei">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1515/popets-2015-0006"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="SPIEGEL" target="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/inside-the-nsa-s-war-on-internet-security-a-1010361.html">
  <front>
    <title>Prying Eyes - Inside the NSA's War on Internet Security</title>
    <author >
      <organization>SPIEGEL</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Rideout" target="http://gmailblog.blogspot.de/2008/07/making-security-easier.html">
  <front>
    <title>Making security easier</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Rideout">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2008"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Schillace" target="http://gmailblog.blogspot.de/2010/01/default-https-access-for-gmail.html">
  <front>
    <title>Default https access for Gmail</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Schillace">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2010"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Peterson" target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the&nbhy;switch/wp/2013/10/14/yahoo-to-make-ssl-encryption-the-default-for-webmail-users-finally/?utm_term=.a17eca45ddfe">
  <front>
    <title>Yahoo to make SSL encryption the default for Webmail users. &nbsp;Finally.</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Peterson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Gellman">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Soltani">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Collins" target="http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2015-07/06/hacking-team-spyware-company-hacked">
  <front>
    <title>Hacking Team's oppressive regimes customer list revealed in hack</title>
    <author initials="K." surname="Collins">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Cath" target="https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/hrpc/current/pdf36GrmRM84S.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>A Case Study of Coding Rights: Should Freedom of Speech Be Instantiated in the Protocols and Standards Designed by the Internet Engineering Task Force?</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Cath">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="CathFloridi">
  <front>
    <title>The Design of the Internet's Architecture by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) and Human Rights</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Cath">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Floridi">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2017" month="April"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Haagsma" target="http://blog.fox-it.com/2015/04/20/deep-dive-into-quantum-insert/">
  <front>
    <title>Deep dive into QUANTUM INSERT</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="Haagsma">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="WynsbergheMoura" target="http://doc.utwente.nl/87095/">
  <front>
    <title>The concept of embedded values and the example of internet security</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Nguyen" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="van Wynsberghe">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="van Wynsberghe">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Moreira Moura">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RSF" target="https://rsf.org/en/news/syria-using-34-blue-coat-servers-spy-internet-users">
  <front>
    <title>Syria using 34 Blue Coat servers to spy on Internet users</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Reporters Without Borders (RSF)</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Schneier" target="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/04/tor-attacks-nsa-users-online-anonymity">
  <front>
    <title>Attacking Tor: how the NSA targets users' online anonymity</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Schneier">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Appelbaum" target="http://daserste.ndr.de/panorama/aktuell/nsa230_page-1.html">
  <front>
    <title>NSA targets the privacy-conscious</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Appelbaum">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Gibson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Goetz">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Kabisch">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Kampf">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Ryge">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Marcak" target="https://citizenlab.org/2015/04/chinas-great-cannon/">
  <front>
    <title>China's Great Cannon</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Marcak">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="Weaver">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Dalek">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Ensafi">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Fifield">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="McKune">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Rey">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Scott-Railton">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Deibert">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Paxson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Googlepatent" target="https://www.google.com/patents/EP2601774A1?cl=en">
  <front>
    <title>Method and device for network traffic manipulation</title>
    <author fullname="Google">
      <organization>Google</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Marquis-Boire" target="https://citizenlab.org/2014/08/cat-video-and-the-death-of-clear-text/">
  <front>
    <title>Schrodinger's Cat Video and the Death of Clear-Text</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Marquis-Boire">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Pidgin" target="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/4322">
  <front>
    <title>[XMPP] Invisible mode violating standard</title>
    <author fullname="js">
      <organization>js</organization>
    </author>
    <author >
      <organization>Pidgin Developers</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2007"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="XMPP-Manifesto" target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/stpeter/manifesto/master/manifesto.txt">
  <front>
    <title>A Public Statement Regarding Ubiquitous Encryption on the XMPP Network</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="XMPP Operators">
      <organization>XMPP Operators</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Namecoin" target="https://namecoin.info/">
  <front>
    <title>Namecoin</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Namecoin</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Douceur" target="https://www.microsoft.com/en&nbhy;us/research/wp&nbhy;content/uploads/2002/01/IPTPS2002.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>The Sybil Attack</title>
    <author initials="J.R." surname="Douceur">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2002"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Ababil" target="http://ddanchev.blogspot.be/2012/09/dissecting-operation-ababil-osint.html">
  <front>
    <title>Dissecting 'Operation Ababil' - an OSINT Analysis</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Danchev">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2012"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="GreenMovement" target="https://www.nartv.org/2009/06/16/iran-ddos/">
  <front>
    <title>Iran DDoS</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Villeneuve">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ICCPR" target="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/CCPR.aspx">
  <front>
    <title>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</title>
    <author >
      <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1966"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Berners-Lee" >
  <front>
    <title>Weaving the Web: The Original Design and Ultimate Destiny of the
World Wide Web</title>
    <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Fischetti">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1999"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="HarperCollins," value="p. 208"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Saltzer" >
  <front>
    <title>End-to-End Arguments in System Design</title>
    <author initials="J.H." surname="Saltzer">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D.P." surname="Reed">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D.D." surname="Clark">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="1984"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ACM Transactions on Computer Systems (TOCS), Volume 2," value="Number 4, pp.&nbsp;277-288"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/357401.357402"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Clark" >
  <front>
    <title>The Design Philosophy of the DARPA Internet Protocols</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Clark">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="1988"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM '88, Proceedings of the ACM CCR, Volume 18,
      Number 4," value="pp. 106-114"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/52324.52336"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Franklin" target="http://houseofanansi.com/products/the-real-world-of-technology-digital">
  <front>
    <title>The Real World of Technology</title>
    <author initials="U.M." surname="Franklin">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="1999"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Dutton" target="http://www.unesco.org/new/en/communication-and-information/resources/publications-and-communication-materials/publications/full-list/freedom-of-connection-freedom-of-expression-the-changing-legal-and-regulatory-ecology-shaping-the-internet/">
  <front>
    <title>Freedom of Connection, Freedom of Expression: The Changing Legal and Regulatory Ecology Shaping the Internet</title>
    <author initials="W." surname="Dutton">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Dopatka">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Law">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Nash">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Kaye" target="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/FreedomOpinion/Pages/Privatesectorinthedigitalage.aspx">
  <front>
    <title>Freedom of expression and the private sector in the digital age</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Kaye">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="FIArch" target="http://www.future-internet.eu/uploads/media/FIArch_Design_Principles_V1.0.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Future Internet Design Principles</title>
    <author >
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2012" month="January"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Brown">
  <front>
    <title>A Prehistory of Internet Governance</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Ziewitz">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="I." surname="Brown" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Research Handbook on Governance of the Internet,"
      value="Part 1, Chapter 1 (pp. 3-26)"/>
  <seriesInfo name="Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd, Cheltenham," value="DOI 10.4337/9781849805049"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="FRAMEWORK">
  <front>
    <title>Information technology - Framework for internationalization</title>
    <author fullname="ISO/IEC">
      <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1998"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="prepared by ISO/IEC JTC&nbsp;1&wj;/SC&nbsp;22&wj;/WG&nbsp;20" value="ISO/IEC TR 11017"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="W3Ci18nDef" target="http://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-i18n.en">
  <front>
    <title>Localization vs. Internationalization</title>
    <author initials="R" surname="Ishida">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Miller">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web" value="Consortium"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="W3CAccessibility" target="https://www.w3.org/standards/webdesign/accessibility">
  <front>
    <title>Accessibility</title>
    <author >
      <organization>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Rachovitsa" target="https://academic.oup.com/ijlit/article/24/4/374/2566975/Engineering-and-lawyering-privacy-by-design">
  <front>
    <title>Engineering and lawyering privacy by design: understanding online privacy both as a technical and an international human rights issue</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Rachovitsa">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Law and Information Technology,"
    value="Volume 24, Issue 4, pp. 374-399"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1093/ijlit/eaw012"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Davidson-etal" target="https://www.cdt.org/files/publications/piais.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Strangers in a Strange Land: Public Interest Advocacy and Internet Standards</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Davidson">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Morris">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Courtney">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2002"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Telecommunications Policy Research Conference," value="Alexandria, VA"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Clark-etal" target="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1074049">
  <front>
    <title>Tussle in cyberspace: defining tomorrow's Internet</title>
    <author initials="D.D." surname="Clark">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Wroclawski">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K.R." surname="Sollins">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Braden">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2005"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (TON) archive,"
       value="Volume&nbsp;13, Issue 3, pp. 462-475"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/TNET.2005.850224"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Broeders" target="http://www.wrr.nl/en/publications/publication/article/de-publieke-kern-van-het-internet-1/">
  <front>
    <title>The public core of the Internet. &nbsp;An international agenda
for Internet governance</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Broeders">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="The Netherlands Scientific Council for Government Policy
      (WRR) Report No. 94" value="(under &quot;Reports to the government&quot;)"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Musiani" target="https://www.westminsterpapers.org/articles/10.16997/wpcc.214/">
  <front>
    <title>Giants, Dwarfs and Decentralized Alternatives to Internet-based Services: An Issue of Internet Governance</title>
    <author initials="F." surname="Musiani">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Westminster Papers in Communication and Culture,"
      value="10(1), pp. 81-94"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.16997/wpcc.214"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BrownMarsden" target="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/regulating-code">
  <front>
    <title>Regulating Code: Good Governance and Better Regulation in the
       Information Age</title>
    <author initials="I." surname="Brown">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Marsden">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="MIT" value="Press"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Brown-etal" target="http://conferences.sigcomm.org/co&nbhy;next/2010/Workshops/REARCH/ReArch_papers/10-Brown.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Should Specific Values Be Embedded In The Internet Architecture?</title>
    <author initials="I." surname="Brown">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Clark">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Trossen">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2010"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ReARCH&nbsp;'10, Proceedings of the Re-Architecting
the Internet Workshop," value="Article No. 10"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/1921233.1921246"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Abbate" target="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/inventing-internet">
  <front>
    <title>Inventing the Internet</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Abbate">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2000"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="MIT" value="Press"/>

</reference>
<reference anchor="Zittrain" target="https://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/4455262/Zittrain_Future%20of%20the%20Internet.pdf?sequence=1">
  <front>
    <title>The Future of the Internet - And How to Stop It</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Zittrain">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2008"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Yale University Press" value="&amp; Penguin UK"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="DeNardis15" target="http://is.gd/7GAnFy">
  <front>
    <title>The Internet Design Tension between Surveillance and Security</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="DeNardis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="IEEE Annals of the History of Computing," value="Volume 37, Issue 2"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/MAHC.2015.29"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="DeNardis14" target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vkz4n">
  <front>
    <title>The Global War for Internet Governance</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="DeNardis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Yale University" value="Press"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Lessig" target="http://codev2.cc/">
  <front>
    <title>Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace, Version&nbsp;2.0 (&apos;Codev2&apos;)</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="Lessig">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2006"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Basic Books," value="New York"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Mueller" target="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/networks-and-states">
  <front>
    <title>Networks and States: The Global Politics of Internet Governance</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Mueller">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2010"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="MIT" value="Press"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.7551/mitpress/9780262014595.001.0001"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Bless1" target="http://www.sigcomm.org/sites/default/files/ccr/papers/2016/April/0000000-0000003.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Values and Networks - Steps Toward Exploring their Relationships</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Orwat">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Bless">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review,"
      value="Volume 46, Number 2, pp. 25-31"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2935634.2935640"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Bless2" target="https://www.ietf.org/proceedings/93/slides/slides-93-hrpc-2.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Values and Networks</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Bless">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Orwat">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Benkler" target="http://is.gd/rxUpTQ">
  <front>
    <title>The Wealth of Networks - How Social Production Transforms Markets and Freedom</title>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Benkler">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2006"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Yale University Press," value="New Haven and London"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Babbie" >
  <front>
    <title>The Basics of Social Research</title>
    <author initials="E." surname="Babbie">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2017"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Cengage," value="Belmont, CA"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Denzin" target="http://www.amazon.com/SAGE-Handbook-Qualitative-Research-Handbooks/dp/1412974178">
  <front>
    <title>The SAGE Handbook of Qualitative Research</title>
    <author initials="N.K." surname="Denzin" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="Y.S." surname="Lincoln" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="SAGE Handbooks," value="Thousand Oaks, CA"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Geertz" target="http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/K/bo25832222.html">
  <front>
    <title>Kinship in Bali</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Geertz">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Geertz">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1975"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="University of Chicago Press," value="Chicago"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Jabri" >
  <front>
    <title>Discourses on violence: conflict analysis reconsidered</title>
    <author initials="V." surname="Jabri">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="1996"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Manchester University" value="Press"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="King" >
  <front>
    <title>Power, Social Violence and Civil Wars</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="King">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2007"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Chapter&nbsp;8 of" value="&quot;Leashing the Dogs of War:
      Conflict Management in a Divided World&quot;"/>
  <seriesInfo name="United States Institute of Peace Press,"
  value="Washington, D.C."/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Ritchie" target="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Qualitative-Research-Practice-Students-Researchers/dp/0761971106">
  <front>
    <title>Qualitative Research Practice: A Guide for Social Science Students and Researchers</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Ritchie">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Lewis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2003"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="SAGE Publishing," value="London"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Doty" target="https://github.com/npdoty/rfc-analysis">
  <front>
    <title>Automated text analysis of Requests for Comment (RFCs)</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Doty">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<!-- draft-pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios (Expired) -->
<reference anchor="Pouwelse">
  <front>
    <title>Media without censorship (CensorFree) scenarios</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Pouwelse" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2012"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Work in Progress," value="draft-pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios-02"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Penney" target="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2769645">
  <front>
    <title>Chilling Effects: Online Surveillance and Wikipedia Use</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Penney">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BernersLeeHalpin" target="http://www.ibiblio.org/hhalpin/homepage/publications/def-timbl-halpin.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Internet Access is a Human Right</title>
    <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Halpin">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Bhargavan" >
  <front>
    <title>Triple Handshakes and Cookie Cutters: Breaking and Fixing Authentication over TLS</title>
    <author initials="K." surname="Bhargavan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Delignat-Lavaud">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Fournet">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Pironti">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Strub">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2014"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="2014 IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy,"
      value="pp. 98-113"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/SP.2014.14"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Adrian" >
  <front>
    <title>Imperfect Forward Secrecy: How Diffie-Hellman Fails in Practice</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Adrian">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Bhargavan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z." surname="Durumeric">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Gaudry">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Green">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J.A." surname="Halderman">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="Heninger">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Springall">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Thome">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Valenta">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="VanderSloot">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Wustrow">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Zanella-Beguelin">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Zimmermann">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer
      and Communications Security," value="pp. 5-17"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2810103.2813707"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Aryan-etal" target="https://jhalderm.com/pub/papers/iran-foci13.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Internet Censorship in Iran: A First Look</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Aryan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Aryan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Alex Halderman">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="sslstrip" target="https://moxie.org/software/sslstrip/">
  <front>
    <title>Software &gt;&gt; sslstrip</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Marlinspike">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Newegg" target="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/11/newegg-on-trial-mystery-company-tqp-re-writes-the-history-of-encryption/">
  <front>
    <title>Newegg on trial: Mystery company TQP rewrites the history of encryption</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Mullin">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="notewell" target="https://www.ietf.org/about/note-well.html">
  <front>
    <title>Note Well</title>
    <author >
      <organization>IETF</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="patentpolicy" target="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">
  <front>
    <title>W3C Patent Policy</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Weitzner" role="editor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2004"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web" value="Consortium"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="FOC" target="https://www.freedomonlinecoalition.com/wp&nbhy;content/uploads/2014/04/FOC-recommendations-consensus.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>The Tallinn Agenda - Recommendations for Freedom Online</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Ministers of the Freedom Online Coalition</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Meyer" >
  <front>
    <title>Defining and Evaluating Resilience: A Performability Perspective</title>
    <author initials="J.F." surname="Meyer">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2009"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="presentation at International Workshop on Performability"
     value="Modeling of Computer and Communication Systems"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="dict" target="http://www.businessdictionary.com/definition/reliability.html">
  <front>
    <title>Reliability (dictionary entry)</title>
    <author >
      <organization>BusinessDictionary.com</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2017"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="WebFinance," value="Inc."/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Farrow" target="https://technet.microsoft.com/library/cc723706.aspx">
  <front>
    <title>Source Address Spoofing</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Farrow">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="WSJ" target="http://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424053111904199404576538721260166388">
  <front>
    <title>Firms Aided Libyan Spies</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Sonne">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Coker">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="The Wall Street" value="Journal"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Insinuator" target="https://www.insinuator.net/2013/08/vulnerabilities-attack-vectors-of-vpns-pt-1/">
  <front>
    <title>Vulnerabilities &amp; attack vectors of VPNs (Pt&nbsp;1)</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Schiess">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Alshalan-etal" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7314859/?arnumber=7314859">
  <front>
    <title>A Survey of Mobile VPN Technologies</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Alshalan">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Pisharody">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Huang">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="IEEE Communications Surveys &amp; Tutorials,"
      value="Volume 18, Issue 2, pp.1177-1196"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/COMST.2015.2496624"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="HTML5" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/">
  <front>
    <title>HTML5</title>
<author initials='I.' surname='Hickson' fullname='Ian Hickson' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Berjon' fullname='Robin Berjon' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Faulkner' fullname='Steve Faulkner' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Leithead' fullname='Travis Leithead' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Navara' fullname='Erika Doyle Navara' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials="E." surname="O'Connor" fullname="Edward O'Connor" role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Pfeiffer' fullname='Silvia Pfeiffer' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
    <date month="October" year="2014"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="W3C" value="Recommendation"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Greenwald" target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/31/nsa-top-secret-program-online-data">
  <front>
    <title>XKeyscore: NSA tool collects 'nearly everything a user does on the internet'</title>
    <author initials="G." surname="Greenwald">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="WP-Tempora" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tempora">
  <front>
    <title>Tempora</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Wikipedia</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2017"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BCP72" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp72">
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Korver' fullname='B. Korver'><organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='72'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3552'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="CoE" target="https://rm.coe.int/CoERMPublicCommonSearchServices/DisplayDCTMContent?documentId=09000016806b5a14">
  <front>
    <title>Applications to ICANN for Community-based New Generic Top Level
Domains (gTLDs): Opportunities and challenges from a human rights perspective</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Council of Europe</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="geekfeminism" target="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Pseudonymity">
  <front>
    <title>Pseudonymity</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Geek Feminism Wiki</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="HORNET" target="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2813628">
  <front>
    <title>HORNET: High-speed Onion Routing at the Network Layer</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Chen">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D.E." surname="Asoni">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Barrera">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Danezis">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Perrig">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2015"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="CCS '15, Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGSAC Conference on
    Computer and Communications Security," value="pp.&nbsp;1441-1454"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2810103.2813628"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Hill2014" target="http://www.apig.ch/UNIGE%20Catalog.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Partial Catalog of Human Rights Related to ICT Activities</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Hill">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="APIP" target="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2626306">
  <front>
    <title>Balancing accountability and privacy in the network</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Naylor">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M.K." surname="Mukerjee">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Steenkiste">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2014"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM '14, Proceedings of the 2014 ACM Conference on
     SIGCOMM," value="pp.&nbsp;75-86"/>
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2740070.2626306"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Sandvine" target="https://www.sandvine.com/pr/2015/12/7/sandvine-over-70-of-north-american-traffic-is-now-streaming-video-and-audio.html">
  <front>
    <title>Sandvine: Over 70% Of North American Traffic Is Now Streaming Video And Audio</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Sandvine</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2015"/>
  </front>
 </reference>

</references>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
<t>A special thanks to all members of the HRPC Research Group who
contributed to this document. The following deserve a special mention:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Joana Varon for helping draft the first iteration of the methodology
  and previous drafts, and for directing the film "Net of Rights" and
  working on the interviews at IETF&nbsp;92 in Dallas.</t>
  <t>Daniel Kahn Gillmor (dkg) for helping with the first iteration of the
  glossary (<xref target="vocabulary-used"/>) as well as a lot of
  technical guidance, support, and language suggestions.</t>
  <t>Claudio Guarnieri for writing the first iterations of the case studies on
  VPNs, HTTP, and P2P.</t>
  <t>Will Scott for writing the first iterations of the case studies on DNS,
  IP, and XMPP.</t>
  <t>Avri Doria for proposing writing a glossary in the first place, help with
  writing the initial proposals and Internet&nbhy;Drafts, her reviews, and her
  contributions to the glossary.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Thanks also to Stephane Bortzmeyer, John Curran, Barry Shein, Joe Hall,
Joss Wright, Harry Halpin, and Tim Sammut, who made a lot of excellent
suggestions, many of which found their way directly into the text. We want to
thank Amelia Andersdotter, Stephen Farrell, Stephane Bortzmeyer, Shane Kerr,
Giovane Moura, James Gannon, Alissa Cooper, Andrew Sullivan, S.&nbsp;Moonesamy,
Roland Bless, and Scott Craig for their reviews and for testing the HRPC
guidelines in the wild. We would also like to thank Molly Sauter, Arturo
Filasto, Nathalie Marechal, Eleanor Saitta, Richard Hill, and all others who
provided input on this document or the conceptualization of the idea. Thanks
to Edward Snowden for his comments at IETF&nbsp;93 in Prague regarding the
impact of protocols on the rights of users.</t>
</section>

  </back>
</rfc>

