<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" number="8176"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title>Authentication Method Reference Values</title>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
        <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Phil Hunt" initials="P." surname="Hunt">
      <organization>Oracle</organization>
      <address>
        <email>phil.hunt@yahoo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Anthony Nadalin" initials="A." surname="Nadalin">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>tonynad@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2017" />

    <area>Security Area</area>

    <workgroup>OAuth Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Authentication Method Reference</keyword>
    <keyword>Authentication Method</keyword>
    <keyword>"amr" Claim</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	The <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> (Authentication Methods References) claim
	is defined and registered in the IANA "JSON Web Token Claims" registry,
	but no standard Authentication Method Reference values are currently defined.
	This specification establishes a registry for Authentication Method Reference
	values and defines an initial set of Authentication Method Reference values.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
	The <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> (Authentication Methods References) claim
	is defined and registered in the IANA "JSON Web Token Claims" registry
	<xref target="IANA.JWT.Claims"/>,
	but no standard Authentication Method Reference values are currently defined.
	This specification establishes a registry for Authentication Method Reference
	values and defines an initial set of Authentication Method Reference values.
      </t>
      <t>
	For context, the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> (Authentication Methods References) claim
	is defined by Section 2 of the OpenID Connect Core 1.0 specification
	<xref target="OpenID.Core"/> as follows:

	<list style="hanging">
<!--Begin DNE text - direct quote -->
	  <t hangText="amr">
	    <vspace/>
	    OPTIONAL.
	    Authentication Methods References.
	    JSON array of strings that are identifiers for authentication methods
	    used in the authentication.
	    For instance, values might indicate that both password and OTP
	    authentication methods were used.
	    The definition of particular values to be used in the
	    <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> Claim
	    is beyond the scope of this specification.
	    Parties using this claim will need to agree upon the meanings of
	    the values used, which may be context-specific.
	    The <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> value is an array of
	    case sensitive strings.
	  </t>

	</list>
<!--End DNE text - direct quote -->
      </t>
      <t>
	Typically, each <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> value provides an identifier for a family of closely related authentication methods.
	For example, the <spanx style="verb">otp</spanx> identifier intentionally covers OTPs (One-Time Passwords) based on both time and HMAC (Hashed Message Authentication Code).
	Many relying parties will be content to know that an OTP has been used in addition to a password;
	the distinction between which kind of OTP was used is not useful to them.
	Thus, there's a single identifier that can be satisfied in two or more nearly equivalent ways.
      </t>
      <t>
	Similarly, there's a whole range of nuances between different fingerprint-matching algorithms.
	They differ in false-positive and false-negative rates over different population samples
	and also differ based on the kind and model of fingerprint sensor used.
	Like the OTP case, many relying parties will be content to know that a fingerprint match was made,
	without delving into and differentiating based on every aspect of the implementation of fingerprint capture and match.
	The <spanx style="verb">fpt</spanx> identifier accomplishes this.
      </t>
      <t>
	Ultimately, the relying party is depending upon the identity provider to do reasonable things.
	If it does not trust the identity provider to do so, it has no business using it.
	The <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> value lets the identity provider signal to the relying party additional information about what it did,
	for the cases in which that information is useful to the relying party.
      </t>
      <t>
	The <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> values defined by this specification
	are not intended to be an exhaustive set covering all use cases.
	Additional values can and will be added to the registry by other specifications.
	Rather, the values defined herein are an intentionally small set
	and are already actually being used in practice.
      </t>
      <t>
	The values defined by this specification only make distinctions that are known to be useful to relying parties.
	Slicing things more finely than would be used in practice would actually hurt interoperability, rather than helping it,
	because it would force relying parties to recognize that several or many different values actually mean the same thing to them.
      </t>
      <t>
	For context, while the claim values registered pertain to authentication,
	note that OAuth 2.0 <xref target="RFC6749"/> is designed for resource authorization
	and cannot be used for authentication without employing appropriate extensions,
	such as those defined by
	OpenID Connect Core 1.0 <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	The existence of the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim and values for it
	should not be taken as encouragement to try to use OAuth 2.0 for authentication
	without employing extensions that enable secure authentication to be performed.
      </t>

      <t>

	When used with OpenID Connect, if the identity provider supplies
	an <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim in the ID Token
	resulting from a successful authentication,
	the relying party can inspect the values returned and thereby
	learn details about how the authentication was performed.
	For instance, the relying party might learn that only a password was used
	or it might learn that iris recognition was used
	in combination with a hardware-secured key.
	Whether <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> values are provided and
	which values are understood by what parties are both
	beyond the scope of this specification.
	The <xref target="OpenID.MODRNA">OpenID Connect MODRNA Authentication Profile 1.0</xref>
	is one example of an application context that uses <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx>
	values defined by this specification.
      </t>

      <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>
	  This specification uses the terms
	  defined by JSON Web Token (JWT) <xref target="RFC7519"/> and
	  OpenID Connect Core 1.0 <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>


    <section anchor="amrValues" title="Authentication Method Reference Values">

      <t>
	The following is a list of Authentication Method Reference values
	defined by this specification:

	<list style="hanging">

	  <t hangText="face">
	    <vspace/>
	    Biometric authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/> using facial recognition.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="fpt">
	    <vspace/>
	    Biometric authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/> using a fingerprint.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="geo">
	    <vspace/>
	    Use of geolocation information for authentication,
	    such as that provided by <xref target="W3C.REC-geolocation-API-20161108"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="hwk">
	    <vspace/>
	    Proof-of-Possession (PoP) of a hardware-secured key.
	    See Appendix C of <xref target="RFC4211"/> for a discussion on PoP.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="iris">
	    <vspace/>
	    Biometric authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/> using an iris scan.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="kba">
	    <vspace/>
	    Knowledge-based authentication <xref target="NIST.800-63-2"/> <xref target="ISO29115"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="mca">
	    <vspace/>
	    Multiple-channel authentication <xref target="MCA"/>.
	    The authentication involves communication over more than one distinct communication channel.
	    For instance, a multiple-channel authentication might involve both entering information into
	    a workstation's browser and providing information on a telephone call to a pre-registered number.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="mfa">
	    <vspace/>
	    Multiple-factor authentication <xref target="NIST.800-63-2"/> <xref target="ISO29115"/>.
	    When this is present,
	    specific authentication methods used may also be included.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="otp">
	    <vspace/>
	    One-time password <xref target="RFC4949"/>.
	    One-time password specifications that this authentication method applies to
	    include <xref target="RFC4226"/> and <xref target="RFC6238"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="pin">
	    <vspace/>
	    Personal Identification Number (PIN) <xref target="RFC4949"/> or pattern
	    (not restricted to containing only numbers)
	    that a user enters to unlock a key on the device.
	    This mechanism should have a way to deter an attacker
	    from obtaining the PIN by trying repeated guesses.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="pwd">
	    <vspace/>
	    Password-based authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="rba">
	    <vspace/>
	    Risk-based authentication <xref target="JECM"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="retina">
	    <vspace/>
	    Biometric authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/> using a retina scan.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="sc">
	    <vspace/>
	    Smart card <xref target="RFC4949"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="sms">
	    <vspace/>
	    Confirmation using SMS <xref target="SMS"/> text message to the user at a registered number.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="swk">
	    <vspace/>
	    Proof-of-Possession (PoP) of a software-secured key.
	    See Appendix C of <xref target="RFC4211"/> for a discussion on PoP.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="tel">
	    <vspace/>
	    Confirmation by telephone call to the user at a registered number.
	    This authentication technique is sometimes also referred to as "call back" <xref target="RFC4949"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="user">
	    <vspace/>
	    User presence test. Evidence that the end user is present and interacting with the device.
	    This is sometimes also referred to as "test of user presence" <xref target="W3C.WD-webauthn-20170216"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="vbm">
	    <vspace/>
	    Biometric authentication <xref target="RFC4949"/> using a voiceprint.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="wia">
	    <vspace/>
	    Windows integrated authentication <xref target="MSDN"/>.
	  </t>

	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acrRelationship"
	     title='Relationship to "acr" (Authentication Context Class Reference)'>
      <t>
	The <spanx style="verb">acr</spanx> (Authentication Context Class Reference)
	claim and <spanx style="verb">acr_values</spanx> request parameter
	are related to
	the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> (Authentication Methods References)
	claim,
	but with important differences.
	An Authentication Context Class specifies a set of business rules that
	authentications are being requested to satisfy.
	These rules can often be satisfied by using a number of different
	specific authentication methods, either singly or in combination.
	Interactions using <spanx style="verb">acr_values</spanx> request that
	the specified Authentication Context Classes be used and that
	the result should contain an <spanx style="verb">acr</spanx> claim
	saying which Authentication Context Class was satisfied.
	The <spanx style="verb">acr</spanx> claim in the reply states that
	the business rules for the class were satisfied
	-- not how they were satisfied.
      </t>
      <t>
	In contrast, interactions using the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim
	make statements about the particular authentication methods that were used.
	This tends to be more brittle than using  <spanx style="verb">acr</spanx>,
	since the authentication methods that may be appropriate for a given
	authentication will vary over time, both because of the evolution of attacks
	on existing methods and the deployment of new authentication methods.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>
	The list of <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim values returned in
	an ID Token reveals information about the way that the end user
	authenticated to the identity provider.
	In some cases, this information may have privacy implications.
      </t>
      <t>
	While this specification defines identifiers for particular kinds of credentials,
	it does not define how these credentials are stored or protected.
	For instance, ensuring the security and privacy of biometric credentials
	that are referenced by some of the defined Authentication Method Reference values
	is beyond the scope of this specification.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	The security considerations in
	OpenID Connect Core 1.0 <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>,
	OAuth 2.0 <xref target="RFC6749"/>, and
	the entire OAuth 2.0 Threat Model <xref target="RFC6819"/>
	apply to applications using this specification.
      </t>
      <t>
	As described in <xref target="acrRelationship"/>, taking a dependence
	upon particular authentication methods may result in brittle systems
	since the authentication methods that may be appropriate for a given
	authentication will vary over time.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section title="Authentication Method Reference Values Registry" anchor="amrRegistry">
	<t>
	  This specification establishes the
	  IANA "Authentication Method Reference Values" registry
	  for <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim array element values.
	  The registry records the Authentication Method Reference value
	  and a reference to the specification that defines it.
	  This specification registers the Authentication Method Reference values
	  defined in <xref target="amrValues"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Values are registered on an Expert Review
	  <xref target="RFC5226"/> basis after a three-week review period on the &lt;jwt-reg-review@ietf.org&gt; mailing
          list, on the advice of one or more Designated Experts.
	  To increase potential interoperability, the Designated Experts are requested to encourage
	  registrants to provide the location of a publicly accessible specification
	  defining the values being registered,
	  so that their intended usage can be more easily  understood.
	</t>
        <t>
          Registration requests sent to the mailing list for review should use
          an appropriate subject
	  (e.g., "Request to register Authentication Method Reference value: otp").
        </t>
        <t>
          Within the review period, the Designated Experts will either approve or
          deny the registration request, communicating this decision to the review list and IANA.
          Denials should include an explanation and, if applicable, suggestions as to how to make
          the request successful.
	  Registration requests that are undetermined for
	  a period longer than 21 days can be brought to the IESG's attention
	  (using the &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt; mailing list) for resolution.
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA must only accept registry updates from the Designated Experts and should direct
          all requests for registration to the review mailing list.
        </t>
	<t>
	  It is suggested that the same Designated Experts evaluate these
	  registration requests as those who evaluate registration requests
	  for the IANA "JSON Web Token Claims" registry <xref target="IANA.JWT.Claims"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Criteria that should be applied by the Designated Experts include
	  determining whether the proposed registration duplicates existing functionality;
	  whether it is likely to be of general applicability
	  or whether it is useful only for a single application;
	  whether the value is actually being used;
	  and whether the registration description is clear.
	</t>

        <section title="Registration Template" anchor="amrTemplate">
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Authentication Method Reference Name:">
                <vspace/>
                The name requested (e.g., "otp") for the authentication method
		or family of closely related authentication methods.
		Because a core goal of this specification is for the resulting
		representations to be compact, it is RECOMMENDED that the name be short
		-- that is, not to exceed 8 characters without a compelling reason to do so.
		To facilitate interoperability, the name must use only
		printable ASCII characters excluding double quote ('"') and backslash ('\')
		(the Unicode characters with code points U+0021, U+0023 through U+005B, and
		U+005D through U+007E).
		This name is case sensitive.
		Names may not match other registered names in a case-insensitive manner
		unless the Designated Experts state that there is a compelling reason
		to allow an exception.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Authentication Method Reference Description:">
                <vspace/>
                Brief description of the Authentication Method Reference
		(e.g., "One-time password").
              </t>
              <t hangText="Change Controller:">
                <vspace/>
                For Standards Track RFCs, state "IESG". For others, give the name of the
                responsible party. Other details (e.g., postal address, email address, home page
                URI) may also be included.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Specification Document(s):">
                <vspace/>
                Reference to the document or documents that specify the parameter,
		preferably including URIs that
                can be used to retrieve copies of the documents.
		An indication of the relevant
                sections may also be included but is not required.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Initial Registry Contents" anchor="amrRegistrations">
          <t> <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">face</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Facial recognition
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>
		Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">fpt</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Fingerprint biometric
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Change Controller: IESG
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">geo</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Geolocation
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">hwk</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Proof-of-possession of a hardware-secured key
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">iris</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Iris scan biometric
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">kba</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Knowledge-based authentication
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">mca</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Multiple-channel authentication
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">mfa</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Multiple-factor authentication
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">otp</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  One-time password
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">pin</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Personal Identification Number or pattern
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">pwd</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Password-based authentication
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">rba</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Risk-based authentication
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">retina</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Retina scan biometric
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">sc</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Smart card
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">sms</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Confirmation using SMS
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">swk</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Proof-of-possession of a software-secured key
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">tel</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Confirmation by telephone call
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">user</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  User presence test
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">vbm</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Voice biometric
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
              </t>
            </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>
		Authentication Method Reference Name: <spanx style="verb">wia</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Authentication Method Reference Description:
		  Windows integrated authentication
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Change Controller: IESG
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Specification Document(s): <xref target="amrValues"/> of [RFC8176]
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	</section>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

      </section>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Core" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
            <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
          </author>

	  <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
	    <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
	  </author>

          <date day="8" month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml"?>
       <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="IANA.JWT.Claims" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/jwt">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token Claims</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
	  <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4211.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4226.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6238.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6819.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-geolocation-API-20161108.xml" ?>

      <reference anchor="NIST.800-63-2" target="http://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-63-2.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Electronic Authentication Guideline</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="NIST" value="Special Publication 800-63-2"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.SP.800-63-2"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISO29115" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/45138.html">
        <front>
          <title>ISO/IEC 29115:2013 Information technology - Security techniques - Entity authentication assurance framework</title>
          <author>
            <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="1" month="April" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="29115:2013"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="MSDN" target="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/benjaminperkins/archive/2011/09/14/iis-integrated-windows-authentication-with-negotiate.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>Integrated Windows Authentication with Negotiate</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>
	  <date day="14" month="September" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="JECM" target="http://utica.edu/academic/institutes/ecii/publications/articles/51D6D996-90F2-F468-AC09C4E8071575AE.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Enhanced Authentication In Online Banking</title>

          <author fullname="Gregory D. Williamson" initials="G.D.W." surname="Williamson">
            <organization />
          </author>

	  <date year="2006" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Journal of Economic Crime Management 4.2:"
                    value="18-19" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.MODRNA" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-modrna-authentication-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect MODRNA Authentication Profile 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Joerg Connotte" initials="J." surname="Connotte">
            <organization>Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization>Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="6" month="March" year="2017"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MCA" target="https://www.ldapwiki.com/wiki/Multiple-channel%20Authentication">
        <front>
          <title>Multiple-channel Authentication</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ldapwiki.com</organization>
          </author>
	  <date day="15" month="August" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SMS" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=141">
        <front>
          <title>Technical realization of the Short Message Service (SMS)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>
	  <date year="2002" month="January" day="11"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo value="03.40 Version 7.5.0 (2001-12)"
		    name="3GPP Technical Specification (TS)"/>
      </reference>

      <reference
	  target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2017/WD-webauthn-20170216/"
	  anchor="W3C.WD-webauthn-20170216">
	<front>
	  <title>Web Authentication: An API for accessing Scoped Credentials</title>
	  <author fullname="Vijay Bharadwaj" surname="Bharadwaj" initials="V."><organization>Microsoft</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Hubert Le Van Gong" surname="Le Van Gong" initials="H."><organization>PayPal</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Dirk Balfanz" surname="Balfanz" initials="D."><organization>Google</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Alexei Czeskis" surname="Czeskis" initials="A."><organization>Google</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Arnar Birgisson" surname="Birgisson" initials="A."><organization>Google</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Jeff Hodges" surname="Hodges" initials="J."><organization>PayPal</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" surname="Jones" initials="M.B."><organization>Microsoft</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="Rolf Lindemann" surname="Lindemann" initials="R."><organization>Nok Nok Labs</organization></author>
	  <author fullname="J.C. Jones" surname="Jones" initials="J.C."><organization>Mozilla</organization></author>
	  <date day="16" month="February" year="2017"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo value="WD-webauthn-20170216"
		    name="World Wide Web Consortium Working Draft"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Examples" title="Examples">
      <t>
	In some cases, the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim value returned
	may contain a single Authentication Method Reference value.
	For example, the following <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim value
	indicates that the authentication performed used an iris scan biometric:
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  "amr": ["iris"]
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </t>
      <t>
	In other cases, the <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim value returned
	may contain multiple Authentication Method Reference values.
	For example, the following <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> claim value
	indicates that the authentication performed used a password and
	knowledge-based authentication:
	<figure>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  "amr": ["pwd", "kba"]
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>
	Caleb Baker participated in specifying the original set
	of <spanx style="verb">amr</spanx> values.
	Jari Arkko,
	John Bradley,
	Ben Campbell,
	Brian Campbell,
	William Denniss,
	Linda Dunbar,
	Stephen Farrell,
	Paul Kyzivat,
	Elaine Newton,
	James Manger,
	Catherine Meadows,
	Alexey Melnikov,
	Kathleen Moriarty,
	Nat Sakimura,
	and Mike Schwartz
	provided reviews of the specification.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
