<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3444 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.3444.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6020 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6020.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6241 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6241.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7950 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7950.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.cheng-supa-applicability SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheng-supa-applicability.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-supa-generic-policy-data-model SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-supa-generic-policy-data-model.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-supa-generic-policy-info-model SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-supa-generic-policy-info-model.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.karagiannis-supa-problem-statement SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.karagiannis-supa-problem-statement.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.klyus-supa-value-proposition SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.klyus-supa-value-proposition.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.zhou-supa-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zhou-supa-framework.xml">
]>

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc number="8328" category="info" submissionType="independent" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>

<title abbrev="SUPA Policy-Based Management Framework">Policy-Based Management
Framework for the Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA)</title>

    <author fullname="Will (Shucheng) Liu" initials="W." surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <code>518129</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>liushucheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chongfeng Xie" initials="C." surname="Xie">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>China Telecom Information Technology Innovation Park</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>102209</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>xiechf.bri@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Strassner" initials="J." surname="Strassner">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95138</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>john.sc.strassner@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Georgios Karagiannis" initials="G."
            surname="Karagiannis">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hansaallee 205</street>
          <city>Dusseldorf</city>
          <code>40549</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Georgios.Karagiannis@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Maxim Klyus" initials="M." surname="Klyus">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>xmaruto@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jun Bi" initials="J." surname="Bi">
      <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Network Research Center, Tsinghua University</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100084</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>junbi@tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Ying Cheng" initials="Y." surname="Cheng">
      <organization>China Unicom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No.21 Financial Street, XiCheng District</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100033</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>chengying10@chinaunicom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
	<author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
		  <street></street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code></code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>	dacheng.zhang@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <date month="March" year="2018"/>

<abstract>

<t>The Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA) policy-based management
framework defines base YANG data models to encode policy. These models point to
device-, technology-, and service-specific YANG data models developed elsewhere.
Policy rules within an operator's environment can be used to express
high-level, possibly network-wide, policies to a network management function (within a controller, an orchestrator, or a network element). The network management function can then control the configuration
and/or monitoring of network elements and services. This document describes the SUPA basic framework, its elements, and interfaces.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">


      <t>Traffic flows over increasingly complex enterprise and service
      provider networks are becoming more and more important. Meanwhile, the
      rapid growth of this variety makes the task of network operations and
      management applications deploying new services much more
      difficult. Moreover, network operators want to deploy new services
      quickly and efficiently. Two possible mechanisms for dealing with this
      growing difficulty are 1) the use of software abstractions to simplify the
      design and configuration of monitoring and control operations and 2) the
      use of programmatic control over the configuration and operation of such
      networks.  Policy-based management can be used to combine these two
      mechanisms into an extensible framework.</t> <t>There is a set of policy rules within an operator's environment that
defines how services are designed, delivered, and operated.</t>
<t>The SUPA
      (Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions) data model represents a
      high-level, possibly network-wide policy, which can be input to a network management function (within a controller, an orchestrator, or a network element).  The network management function can then control the configuration
and/or monitoring of network elements and services according to such policies.</t>

       <t>SUPA defines a Generic
      Policy Information Model (GPIM) <xref target="SUPA-INFO"/> for use in network
      operations and management applications. The GPIM defines concepts and
      terminology needed by policy management independent of the form and
      content of the policy rule. The Event-Condition-Action (ECA)
	  Policy Rule Information Model (EPRIM) <xref target="SUPA-INFO"/> extends the GPIM by defining how to build policy rules
	  according to the ECA paradigm. 
	  </t>

      <t>Both the GPIM and the EPRIM are targeted at controlling the
      configuration and monitoring of network elements throughout the service
      development and deployment life cycle. The GPIM and the EPRIM can both
      be translated into corresponding YANG <xref target="RFC6020"/> <xref
      target="RFC7950"/> modules that
      define policy concepts, terminology, and rules in a generic and
      interoperable manner; additional YANG modules may also be derived from
      the GPIM and/or EPRIM to manage specific functions.</t>

      <t>The key benefit of policy management is that it enables different
      network elements and services to be instructed to behave the same way,
      even if they are programmed differently. Management applications will
      benefit from using policy rules that enable scalable and consistent
      programmatic control over the configuration and monitoring of network
      elements and services.</t>

	<t>Some typical and useful instances for authors to understand the
	applicability of SUPA, such as SNMP blocking upon load of link
	reaching a threshold and virtual matching migration upon the changing
	of user location, are described in <xref target="SUPA-APP"/>. </t>
    

    </section>
	
    <section title="Terminology">
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Abbreviations and Definitions">

<t>SUPA: The Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions is a policy-based management
framework that defines a data model to be used to represent high-level,
possibly network-wide policies.  This data model can be input to a network
management function (within a controller, an orchestrator, or a network element).</t>
	  <t>YANG: An acronym for "Yet Another Next Generation". YANG is a data modeling language used to model configuration and
   state data manipulated by the Network Configuration Protocol
   (NETCONF), NETCONF remote procedure calls, and NETCONF notifications <xref
   target="RFC6020"/></t>
   
	  <t>ECA: Event-Condition-Action is a shortcut for referring to the structure of active rules in event-driven architecture and active database systems.</t>
	  
	  <t>EMS: An Element Management System is software used to monitor and control network elements (devices) in telecommunications.</t>
	  
	  <t>NMS: A Network Management System is a set of hardware and/or software tools that allow an IT professional to supervise the individual components of a network within a larger network management framework.</t>
	  
	  <t>OSS: An Operations/Operational Support System is a computer system used by telecommunications service providers to manage their networks (e.g., telephone networks).</t>
	  
	  <t>BSS: A Business Support System is used to support various end-to-end telecommunication services.</t>
	  
	  <t> GPIM: A Generic Policy Information Model defines concepts and
      terminology needed by policy management independent of the form and
      content of the policy rule. </t> 		
 		
	  <t> EPRIM: An ECA Policy Rule Information Model extends the GPIM by defining how to build policy
      rules according to the ECA paradigm.</t>
	  
	  <t>GPDM: Generic Policy Data Models <xref target="SUPA-DATA"/> are created from
        the GPIM. These YANG data model policies are used to control the
        configuration of network elements that model the service(s) to be
        managed. The relationship between the information model (IM) and data model (DM) can be
	founded in <xref target="RFC3444"/>.</t>
		
	  <t>Declarative Policy: Policies that specify the goals to be achieved but not
        how to achieve those goals (also called "intent-based" policies). Please note that declarative policies are
        out of scope for the initial phase of SUPA. </t>
	</section></section>
	
    <section title="Framework for Generic Policy-Based Management">
      <t>This section briefly describes the design and operation of the SUPA
      policy-based management framework.</t>

      <section title="Overview">
        <t><xref target="frame"/> shows a simplified functional architecture of how SUPA is
        used to define policies for creating snippets of network element configurations.  SUPA uses the GPIM to
        define a consensual vocabulary that different actors can use to
        interact with network elements and services. The EPRIM defines a
        generic structure for imperative policies. The GPIM, and/or the
        combination of the GPIM and the EPRIM, is converted to generic YANG modules.</t>


        <t>In one possible approach (shown with
   asterisks in <xref target="frame"/>), SUPA Generic Policy and SUPA ECA Policy
        YANG modules together with the Resource and Service YANG data
        models specified in the IETF (which define the specific elements that will
        be controlled by policies) are used by the Service Interface Logic.
        This Service Interface Logic creates appropriate input mechanisms for
        the operator to define policies (e.g., a web form or a script) for
        creating and managing the network configuration. The operator
        interacts with the interface, and the policies input by operators are then translated into
        configuration snippets.</t>

        <t>Note that the Resource and Service YANG data models may not exist. In this case, the SUPA generic
		policy YANG modules serve as an extensible basis to develop new
		YANG data models for the Service Interface Logic. This transfers the work specified by the Resource and Service YANG
		data models specified in the IETF into the Service Interface Logic.
		</t>

        <figure title="SUPA Framework" anchor="frame">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                    
                       +---------------------+
   +----------+       \|        SUPA         |
   |   IETF   |---+----+  Information Models |
   +----------+   |   /|    GPIM and EPRIM   |
                  |    +---------+-----------+
      Assignments |              | Defines Policy Concepts
      and Managed |             \|/
        Content   |    +---------+-----------+
                  |   \|    SUPA Generic     |
                  +----+    & ECA Policy     |
                      /|    YANG modules     |
                       +---------+-----------+
                                 *  Possible Approach
   +-----------------------------*-----------------------------+
   |  Management System          *                             |
   |                            \*/                            |
   |            Fills  +---------+---------+  +-------------+  |
   | +--------+ Forms \| Service Interface |/ |Resource and |/ | +----+
   | |Operator|--------+       Logic       +--|Service YANG |----|IETF|
   | +--------+ Runs  /| (locally defined  |\ | data models |\ | +----+
   |           scripts |forms, scripts,...)|  +-------------+  |
   |                   +---------+---------+                   |
   |                            \|/                            |
   |                     +-------+--------+                    |
   |                     |  Local Devices |                    |
   |                     | and Management |                    |
   |                     |     Systems    |                    |
   |                     +----------------+                    |
   +-----------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t><xref target="frame"/> shows the SUPA Framework at a high level of abstraction. The operator actor can
        interact with SUPA in other ways not shown in <xref target="frame"/>. In addition,
        other actors (e.g., an application developer) that can interact with
        SUPA are not shown for simplicity.</t>

        <t>The EPRIM defines an ECA policy as an
        example of imperative policies. An ECA policy rule is activated when
        its event clause is true; the condition clause is then evaluated and,
        if true, signals the execution of one or more actions in the action
        clause. This type of policy explicitly defines the current and desired
        states of the system being managed. Imperative policy rules require
        additional management functions, which are explained in <xref target="operation"/>.</t>

        <t><xref target="model"/> shows how the SUPA Policy Model is used to create policy
        data models step-by-step and how the policy rules are used to
        communicate among various network management functions located on
        different layers.</t>

        <t>The GPIM is used to construct
        policies. The GPIM defines generic policy concepts as well as two
        types of policies: ECA policy rules and declarative policy
        statements. </t>

        <t>A set of Generic Policy Data Models (GPDM) are then created from
        the GPIM. These YANG data model policies are then used to control the
        configuration of network elements that model the service(s) to be
        managed.</t>
		
		<t>Resource and Service YANG Data Models: Models of the service as
        well as physical and virtual network topology including the resource
        attributes (e.g., data rate or latency of links) and operational
        parameters needed to support service deployment over the network
        topology.</t>

        <figure title="SUPA Policy Model Framework" anchor="model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                              |  SUPA Policy Model
                              |
                              |  +----------------------------------+
                              |  | Generic Policy Information Model |
                              |  +----------------------------------+
                              |        D                 D
                              |        D   +-------------v-------------+
 +----------------------+     |        D   |   ECA Policy Rule         |
 | OSS/BSS/Orchestrator <--+  |        D   |   Information Model       |
 +----------^-----------+  |  |        D   +---------------------------+
            C              |  |        D                          D
            C              |  |  +----+D+------------------------+D+---+
            C              +-----+     D  SUPA Policy Data Model  D    |
 +----------v-----------+     |  | ----v-----------------------+  D    |
 |  EMS/NMS/Controller  <--------+ | Generic Policy Data Model |  D    |
 +----------^-----------+     |  | ----------------------------+  D    |
            C              +-----+              D                 D    |
            C              |  |  |    +---------v-----------------v--+ |
 +----------v-----------+  |  |  |    |  ECA Policy Rule Data Model  | |
 |  Network Element     <--+  |  |    +------------------------------+ |
 +----------------------+     |  +-------------------------------------+
                              |
                              |
Legend:			      
The double-headed arrow with Cs = "communication"
The arrow with Ds = "derived from"
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="SUPA Policy Model:">This model represents one or more policy modules that
        contain the following entities:
<list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Generic Policy Information Model:">A model for defining policy rules
        that are independent of data repository, data definition, query,
        implementation language, and protocol. This model is abstract and is
        used for design; it MUST be turned into a data model for
        implementation.</t>

        <t hangText="Generic Policy Data Model:">A model of policy rules that are
        dependent on data repository, data definition, query, implementation
        language, and protocol.</t>

        <t hangText="ECA Policy Rule Information Model (EPRIM):">This model represents a policy
        rule as a statement that consists of an event clause, a condition
        clause, and an action clause. This type of policy rule explicitly
        defines the current and desired states of the system being managed.
        This model is abstract and is used for design; it MUST be turned into
        a data model for implementation.</t>

<t hangText="ECA Policy Rule Data Model:"> A model
of policy rules, derived from EPRIM, where each policy rule consists of an
event clause, a condition clause, and an action clause.</t>
        <t hangText="EMS/NMS/Controller:">This represents one or more entities that are able
        to control the operation and management of a network infrastructure
        (e.g., a network topology that consists of network elements).</t>

        <t hangText="Network Element (NE):">An element that can interact with the local or remote
        EMS/NMS/Controller in order to exchange information, such as
        configuration information, policy-enforcement capabilities, and
        network status.</t>
	</list></t></list></t>

        <t>Relationships among Policy, Service, and Resource models are
        illustrated in <xref target="relation"/>.</t>

        <figure title="Relationship among Policy, Service, and
		       Resource Models" anchor="relation">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                    
      +---------------+                   +----------------+
      |    Policy     |         (1)       |    Service     |
      |               |*******************|                |
      |   ( SUPA )    |*******************| ( L3SM, ... )  |
      +---------------+                   +----------------+
             **                                  /*\
               **                                *
                 **                            *
              (2)  **                        *   (3)
                     **                    *
                       **                *
                         **            *
                     +-------------------+
                     |    Resource       |
                     |                   |
                     | (Inventory, ... ) |
                     +-------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>In <xref target="relation"/>: <list style="format (%d)">
            <t>The policy manages and can adjust service behavior as necessary
            (1:1..n). In addition, data from resources and services are used to select
			and/or modify policies during runtime.</t>
	    <t>The policy manages and can adjust resource
            behavior as necessary (1:1..n).</t>
	    <t>Resource hosts
            service; changing resources may change service behavior as
            necessary.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Policies are used to control the management of resources and
        services, while data from resources and services are used to select
        and/or modify policies during runtime. More importantly, policies can
        be used to manage how resources are allocated and assigned to
        services. This enables a single policy to manage one or multiple
        services and resources as well as their dependencies. The use of (1:1..n) in point (1)
        and (2) above show that one policy rule is able to manage and
        can adjust one or multiple services/resources. Lines (1) and (2)
        (connecting policy to resource and policy to service) are the same, and line
        (3) (connecting resource to service) is different as it's navigable only
        from resource to service.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operation" anchor="operation">

<t>SUPA can be used to define various types of policies, including
   policies that affect services and/or the configuration of individual network elements
   or groups of network elements. SUPA can be used by a centralized
        and/or distributed set of entities for creating, managing, interacting
        with, and retiring policy rules.</t>

        <t>The SUPA scope is limited to policy information and data models.
        SUPA does not define network resource data models or network service
        data models; both are out of scope. Instead, SUPA makes use of
        network resource data models defined by other working groups or
	Standards Development Organizations (SDOs).</t>

        <t>Declarative policies are out of scope for the initial phase of SUPA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The GPIM and the EPRIM">
        <t>The GPIM provides a shared vocabulary for representing concepts
        that are common to different types of policies, but which are
        independent of language, protocol, repository, and level of
        abstraction. Hence, the GPIM defines concepts and vocabulary needed by
        policy management systems independent of the form and content of the
        policy. The EPRIM is a more specific model that refines the GPIM to
        specify policy rules in an ECA form.</t>

        <t>This enables different policies at different levels of abstraction
        to form a continuum, where more abstract policies can be translated
        into more concrete policies and vice versa. For example, the
        information model can be extended by generalizing concepts from an
        existing data model into the GPIM; the GPIM extensions can then be
        used by other data models.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Creation of Generic YANG Modules">
        <t>An information model is abstract. As such, it cannot be directly
        instantiated (i.e., objects cannot be created directly from it).
        Therefore, both the GPIM and the combination of the GPIM and the
        EPRIM are translated into generic YANG modules.</t>

        <t>SUPA will provide guidelines for translating the GPIM (or the
        combination of the GPIM and the EPRIM) into concrete YANG data models
        that define how to manage and communicate policies between systems.
        Multiple imperative policy YANG data models may be instantiated from
        the GPIM (or the combination of the GPIM and the EPRIM). In
        particular, SUPA will specify a set of YANG data models that will
        consist of a base policy model for representing policy management
        concepts independent of the type or structure of a policy; it will also specify
        an extension for defining policy rules according to the ECA
        paradigm. (Note: This means that policies can be defined
   using the GPIM directly, or using the combination of the GPIM and the
   EPRIM. If you use only the GPIM, you get a technology- and vendor-independent
   information model that you are free to map to the data model of your choice;
   note that the structure of a policy is NOT defined. If you use the GPIM and
   the EPRIM, you get a technology- and vendor-independent information model that
 defines policies as an ECA policy rule (i.e., imperative).)</t>

        <t>The process of developing the GPIM, the EPRIM, and the
        derived/translated YANG data models is realized following the sequence
        shown below. After completing this process and, if the implementation
        of the YANG data models requires it, the GPIM and EPRIM and the
        derived/translated YANG data models are updated and synchronized.</t>

        
<figure title=""><artwork><![CDATA[
   (1)=>(2)=>(3)=>(4)=>(3')=>(2')=>(1')

   Where:
   (1)=GPIM
   (2)=EPRIM
   (3)=YANG data models
   (4)=Implementation
   (3')=update of YANG data models
   (2')=update of EPRIM
   (1')=update of GPIM
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

        <t>The YANG module derived from the GPIM contains concepts and
        terminology for the common operation and administration of policy-
        based systems as well as an extensible structure for policy rules of
        different paradigms. The YANG module derived from the EPRIM extends
        the generic nature of the GPIM by representing policies using an
        ECA structure.</t>

        <t>The above sequence allows for the addition of new model elements, as well as the
        editing of existing ones, in the GPIM and EPRIM. In practice,
        the implementation sequence may be much simpler. Specifically, it is
        unlikely that the GPIM will need to be changed. In addition, changes
        to the EPRIM will likely be focused on fine-tuning the behavior
        offered by a specific set of model elements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations ">
      <t>This informational document presents the framework and workflow of
      SUPA as well as an explanation on the relationship of policy, service
      and resources. This document does not introduce any new security issues,
      and the framework has no security impact on the Internet. The same
      considerations are relevant as those for the base NETCONF protocol (see
      Section 9 in <xref target="RFC6241"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations ">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

                &RFC2119;
                &RFC8174;


    </references>


    <references title="Informative References">
                   &RFC3444;
               &RFC6020;
               &RFC6241;
               &RFC7950;
    
<!-- draft-cheng-supa-applicability-01 IESG state: Expired -->
<reference anchor='SUPA-APP'>
<front>
<title>Applicability of SUPA</title>

<author initials='Y' surname='Cheng' fullname='Ying Cheng'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Liu' fullname='Dapeng Liu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Fu' fullname='Borui Fu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='D' surname='Zhang' fullname='Dacheng Zhang'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='N' surname='Vadrevu' fullname='Narasimha Vadrevu'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='13' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-cheng-supa-applicability-01' />

</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-supa-generic-policy-data-model-04 IESG state: Expired-->
<reference anchor='SUPA-DATA'>
<front>
<title>Generic Policy Data Model for Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA)</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Halpern' fullname='Joel Halpern'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Strassner' fullname='John Strassner'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Van der Meer' fullname='S. Van der Meer'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' day='18' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-supa-generic-policy-data-model-04' />

</reference>


<!-- draft-ietf-supa-generic-policy-info-model-03 IESG state: Expired-->

<reference anchor='SUPA-INFO'>
<front>
<title>Generic Policy Information Model for Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA)</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Strassner' fullname='John Strassner'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Halpern' fullname='Joel Halpern'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Meer' fullname='Sven van der Meer'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='30' year='2017' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-supa-generic-policy-info-model-03' />

</reference>

<!-- draft-karagiannis-supa-problem-statement-07 IESG state: Replaced by
     draft-bi-supa-problem-statement, draft-klyus-supa-value-proposition-->

<reference anchor='SUPA-STATE'>
<front>
<title>Problem Statement for Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA)</title>

<author initials='G' surname='Karagiannis' fullname='Georgios Karagiannis'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Strassner' fullname='John Strassner'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Q' surname='Sun' fullname='Qiong Sun'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Contreras' fullname='Luis Contreras'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Yegani' fullname='Parviz Yegani'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Bi' fullname='Jun Bi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' day='7' year='2015' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-karagiannis-supa-problem-statement-07' />

</reference>

<!-- draft-klyus-supa-value-proposition-00 IESG state: Replaced by draft-bi-supa-problem-statement-->

<reference anchor='SUPA-VALUE'>
<front>
<title>SUPA Value Proposition</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Klyus' fullname='Maxim Klyus'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Strassner' fullname='John Strassner'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Liu' fullname='Shucheng Liu (Will)'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='G' surname='Karagiannis' fullname='Georgios Karagiannis'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Bi' fullname='Jun Bi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='21' year='2016' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-klyus-supa-value-proposition-00' />

</reference>

<!-- draft-zhou-supa-framework-02 IESG state: Replaced by draft-liu-supa-policy-based-management-framework-->

<reference anchor='SUPA-FRAME'>
<front>
<title>The Framework of Simplified Use of Policy Abstractions (SUPA)</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Zhou' fullname='Cathy Zhou'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='L' surname='Contreras' fullname='Luis Contreras'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Q' surname='Sun' fullname='Qiong SUn'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Yegani' fullname='Parviz Yegani'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='8' year='2015' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-zhou-supa-framework-02' />

</reference>

    </references>

<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no"><t>This document has benefited
from reviews, suggestions, comments, and proposed text provided by the
following members, listed in alphabetical order: Andy Bierman, Marc Blanchet,
Mohamed Boucadair, Scott O.&nbsp;Bradner, Scott Cadzow, Zhen Cao, Vikram
Choudhary, Benoit Claise, Spencer Dawkins, Mehmet Ersue, Ian Farrer, Fernando
Gont, Joel Halpern, Jonathan Hansford, Jing Huang, Xing Li, Marco Liebsch,
Diego R.&nbsp;Lopez, Johannes Merkle, Marie-Jose Montpetit, Kostas
Pentikousis, Simon Perreault, Hosnieh Rafiee, Raghav Rao, Jose Saldana, Jon
Saperia, Tom Taylor, Jean Francois Tremblay, Tina Tsou, Eric Voit, Gunter Wang,
Yangyang Wang, Bert Wijnen, and Tianran Zhou.</t>

<t>Part of the initial draft of this document was picked up from previous
documents: <xref target="SUPA-VALUE"/>, <xref target="SUPA-STATE"/>, and <xref target="SUPA-FRAME"/>.  We
appreciatively acknowledge the authors, contributors, and acknowledged parties of those documents.</t>
</section>

          <section title="Contributors" numbered="no">
      <t>The following people contributed to the creation of this document,
      listed in alphabetical order: <list>
          <t>Luis M.&nbsp;Contreras, Telefonica I+D <vspace blankLines="0"/> Dan Romascanu,
          Avaya<vspace blankLines="0"/> Juergen Schoenwaelder, Jacobs
	  University, Germany<vspace blankLines="0"/> Qiong Sun, China Telecom<vspace blankLines="0"/> Parviz
	  Yegani, Huawei Technologies<vspace blankLines="0"/>Cathy Zhou, Huawei Technologies</t>

        </list></t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
