<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc number="8510"  category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="OSPF LLS Extensions for Interface ID">OSPF Link-Local
    Signaling (LLS) Extensions for Local Interface ID Advertisement</title>

    <author fullname="Peter Psenak" initials="P." role="editor"
            surname="Psenak">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Apollo Business Center</street>

          <street>Mlynske nivy 43</street>

          <city>Bratislava</city>

          <code>821 09</code>

          <country>Slovakia</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" initials="K." surname="Talaulikar">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>S.No. 154/6, Phase I, Hinjawadi</street>

          <city>Pune, Maharashtra</city>

          <code>411 057</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ketant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Wim Henderickx" initials="W." surname="Henderickx">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Copernicuslaan 50</street>

          <city>Antwerp</city>

          <code>2018</code>

          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wim.henderickx@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Padma Pillay-Esnault " initials="P." surname="Pillay-Esnault">
      <organization>Huawei USA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>

          <city>Santa Clara,</city>

          <code>CA 95050</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>padma@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>   

    <date month="January" year="2019"/>

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Open Shortest Path First IGP</workgroup>

    <keyword>IGP, OSPF</keyword>

    <abstract>
       <t>Every OSPF interface is assigned an Interface ID that uniquely 
       identifies the interface on the router. In some cases, it is useful to know the 
       assigned Interface ID on the remote side of the adjacency (Remote Interface ID).</t>
      
      <t>This document describes the extensions to OSPF link-local signaling (LLS) 
      to advertise the Local Interface ID.</t>
    </abstract>

   </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>Every OSPF interface is assigned an Interface ID that uniquely identifies the 
      interface on the router. <xref target="RFC2328"/> uses this Interface ID in the 
      Router Link State Advertisement (Router-LSA) Link Data for unnumbered links and
      uses the value of the MIB-II ifIndex
      <xref target="RFC2863"/>. <xref target="RFC4203"/> refers to these Interface IDs 
      as the  Link Local/Remote Identifiers and defines a way to advertise and 
      use them for GMPLS purposes. 

      <xref target="RFC8379"/> defines a way to advertise Local/Remote Interface IDs in
      the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA.</t> 
      
      <t>There is a known OSPFv2 protocol problem in verifying the bidirectional 
      connectivity with parallel unnumbered links. If there are two parallel unnumbered 
      links between a pair of routers and each link is only advertised from a single 
      direction, such two unidirectional parallel links could be considered as a valid 
      single bidirectional link during the OSPF route computation on some other router. 
      If each link is advertised with both its Local and Remote Interface IDs, the 
      advertisement of each link from both sides of adjacency can be verified by 
      cross-checking the Local and Remote Interface IDs of both advertisements.</t>


      <t>From the perspective of the advertising router, the Local Interface ID 
      is a known value. However, the Remote Interface ID needs to be learned before
      it can be advertised. <xref target="RFC4203"/> suggests using the TE Link Local LSA 
      <xref target="RFC3630"/> to communicate the Local Interface ID to neighbors
      on the link. Though such a mechanism works, it has some drawbacks.</t>
      
      <t>This document proposes an extension to OSPF link-local signaling (LLS) 
      <xref target="RFC5613"/> to advertise the Local Interface ID.</t>


   <section title="Interface ID Exchange Using Link Local TE Opaque LSA">

    <t>Usage of the Link Local TE Opaque LSA to propagate the Local Interface ID 
       to the neighbors on the link is described in <xref target="RFC4203"/>. This 
       mechanism has the following problems:
       
       <list style="symbols">
            <t>LSAs can only be flooded over an existing adjacency that is in Exchange 
            state or greater. The adjacency state machine progresses independently on each 
            side of the adjacency and, as such, may reach the Full state on one side before
            the Link Local TE Opaque LSA arrives. The consequence of this is that
	    the link can be 
            initially advertised without the Remote Interface ID. Later, when the
            Link Local TE Opaque LSA arrives, the link must be advertised again but this time
            with the valid Remote Interface ID. Implementations may choose 
            to wait before advertising the link, but there is no guarantee that the neighbor 
            will ever advertise the Link Local TE Opaque LSA with the Interface ID.
            In summary, the existing mechanism does not guarantee that the Remote Interface 
            ID is known at the time the link is advertised.</t>

            <t>The Link Local TE Opaque LSA is defined for MPLS Traffic Engineering, but the knowledge 
            of the Remote Interface ID is useful also for cases where MPLS TE is not 
            used. One example is the mentioned lack of a valid 2-way connectivity check for  
            parallel point-to-point links between OSPF routers.</t>
                 
     </list></t>
    </section>

<section title="Requirements Language">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>       

</section>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Interface ID Exchange Using OSPF LLS">
    
      <t>To address the problems described earlier and to allow the Interface ID
      exchange to be part of the neighbor discovery process, we propose to extend OSPF 
      link-local signaling to advertise the Local Interface ID in OSPF Hello 
      and Database Description (DD) packets.</t>

      <section anchor="IDTLV" title="Local Interface ID TLV">
        <t>The Local Interface ID TLV is an LLS TLV. It has the following
        format:<figure>
            <artwork> 
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              Type             |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                   Local Interface ID                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
          </figure>

<list style="hanging">
            <t>Type: 18</t>

            <t>Length: 4 octets</t>

            <t>Local Interface ID: The value of the Local Interface ID.</t>
</list></t>
        <t>Local Interface ID TLV signaling using LLS is applicable to 
        all OSPF interface types other than virtual links.
        </t>     
        
     </section>
    </section>

   <section anchor="BACKW" title="Backward Compatibility with RFC 4203">
   
   <t>If the Local Interface ID signaling via the Link Local TE Opaque LSA is supported in addition
    to the new LLS mechanism, implementations that support Local Interface ID signaling 
    using LLS MUST prefer the Local Interface ID value received through LLS over the value 
    received through the Link Local TE Opaque LSA if both are received from the same OSPF router.</t> 
   
   <t>Implementations that support Local Interface ID signaling via the Link Local
    TE Opaque LSA MAY continue to do so to ensure backward compatibility. If they also 
    support Local Interface ID signaling using LLS as described in the document, they MUST
    signal the same Local Interface ID via both mechanisms.</t>
    
    <t>During the rare conditions in which the Local Interface ID changes, a timing interval 
    may exist where the received values of the Local Interface ID advertised through LLS
    and the Link Local TE Opaque LSA may differ. Such a situation is temporary, and received values
    via both mechanisms should become equal as soon as the next Hello and/or Link Local 
    TE Opaque LSA is regenerated by the originator.</t> 
     
   </section>
   
   
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has allocated the following code point in the "Link Local
      Signalling TLV Identifiers (LLS Types)" subregistry of the "Open Shortest Path 
      First (OSPF) Link Local Signalling (LLS) - Type/Length/Value Identifiers (TLV)"
      registry.</t>
      
        <t>18 - Local Interface ID TLV</t>
    </section>
    
   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>The security considerations for "OSPF Link-Local Signaling" <xref target="RFC5613"/> 
      also apply to the Local Interface ID TLV described in this document. The current
      usage of a neighbor's Local Interface ID is to disambiguate parallel
      links between OSPF routers. Hence, modification of the advertised Local
      Interface ID TLV may result in the wrong neighbor Interface ID
      being advertised in the OSPFv2 Extended Link Opaque LSA <xref target="RFC7684"/>
      and could prevent the link from being used. If authentication is being used in
      the OSPF routing domain <xref target="RFC5709"/><xref target="RFC7474"/>, then the Cryptographic Authentication
      TLV <xref target="RFC5613"/> SHOULD also be used to protect the contents of the
      LLS block.</t>

    <t>Receiving a malformed LLS Local Interface ID TLV MUST NOT result in a hard router
     or OSPF process failure. The reception of malformed LLS TLVs or sub-TLVs SHOULD be 
     logged, but such logging MUST be rate-limited to prevent denial-of-service (DoS)
     attacks.</t>
     
     <t>The Interface ID is assigned by the advertising OSPF router as a locally
      unique identifier and need not be unique in any broader context; it is 
      not expected to contain any information about the device owner or
      traffic transiting the device, so there are no privacy concerns 
      associated with its advertisement.</t>
      
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
             
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml"?>
      
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5613.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4203.xml"?>
      
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml"?>
      
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7684.xml"?>
      
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8379"?>    
    
    </references>  
    
    <references title="Informative References">
    

    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5709"?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7474.xml"?>
    
    <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2863.xml"?>
    
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments" numbered="no">
    <t>Thanks to Tony Przygienda for his extensive review and useful comments.</t>
    </section>      

  </back>
</rfc>
