<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8077 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8077.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5036 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5036.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5003 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5003.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5331 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5331.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5332 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5332.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6388 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6388.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4875 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4875.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6514 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6514.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5561 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5561.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5918 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6667 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6667.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3985 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3985.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6074 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6074.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7338 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7338.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6425 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6425.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4446 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4446.xml">
]>

<!-- XML source generated using id2xml January 2018
-->

<rfc submissionType="IETF" number="8338"
     category="std" consensus="yes" updates="7385">

        <?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="*o+-"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<front>

<title abbrev="Root-Initiated P2MP Pseudowire">Signaling Root-Initiated Point-to-Multipoint Pseudowire Using LDP</title>

  <author fullname="Sami Boutros" initials="S" surname="Boutros" role="editor">
     <organization abbrev="VMWare">VMware, Inc.</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>
         <city></city>
         <region></region>
         <code></code>
         <country></country>
       </postal>
       <phone></phone>
       <email>sboutros@vmware.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

  <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S" surname="Sivabalan" role="editor">
     <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>
         <city></city>
         <region></region>
         <code></code>
         <country></country>
       </postal>
       <phone></phone>
       <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

<date month="March" year="2018"/>
	<abstract><t>
   This document specifies a mechanism to signal Point-to-Multipoint
   (P2MP) Pseudowire (PW) trees using LDP. Such a mechanism is suitable
   for any Layer 2 VPN service requiring P2MP connectivity over an IP or
   MPLS-enabled PSN. A P2MP PW established via the proposed mechanism is
   root initiated. This document updates RFC 7385 by reassigning
   the reserved value 0xFF to be the wildcard transport tunnel type.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	<section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
   A Point-to-Multipoint (P2MP) Pseudowire (PW) emulates the essential
   attributes of a unidirectional P2MP Telecommunications service such
   as P2MP ATM over PSN. A major difference between a Point-to-Point
   (P2P) PW outlined in <xref target="RFC3985"/> and a P2MP PW is that the former is
   intended for bidirectional service whereas the latter is intended for
   both unidirectional and, optionally, bidirectional service.
   Requirements for P2MP PWs are described in <xref target="RFC7338"/>. P2MP PWs can be
   constructed as either Single Segment Pseudowires (P2MP SS-PWs) or
   Multi-Segment Pseudowires (P2MP MS-PWs) as mentioned in <xref
   target="RFC7338"/>. P2MP MS-PW is 
   outside the scope of this document. A reference model or a P2MP PW is
   depicted in <xref target="ref-p2mp-pw"/>. A transport Label Switched Path (LSP) associated with a P2MP
   SS-PW SHOULD be a P2MP MPLS LSP (i.e., P2MP Traffic Engineering (TE) tunnel established via
   RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC4875"/> or P2MP LSP established via Multipoint LDP (mLDP) <xref target="RFC6388"/>)
   spanning from the Root PE (Provider Edge) to the Leaf PE(s) of the P2MP SS-PW tree.
   For example, in <xref target="ref-p2mp-pw"/>, PW1 can be associated with a P2MP TE tunnel
   or P2MP LSP setup using mLDP originating from PE1 and terminating at
   PE2, PE3, and PE4.</t>

	<figure title="P2MP PW" anchor="ref-p2mp-pw"><artwork><![CDATA[
              |<--------------P2MP PW---------------->|
       Native |                                       |  Native
      Service |     |<--PSN1->|      |<--PSN2->|      |  Service
       (AC)   V     V         V      V         V      V   (AC)
         |    +-----+         +------+         +------+    |
         |    |     |         |   P1 |=========|T-PE2 |AC3 |    +---+
         |    |     |         |   .......PW1.........>|-------->|CE3|
         |    |T-PE1|=========|   .  |=========|      |    |    +---+
         |    |  .......PW1........  |         +------+    |
         |    |  .  |=========|   .  |         +------+    |
         |    |  .  |         |   .  |=========|T-PE3 |AC4 |    +---+
 +---+   |AC1 |  .  |         |   .......PW1.........>|-------->|CE4|
 |CE1|------->|...  |         |      |=========|      |    |    +---+
 +---+   |    |  .  |         +------+         +------+    |
         |    |  .  |         +------+         +------+    |
         |    |  .  |=========|   P2 |=========|T-PE4 |AC5 |    +---+
         |    |  .......PW1..............PW1.........>|-------->|CE5|
         |    |     |=========|      |=========|      |    |    +---+
         |    +-----+         +------+         +------+    |
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   Mechanisms for establishing a P2P SS-PW using LDP are described in
   <xref target="RFC8077"/>. This document specifies a method of signaling P2MP PW
   using LDP. In particular, this document defines a new Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC), TLVs,
   parameters, and status codes to facilitate LDP signaling and maintaining
   P2MP PWs.</t>

	<t>
   As outlined in <xref target="RFC7338"/>, even though the traffic flow from a Root PE
   (R-PE) to Leaf PE(s) (L-PEs) is P2MP in nature, it may be desirable
   for any L-PE to send unidirectional P2P traffic destined only to the
   R-PE. The proposed mechanism takes such an option into consideration.</t>

	<t>
   The P2MP PW requires an MPLS LSP to carry the PW traffic, and the
   MPLS packets carrying the PW upstream label will be encapsulated
   according to the methods described in <xref target="RFC5332"/>.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Terminology" anchor="section-1.1">
          <section title="Requirements Language" anchor="section2.1">

	            <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t></section>
    
<section title="Abbreviations" anchor="section2.2">
  <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">


    
    <t hangText="AGI:  ">Attachment Group Identifier</t>
    <t hangText="CE:   ">Customer Edge</t>
     <t hangText="FEC:  ">Forwarding Equivalence Class</t>
    	<t hangText="L-PE: ">Leaf PE (egress PE)</t>

	<t hangText="LDP:  ">Label Distribution Protocol</t>

	<t hangText="LSP:  ">Label Switched Path</t>

	<t hangText="mLDP: ">Multipoint Label Distribution Protocol (for P2MP/MP2MP LSP)</t>


	<t hangText="MS-PW:">Multi-Segment Pseudowire</t>
	<t hangText="P2MP: ">Point-to-Multipoint</t>
	<t hangText="P2P:  ">Point-to-Point</t>
	
	<t hangText="PE:   ">Provider Edge</t>

	<t hangText="PSN:  ">Packet Switched Network</t>

	<t hangText="PW:   ">Pseudowire</t>
        <t hangText="R-PE: ">Root PE (ingress PE, PE initiating P2MP PW setup)</t>
        <t hangText="S-PE: ">Switching Provider Edge (of MS-PW)</t>
	<t hangText="SS-PW:">Single-Segment Pseudowire</t>

	<t hangText="TE:   ">Traffic Engineering</t>




      </list></t>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section title="Signaling P2MP PW" anchor="section-2">
<t>In order to advertise labels as well as exchange PW-related LDP messages,
PEs must establish LDP sessions among themselves. A PE discovers other PEs
that are to be connected via P2MP PWs either via manual configuration or
autodiscovery <xref target="RFC6074"/>.</t>

   <t>An R-PE and each L-PE MUST be configured with the same FEC as defined in
   <xref target="section-2.2"/>.</t>
	<t>
   P2MP PW requires that there be an active P2MP PSN LSP set up between
   an R-PE and L-PE(s). Note that the procedure to set up the P2MP PSN LSP
   is different depending on the signaling protocol used (RSVP-TE or
   mLDP).</t>

	<t>
   In the case of mLDP, a Leaf PE can decide to join the P2MP LSP at any
   time. In the case of RSVP-TE, the P2MP LSP is set up by the R-PE,
   generally at the initial service provisioning time. It should be
   noted that local policy can override any decision to join, add, or
   prune existing or new L-PEs from the tree. In any case, the PW
   setup can ignore these differences and simply assume that the P2MP
   PSN LSP is available when needed.</t>

<t>P2MP PW signaling is initiated by the R-PE, which sends a separate P2MP PW
LDP Label Mapping Message to each of the L-PE(s) belonging to that P2MP
PW. This Label Mapping Message will contain the following:</t>
<t><list style="numbers">

<t>A FEC TLV containing a P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element that includes a Transport
LSP sub-TLV.</t>
<t>An Interface Parameters TLV, as described in <xref target="RFC8077"/>.</t>


<t>A PW Group ID TLV, as described in <xref target="RFC8077"/>.</t>
<t>A label TLV for the upstream-assigned label used by an R-PE for the traffic
going from the R-PE to L-PE(s).</t>
</list></t>

	<t>
   The R-PE imposes the upstream-assigned PW label on the outbound
   packets sent over the P2MP PW; using this label, an L-PE
   identifies the inbound packets arriving over the P2MP PW.</t>

	<t>
   Additionally, the R-PE MAY send Label Mapping Messages to one or
   more L-PEs to signal a unidirectional P2P PW(s). The L-PE(s) can use
   such a PW(s) to send traffic to the R-PE. This optional Label Mapping
   Message will contain the following:</t>

	<t><list style="numbers">
	 
	<t>A P2P PW Downstream FEC Element</t>
	<t>A label TLV for the downstream-assigned label used by the
            corresponding L-PE to send traffic to the R-PE</t>
	</list>

	</t>

	<t>
   The LDP liberal label retention mode MUST be used; per
   requirements specified in <xref target="RFC5036"/>, the Label Request message MUST
   also be supported.</t>

	<t>
   The upstream-assigned label is allocated according to the rules in
   <xref target="RFC5331"/>.</t>

	<t>
   When an L-PE receives a PW Label Mapping Message, it MUST verify the
   associated P2MP PSN LSP is in place. If the associated P2MP PSN LSP
   is not in place and its type is LDP P2MP LSP, the L-PE MUST attempt
   to join the P2MP LSP associated with the P2MP PW. If the associated
   P2MP PSN LSP is not in place, and its type is RSVP-TE P2MP LSP, the
   L-PE SHOULD wait till the P2MP transport LSP is signaled.
   If an L-PE
   fails to join the P2MP PSN LSP, that L-PE MUST not enable the PW and
   MUST notify the user. In this case, a PW status message with status
   code of 0x00000008 (Local PSN-facing PW (ingress) Receive Fault) MUST
   also be sent to the R-PE.</t>

   <section title="PW Ingress-to-Egress Incompatibility Issues" anchor="section-2.1"><t>

   If an R-PE signals a PW with a PW Type, Control Word (CW) mode, or interface
   parameters that a particular L-PE cannot accept, then the L-PE MUST
   NOT enable the PW and should notify the user. In this case, a PW status
   message with status code of 0x00000001 (Pseudowire Not Forwarding)
   MUST also be sent to the R-PE.</t>

	<t>
   Note that this procedure does not apply if the L-PE was not 
   provisioned with this particular P2MP PW. In this case, according to
   the LDP liberal label retention rules, no action is taken.</t>

	</section>


	<section title="P2MP PW FEC" anchor="section-2.2"><t>
   <xref target="RFC8077"/> specifies two types of LDP FEC elements used to signal P2P PWs: "PWid FEC Element" and "Generalized PWid FEC Element".
   This document uses two FEC elements: "P2MP PW Upstream FEC
   Element" and "P2P PW Downstream FEC Element". These FEC 
   elements are associated with a mandatory upstream-assigned label and
   an optional downstream-assigned label, respectively.</t>

	<section title="P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element" anchor="section-2.2.1"><t>
   The FEC type for the P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element is encoded as
   follows:</t>

   <figure title="P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element" anchor="ref-p2mp-pw-upstream-fec-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
   
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |P2MP PW Up=0x82|C|           PW Type           | PW Info Length|
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |    AGI Type   | AGI Length    |         AGI Value             |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 ~                       AGI Value (contd.)                      ~
 |                                                               |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |   AII Type    | SAII Length   |         SAII Value            |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 ~                       SAII Value (contd.)                     ~
 |                                                               |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |PMSI Tunnel Typ|PMSI TT Length |                               |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
 +                                                               +
 ~                   Transport LSP ID                            ~
 |                                                               |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |                                                               |
 |                       Optional Parameters                     |
 ~                                                               ~
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>P2MP PW Up:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	8-bit representation for the P2MP PW Upstream FEC type.</t>

		<t>C bit:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   A value of 1 or 0 indicating whether a control word is present or absent
   for the P2MP PW.</t>

	<t>PW Type:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   15-bit representation of PW Type as specified in <xref target="RFC8077"/>.</t>


	<t>PW Info Length:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/> 

Sum of the AGI Length, SAII Length, PMSI Tunnel Type Length, and Optional Parameters fields in octets.  If this value is 0, then it references
   all PWs using the specified group ID. In this case, there are
   neither other FEC element fields (AGI Type, SAII Value, etc.) present, nor any
   interface parameters TLVs. Alternatively, typed wildcard FEC
   described in Section 2.3, can be used to achieve the same or to have
	better filtering.</t>

	<t>AGI:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   An Attachment Group Identifier TLV can be used to uniquely identify a VPN or
   Virtual Private LAN Service (VPLS) instance associated with the P2MP PW. This has the same format
   as the Generalized PWid FEC Element <xref target="RFC8077"/>.</t>

	<t>SAII Value:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   A Source Attachment Individual Identifier is used to identify the root
   of the P2MP PW. The root is represented using AII Type 2 format
   specified in <xref target="RFC5003"/>.  Note that the SAII can be omitted by simply
   setting the length and type to zero.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The P2MP PW is identified by the Source Attachment Identifier (SAI). If
   the AGI is non-null, the SAI is the combination of the SAII and the
   AGI, if the AGI is null, the SAI is the SAII.</t>

 <t>PMSI Tunnel Info:
 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The PMSI Tunnel Info is the combination of the PMSI Tunnel Type, PMSI Tunnel Type Length (shown in the figure as PMSI TT Length), and
   Transport LSP ID fields.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   A P2MP PW MUST be associated with a transport LSP, which can be
   established using RSVP-TE or mLDP.</t>

	<t>PMSI Tunnel Type:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	The PMSI Tunnel Type is defined in <xref target="RFC6514"/>.
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   When the type is set to mLDP P2MP LSP, the Tunnel Identifier is a
   P2MP FEC Element as defined in <xref target="RFC6388"/>. The new mLDP Opaque Value
   Element type for the L2VPN-MCAST application TLV (as specified in the IANA
   Considerations section (<xref target="section-7"/>)) MUST be used.</t>

   <t>Transport LSP ID: 
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   This is the Tunnel Identifier that is defined in
   <xref target="RFC6514"/>.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   An R-PE sends a Label Mapping Message as soon as the transport LSP ID
   associated with the P2MP PW is known (e.g., via configuration)
   regardless of the operational state of that transport LSP. Similarly,
   an R-PE does not withdraw the labels when the corresponding transport
   LSP goes down. Furthermore, an L-PE retains the P2MP PW labels
   regardless of the operational status of the transport LSP.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Note that a given transport LSP can be associated with more than one
   P2MP PW; in which case, P2MP PWs will be sharing the same R-PE and L-PE(s). An R-PE may also have many P2MP PWs with disjoint L-PE sets.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   In the case of LDP P2MP LSP, when an L-PE receives the Label Mapping
   Message, it can initiate the process of joining the P2MP LSP tree
   associated with the P2MP PW.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   In the case of RSVP-TE P2MP LSP, only the R-PE initiates the
   signaling of P2MP LSP.
 </t>

	<t>Optional Parameters:
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The Optional Parameter field can contain some TLVs that are not part
   of the FEC, but are necessary for the operation of the PW. This
   proposed mechanism uses two such TLVs: the Interface Parameters TLV and the 
   PW Group ID TLV.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The Interface Parameters TLV and PW Group ID TLV specified in
   <xref target="RFC8077"/> can also be used in conjunction with P2MP PW FEC in a
   label message. For the PW Group ID TLV, the sender and receiver of these
   TLVs should follow the same rules and procedures specified in
   <xref target="RFC8077"/>. For the Interface Parameters TLV, the procedure differs
   from the one specified in <xref target="RFC8077"/> due to specifics of P2MP
   connectivity. When the interface parameters are signaled by an R-PE,
   each L-PE must check if its configured value(s) is less than or equal
   to the threshold value provided by the R-PE (e.g., MTU size
   (Ethernet), max number of concatenated ATM cells, etc.).  For other
   interface parameters, like CEP/TDM Payload Bytes, the value MUST
   exactly match the values signaled by the R-PE.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   A multicast traffic stream associated with a P2MP PW can be selective
   or inclusive. To support the former, this document defines a new
   optional Selective Tree Interface Parameter sub-TLV, as described in
   the IANA Considerations section (<xref target="section-7"/>) and according to the format described in
   <xref target="RFC8077"/>. The value of the sub-TLV contains the source and the
   group for a given multicast tree, as shown in <xref target="figure3"/>. Also, if a
   P2MP PW is associated with multiple selective trees, the
   corresponding Label Mapping Message will carry more than one instance
   of this sub-TLV. Furthermore, in the absence of this sub-TLV, the
   P2MP PW is associated with all multicast traffic streams originating
   from the root.</t></list></t>

	<figure title="Selective Tree Interface Parameter Sub-TLV Value" anchor="figure3"><artwork><![CDATA[

           +-----------------------------------------+
           |            Sub-TLV Type (1 Octet)       |
           +-----------------------------------------+
           |              Length (1 Octet)           |
           +-----------------------------------------+
           | Multicast Source Length (1 Octet)       |
           +-----------------------------------------+
           | Multicast Source (variable length)      |
           +-----------------------------------------+
           | Multicast Group Length (1 Octet)        |
           +-----------------------------------------+
           | Multicast Group (variable length)       |
           +-----------------------------------------+

]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t><list style="empty"><t>
   Note that since the LDP Label Mapping Message is only sent by the R-PE to all the L-PEs, it is not possible to negotiate any interface
   parameters.</t></list></t>

	</section>

	<section title="P2P PW Downstream FEC Element" anchor="section-2.2.2">
	  <t>The optional P2P PW Downstream FEC Element is encoded as follows:</t>

	<figure title="P2P PW Downstream FEC Element" anchor="ref-p2p-pw-downstream-fec-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |P2P PWDown=0x84|C|           PW Type           | PW Info Length|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    AGI Type   |     Length    |         AGI Value             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   ~                       AGI Value (contd.)                      ~
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    AII Type   |     Length    |         SAII Value            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   ~                       SAII Value (contd.)                     ~
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   The definition of the fields in the P2P PW Downstream FEC Element is
   the same as those of P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element, shown in <xref target="ref-p2mp-pw-upstream-fec-element"/>.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Typed Wildcard FEC Format for a New FEC" anchor="section-2.3"><t>
   <xref target="RFC5918"/> defines the general notion of a Typed Wildcard FEC
   Element; it requires FEC designers to specify a Typed Wildcard FEC
   Element for newly defined FEC element types. This document uses
   two FEC elements: "P2MP PW Upstream" and "P2P PW Downstream". Hence, definition of their Typed Wildcard format is required.</t>

	<t>
   <xref target="RFC6667"/> defines the Typed Wildcard FEC Element format for other PW FEC
   Element types (PWid and Generalized PWid FEC Element) in <xref target="section-2"/> as
   follows:</t>

	<figure title="Typed Wildcard Format for P2MP PW FEC Elements" anchor="ref-typed-wildcard-format-for-p2mp-pw-fec-elements"><artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |Typed Wcard=0x5|Type=PW FEC    |   Len = 3     |R|   PW Type   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    . . .      | PMSI Tun Type |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   <xref target="RFC6667"/> specifies that the Type field can be either the "PWid" (0x80) or
   "Generalized PWid" (0x81) FEC Element type. This document reuses the
   existing Typed Wildcard format specified in <xref target="RFC6667"/> and
   illustrated in <xref target="ref-typed-wildcard-format-for-p2mp-pw-fec-elements"/> and extends the definition of the Type field to
   also include the P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element and P2P PW Downstream FEC Element
   types. This document adds an additional field called the "PMSI Tunnel Type".
  This
   document reserves PMSI Tunnel Type 0xFF to mean "wildcard transport
   tunnel type". The PMSI Tunnel Type field only applies to the Typed
	Wildcard P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element and MUST be set to "wildcard" for "P2P PW Downstream FEC Element" typed wildcard.</t>



	</section>

	<section title="Group ID Usage" anchor="section-2.4"><t>
   The PW Group ID TLV as defined in <xref target="RFC8077"/> contains a group ID
   capable of indicating an arbitrary group membership of a P2MP PW.
   This group ID can be used in LDP "wildcard" status and withdraw
   label messages, as described in <xref target="RFC8077"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Generic Label TLV" anchor="section-2.5"><t>
   As in the case of P2P PW signaling, P2MP PW labels are carried within
   the Generic Label TLV contained in the LDP Label Mapping Message. A Generic
   Label TLV is formatted and processed as per the rules and procedures
   specified in <xref target="RFC8077"/>. For a given P2MP PW, a single upstream-assigned label is allocated by the R-PE and is advertised to all L-PEs using the Generic Label TLV in Label Mapping Messages containing
   the P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element.</t>

	<t>
   The R-PE can also allocate a unique label for each L-PE from which it
   intends to receive P2P traffic. Such a label is advertised to the L-PE using the Generic Label TLV and P2P PW Downstream FEC Element in Label Mapping
   Messages.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="LDP Capability Negotiation" anchor="section-3"><t>
   The capability of supporting P2MP PWs MUST be advertised to all LDP
   peers. This is achieved by using the methods in <xref target="RFC5561"/> to
   advertise the LDP P2MP PW Capability TLV. If an LDP peer supports
   the dynamic capability advertisement, this can be done by sending a
   new Capability message with the S bit set for the P2MP PW Capability
   TLV. If the peer does not support dynamic capability advertisement,
   then the P2MP PW Capability TLV MUST be included in the LDP
   Initialization message during session establishment. A Label Switched Router (LSR)
   having P2MP PW capability MUST recognize both the P2MP PW Upstream FEC
   Element and P2P PW Downstream FEC Element in LDP label messages.</t>

	<t>
   In line with requirements listed in <xref target="RFC5561"/>, the following TLV is
   defined to indicate the P2MP PW capability:</t>

	<figure title="LDP P2MP PW Capability TLV" anchor="ref-ldp-p2mp-pw-capability-tlv"><artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |U|F| P2MP PW Capability TLV    |            Length             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |S| Reserved    |    Reserved   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t><list style="symbols">


	  <t>U bit:<vspace blankLines="1"/>The Unknown bit <xref target="RFC5036"/> SHOULD be 1 (ignore if not understood).
	</t>

	<t>F bit:<vspace blankLines="1"/>The Forward unknown bit <xref target="RFC5036"/> SHOULD be 0 (don't forward if not understood).
	</t>

	<t>P2MP PW Capability TLV Code Point:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	The TLV type, which identifies a specific capability. Note that the P2MP PW
	Capability Code Point appears in the IANA Considerations section (<xref target="section-7"/>).</t>

	<t>S bit:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	The State Bit indicates whether the sender is advertising or
	withdrawing the P2MP PW capability. The State bit is used as
	follows:

	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">

	  <t hangText="  1 -">The TLV is advertising the capability specified by the
             P2MP PW Capability TLV Code Point.</t>
	   <t hangText="  0 -">The TLV is withdrawing the capability specified by the P2MP PW Capability TLV
	  Code Point.</t>
	</list></t>
	
	<t>Length:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	MUST be set to 2 (octet).
	</t>
      </list></t>

     	</section>

	<section title="P2MP PW Status" anchor="section-4"><t>
   In order to support the proposed mechanism, an LSR MUST be capable of
   handling PW status. As such, the PW status negotiation procedures
   described in <xref target="RFC8077"/> are not applicable to P2MP PW. An LSR MUST
   NOT claim to be P2MP PW capable by sending an LDP P2MP PW Capability
   TLV  if it is not also capable of handling PW status.</t>

	<t>
   Once an L-PE successfully processes a Label Mapping Message for a
   P2MP PW, it MUST send appropriate PW status according to the
   procedure specified <xref target="RFC8077"/> to report the PW status. If no PW
   status notification is required, then no PW status notification is
   sent (for example, if the P2MP PW is established and operational with
   a status code of 0x00000000 (Success), a PW status message is not
   necessary). A PW status message sent from an L-PE to an R-PE MUST
   contain the P2P PW Downstream FEC Element to identify the PW.</t>

	<t>
   An R-PE also sends PW status to L-PE(s) to reflect its view of a P2MP
   PW state. Such a PW status message contains a P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element to
   identify the PW.</t>

	<t>
   Connectivity status of the underlying P2MP LSP that the P2MP PW is
   associated with can be verified using LSP ping and traceroute
   procedures described in <xref target="RFC6425"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="section-5"><t>
   In general, the security measures described in <xref target="RFC8077"/> are
   adequate for this protocol. However, the use of MD5 as the method of
   securing an LDP control plane is no longer considered adequately
   secure. Implementations should be written in such a way that they can
   migrate to a more secure cryptographic hash function when the next
   authentication method to be used in the LDP might not be a simple hash-based authentication algorithm.</t>

	</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-7"><section
title="FEC Type Name Space" anchor="section-7.1">

<t>This document uses two FEC element types, 0x82 and 0x84, in the "Forwarding
   Equivalence Class (FEC) Type Name Space" registry 
   for the Label Distribution Protocol (LDP) <xref target="RFC5036"/>.  IANA
   has added this document as a reference for the following entries:</t>


	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Value   Hex    Name                            Reference
------  -----  -----------------------------   --------------------
 130    0x82   P2MP PW Upstream FEC Element    [RFC8338] [RFC7358]
 132    0x84   P2P PW Downstream FEC Element   [RFC8338] [RFC7358] 
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	</section>

	<section title="LDP TLV Type" anchor="section-7.2"><t>
   This document defines a new LDP TLV type in the "TLV Type Name Space"
   registry <xref target="RFC5036"/>. IANA has assigned the the following value:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
TLV Type  Description
--------  ----------------------
0x0703    P2MP PW Capability TLV
]]></artwork></figure>
	</section>

	<section title="mLDP Opaque Value Element TLV Type" anchor="section-7.3"><t>
   IANA has assigned a new mLDP Opaque Value Element
   Type in the "LDP MP Opaque Value Element basic type" registry <xref
   target="RFC6388"/> as follows:</t>

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        TLV Type  Description
        -------   ---------------------------
          13      L2VPN-MCAST application TLV
        
        Length:   4

        Value:    A 32-bit integer, unique in the context of the 
                  root, as identified by the root's address.
        ]]></artwork></figure>
	</section>

	<section title="Selective Tree Interface Parameter Sub-TLV Type"
		 anchor="section-7.4">
<t>

IANA has assigned a sub-TLV from the "Pseudowire Interface Parameters
Sub-TLV type Registry" <xref target="RFC4446" /> as follows:</t>

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        TLV Type  Description
        --------  ----------------------------------
        0x1B      Selective Tree Interface Parameter
         ]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>

	<section title="Wildcard PMSI Tunnel Type" anchor="section-7.5"><t>
  IANA has modified an entry in the "P-Multicast Service Interface Tunnel
  (PMSI Tunnel) Tunnel Types" registry within the "Border Gateway Protocol
  (BGP) Parameters" registry <xref target="RFC7385"/>.  Value 0xFF, which was
  previously marked as "Reserved", has been been updated as follows:</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        Value     Meaning                             Reference
        -----     ------------------------------      ---------
        0xFF      wildcard transport tunnel type      [RFC8338]
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	</section>

	</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
	&RFC2119;


<!--draft-ietf-pals-rfc4447bis-05: I-D Now RFC 8077-->
	&RFC8077;
	&RFC5036;
	&RFC5003;
	&RFC5331;
	&RFC5332;
	&RFC6388;
	&RFC4875;
&RFC4446;
	&RFC6514;
	&RFC5561;
	&RFC5918;
	&RFC6667;
	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7385"?>
	 <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	&RFC3985;
	&RFC6074;
	&RFC7338;
	&RFC6425;
	
	</references>
	<section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="acks" numbered="no"><t>
   The authors would like thank Andre Pelletier and Parag Jain for their
   valuable suggestions.</t>

	</section>
	
	<section title="Contributors" numbered="no" anchor="contributors"><t><list hangIndent="3" style="hanging"><t>
     The following people contributed substantially to the content of
 this document and should be considered coauthors:</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Luca Martini
   Cisco Systems, Inc.

   Email: lmartini@cisco.com

   Maciek Konstantynowicz
   Cisco Systems, Inc.

   Email: maciek@cisco.com

   Gianni Del Vecchio
   Swisscom

   Email: Gianni.DelVecchio@swisscom.com

   Thomas D. Nadeau
   Brocade

   Email: tnadeau@lucidvision.com

   Frederic Jounay
   Orange CH

   Email: Frederic.Jounay@salt.ch

   Philippe Niger
   Orange CH

   Email: philippe.niger@orange.com

   Yuji Kamite
   NTT Communications Corporation

   Email: y.kamite@ntt.com

   Lizhong Jin

   Email: lizho.jin@gmail.com

   Martin Vigoureux
   Nokia

   Email: martin.vigoureux@nokia.com

   Laurent Ciavaglia
   Nokia

   Email: laurent.ciavaglia@nokia.com

   Simon Delord
   Telstra

   Email: simon.delord@gmail.com

   Kamran Raza
   Cisco Systems

   Email: skraza@cisco.com
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	</section>



	</back>

	</rfc>
	
