<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.28 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>  
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc number="8128" category="info" submissionType="IAB" consensus="yes"
  ipr="trust200902">


  <front>
    <title abbrev="rzerc">IETF Appointment Procedures for the&nbsp;ICANN&nbsp;Root&nbsp;Zone&nbsp;Evolution&nbsp;Review&nbsp;Committee</title>

    <author initials="C." surname="Morgan" fullname="Cindy Morgan">
      <organization>AMS</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cmorgan@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017" month="March" />

    <area>iab</area>
    
<keyword>rzerc</keyword>


    <abstract>


<t>This memo outlines the process by which the IETF makes an appointment to
the ICANN Root Zone Evolution Review Committee (RZERC).</t>


    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>The ICANN Root Zone Evolution Review Committee (RZERC) reviews proposed 
architectural changes to the content of the DNS root zone, the systems 
including both hardware and software components used in executing 
changes to the DNS root zone, and the mechanisms used for distribution 
of the DNS root zone, and makes recommendations to the ICANN Board. As 
stipulated in <xref target="RZERC-Charter" />, the IETF is called upon to name its delegate 
to the committee.</t>

<t>The IAB will select one person for a one-year term.  This appointment 
can be renewed for up to three additional one-year terms. This memo 
outlines the process by which the IETF makes that selection.  
</t>

<t>In brief, this document describes the timeframe and procedures for the 
IAB to solicit public input and make a selection for the open position.

</t>

</section>
<section anchor="desirable-qualifications-for-an-ietf-nominated-rzerc-member" title="Desirable Qualifications for an IETF-Nominated RZERC Member">

<t>Candidates for the RZERC should have a demonstrable involvement in the 
IETF with a particular focus on active participation in IETF Working 
Groups.
</t>

<t>The candidate is expected to possess clearly demonstrated technical 
competence in Internet technology relating to the DNS root zone and be 
able to articulate those technology issues such that the ICANN Board can 
be provided with sound technical perspectives.  The candidate is also 
expected to be able to understand the respective roles and 
responsibilities of the IETF and ICANN and be able to articulate these 
roles within both organizational communities.</t>

<t>The candidate will be a representative or a delegate of the IETF.  It is 
expected that the candidate would be able to call on experts in the IETF 
community as required, to ensure that the ICANN Board receives the 
highest-quality technical advice available.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-nomination-rzerc-member-selection-process" title="IETF-Nominated RZERC Member Selection Process">

<section anchor="term-length" title="Term Length">

<t>The IETF appointment to the RZERC will serve a one-year term.  This
   appointment can be renewed for up to three additional one-year
   terms.</t>

<t>In cases when the incumbent is willing to serve for an additional
   term and has not yet exceeded the term limits described above, the
   IAB may ask the IETF community for feedback on the incumbent to find
   out whether it is necessary to run a full selection process. If the 
   IAB determines that it is not necessary to run a full selection 
   process, the incumbent may be reappointed by the IAB for another 
   year.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="nominations-and-eligibility" title="Nominations and Eligibility">

<t>Except in cases when the IAB has decided to reappoint the incumbent, 
   each year, the IAB will make a public call for nominations on the
   IETF Announce &lt;ietf-announce@ietf.org&gt; mailing list.  The public call will specify
   the manner by which nominations will be accepted and the means by
   which the list of nominees will be published. The call for 
   nominations will also include the expected workload for the position, 
   as provided by the current IETF-appointed RZERC member.</t>

<t>Self-nominations are permitted.  Along with the name and contact
   information for each candidate, details about the candidate's
   background and qualifications for the position should be attached to
   the nomination. All IETF participants are eligible for nomination.  
   While IETF NomCom members, IAB members, IAOC members, and IESG 
   members are eligible, the IAB will balance time constraints and 
   potential conflicts of interest from those members in its 
   consideration of nominees.</t>

<t>IAB members who accept a nomination will recuse themselves from selection 
discussions.</t>

</section>


<section anchor="selection" title="Selection">

<t>The IAB will publish the list of nominated persons, review the material, 
and make a selection.</t>

<t>The IAB will consider potential conflicts with a position on the ICANN 
RZERC and any other ICANN committees supported by nominated candidates.</t>

</section>


<section anchor="timeframe" title="Timeframe">

<t>The IAB expects to seat new RZERC members in time for ICANN's annual 
general meeting in Q4 of each year.  Basic timeframe requirements for 
the IETF process are as follows:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>4-6 weeks for solicitation of nominations or review of incumbent</t>
  <t>4-6 weeks for review of nominees, deliberation, and selection</t>
</list></t>

<t>In Q2 of each year, the IAB will announce the specific dates for the 
RZERC selection process for that year (taking into account the 
particular dates of IETF and ICANN meetings, etc.) following the 
guidelines above.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="mid-term-vacancies" title="Mid-term Vacancies">

<t>This document describes the process for the general, annual appointment of RZERC 
members to fill the seats of members whose terms are ending.  However, 
if an IETF-appointed member of the RZERC is unable to serve his or her 
full term, the IAB may, at its discretion, immediately select a 
replacement to serve the remainder of the term using the interim process 
defined in <xref target="interim"/>.  If the IAB does not invoke the interim 
process, the next annual selection process will fill the vacancy.</t>

<section anchor="interim" title="Interim Appointment Process">

<t>If the IAB elects to fill the mid-term vacancy before the next annual 
selection, a separate timeline will be announced and the rest of the 
process described in this document will be followed.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This document does not describe any technical protocols and has no
implications for network security.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

<reference anchor="RZERC-Charter" target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/revised&nbhy;rzerc-charter-08aug16-en.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Root Zone Evolution Review Committee (RZERC) Charter</title>
    <author >
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016" month="August" day="8"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>


<section anchor="iab-members-at-the-time-of-this-writing" title="IAB Members at the Time
of Approval">

<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<t>
<list>
<t>Jari Arkko</t>
<t>Ralph Droms</t>
<t>Ted Hardie</t>
<t>Joe Hildebrand</t>
<t>Russ Housley</t>
<t>Lee Howard</t>
<t>Erik Nordmark</t>
<t>Robert Sparks</t>
<t>Andrew Sullivan</t>
<t>Dave Thaler</t>
<t>Martin Thomson</t>
<t>Brian Trammell</t>
<t>Suzanne Woolf</t>
</list></t>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
</section>


  </back>
</rfc>

